<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin I. The complex interplay between stratification and rotation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-10-02">October 2, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Auclair-Desrotour</surname></persName>
							<email>pierre.auclair-desrotour@u-bordeaux.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">LAB</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">UMR 5804</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Bordeaux</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Université de Bordeaux -Bât. B18N</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Allée Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire CS50023</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>33615</postCode>
									<settlement>Pessac Cedex</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire AIM Paris-Saclay, CEA/DRF -CNRS -Université Paris Diderot, IRFU/DAp Centre de Saclay</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-91191</postCode>
									<settlement>Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">LESIA</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Observatoire de Paris</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">PSL Research University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">UPMC Univ</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Paris 6</addrLine>
									<region>Sorbonne</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Univ. Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sorbonne Paris Cité, 5 place Jules Janssen</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-92195</postCode>
									<settlement>Meudon</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">IMCCE, Observatoire de Paris, CNRS UMR 8028</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">PSL Research University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>77 Avenue Denfert-Rochereau</addrLine>
									<postCode>75014</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin I. The complex interplay between stratification and rotation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-10-02">October 2, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. ADML2017 c ESO 2017 Received ...; accepted ...</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>hydrodynamics -waves -turbulence -planet-star interactions -planets and satellites: dynamical evolution and stability</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. Thermal atmospheric tides can torque telluric planets away from spin-orbit synchronous rotation, as observed in the case of Venus. They thus participate to determine the possible climates and general circulations of the atmospheres of these planets. Aims. The thermal tidal torque exerted on an atmosphere depends both on its internal structure and rotation, and the tidal frequency. Particularly, it strongly varies with the convective stability of entropy stratification. This dependence has to be characterized to constrain and predict the rotational properties of observed telluric exoplanets. Moreover, it is necessary to validate the approximations used in global modelings such as the traditional approximation, which is used to obtain separable solutions for tidal waves. Methods. We write the equations governing the dynamics of thermal tides in a local vertically-stratified section of a rotating planetary atmosphere by taking into account the effects of the complete Coriolis acceleration on tidal waves. This allows us to derive analytically the tidal torque and the tidally dissipated energy, which we use to discuss the possible regimes of tidal dissipation and examine the key role played by stratification. Results. In agreement with early studies, we find that the frequency dependence of the thermal atmospheric tidal torque in the vicinity of synchronization can be approximated by a Maxwell model. This behaviour corresponds to weakly stably stratified or convective fluid layers, as observed in Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a). A strong stable stratification allows gravity waves to propagate, which makes the tidal torque become negligible. The transition is continuous between these two regimes. The traditional approximation appears to be valid in thin atmospheres and in regimes where the rotation frequency is dominated by the forcing or the buoyancy frequencies. Conclusions. Depending on the stability of their atmospheres with respect to convection, observed exoplanets can be tidally driven toward synchronous or asynchronous final rotation rates. The domain of applicability of the traditional approximation is rigorously constrained by calculations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The end of the year 2016 and the beginning of the year 2017 have been marked by the discovery of potentially habitable Earth-like exoplanets orbiting two stars located in the close neighborhood of the Solar system. The first star is Proxima Centauri, where a planet with a minimum mass of 1.3 M C , Proxima b, has been detected ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Anglada-Escudé et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ribas et al. 2016</ref>). The second one is the ultra-cool dwarf star Trappist-1, which hosts seven telluric planets of masses between 0.2 M C and 2 M C , and radii between 0.7 R C and 1.2 R C ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gillon et al. 2017)</ref>. Proxima b and Trappist-1 e, f, and g orbit in the habitable zone of their host stars. Besides, they are likely to be covered with an atmosphere like the Earth, Venus or Mars in the Solar system. Their habitability is hence strongly constrained by their atmospheric dynamics (i.e. the general circulation, zonal winds), which plays a prominent role in the heat transport and determines their climate and surface temperature.</p><p>The atmosphere dynamics is tightly related to the rotational dynamics of planets. For instance, the general circulation of rapidly rotating planets such as the Earth is driven by geostrophic flows while planets close to spin-orbit synchronous rotation are subject to large scale convective cells that transport heat from the day side to the night side (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Leconte et al. 2013</ref>). It is thus of great importance to characterize the rotational evolution of the observed rocky exoplanets.</p><p>Those hosted by Trappist-1 are expected to be either tidally synchronized with the star, or trapped in a higher-order spinorbit resonance, since they are submitted to a strong tidal gravitational potential applied on their telluric core ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gillon et al. 2017</ref>). However, as noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ribas et al. (2016)</ref>  atmospheric tides in addition to the standard gravitational tide. Thermal tides have been proved to be able to compensate the solid tidal torque and to torque the planet away from synchronization. This is the case of Venus, which is maintained in a retrograde rotation state of equilibrium by the competition between solid and atmospheric tides <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gold &amp; Soter 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dobrovolskis &amp; Ingersoll 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Correia &amp; Laskar 2001</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">, 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017b</ref>).</p><p>In a previous study, by using a global ab initio modeling, we investigated the role played by the structure and properties of the atmosphere in response to a semidiurnal quadrupolar tidal forcing <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). Particularly, we showed that stable stratification is able to modify the dependence of the atmospheric tidal torque on the tidal frequency. These results suggest that the Maxwell-like 1 frequency dependence obtained by early works with parametrized models <ref type="bibr">(Ingersoll &amp; Dobro- volskis 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Correia &amp; Laskar 2001)</ref> or General Circulation Models (or GCMs, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015</ref>) corresponds to the tidal response of a neutrally-stratified atmosphere with respect to convection. They also show that a strong stable stratification tends to annihilate the global tidal bulge by allowing gravity waves to propagate, so that the resulting atmospheric tidal torque becomes negligible. This has large repercussions on the final rotation rate of the planet. In the neutrally-stratified case, an asynchronous rotation rate can be reached, while the solid tide dominates in the second case, leading the body to spin-orbit synchronization.</p><p>However, these tendencies were obtained by considering asymptotic cases (neutrally slowly rotating and isothermal stably stratified atmospheres), which let the details of the continuous variation of the tidal response with stratification aside. Moreover, the global model used to describe the dynamics of tidal waves in this early work is based upon an approximation on the hierarchy between rotation and stratification, the traditional approximation. It consists in neglecting the latitudinal projection of the rotation vector in the Coriolis acceleration, which allows to integrate separately the vertical and horizontal structure of the tidal response. The traditional approximation is not valid for all configurations and its domain of applicability is not clearly established <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Gerkema &amp; Zimmerman 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Tort &amp; Dubos 2014</ref>). Some of the limitations of the traditional approximation have been identified in geophysical and astrophysical fluid dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Gerkema &amp; Shrira 2005)</ref>. Particularly, the general case is fully 2D and thus the coordinates cannot be separated ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mathis et al. 2014</ref>). Hence, the traditional approximation needs to be validated for thermal atmospheric tides. It is thus necessary to develop a tractable model enabling us to explore widely the possible stratifications and rotations without any approximation on the Coriolis acceleration. Such a model would also allow us to discuss the different tidal regimes, their consequences on the evolution of the rotation rate of a planet, and the possible bias resulting from approximations made in the global modeling.</p><p>Therefore, we propose in this study to characterize the behaviour of the atmospheric tidal torque with respect to stratification in the framework of a 2D simplified local Cartesian modeling where the effect of rotation is fully taken into account. This approach is based on the early works by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mathis et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">André et al. (2017)</ref>, who examine the effect of stratification and rotation on waves propagating within planetary oceans, stars and gaseous envelopes of giant planets. We generalize their formalism to treat the case of strat-1 So called in reference to the Maxwell model (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Greenberg 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Correia et al. 2014</ref>). ified atmospheres with vertically-dependent hydrostatic equilibrium structures.</p><p>We introduce the physical setup of the local model in Section 2 and write the equations describing the dynamics of thermally generated tidal waves in a planetary fluid layer in Section 3. Then we derive, in Section 4, the energy balance associated to a propagating tidal mode. In Section 5, analytic solutions are computed in the case of simplified atmospheric models, namely a homogeneous fluid with uniform background distributions and of an isothermal stably-stratified atmosphere. In Section 6, these solutions are used to discuss the possible tidal regimes and the dependence of the atmospheric tidal torque on stratification in the non-traditional framework. We show that beyond a critical value of the Brunt-Väisälä frequency this torque becomes negligible. We then illustrate the consequences of this behaviour on the planet's rotation by computing the evolution of this later for various stratifications. We end this work with a study of the applicability of the traditional approximation in Section 7 that allows us to identify asymptotic regimes where it can be applied. Finally, we give our conclusions in Section 8. <ref type="bibr">Following Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mathis et al. (2014)</ref>, we consider a local volume within a planetary atmospheric layer <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref>. This volume is a Cartesian box of side L such that L ! R, R being the planet radius. It is rotating uniformly at the angular velocity Ω. We denote by Ω the corresponding spin vector. The position of the fluid box is located in the co-rotating frame attached to the body R E : tO, X E , Y E , Z E u, such that Z E " Ω{ |Ω|, with the usual system of spherical coordinates pr, θ, ϕq, where r stands for the vertical coordinate, θ for the colatitude and ϕ for the longitude. The associated vectorial basis is denoted pe r , e θ , e ϕ q. To study the dynamics of tidal waves inside the box, we use the Cartesian coordinates x (west-east), y (south-north) and z (vertical, positive upward), and the associated basis pe x , e y , e z q " pe ϕ , ´e θ , e r q. Finally, the time is denoted t. For convenience, we will use as much as possible the same notations as <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref> for physical quantities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Physical setup and background structure</head><p>The structure of the layer is described by the background spatial distributions of gravity g, pressure p 0 , density ρ 0 and temperature T 0 . To simplify the problem, we assume that these quantities vary with the vertical coordinate (z) only. This corresponds to ignoring the effects of centrifugal distortion and the day-night variations of the atmosphere. We also introduce the pressure scale height of the fluid,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">H pzq " p 0 gρ 0 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>and its Brunt-Väisälä frequency, i.e. the frequency characterizing the stability of the vertical entropy stratification, defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">N 2 pzq " g " 1 Γ 1 d ln p 0 dz´d dz´ dz´d ln ρ 0 dz  ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where Γ 1 stands for the first adiabatic exponent (e.g. Gerkema &amp; Zimmerman 2008). We will consider in the following that the fluid is a perfect gas, so that Γ 1 " 1.4. As the atmosphere is supposed to be in solid rotation with the body, mean flows are ignored in this first paper. However, the internal dissipation due to radiative cooling is taken into account. In the Maxwell approximation mentioned above, the maximal amplitude of the atmospheric torque corresponds to equalizing the tidal period τ tide and an effective thermal time associated with internal diffusive and radiative processes τ 0 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). These processes can be described at first order by a Newtonian cooling as in Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a) (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lindzen &amp; McKenzie 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Dickinson &amp; Geller 1968)</ref>. This introduces a parameter for the efficiency of dissipation, the frequency σ 0 , which is the inverse of the local radiative time of the fluid. Like the other quantities, σ 0 can vary along the vertical direction (see for example <ref type="bibr">Pollack &amp; Young 1975, for Venus)</ref>; it will be set to a constant value here for the sake of simplicity. The effect of a radiative time varying with altitude on the tidal perturbation has been studied in the framework of the classical theory of atmospheric tides (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Dickinson &amp; Geller 1968;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Lindzen &amp; McKenzie 1967</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Tidal wave dynamics</head><p>The fluid is forced thermally by the perturber with the thermal power per unit mass J. The resulting perturbed quantities are the variations of pressure δp, density δρ and the velocity field u " pu, v, wq. To simplify the equations of dynamics, we will use the reduced pressure variations p " δp{ρ 0 and the buoyancy b " ´gδρ{ρ 0 instead of δp and δρ (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira 2005)</ref>. The effect of rotation on the tidal perturbation is taken into account through the Coriolis acceleration. Hence, we introduce the Coriolis parameters f " 2Ω cos θ and˜fand˜ and˜f " 2Ω sin θ and suppose them to be constant in the box, which is the so-called f-plane approximation. Note that f corresponds to the vertical projection of the rotation vector and˜fand˜ and˜f to its latitudinal component, which is responsible for the coupling of the latitudinal and vertical structures of tidal waves. To make the problem separable and tractable analytically within spherical geometry, it is necessary to assume the traditional approximation, i.e. to ignore this term. Here, the simplified Cartesian geometry of the local modeling allows us to conserve the complete Coriolis acceleration that includes terms iñ f . We assume that asynchronous rotation rates are possible only in the vicinity of synchronous rotation, in range of forcing periods defined by τ tide " τ 0 . This allows us to ignore the effects of compressibility and to simplify calculations by applying the anelastic approximation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Spiegel &amp; Veronis 1960)</ref>. Thus, following <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mathis et al. (2014)</ref>, we neglect the contribution of acoustic waves. Note that compressibility can nevertheless contribute to the atmospheric tidal response in a non-negligible way in the regime of rapidly rotating bodies, where horizontally propagating acoustic waves can be generated, the so-called Lamb modes. Finally, we assume the so-called Cowling approximation <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cowling 1941)</ref>, which consists in ignoring the perturbation of the self-gravitational potential. The dynamics of the tidally forced fluid response is thus described by the following linearized Navier-Stokes equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">u t ` 2Ωû2Ωû " ´p`b´p`´p`b e z ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>the equation of mass conservation¨pρ</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">conservation¨conservation¨pρ 0 uq " 0,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and the equation of energy</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">b t ` N 2 w " κ H J ´ σ 0 b,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where the subscript t denotes the partial derivative in time, κ " pΓ 1 ´ 1q {Γ 1 , and σ 0 b stands for the sink term associated with the Newtonian cooling. Because of the periodicity in time of the tidal forcing (thermal and gravitational), any perturbed quantity q can be expanded as a Fourier series of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">q px, tq " ÿ σ q σ pxq e iσt ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>the parameter σ being the tidal frequency of a component and q σ the Fourier coefficient of the expansion. In the following, the superscript σ will be omitted in order to lighten expressions. By substituting Eq. (6) in Eqs. (3-5), we end up with the system of linearized primitive equations</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">iσú f v ` ˜ f w " ´p x , (7) iσv`fiσv`iσv`f u " ´p y ,<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">iσw´˜iσw´iσw´˜ f u " ´p z ` b,<label>(9)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">u x ` v y ` w z ` d ln ρ 0 dz w " 0,<label>(10)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">piσ`σpiσ`piσ`σ 0 q b ` N 2 w " κ H J.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Note that the notations u, v, w, p and b now refer to the spatial distributions of perturbed quantities.</p><p>We consider waves propagating in the horizontal direction along the vector e α " cos α e x `sin α e y , α being the angle of the direction of propagation in the pe x , e y q plane. Hence, using the change of variable χ " x cos α ` y sin α, the system of Eqs. (7-11) can be reduced to a single equation for w,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Aw χχ`2Bwχχ`χχ`2Bw χz`Cwχz`χz`Cw zz`Dwzz`zz`Dw χ ` Ew z ` Fw " S ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where the subscripts χ and z refer to the horizontal and vertical derivatives respectively. The coefficients associated with secondorder derivatives are expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">A pzq " N 2 ` η ´1`f´1` ´1`f 2 s ´ σ 2 ˘ ,<label>(13)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">B pzq " η ´1 f f s ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>C pzq " ´η´1`σ´η´1´η´1`</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">´η´1`σ 2 ´ f 2 ˘ ,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Article number, page 3 of 12</p><p>A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. ADML2017</p><p>those associated with first order derivatives as</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">D pzq " η ´1 d ln ρ 0 dz˜f dz˜ dz˜f piσ cos α ` f sin αq , (16) E pzq " η ´1`f´1` ´1`f 2 ´ σ 2 ˘ d ln ρ 0 dz , (17) F pzq " η ´1`f´1` ´1`f 2 ´ σ 2 ˘ d dzˆd dzˆ dzˆd ln ρ 0 dz ˙ ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>and the source term S due to the thermal forcing is written</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">S pz, χq " κ H J χχ .<label>(19)</label></formula><p>In these expressions, we have introduced the modified Coriolis parameter of <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref>, f s " ˜ f sin α, and the function</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">η pσq " σ σ ´ iσ 0 ,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>which is such that η " 1 if the radiative cooling is ignored and 0 ď |η| ă 1 otherwise. In the asymptotic regime dominated by the radiative cooling (|σ{σ 0 | Ñ 0), η Ñ 0. In the regime where thermal time is far greater than the tidal period</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(|σ{σ 0 | Ñ `8), η Ñ 1.</formula><p>Hence, by setting σ 0 " 0 and a uniform density profile (d ln ρ 0 {dz " 0), we eliminate terms associated with first-order derivatives and recover the equations given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref>.</p><p>Following this early work, we seek 2D solutions expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">w pz, χq " Ψ pzq e irk K χ`δpzqs ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where k K stands for the horizontal wavenumber, δ is the function defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">δ pzq " k K f f s σ 2 ´ f 2 z ` i 1 2 ln ρ 0 ,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>and Ψ the solution of the Schrödinger-like vertical structure equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">d 2 Ψ dz 2 ` k 2 z Ψ " ´k 2 K p S C Φ ´1 .<label>(23)</label></formula><p>In this equation, p S denotes the vertical profile of S resulting from the above separation of coordinates and k z the local vertical wavenumber of the mode, defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">k 2 z " k 2 K « ηN 2 ´ σ 2 σ 2 ´ f 2 ` ˆ σ f s σ 2 ´ f 2 ˙ 2 ff`d ff` ff`d ln ρ 0 dzˆk dzˆ dzˆk K σ ˜ f cos α σ 2 ´ f 2 ´ 1 4 d ln ρ 0 dz ˙ ` 1 2 d 2 ln ρ 0 dz 2 ,<label>(24)</label></formula><p>while Φ pzq " exp piδq. We recognize in the first term of Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(24)</ref> the classical vertical wavenumber of gravito-inertial waves. Other terms are associated with the variation of background distributions. The polarization relations giving the vertical profiles of perturbed quantities as functions of Ψ and its first derivative are deduced straightforwardly from primitive equations. Denoting by p q the vertical profile of a quantity q (such that q pz, χq " p q pzq e ik K χ ), we thus obtain, for the buoyancy,</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">p b pzq " ´ i σ ´ iσ 0 " κ H p J ´ N 2 ΦΨ ı ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>for the pressure,</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">p p pzq " i f 2 ´ σ 2 σk 2 K Φ " dΨ dz`ˆ dz` dz`ˆ 1 2 d ln ρ 0 dz`A dz`dz`A ˙ Ψ  ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>and for the components of the velocity field,</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">p u pzq " iσ cos α ` f sin α σk K Φ " dΨ dz`ˆ dz` dz`ˆ 1 2 d ln ρ 0 dz`B dz`dz`B ˙ Ψ  ,<label>(27)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">p v pzq " ´ f cos α ´ iσ sin α σk K Φ " dΨ dz`ˆ dz` dz`ˆ 1 2 d ln ρ 0 dz`C dz`dz`C ˙ Ψ  ,<label>(28)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">p w pzq " ΦΨ,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>with the coefficients</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">A " ´k K σ ˜ f cos α σ 2 ´ f 2 ,<label>(30)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">B " ik K f s " f σ 2 ´ f 2 ` sin α iσ cos α ` f sin α  ,<label>(31)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">C " ik K f s " f σ 2 ´ f 2 ` cos α f cos α ´ iσ sin α  .<label>(32)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Energy balance</head><p>The vertical profiles of the perturbed quantities being established in Eqs. (25-29), we can compute the energy balance and torque associated with the atmospheric tide. The equation for the energy is obtained by multiplying the momentum equation Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref> by u and the equation of buoyancy Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(5)</ref> by b. We get:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">` E c ` E p ˘ t " ´ ¨ pρ 0 puq`Dpuq`puq`D diss`Pdiss`diss`P for ,<label>(33)</label></formula><p>where we have introduced the kinetic energy per unit volume,</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">E c " 1 2 ρ 0 u 2 ,<label>(34)</label></formula><p>the potential energy per unit volume associated with stratification,</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">E p " 1 2 ρ 0 b 2 N 2 ,<label>(35)</label></formula><p>the power dissipated per unit volume by the radiative cooling,</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">D diss " ρ 0 σ 0 b 2 N 2 (36)</formula><p>Article number, page 4 of 12 P. Auclair-Desrotour et al.: Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin and the power injected per unit volume by the thermal tidal forcing,</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">P for " ρ 0 κ HN 2 bJ.<label>(37)</label></formula><p>Averaged over time, these quantities become</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">E c " 1 2 ρ 0 xu 2 y t , E p " 1 2 ρ 0 N 2 xb 2 y t , D diss " ρ 0 σ 0 N 2 xb 2 y t , P for " ρ 0 κ HN 2 xbJy t ,<label>(38)</label></formula><p>where x. . .y t is the average in time. Finally, we use the identity</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">x tpu tquy t " 1 2 tp p p q ˚ u ,<label>(39)</label></formula><p>the notations and˚referringand˚and˚referring to the real part and conjugate of a complex number respectively. We obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">E c " 1 4 ρ 0 |p u| 2 , E p " 1 4 ρ 0 N 2 ˇ ˇ ˇ p b ˇ ˇ ˇ 2 , D diss " 1 2 ρ 0 σ 0 N 2 ˇ ˇ ˇ p b ˇ ˇ ˇ 2 , P for " 1 2 ρ 0 κ HN 2 ! p b p J ˚ ) .<label>(40)</label></formula><p>We recall that, in these expressions, p b and p u " pp u, p v, p wq designate the vertical profiles of the complex perturbed quantities that are given by Eqs. <ref type="bibr">(25)</ref><ref type="bibr">(26)</ref><ref type="bibr">(27)</ref><ref type="bibr">(28)</ref><ref type="bibr">(29)</ref>.</p><p>Similarly, the tidal torque exerted by the star on the fluid layer with respect to the spin axis of the planet is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">T " ż V rsinθ tδρu F T,ϕ dV (41)</formula><p>where F T;ϕ is the latitudinal component of the tidal force, ϕ the longitudinal coordinate and V the volume of the fluid shell. This expression can be written as a function of the tidal potential generating the tidal force U, which is such that F " U, and becomes (e.g. Zahn 1966; Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a)</p><p>T "</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">" 1 2 ż V U ϕ δρ˚dVδρ˚δρ˚dV * .<label>(42)</label></formula><p>One can note that δρ has two components: the adiabatic component tδρu, which is in phase with the tidal potential and does not contribute to the tidal torque, and the dissipative component delayed with respect to the forcing, tδρu, the notation referring to the imaginary part of a complex number. Hence, the equivalent local tidal torque exerted on the fluid box scales as</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">T 9 ´ "ż z b 0 ρ 0 p bdz 1 * .<label>(43)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Simplified atmospheric models</head><p>The above equations are formulated in the general case, for any background distribution. In order to explore analytically the domain of parameters, we compute in this section analytic solutions of the thermal tide in two simplified cases: in a homogeneous fluid with uniform background distributions and in an isothermal stably-stratified gas. In both cases, we consider a uniform profile of thermal forcing ( p J is now a constant) for the sake of simplicity, as done before in the global model <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Auclair- Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). Such a profile physically corresponds to an optically thin atmosphere homogeneous in composition, where the stellar incoming flux is absorbed over the whole depth of the fluid layer. Is can also be seen in the general case as a zeroorder approximation of the effective energy input per unit mass generating the thermal tide. Assuming p J to be constant allows us to reduce the right-hand member of the vertical structure equation (Eq. 23) to a simple exponential function of the altitude.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">In a homogeneous fluid</head><p>The simplest case is that of uniform background distributions, which corresponds to the case studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref>. We assume that ρ 0 , H and σ 0 do not vary with the altitude. As a consequence, the vertical structure equation reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">d 2 Ψ dz 2 `k 2 K « ηN 2 ´ σ 2 σ 2 ´ f 2 ` ˆ σ f s σ 2 ´ f 2 ˙ 2 ff Ψ " k 2 K κη p J H pσ 2 ´ f 2 q e ´iδ c z ,<label>(44)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">with δ c " k K f f s σ 2 ´ f 2 .<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Solving Eq. (44) requires us to choose two boundary conditions. As the guideline of this work is to characterize the atmospheric tidal response of a terrestrial planet, we use an impenetrable rigid-wall condition at z " 0, i.e. Ψ " 0. For the upper boundary, following <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Shen &amp; Zhang (1990)</ref>, we assume that there is no material escape at the top of the atmosphere. Thus, the obtained solution shall not diverge at z " `8. This amounts to eliminating the diverging term of the solution,</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">Ψ " A e ik z z ` Béik z z ` Ψ S e ´iδ c z ,<label>(46)</label></formula><p>where Ψ S is the amplitude of the particular solution, and A and B integration constants. With the convention tk z u ą 0, it follows that</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">Ψ " A e ik z z ` Ψ S e ´iδ c z ,<label>(47)</label></formula><p>at the upper boundary. Thus, denoting by ν the dimensionless complex factor expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">ν pσq " ηN 2 ηN 2 ´ σ 2 ` f 2 s ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>we end up with the solution</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">Ψ pzq " Ψ S ` e ´iδ c z ´ e ik z z ˘ ,<label>(49)</label></formula><p>Article number, page 5 of 12</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. ADML2017</formula><p>where the constant Ψ S is written</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">Ψ S pσq " κ p J HN 2 ν.<label>(50)</label></formula><p>Note that the case ν " 0 corresponds to a neutral stratification (see Eq. (48) with N 2 " 0). In this case,</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">Ψ S " κ p J{ " H ` f 2 s ´ σ 2 ˘‰</formula><p>. We then substitute Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(49)</ref> in Eqs. (25-29) and introduce the parameters</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">D pzq " 1 ´ e ipδ c `k z qz and E pzq " ´i pδ c ` k z q e ipδ c `k z qz ,<label>(51)</label></formula><p>to get the vertical profiles of the tidal fluctuation of buoyancy</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">p b pzq " ´ i σ ´ iσ 0 κ p J H p1´νDqp1´p1´νDq ,<label>(52)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">pressure p p pzq " i f 2 ´ σ 2 σk 2 K Ψ S " E ` k K ˜ f σ cos α ` i f sin α f 2 ´ σ 2 D  ,<label>(53)</label></formula><p>and velocity field</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">p u pzq " i cos α k K Ψ S " E ` ik K ˜ f sin 2 α iσ cos α ` f sin α D  ,<label>(54)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">p v pzq " ´ f cos α ´ iσ sin α σk K Ψ S " E ` ik K ˜ f sin α cos α f cos α ´ iσ sin α D  ,<label>(55)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">p w pzq " Ψ S D.<label>(56)</label></formula><p>Finally, denoting z b the altitude of the upper boundary and substituting Eq. (52) into Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(40)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(43)</ref>, we obtain the total averaged dissipated energy per unit area of the pσ, k K q-mode in the fluid Cartesian box,</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">ˆ D diss " 1 2 ρ 0 σ 0 N 2 ` σ 2 ` σ 2 0 ˘ ˜ κ p J H ¸ 2 ż z b 0 |1´νD|1´|1´νD pz 1 q| 2 dz 1 ,<label>(57)</label></formula><p>and the dimensionless tidal torque</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">T 9 2σ 0 " i 1 ´ ν σ ´ iσ 0 * ,<label>(58)</label></formula><p>which is normalized so that max |T | " 1 when ν " 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">In an isothermal atmosphere</head><p>The isothermal approximation is the zero-order approximation of the atmospheric structure of terrestrial planets such as the Earth. It is also the simplest structure allowing us to examine the repercussions of the variations of background distributions on the tidal response. Indeed, an isothermal atmosphere is characterized by exponentially decaying density and pressure distributions and a uniform pressure height-scale depending on the temperature. Hence, ρ 0 is now given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">ρ 0 pzq " ρ s e ´τz , with τ " 1 H ,<label>(59)</label></formula><p>the notations ρ s and τ designating the density at the surface of the solid part of the planet and the vertical decaying rate respectively. Since the density profile follows an exponential law, d ln ρ 0 {dz " ´τ. Therefore, noticing that N 2 does not vary with the altitude either, we obtain for the vertical structure of tidal waves an equation of the same form as Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(44)</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">d 2 Ψ dz 2 ` k 2 z Ψ " k 2 K κη p J H pσ 2 ´ f 2 q e ´iδ c z ,<label>(60)</label></formula><p>with in this case</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">δ c " k K f f s σ 2 ´ f 2 ´ i τ 2<label>(61)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">k 2 z " k 2 K « ηN 2 ´ σ 2 σ 2 ´ f 2 ` ˆ σ f s σ 2 ´ f 2 ˙ 2 ff´τk ff´ff´τk K σ ˜ f cos α σ 2 ´ f 2 ` τ 2 4 .<label>(62)</label></formula><p>Hence, by applying the same boundary conditions as in the previous case, we obtain an analytic solution, which is written similarly as Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(49)</ref>. The parameter ν is modified solely and is written</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">ν " ηN 2 ηN 2 ´ σ 2 ` f 2 s ` γ ˜ f pi f sin α ´ σ cos αq`1αq`αq`1 2 γ 2 pσ 2 ´ f 2 q ,<label>(63)</label></formula><p>where the parameter γ is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">γ " τ k K ,<label>(64)</label></formula><p>and compares the horizontal wavelength of the mode to the typical scale height of the background vertical distributions. The vertical profiles of perturbed quantities derived from this solution are written for the buoyancy</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">p b pzq " ´ i σ ´ iσ 0 κ p J H p1´νDqp1´p1´νDq ,<label>(65)</label></formula><p>for the pressure</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">p p pzq " i f 2 ´ σ 2 σk 2 K Ψ S " E ` ˆ k K ˜ f σ cos α ` i f sin α f 2 ´ σ 2 ´ τ ˙ D  ,<label>(66)</label></formula><p>and for the velocity field</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">p u pzq " i cos α k K Ψ S " E ` ˆ ik K ˜ f sin 2 α iσ cos α ` f sin α ´ τ ˙ D  ,<label>(67)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">p v pzq " ´ f cos α ´ iσ sin α σk K Ψ S rE<label>(68)</label></formula><p>`</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">ˆ ik K ˜ f sin α cos α f cos α ´ iσ sin α ´ τ ˙ D  , p w pzq " Ψ S D.<label>(69)</label></formula><p>Article number, page 6 of 12</p><note type="other">P. Auclair-Desrotour et al.: Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin In these expressions, the parameters D and E are those defined by Eq. (51). Basically, it shall be noted that we recover all of the results</note><p>of the previous case by setting τ " 0 since a uniform density distribution is just the asymptotic limit of an exponentially decaying one with H Ñ `8. We finally compute the energy dissipated per unit surface by the radiative cooling in the fluid section</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">ˆ D diss " 1 2 ρ s σ 0 N 2 ` σ 2 ` σ 2 0 ˘ ˜ κ p J H ¸ 2 ż z b 0 |1´νD|1´|1´νD pz 1 q| 2 e ´τz 1 dz 1 ,<label>(70)</label></formula><p>and of the normalized dimensionless tidal torque,</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">T " 2σ 0 # i σ ´ iσ 0 ˜ 1 ´ ν ´ ν 1 ´ i δ c `k z τ ¸+ ,<label>(71)</label></formula><p>which is obtained in a similar way as Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(58)</ref> and is such that max |T | " 1 when ν " 0. As noted for other quantities, we easily verify that these two expressions simplify into those obtained in the case of uniform background distributions, i.e. Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(57)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(58)</ref> respectively, when τ Ñ 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Tidal regimes and their implications on the rotational dynamics of terrestrial planets</head><p>In this section, we use the results derived in the framework of our Cartesian model to explore the domain of parameters and understand the behaviour of the atmospheric tidal response predicted by the much more complex previous global modelings (AuclairDesrotour et al. 2017a; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015</ref>). Particularly, we examine the tidal torque exerted on the atmosphere, which contributes to the evolution of the rotation rate of the planet with the torque resulting from the tidal elongation and the viscous friction of the solid core. In the vicinity of synchronization, the atmospheric and solid tidal torques can balance each other, the first one torquing the planet away from synchronous rotation and the second one towards it. This can explain the locking of the planet Venus at the observed asynchonous retrograde rotation rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gold &amp; Soter 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ingersoll &amp; Dobrovolskis 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr">Do- brovolskis &amp; Ingersoll 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Correia &amp; Laskar 2001</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">, 2003</ref>. If the tidal response of the atmosphere is reduced to its non-wavelike part 2 (Ogilvie 2013), which is associated with a quadrupolar bulge, the atmospheric tidal torque can be approximated with a Maxwell rheology characterized by the effective radiative frequency of the atmosphere <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Ingersoll &amp; Dobrovolskis 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>,b), i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">T 9 σ σ 2 ` σ 2 0 .</formula><p>(72) <ref type="bibr">2</ref> The separation of the fluid tidal response into non-wavelike and wavelike part was introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Ogilvie (2013)</ref> in the context of gravitational tides. The non-wavelike part designates the instantaneous global elongation of the atmosphere and the induced large-scale flow, while the wave-like part encompasses the effects of internal waves generated by the forcing and resonances they can induce. In the present work, the term non-wavelike refers to the global elongation of the atmosphere due to the thermal forcing by analogy with the gravitational tidal potential. It is however different from the equilibrium tide, which designates the tidal response of the fluid in the zero-frequency limit (σ Ñ 0). Normalized tidal torque as a function of the frequency of the perturber ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb for various values of the Brunt-Väisälä frequency from weak to strong stable stratification, i.e. log pNq " t´8, ´6, ´4, ´2u. The tidal torque is computed using the normalized function given by Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(71)</ref> and we consider the case of a Venus-like planet with the following set of values: n orb " 1.991ˆ10´7991ˆ991ˆ10991ˆ10´7 s ´1 , Γ 1 " 1.4 (perfect gas), H " 15.9 km, θ " π{3, α " 0 (westward propagating wave), σ 0 " 7.5 ˆ 10´710´7 s ´1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015</ref>), and k K " 2π{λ with λ " 1000 km.</p><p>However, in Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a), we pointed out the fact that stable stratification is able to annihilate the tidal torque due to the thermal non-wavelike tide in the vicinity of synchronization because it induces a wavelike tide composed of gravity waves. As a consequence, the planet would be led in this case towards synchronous rotation by the solid tide. To study this effect, the global modeling used in this early study should be completed for two reasons. First, it describes the tidal atmospheric response in a spherical geometry. This tends to dilute the physics into mathematical aspects. Second, it is based upon the traditional approximation, and can be affected by the bias induced by this hypothesis, which will be studied in the next section. Typically, when 2Ω Á N, the traditional approximation can lead us to overestimate the amplitude of the tidal torque, as discussed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Ogilvie &amp; Lin (2004)</ref>. These authors show that the static approximation, in which the effect of rotation is ignored, is better in this case. Following them, we used this last approximation instead of the traditional approximation to establish the Maxwell law in the global model <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>).</p><p>Hence, the local Cartesian modeling developed in the present study will allow us to explore the full domain of parameters in rotation and stratification with taking into account the complete Coriolis acceleration, filtering out complexities due to the spherical geometry but keeping the key physical ingredients.</p><p>Considering the expressions of ν in the two cases treated in the previous section, Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(48)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(63)</ref>, we recover the asymptotic regimes observed with global modelings. On the one hand, in the convective atmosphere limit (i.e. N 2 Ñ 0), ν Ñ 0. The expressions of the tidal torque given by Eqs. (58) and (71) both reduce to Eq. (72), i.e. a Maxwell law. On the other hand, in the stably-stratified atmosphere limit (N 2 Ñ `8), ν Ñ 1. Thus, the torque obtained in the case of a uniform background readily tends to zero. The case of the isothermal atmosphere is a little bit more complex because we have to take into account the dependence of the vertical wavelengths of tidal gravito-inertial waves on the tidal frequency. Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(62)</ref> shows that k z pσq diverges Article number, page 7 of 12 A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. ADML2017 in the vicinity of spin-orbit synchronization (σ " 0), namely k z 9 ˇ ˇ σ 2 ´ f 2 ˇ ˇ ´1{2 if |σ| " σ 0 , and k z 9 ˇ ˇ σ{`σ σ{`σ{`σ 2 ´ f 2 ˘ˇˇ ˘ˇˇ 1{2 otherwise. As a consequence, |k z {τ| " 1 and the third term associated with the propagation of gravito-inertial waves in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(71)</ref> becomes negligible. We identify here how the tidal torque is flattened by the stable stratification. This behaviour corresponds to the equilibrium thermal tide of a stably stratified fluid region studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Arras &amp; Socrates (2010)</ref> in the case of fluid extrasolar planets. As demonstrated analytically by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Arras &amp; Socrates (2010)</ref>, the N 2 ξ r {g term of the heat transport equation tends to equalize the heat source term (J) in the equation of energy (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(5)</ref>) while σ Ñ 0. This means that the local density decreases generated by the thermal forcing are exactly cancelled by the vertical displacement of denser fluid brought up from below.</p><p>This behaviour is illustrated by <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figs. 2 and 3</ref> where the case of the stellar semidiurnal thermal tide is examined. The planet is supposed to orbit its host star circularly at the orbital frequency n orb , and its equatorial plane is coplanar with the orbital plane, so that the perturbation reduces to the quadrupolar tidal forcing of frequency σ " 2 pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q. We set for the studied mode k K " 2π{λ, with the wavelength λ " 1000 km, so that γ " τ{k K " 1 (asymptotic regime of large wavelengths). The tidal torque is plotted as a function of the normalized apparent orbital frequency of the star in the reference frame in corotation with the planet, namely the normalized tidal frequency ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb , for different values of the Brunt-Väisälä frequency from the convective isentropic limit (N " 10´810´8 s ´1 ) to strong stable stratification (N " 10´210´2 s ´1 ). These boundaries are chosen in such way that N ! t2Ω, σ, σ 0 u in the first asymptotic regime and N " t2Ω, σ, σ 0 u in the other one. We recover in the first case (red curve) the Maxwell-like tidal response predicted by early studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Ingersoll &amp; Dobrovolskis 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Correia &amp; Laskar 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>), and in the second one (violet curve) the weak torque obtained with the ab initio modeling of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a)</ref> that takes tidal gravity waves into account.</p><p>Several resonances can be observed in the transition regime. They result directly from the equality of characteristic frequencies of the system (N 2 , σ, 2Ω), which occurs in the denominator of the parameter ν. They are related to the local nature of the model since their positions depend on the colatitude, and consequently do not exist in the global tidal response, where the tidal equation is integrated over the sphere <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). However, we have to characterize them here to clarify the tidal torque frequency spectra observed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>.</p><p>In the regime of large wavelengths (γ " 1), the denominator of Eq. (63) can be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">d " ηN 2 ` 1 2 γ 2 ` σ 2 ´ f 2 ˘ .<label>(73)</label></formula><p>Let us assume σ 0 À σ, which corresponds to the quasi-adiabatic regime <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Press 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Auclair Desrotour et al. 2015</ref>), and substitute σ " 2 pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q in Eq. (73). Resonances thus correspond to the zeros of the polynomial</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">P pΩq " sin 2 θ Ω 2 ´ 2n orb Ω ` n 2 orb`1orb` orb`1 2 γ ´2 N 2 .<label>(74)</label></formula><p>We obtain the roots</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">Ω ˘ " 1 sin 2 θ « n orb ˘ c n 2 orb cos 2 θ ´ 1 2 γ ´2 N 2 sin 2 θ ff ,<label>(75)</label></formula><p>which, expressed in the normalized tidal frequency ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>, become</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">ω ˘ " cos θ sin 2 θ » -cos θ ˘ d 1 ´ 1 2 γ ´2ˆN ´2ˆ ´2ˆN n orb ˙ 2 tan 2 θ fi fl .<label>(76)</label></formula><p>In the limit N 2 Ñ 0, they tend to ω ´ " tan´2tan´2 θ ´ 1 and ω ` " sin´2sin´2 θ. As a consequence, ω ´ " ´1 and ω ` " `8 at the poles. These features are represented on the right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> where the tidal torque is plotted as a function of the tidal frequency (ω) and Brunt-Väisälä frequency in logarithmic scale. Black vertical dashed lines indicate the positions of resonances, while the horizontal dashed line designates the transition between the flat and Maxwell-like regimes for the tidal torque identified above, which corresponds to N " tγσ, γ f u. For the evolution of planetary systems, this means that rocky planets with an atmospheric Brunt-Väisälä frequency below this critical value are likely to tend towards non-synchronized rotation states of equilibrium, like Venus, while those beyond it will be led towards spin-orbit synchronization, in good agreement with predictions obtained in Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a) (Section 6.3).</p><p>In the right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>, the imaginary part of the surface pressure oscillation is plotted as a function of ω and N. This plot shows that we retrieve the asymptotic behaviours identified for the tidal torque in surface pressure oscillations. In a weakly stratified atmosphere, a net tidal bulge appears, leading to surface pressure oscillations of high amplitude in agreement with the lag of the bulge. In the strongly stratified regime, pressure oscillations vanish as there is no net tidal bulge anymore. However, we note that tp pu has not the same functional form as the tidal torque. Besides, one should bear in mind the fact that it partly depends on the chosen boundary conditions, which prevents us to proceed to a more quantitative analysis.</p><p>To illustrate the impact of the atmospheric structure on the long-term rotational evolution, we study the evolution of the rotation rate of an idealized Venus-like rocky planet submitted to both atmospheric and solid semidiurnal tides due to a host star. As the goal of these calculations is to isolate the different possible evolutions, we choose simple values of parameters. We use for the solid torque the simplified model expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">T S " ´T S;0 tanhˆσ tanhˆtanhˆσ σ S ˙ ,<label>(77)</label></formula><p>where T S;0 " 5.0 ˆ 10 16 N.m designates the amplitude of the torque and σ S the effective relaxation frequency of the material composing the rocky core. This model can be interpreted as a zero-order approximation of the Andrade model (Andrade 1910; Efroimsky 2012; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015</ref>), which describes the forced visco-elastic response of metals and silicates. The relaxation frequency of a rocky planet is usually far smaller than the orbital frequency (σ S " 10´1010´10 s ´1 , e.g. Efroimsky 2012).</p><p>Here, we set σ S " 10´210´2 n orb . In the Andrade model, the decaying rate of the tidal torque is far smaller than the one of the atmosphere for σ " σ S . So, it is well approximated by a constant in the vicinity of synchronous rotation. Concerning the atmospheric torque, we apply Eq. (71) with the effective radiative frequency σ 0 " 3 n orb and the amplitude T A;0 " 1.52 T S;0 , which is arbitrarily chosen in such way that the final rotation rate corresponds to ω " 4 in case of asynchronous state of equilibrium.</p><p>Article number, page 8 of 12 P. Auclair-Desrotour et al.: Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Normalized tidal torque (left panel) and imaginary part of the surface pressure oscillation (right panel) as functions of the normalized tidal frequency ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb (horizontal axis) and Brunt-Väisälä frequency in logarithmic scale (vertical axis). The tidal torque and pressure variations are computed using the functions given by Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(71)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(66)</ref> respectively. The torque is normalized by its maximum value in the asymptotic regime of neutral stratification. The imaginary part of pressure oscillations is normalized by its maxima in absolute value. We consider the case of a Venus-like planet with the following set of values: n orb " 1.991ˆ10´7991ˆ991ˆ10991ˆ10´7 s ´1 , Γ 1 " 1.4 (perfect gas), H " 15.9 km, θ " π{3, α " 0 (westward propagating wave), σ 0 " 7.5 ˆ 10´710´7 s ´1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015</ref>), and k K " 2π{λ with λ " 1000 km. The frequencies ω ´ and ω ` are the resonant frequencies identified in Section 6 (see Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(76)</ref>).</p><p>The planet is assumed to have the same moment of inertia as Venus, i.e. I p " 5.88ˆ1088ˆ88ˆ10 37 kg.m 2 , and to orbit its host star at the orbital period P orb " 100 d (let us recall that n orb " 2π{P orb ). The equation describing the evolution of the planet's rotation rate is written</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">I p dΩ dt " T S pΩq`TpΩq`pΩq`T A pΩq .<label>(78)</label></formula><p>It is integrated over 10 billion years using the ODEX code implemented in the algebraic manipulator TRIP (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hairer et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gastineau &amp; Laskar 2014)</ref>, with the initial condition Ω p0q " 10 n orb . Simulations are achieved for a large range of Brunt-Väisälä frequencies N " 10 β with β " ´7 to β " ´3. Results are plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref> as a function of time.</p><p>We can observe in this figure that rotational evolutions divide into two distinct families. The first family (β ě ´4), which encompasses strongly-stratified cases, is driven by the solid tidal torque solely. In this family, the rotation rate invariably converges towards synchronous rotation (ω " 0). Planets of the second family (β ď ´5.5) are driven by both solid and atmospheric tidal torques. The evolution rate of their spin varies depending on the strength of the atmospheric tidal torque, which tends to push the planet away from synchronous rotation. They finally reach a stable non-synchronized state of equilibrium corresponding to the frequency where the solid and atmospheric torques exactly balance each other. We can notice two evolutions behaving in a different way than those detailed above, namely β " ´4.5 and β " ´5. These cases are associated with the transition regime. In the first one (β " ´4.5) a non-synchronized state of equilibrium closer to synchronization is reached, while the rapid evolution of Ω in the second one (β " ´5) around t " 600 Myr results from one of the resonances studied above (see Eqs <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(73)</ref> to <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(76)</ref>). We note that the rotation tends towards synchronization in this case.</p><p>In the general case, it seems difficult to predict the final rotation rate of the planet using the formula given by Eq. (71). However, it can be done in the asymptotic regime described by The normalized frequency ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb is plotted as a function of time (Myr) in logarithmic scale. The Brunt-Väisälä frequency N " 10 β is increased from β " ´7 (weak stable stratification) to β " ´3 (strong stable stratification) with a step ∆β " 0.5.</p><p>the Maxwell model (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017b</ref>, in the case where the tidal torque of the rocky core is modeled by a Maxwell law). With the law chosen for the tidal torque applied to the rocky core in the present work (Eq. 77), the frequencies ω ˘ of possible states of equilibrium are expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">ω ˘ " 1 2 σ 0 n orb T A;0 T S;0 » -1 ˘ d 1 ´ ˆ T S;0 T A;0 ˙ 2 fi fl ,<label>(79)</label></formula><p>although only ω ` corresponds to a stable state leading to an asynchronous final rotation rate.</p><p>Article number, page 9 of 12 A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. ADML2017 <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Relative difference between the parameters ν TA and ν NTA corresponding to the cases with and without traditional approximation respectively, as a function of the ratio N{σ (horizontal axis) and 2Ω{σ (vertical axis) in logarithmic scales, and for various values of the ratios σ 0 {σ and γ " τ{k. From left to right, log pγq " t´2, 2u. From bottom to top, log pσ 0 {σq " t´2, 2u. The normalized relative difference between ν TA and ν NTA is given by ς " |ν TA´νTA´TA´ν NTA | { |ν TA`νTA`TA`ν NTA |. Blue (red) areas designate regions where the traditional approximation is (not) appropriate. Parameters: θ " π{4 and α " π{2.</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">= 10 2 = 10 2 0 / = 10 2 log ✓ 2⌦ ◆ 0 / = 10 2 log ✓ 2⌦ ◆ log ✓ N ◆ log ✓ N ◆</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Domain of validity of the traditional approximation</head><p>As mentioned in Section 3, the traditional approximation consists in ignoring terms involving the factor˜ffactor˜ factor˜f in the momentum equation components, Eqs. (7-9). This is convenient to eliminate the coupling between the horizontal and vertical structures of the tidal response induced by the Coriolis acceleration in global modelings (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Chapman &amp; Lindzen 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). However, the regime of parameters where the approximation is appropriate still remains only partially determined. Early studies generally agree on the fact that the approximation can be applied if 2Ω ! σ, that is in the regime of superinertial waves, where the fluid tidal response is weakly affected by the rotation of the planet. It has also been shown that the above condition could be extended to 2Ω À σ in the case of a stably-stratified fluid (σ ! N) (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Friedlander 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Mathis et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Mathis 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Prat et al. 2017</ref>).</p><p>We propose here to quantify the conditions of applicability of the traditional approximation by establishing the boundaries of its domain of validity as a function of the characteristic frequencies of the system (i.e. σ, σ 0 , 2Ω, N), and of the length scale ratio γ.</p><p>In light of the expressions of the dissipated power and tidal torque, given in Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_69">(70)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(71)</ref>, the dimensionless parameter ν introduced in Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(48)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(63)</ref> appears as a key parameter to characterize the domain of validity of the traditional approximation. Indeed, it intervenes in an essential way inˆDinˆ inˆD diss and T , and contains all the information concerning the hierarchy of characteristic frequencies and control parameters of the system. Therefore, considering that the impact of the traditional approximation on obtained results is directly related to the variation of ν with˜fwith˜ with˜f , we adopt as index of validity the normalized relative difference between the parameters ν TA and ν NTA corresponding to the cases with ( ˜ f " 0) and without ( ˜ f ‰ 0) the traditional approximation respectively (the subscripts TA and NTA stand for Traditional Approximation and No Traditional Approximation respectively), which is expressed as ς "</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">ˇ ˇ ˇ ˇ ν TA´νTA´TA´ν NTA ν TA`νTA`TA`ν NTAˇˇ NTAˇ NTAˇˇ ˇ ˇ .<label>(80)</label></formula><p>In this approach, the condition of validity of the traditional approximation is ς ! 1. Otherwise, neglecting the latitudinal projection of the rotation vector strongly modifies the tidal response, leading to ς « 1, and the traditional approximation should be abandoned.</p><p>The parameter ς is plotted in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> as a function of the frequencies ratios N{σ, 2Ω{σ and for asymptotic values of σ 0 {σ and the length-scale parameter γ " τ{k K . Angles are set to θ " π{12 and α " π{2. The values taken by ς are indicated by colors. Blue regions indicate the domain of parameters where the traditional approximation can be applied (ς ! 1) while red ones designate regimes where it is not relevant (ς « 1). Hence, we note that the traditional approximation is appropriate whatever the hierarchy of characteristic frequencies if the wavelength of the mode is far greater than the pressure height-scale, i.e. if Article number, page 10 of 12 P. Auclair-Desrotour et al.: Atmospheric thermal tides and planetary spin γ " 1. This is due to the fact that the term p1{2q γ 2 ` σ 2 ´ f 2 ˘ is always far greater in this case than terms associated with the latitudinal component of the Coriolis acceleration in the denominator of ν,</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">d " ηN 2 ´ σ 2 ` f 2 s ` γ ˜ f pi f sin α ´ σ cos αq (81) ` 1 2 γ 2 ` σ 2 ´ f 2 ˘ .</formula><p>This suggests that the traditional approximation is well adapted to the treatment of the tidal response of thin atmospheres, where the horizontal wavelength of dominating propagating modes is comparable to the radius of the planet in order of magnitude. In the case of small wavelengths (γ ! 1), we recover the domain of validity established by early studies: 2Ω ! σ if the layer is weakly stably-stratified or convective (N ! σ), and 2Ω À σ in the case of strong stable stratification (N " σ). Particularly, the bottom left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> show that the boundary of the domain of validity of the approximation corresponds to 2Ω " N in the regime of strong stable stratification, which is in good agreement with the diagnosis done in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a)</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 21)</ref>. This boundary is slightly modified by the radiative/diffusive cooling (top left panel), with a downward translation of magnitude p1{2q log pσ{σ 0 q resulting from the equality of the dominating terms of Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(81)</ref>: pσ{σ 0 q N 2 " f 2 s .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Conclusions</head><p>Motivated by the understanding of the role played by thermally forced gravity waves in the atmospheric tidal response of a terrestrial planet submitted to the irradiation of its host star, we have studied the tidal perturbation of a local atmospheric section in solid rotation with the body. In this ab initio approach, inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gerkema &amp; Shrira (2005)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Mathis et al. (2014)</ref>, the dynamics of tidal waves are reduced to the essentials, which allowed us to conserve the whole physics of tides, and particularly all the components of the Coriolis acceleration while avoiding complexities associated with spherical geometry. The goal of this work was to provide a diagnosis of the results obtained in our previous global analytic study <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>) where two asymptotic regimes were identified: a weakly stratified regime inducing a Maxwell-like tidal torque applied on the atmosphere and a strongly stably-stratified one associated with a weak torque. We wrote the linearized equations of tides for a fluid section characterized by radial background distributions and dissipative processes modelled with a Newtonian cooling as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair- Desrotour et al. (2017a)</ref>. We computed analytic solutions describing the forced oscillatory response in two typical cases: a homogeneous fluid with uniform background distributions and an isothermal atmosphere. In both cases, the tidal torque exerted and the energy dissipated by diffusive/radiative processes were also derived analytically. We showed that tidal regimes are defined by a small number of physical parameters, namely the tidal (σ), inertia (2Ω), Brunt-Väisälä (N) and radiative (σ 0 ) frequencies, and the ratio between the horizontal wavelength of a propagating tidal wave and the pressure height-scale of the fluid (γ).</p><p>Considering the semidiurnal stellar tide, we recovered the results obtained with global modelings in early works. The dependence of the tidal torque on the forcing frequency can be described by a Maxwell model in the vicinity of spin-orbit synchronous rotation ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leconte et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>) in the case of weakly stably-stratified or convective atmospheres. If the stratification is strong, gravito-inertial waves are generated. This wavelike response breaks the large scale quadrupolar hydrostatic elongation caused by the stellar heating at zero order, so that there is no net tidal bulge. As a consequence, the amplitude of the tidal torque diminishes and becomes negligible compared to the convective case. This suggests that Venus-like planets with a stably-stratified atmosphere are likely to tend towards spin-orbit synchronous rotation while those with a convective atmosphere rather evolve towards nonsynchronized states like Venus, as predicted by the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. (2017a)</ref>. Hence, the Cartesian approach allows us to explore the domain of parameters, to confirm the previously identified asymptotic regimes and to highlight the continuous transition between them. This transition occurs for N " tγσ, γσ 0 u. In the case of Venus itself, the structure of the atmosphere is characterized by a strong negative temperature gradient near the surface of the planet ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Seiff et al. 1980)</ref>. This implies that the densest layers of the atmosphere, which are also the better viscously coupled to the solid part, are neutrally stratified. Hence, our simplified modeling suggests in this case a strong atmospheric torque that agrees with the conclusions of early works dealing the rotation of Venus (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gold &amp; Soter 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dobrovolskis &amp; Ingersoll 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Correia &amp; Laskar 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017b</ref>).</p><p>By isolating in obtained solutions a characteristic scaling parameter (ν), we were also able to delimit the domain of validity of the traditional approximation used in global models as a function of the system's control parameters, and to characterize the asymptotic regimes. In the short wavelengths approximation, we recovered the domain of validity identified in early studies, namely the validity conditions 2Ω ! σ in the case of weakly stratified fluids, and 2Ω ! N in the case of strongly stratified ones <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Friedlander 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Mathis et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Mathis 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Auclair-Desrotour et al. 2017a</ref>). This domain is slightly modified by dissipative mechanisms in this case. In the long wavelength asymptotic regime, where the pressure scale height is smaller than the horizontal wavelength of a propagating mode, we found that the Coriolis terms neglected in the traditional approximation do not affect the tidal response, except at the boundary of the inertial regime, defined by 2Ω " σ. This result is appropriate to characterize the forced response of the fluid up to meso-scale modes, that is the application limit of the f-plane approximation used in our modeling. Therefore, the impact of the traditional approximation on global tidal modes should be studied in general with global modelings, as done by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Ogilvie &amp; Lin (2004)</ref> in the case of giant planets or <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Tort &amp; Dubos (2014)</ref> for atmospheric dynamics.</p><p>However, the local approach developed here still remains an efficient way to peer into the large domain of parameters of atmospheric tidal responses and to clarify the predictions of global modelings obtained with assumptions. Indeed, it offers a simplified but robust picture of the tidal waves dynamics with the essential physical ingredients. Its predictive power on the rotation state of exoplanets as a function of the convective stability of their atmosphere is of great interest with their probe by forthcoming space missions like JWST (Lagage 2015). Such missions will be able to provide constraints on the temperature gradient at different depths in the atmospheres of exoplanets thanks to multi-wavelenght observations in the near IR. In forthcoming studies, we will complete this picture by including in the Cartesian fluid section stratified background flows. These flows are likely to strongly modify the atmospheric tidal response but can-</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Spherical and Cartesian reference frames and systems of coordinates. The vectors Ω and g designate the rotation and the gravity respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Normalized tidal torque as a function of the frequency of the perturber ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb for various values of the Brunt-Väisälä frequency from weak to strong stable stratification, i.e. log pNq " t´8, ´6, ´4, ´2u. The tidal torque is computed using the normalized function given by Eq. (71) and we consider the case of a Venus-like planet with the following set of values: n orb " 1.991ˆ10´7991ˆ991ˆ10991ˆ10´7 s ´1 , Γ 1 " 1.4 (perfect gas), H " 15.9 km, θ " π{3, α " 0 (westward propagating wave), σ 0 " 7.5 ˆ 10´710´7 s ´1 (Leconte et al. 2015), and k K " 2π{λ with λ " 1000 km.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Evolution of the rotation rate of a Venus-like planet for various Brunt-Väisälä frequencies. The normalized frequency ω " pΩ´npΩ´pΩ´n orb q {n orb is plotted as a function of time (Myr) in logarithmic scale. The Brunt-Väisälä frequency N " 10 β is increased from β " ´7 (weak stable stratification) to β " ´3 (strong stable stratification) with a step ∆β " 0.5.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N D C</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1910" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>André</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Anglada-Escudé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Amado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">536</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Arras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">714</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Auclair-Desrotour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">603</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Auclair-Desrotour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">603</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Auclair</forename><surname>Desrotour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Le Poncin-Lafitte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">581</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Atmospheric tides: Thermal and gravitational</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lindzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Reidel</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boué</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">571</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">767</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research (Planets)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cowling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">367</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1941" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dickinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Geller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Atmospheric Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">932</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1968" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dobrovolskis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ingersoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Efroimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">746</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Friedlander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">637</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gastineau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.imcce.fr/trip/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>TRIP 1.3.8, TRIP Reference manual, IMCCE, Paris Observatory</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gerkema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Shrira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">195</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gerkema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nioz</forename><surname>Royal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H M J</forename><surname>Triaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B.-O</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lecture Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">542</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">456</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">356</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">698</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Solving Ordinary Differential Equations I Nonstiff problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hairer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nørsett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd edn.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ingersoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dobrovolskis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-O</forename><surname>Lagage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id.EPSC2015-757</idno>
		<ptr target="http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EPSC2015/EPSC2015&quot;&gt;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EPSC2015&lt;/A&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">European Planetary Science Congress</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-09-27" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2015</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online at &lt;A href=</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leconte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Forget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Charnay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">554</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leconte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">632</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lindzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pure and Applied Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">811</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Neiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tran Minh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Talon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F.-P</forename><surname>Pantillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Zahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sol. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">251</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ogilvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">429</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">613</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ogilvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">610</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">477</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pollack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Atmospheric Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1025</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Prat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lignières</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ballot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-M</forename><surname>Culpin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">598</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">245</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">286</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bolmont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">596</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seiff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kirk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7903</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Spiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Veronis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1960" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dubos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2388</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Annales d&apos;Astrophysique</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
