<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-11T12:27+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">POLARIZATION OF TRAPPIST-1 BY THE TRANSIT OF ITS PLANETS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-05-16">16 May 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sujan</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
							<email>sujan@iiap.res.in</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Indian Institute of Astrophysics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Koramangala 2nd Block</addrLine>
									<postCode>560 034</postCode>
									<settlement>Bangalore</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">POLARIZATION OF TRAPPIST-1 BY THE TRANSIT OF ITS PLANETS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-05-16">16 May 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">(Received 10 February, 2018; Accepted 16 May, 2018)</note>
					<note>Accepted for publication in The Astrophysical Journal Preprint typeset using L A T E X style AASTeX6 v. 1.0</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>stars: individual: TRAPPIST-1 -stars: low-mass -polarization -scattering -planets and satellites: detection -occultations</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>As the first and till date the only one multiple planet hosting dwarf star that is sufficiently cool to form condensate cloud in it atmosphere, Trappist-1 provides unique opportunity to test the efficiency of image polarimetry as a tool to detect and characterize exoplanets around Land late M-dwarfs and Exomoons around directly imaged self-luminous giant exoplanets. Although scattering of light by atmospheric dust particles should produce significant amount of linear polarization in the far optical and near infra-red, the disk-averaged net detectable polarization of the star must be zero owing to spherical symmetry. However, the transit of its planets would give rise to significant asymmetry and produce phase-dependent polarization with the peak polarization occurring at the inner contact points of planetary transit ingress and egress epoch. Adopting the known stellar and planetary physical parameters and employing a self-consistent cloudy atmosphere model of M8 dwarf star, the transit polarization profiles and the expected amount of polarization of Trappist-1 during the transit phase of each individual planets as well as that during simultaneous transit of two planets are presented in this paper. It is emphasized that the amount of polarization expected is within the detection limit of a few existing facilities. If polarization is detected confirming the prediction, time resolved image polarimetry will emerge out as a potential tool to detect and characterize small planets around cloudy ultra-cool dwarfs.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Two decades after the first confirmed discovery of planets outside the solar system <ref type="bibr">(Wolszczan &amp; Frail 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wolszczan 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Mayor &amp; Queloz 1995)</ref>, more than 3000 planets of different size, mass and composition are detected. Most of these planets are found to be orbiting around solar-type star. It is known that Red dwarfs and Brown Dwarfs account for about 80 % of the stellar population in our galaxy <ref type="bibr">(Apai 2013)</ref>. As a consequence search for planets around these ultra-cool dwarfs will enable to test the formation models because it'll provide a complete and comprehensive knowledge on the planetary architecture as a function of the mass of the host. Therefore, the discovery of 7 Earth-sized planets transiting the M8V star Trappist-1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gillon et al. 2016</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gillon et al. , 2017</ref>) is a significant step. Trappist-1 (2MASS J23062928-0502285) is located 12.14 pc from the Sun (Van <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Grootel et al. 2018)</ref>. It is the first planetary system found to transit a very low mass, Jupiter-sized star. The favorable planet-to-star ratio offers the opportunity to probe their atmospheric properties with the current and next-generation telescopes (De Witet al 2016; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barstow &amp; Irwin 2016)</ref>. Furthermore, a unique system such as Trappist-1 enables to test planet formation and evolution theories and to investigate the prospects for habitability among Earth-sized exoplanets orbiting cool M-dwarfs.</p><p>The atmospheres of dwarf stars with spectral type M7 and later are cold enough for the condensation of silicate cloud ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Tsuji et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Allard et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackerman &amp; Marley 2001)</ref>. The spectra of L-dwarfs are well explained by the inclusion of condensate cloud of various species such as iron, forsterite, and enstatite ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cushing et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Marley &amp; Robinson 2015)</ref>. Scattering of thermal radiation by these dust particles in the visible atmosphere of ultracool dwarfs gives rise to significant amount of linear polarization in the far-optical and in the infra-red regions. Linear polarization has been detected in the optical bands from a good number of L-dwarfs covering almost the entire range of spectral types L0-L8 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ménard et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zapatero Osorio et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Tata et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zapataro Osorio et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Miles-Páez et al. 2013</ref>). Scattering by horizontally homogeneous clouds in the atmosphere of a rotation-induced oblate L-dwarf can explain the observed polarization <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Sengupta &amp; Krishan 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Sengupta 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta &amp; Kwok 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta &amp; Marley 2010</ref>).</p><p>Similar to the L-dwarfs, Trappist-1, a dwarf star of M8V spectral type with effective temperature about 2500 K and about the size of Brown Dwarfs, is expected to have thin cloud in the upper atmosphere. Therefore, the thermal radiation of Trappist-1 should also be linearly polarized due to scattering by dust particles. However, as a slow rotator with a spin rotation period as high as 79.2 h ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Luger et al. 2017)</ref>, the object should be almost spherical and hence the disk-integrated polarization of Trappist-1 should be negligible. But, transit by the planets would give rise to significant asymmetry by blocking the stellar disk partially during the transit epoch <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Sengupta 2016)</ref>. As a consequence, transit of planets around Trappist-1 would give rise to net non-zero time-dependent disk integrated polarization. Since Trappist-1 is presently the only discovered ultra-cool dwarf with a cloudy atmosphere and with a system of seven rocky planets, it can very well serve as a test object for verifying the potential of image polarimetry as a tool to detect planets around similar late M-dwarfs and L-dwarfs as well as Exomoon around self-luminous giant exoplanets.</p><p>In this paper, I present the transit polarization profiles for Trappist-1 with specific prediction of the expected amount of polarization. In the next section, the employed atmosphere model and the adopted formalism for calculating the transit polarization is described. In section 3, I discuss the results and in section 4, I conclude that if confirmed, time-resolved image polarimetry will open up a new avenue to detect and characterize exoplanets around ultra-col dwarfs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">METHOD FOR CALCULATING THE TRANSIT POLARIZATION</head><p>The disk-integrated polarization of a spherical star is zero. However, when a planet transit the star, the net polarization during the transit is non-zero owing to the asymmetry caused by partial blocking of the stellar disk. The transit polarization of the star is the product of the intensity and scattering polarization at each radial point along the disk of the star with the fractional circumference occulted by the projection of the planet over the surface of the star. The disk-integrated polarization during the transit phase is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta &amp; Marley (2016)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta (2016)</ref>; <ref type="bibr">Wiktorowicz &amp; Laughlin (2014)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Carciofi &amp; Magalhaes (2005)</ref> :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">p ( t, λ) = 1 F r2 r1 2 [(1 − µ 2 ) 1/2 − r m (t)] 2 − w 2 1 − µ 2 I(µ, λ)p(µ, λ)µdµ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where t is the time since mid-transit and F is the flux of the unobscured star at a given wavelength or band. In the above expression, I(µ, λ) and p(µ, λ) are the wavelength dependent specific intensity and polarization respectively along µ, µ = cos θ = √ 1 − r 2 with θ being the angle between the normal to the surface of the star and the line of sight and r being the radial points along the disk of the primary, 0 ≤ r ≤ 1,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">r 1 = 1 − [r m (t) + w] 2 and r 2 = 1 − [r m (t) − w] 2 , r m (t)</formula><p>is the instantaneous position of the center of the planet and is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">r m (t) = b 2 + 4 (1 − 2w) 2 − b 2 t τ 2 1/2 ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where b = a cos i/R ⋆ is the impact parameter of the planet with a circular orbit of radius a and the orbital inclination angle i and R ⋆ is the radius of the star, w = R P /R ⋆ is the ratio of the planetary radius (R P ) to the radius of the star and τ is the total transit duration given by Scharf (2009)</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">τ = P π sin −1 R p a (1 + w) 2 − b 2 1 − cos 2 i 1/2 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>P being the orbital period of the planet. The physical parameters used are presented in table 1. These are derived by using the values of R P , a, P and i as given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gillon et al. (2017)</ref>. In order to calculate the specific intensity I(µ, λ) and scattering polarization p(µ, λ) for Trappist 1, I have employed the well-used one-dimensional, non-grey, hydrostatic and radiative-convective atmospheric model for the relatively hotter L-dwarfs developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackerman &amp; Marley (2001)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Marley et al. (2002)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Freedman et al. (2008)</ref>. This model fits reasonably well the spectra and photometry of a large number of cloudy L dwarfs at a wide range of wavelengths covering near optical to mid-infrared regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Marley &amp; Robinson 2015)</ref>. The effective temperature of Trappist-1 is T eff = 2516 ± 41 K and surface gravity g = 1686.55ms −2 (Van Grootel et al. 2018). I adopt a grid of atmosphere model with T eff = 2400 K and g = 1000ms −2 . The slightly lower temperature compensates the cloud thickness for a lower surface gravity and hence the model atmosphere does not differ significantly from that of the actual atmosphere of Trappist-1. In fact it is known that the synthetic spectra of L-dwarfs or ultra-cool dwarfs such as Trappist-1 (M8) remain the same for a wide range of surface gravity. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> (upper panel) presents a comparision of the theoretical spectrum to the observed spectral energy distribution of Trappist-1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Burgasser et al 2015)</ref>. Owing to the low spectral resolution of the thoeretical spectrum, a better fit to the observed spectrum at wavelengths longer than 1.4 micron is not achieved. However, polarization changes slowly with wavelength and this resolution is adequate for the present purpose. Note that the polarization profiles are presented in I-and J-band by using the response functions of SDSS filters. The I-and J-bands cover wavelength region from 0.65 to 1.4 micron. Therefore, the models serve the present purpose well.</p><p>In this atmosphere model, spatially uniform dust cloud is included self consistently. The efficiency of sedimentation of cloud particles in the atmospheric models is controlled through a scaling factor f sed . In the present work I adopt f sed = 2.0 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cushing et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Stephens et al. 2009</ref>) that incorporates moderately thick condensate cloud. However, in order to investigate how sensitive the polarization is to the cloud opacity, I have also calculated polarization with 5%, 10% and 15% increase in the dust opacity without changing gas opacity in the model. This does not affect the emergent spectra of the star as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> (bottom panel) but alters the amount of polarization significantly.</p><p>The detailed formalisms as well as the numerical methods for calculating the angle dependent intensity and linear polarization are described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta &amp; Marley (2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">, 2010</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS</head><p>The formation of dust grains in the cloudy atmosphere of ultra-cool dwarfs provides an additional scattering opacity to the gas opacity. The thermal radiation of such cloudy dwarf stars and self-luminous giant exoplanets is polarized by dust scattering in the far-optical and infra-red wavelengths <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Sengupta &amp; Marley 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Marley &amp; Sengupta 2011</ref>). The net non-zero disk integrated polarization of such cloudy objects arises only during the transit epoch unless the object is non-spherical. However, slow spin rotation ensures Trappist-1 has almost perfect spherical symmetry and hence the disk integrated polarization should be zero during non-transit epoch.</p><p>As depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>, the polarization increases significantly with the increase in dust opacity even by 5% of the original cloud model. The scattering opacity is determined by a balance between the upward turbulent diffusion and downward transport by sedimentation of condensates and gas. These are governed by the surface gravity and effective temperature and hence the polarization varies with different effective temperature and surface gravity. While polarization reduces with the decrease in surface gravity, a decrease in temperature causes the cloud base to shift downward yielding a larger column of dust grains in the observed atmosphere and hence the polarization increases with the decrease in effective temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Sengupta 2016)</ref>. Therefore, while the adopted effective temperature of Trappist-1 is slightly less than the actual value, a reduced value of surface gravity considered should yield into the expected amount of polarization of Trappist-1. However, the actual cloud opacity is highly model dependent and so the polarization profile is calculated with varying scattering opacity. The peak polarization at the inner contact points of transit ingress/egress phase is thus determined by the scattering opacity as well as the size of the transiting planet. The amount of polarization is also wavelength dependent. Polarization is found to be maximum at J-band.</p><p>As discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta &amp; Marley (2016)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sengupta (2016)</ref>, the general feature of transit polarization of any star is the double peaked polarization profile that arises because the maximum polarization occurs at the inner contact points of transit ingress/egress phases. For central transit i.e., when the impact parameter b = 0, the projected position of the center of the planet coincides with the center of the star during mid transit giving rise to a symmetry to the projected stellar disk. Hence the disk integrated polarization for central transit or transit with a small value of the impact parameter b is zero or negligibly small during mid transit. Although, the orbital inclination angle of all the seven planets are almost the same, owing to a closer orbit, the values of the impact parameters of Trappist-1b, Trappist-1c, Trappist-1d and Trappist-1e are quite small (see table 1) and hence the amount of polarization during mid transit of these four planets is negligibly small as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. However, as the orbital distance a increases, the impact parameter b increases for i = 0 making the transit significantly off center. Therefore, the polarization is non-zero during the whole transit epoch including the mid transit time of Trappist-1f, Trappist-1g and Trappist-1h (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3)</ref>.</p><p>The polarization increases sharply from zero at the outer contact point and peaks at the inner contact point of transit ingress. Similarly, the polarization falls rapidly to zero at the outer contact point from its peak value at the inner contact point of transit egress. Therefore, the polarization profile can provide the ingress/egress duration τ ingress/egress . The asymmetry to the stellar disk decreases as the planet moves to the center (t = 0) from the limb (t=±τ /2) of the stellar disk. Hence the disk-integrated polarization decreases. However, the peak polarization at the inner contact points of transit ingress/egress phases is independent of the impact parameter but depends on the ratio of the planetary to stellar radii.</p><p>The repeated occurrence of non-zero polarization with double peak would provide the orbital period of the planets.</p><p>The total transit duration can be found from the transit polarization profile and the impact parameter b for a given radius of the star and orbital distance of the planet can be determined from the polarization during the mid transit at t = 0. Hence, the duration of the transit ingress/egress phase will provide an estimation of the size of the planet independent of any limb-darkening model by using the following expression :</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">τ ingress/egress τ total = 1 2 − 1 4 − w (1 + w) 2 − b 2 .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Such a way of estimating the physical parameters of the transiting planet will serve as a complementary of and check for the transit method. Further, any stellar activity such as flare may cause difficulties in confirming the detection of a planet through transit method. But such activities would not affect the polarization profile in the infra-red. Hence time resolved image polarimetry may be advantageous over transit method in detecting planets around cloudy ultra-cool dwarfs.</p><p>Finally, Trappist-1 has a compact planetary system with several planets orbiting close to the star. Therefore, occasionally two or three planets transit the star simultaneousely ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gillon et al. 2016</ref>). Simultaneous transit alters the symmetry and hence the polarization profile. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> the polarization profile is presented for the case when the planet Trappist-1b attains its mid transit phase while the planet Trappist-1c touches the inner contact point of its ingress phase. During the mid transit of Trappist-1b, the symmetry would otherwise give rise to zero polarization as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> but the transit of Trappist-1c would provide the necessary asymmetry and hence the polarzation peaks even during the mid transit (t=0) of Trappis-1b. Therefore, a triple peak polarzation profile arises in such scenario. Similarly, I consider another extreme case when one planet reaches the inner contact point of its egress phase while the second one reaches the inner contact point of its ingress phase. Under such situation, the polarization at the inner contact point of the transit egress epoch of one planet would be the sum of the peak polarization during the inner contact point of the transit ingress/egress epoch of individual planets as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>. Although such occasional event would favour polarimetric observation and detection, repeat image polarimetry during the transit phase of individual planet is required to estimate the physical properties of the planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In this letter, I have presented the transit polarization profiles of Trappist-1 during the individual transit of all the seven planets around it and estimated the expected peak polarization at the inner contact points of transit ingress/egress phase for each planet. Polarization profiles during simultaneous transits of two planets are also presented. For this purpose, the atmospheric model appropriate for Trappist-1 is employed. The theoretical spectrum calculated by using the model atomoshere is copmared with the observed spectral energy distribution of Trappist-1 at the optical. I-and J-bands linear polarization due to scattering by dust grains in the atmosphere of Trappist-1 is calculated by solving the multiple-scattering vector radiative transfer equations. The model estimation predicts detectable amount of transit polarization in both I-and J-bands of Trappist-1 by the transit of all the planets orbiting it.</p><p>Usually it is difficult to detect exoplanets around ultra-cool dwarfs by using the techniques that are employed to look for exoplanets around solar-like stars, e.g., radial velocities, transits, direct imaging, or micro-lensing. Thus, the confirmation of the polarimetric modulation depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>      </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .Figure 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Top panel: Comparison of the model spectrum to the observed spectrum of Trappist-1. Thick line is the theoretical model spectrum and thin line is the observed spectral energy distribution (Burgasser et al 2015). Bottom panel : Comparison of the original model spectrum to that with 5%, 10% and 15% increase in the dust opacity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Same as figure 1 but due to the transit of planets Trappist-1f, Trappist-1g and Trappist-1h.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Polarization profile during simultaneous transits of Trappis-1b and Trappist-1c. Trappist-1b is at mid transit epoch (t=0) when Trappist-1c is at the inner contact point of the transit ingress epoch.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Polarization profile during simultaneous transits of Trappis-1b and Trappist-1c. Trappist-1b is at the inner contact point of its egress epoch while Trappist-1c is at the inner contact point of its ingress epoch. t=0 is the mid transit epoch of Trappist-1b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Physical parameters of the seven planets transiting Trappist-1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Planets 
w = RP /R⋆ b = a cos i/R⋆ τ (mins) 

Trappist-1b 
0.085 
0.125 
36.48 

Trappist-1c 
0.083 
0,161 
42.42 

Trappist-1d 
0.060 
0.172 
49.18 

Trappist-1e 
0.072 
0.126 
57.34 

Trappist-1f 
0.082 
0.380 
62.52 

Trappist-1g 
0.088 
0.419 
68.425 

Trappist-1h 
0.059 
0.454 
75.697 </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>I thank Mark S. Marley for kindly providing the atmosphere model data and Adam Burgasser for kindly providing the observed spectrum of Trappist-1. Thanks are due to Enric Palle for many useful discussions and to the reviewer for providing critical comments and valuable suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ackerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron.Nachr</title>
		<editor>357. Apai, D. 2013</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">556</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Barstow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burgasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Logsdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gagn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Carciofi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Magalhaes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cushing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Astronomy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">635</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1085" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<editor>279. Marley, M. S. &amp; Sengupta, S</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scharf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Extrasolar Planets and Astrobilogy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University Science Books</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Krishan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>L123</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">561</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kwok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maiti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stephens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<editor>30. Wiktorowicz, S. J., &amp; Laughlin, G. P</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">625</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">445</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1147" />
			<publisher>Wolszczan, A. &amp; Frail, D. A</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zapatero</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Béjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J S</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">740</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
