<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:44+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ASTEROSEISMOLOGY OF THE TRANSITING EXOPLANET HOST HD 17156 WITH HST FGS 1</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010-11-01">1 Nov 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edmund</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philip</forename><surname>Nutzman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jørgen</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Las Cumbres Observatory Global Telescope</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Space Telescope Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3700 San Martin Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>21218, 93117</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore, Goleta</settlement>
									<region>MD, CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>60 Garden St</addrLine>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Aarhus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>DK-8000</postCode>
									<settlement>Aarhus C</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ASTEROSEISMOLOGY OF THE TRANSITING EXOPLANET HOST HD 17156 WITH HST FGS 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2010-11-01">1 Nov 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Submitted to The Astrophysical Journal Submitted to The Astrophysical Journal</note>
					<note>Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 11/10/09</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: planetary systems -stars: oscillations -stars: individual (HD 17156) -tech- niques: photometric</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Observations conducted with the Fine Guidance Sensor on Hubble Space Telescope (HST) providing high cadence and precision time-series photometry were obtained over 10 consecutive days in December 2008 on the host star of the transiting exoplanet HD 17156b. During this time 1.0×10 12 photons (corrected for detector deadtime) were collected in which a noise level of 163 parts per million per 30 second sum resulted, thus providing excellent sensitivity to detection of the analog of the solar 5-minute p-mode oscillations. For HD 17156 robust detection of p-modes supports determination of the stellar mean density of ρ * = 0.5301 ± 0.0044 g cm −3 from a detailed fit to the observed frequencies of modes of degree l = 0, 1, and 2. This is the first star for which direct determination of ρ * has been possible using both asteroseismology and detailed analysis of a transiting planet light curve. Using the density constraint from asteroseismology, and stellar evolution modeling results in M * = 1.285 ± 0.026 M ⊙ , R * = 1.507 ± 0.012R ⊙ , and a stellar age of 3.2 ± 0.3 Gyr.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>General knowledge of stellar structure and evolution for normal main-sequence stars has long been a mature topic, with forefront research driven by increasingly precise observational constraints, and theoretical investigations including effects such as heavy element diffusion and overshoot of material at convection zone boundaries. Transiting planets, the first of which HD 209458 was discovered only a decade ago ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Charbonneau et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Henry et al. 2000</ref>) have provided a wealth of detailed physical information about dozens of planets. Of more relevance to the current paper, high quality transit light curves also return a direct determination of the mean density of the host star, ρ * , independent of stellar evolution models (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Seager &amp; Mallén-Omelas 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sozetti et al. 2007, and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Winn 2008)</ref>. Asteroseismology has long promised fundamentally new and precise constraints on stellar structure and evolution (e.g. see review of <ref type="bibr">Brown &amp; Gilliland 1994)</ref>, and with the use of state-of-the-art ground-based spectroscopic radial velocities prompted largely by the burgeoning efforts for RV planet discovery has delivered several successes in recent gillil@stsci.edu 1 Based on observations with the NASA/ESA Hubble Space Telescope, obtained at the Space Telescope Science Institute, which is operated by AURA, Inc., under NASA contract NAS <ref type="bibr">5-26555.</ref> years (e.g. see review of . The advent of space-based photometric missions promises to provide robust results from oscillations on a much larger number of stars, as hinted at by the early successes from CoRoT <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Michel 2008)</ref>. Detection of several low-angulardegree p-modes also provides a direct constraint on ρ * as will be discussed at length for HD 17156 herein.</p><p>In this paper we present photometry of the host for the unusually interesting exoplanet HD 17156b given its long orbital period of 21.2 days discovered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Fischer et al. (2007)</ref> in a Doppler survey, and shown to have transits by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barbieri et al. (2007)</ref>. The nearly 10 days of high precision HST photometry suffices to obtain secure detection of some 8 individual p-modes, an accurate determination of the asteroseismic large separation, and hence accurate measure of the stellar mean density. A companion paper by <ref type="bibr">Nutzman et al. (2010)</ref> will present analyses of complementary HST observations through three separate transits of HD 17156b to fix ρ * from transit light curve analysis. This provides the first instance of obtaining such precise measures of this fundamental stellar parameter from two entirely different techniques, thus providing not only the intrinsically interesting physical measurement and associated interpretations, but also providing a test of the two methods. We find a gratifying level of consistency from independent application of the two techniques, thus providing enhanced confidence that both perform as expected.</p><p>Selection of HD 17156 as the target and the observations obtained for the asteroseismology part of this project are discussed in §2. Extensive, and unique, procedures invoked for the analysis of HST Fine Guidance Sensor time-series photometry are discussed in §3. The evidence for, and detailed results of power spectral and related analyses for stellar oscillations are covered in §4. §5 presents interpretation using stellar evolution and eigenfrequency analyses. Comparisons with the transit light curve analyses are provided in §6 along with a look to the future prospects for similar results on a much larger number of systems from the Kepler Mission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">TARGET CHOICE AND OBSERVATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Target Choice and Background on FGS Use for Photometry</head><p>The underlying motivation of this study, anticipated for years in application with the Kepler Mission, was to simultaneously challenge the two relatively new techniques of transit light curve analysis and asteroseismology by comparing results for ρ * on the same object, while at the same time providing a new benchmark of accuracy for stellar and planetary quantities. Application of asteroseismology, with well-posed observations, promises determinations of stellar density to &lt;1%, and ages to &lt;10% -very desirable constraints on stellar structure and evolution. However, to reach such results requires a large allocation of observing time, both to reach the necessary precisions of better than a meter per second if through radial velocities, or near 1 part-permillion (ppm) if through broadband photometry, and to reach the necessary frequency resolution of order 1 µHz. For photometry these constraints essentially come down to requiring that of order 10 12 photons be collected over a period spanning about 10 days, and for which near Poisson limited results can be maintained. The best groundbased attempt with photometry to date involved using a longitude-distributed network of 4-m telescopes for a one week period in 1992 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gilliland et al. 1993</ref>) to find oscillations in a cluster of slightly evolved stars expected to have favorable amplitudes of a few times solar; although a technical success this study failed to detect oscillations. The capability of HST to provide successful asteroseismology of solar-like stars has long been expected to hold, but the necessity of dedicating 10 days of observations to one bright star has not supported successful applications. In the fall of 2008 HST had lost the use of its primary instruments, ACS, NICMOS and STIS, leaving only the imager WFPC2 with nearly 15 year on-orbit in service. In addition, Side A of the HST electronics communication package required to utilize WFPC2 failed, thus precipitating a delay in the much anticipated recent servicing mission to upgrade Hubble's instruments. When use of Side B did not initially succeed, we submitted this program to allow good use of the remaining science capability of HST at that time: the Fine Guidance Sensors ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Nelan et al. 2008</ref>). The FGS can provide exquisite interferometric position determinations, and time series photometry through summing the counts of the 4 photomultipliers (PMTs) on each FGS in POSition mode, as well as high angular resolution, narrow field interferometry with TRANSfer mode observations, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Nelan et al. (2008)</ref> for in-depth discussion of general FGS capabilities.</p><p>Our application for DD time on HST was granted as GO/DD-11945, "Asteroseismology of Extrasolar Planet Host Stars". Our photometric requirements from the FGS exceeded those reached in its previous use, which usually involved single-orbit visits timed to coincide with ingress or egress of planet transits ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Wittenmyer et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bean 2008)</ref>. Extensive experience has shown with other instruments on HST that during the first orbit, as the spacecraft thermally adjusts at a new orientation, photometric stability is much lower than in successive orbits. We were initially granted a test block of 8 contiguous orbits to coincide with a transit of HD 17156b. As we expected, after the first orbit much better stability followed and these observations are discussed and used in <ref type="bibr">Nutzman et al. (2010)</ref>. With this successful demonstration of FGS capability we were granted the 150 orbits necessary to follow HD 17156 for 10 days during which it was in the Continuous Viewing Zone (CVZ) of HST for much of this time.</p><p>The choice of HD 17156 as a target followed from a review of all 42 then known transiting planet host stars to see which would hold the best prospect of asteroseismology with a 10 day block of dedicated HST time with FGS. Adopting stellar parameters from Frederic Pont's table at http://www.inscience.ch/transits (no longer activethe equivalent, albeit updated information may be found at http://exoplanet.eu) and scalings for expected oscillation properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Kjeldsen &amp; Bedding 1995)</ref> resulted in a prediction of amplitudes at 6.9 ppm for HD 17156. With 10 days in the HST CVZ a signal-to-noise of ∼ 7 was predicted for the highest amplitude modes (and ultimately close to the value reached) for these FGS observations. Since this S/N for p-mode detections was well above that predicted for any other transiting planet host, and the system is unusually interesting given its 21.2 day period compared to the more common 3 -5 days of Hot Jupiters studied to date, the target choice was clear.</p><p>Although the discovery paper for HD 17156 appeared only three years ago, the system is now very well studied. In addition to its 21.2 day orbit, the planet has an eccentricity of 0.68. HD 17156 is one of just three transiting extrasolar planets for which Rossiter-McLaughlin radial velocity observations through transit have determined the relative stellar rotation and orbital plane alignments to good accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Cochran 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Narita et al. 2009</ref>). For HD 17156 the stellar rotation and orbit of HD 17156b are well aligned. Asteroseismology holds the promise of also providing information on the stellar rotation angle relative to the plane of the sky when rotational splitting of individual nonradial oscillation modes can be detected. For HD 17156 the Rossiter-McLaughlin study of <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Narita et al. (2009)</ref> fixes v sin i at 4.07 ± 0.28 km s −1 , which coupled with the estimate of 1.45 R ⊙ for HD 17156 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. 2009</ref>) leads to an estimate of the stellar rotation period of 18.6±1.4 days. Since our observations span only half the expected rotation period, rotational splitting of nonradial mode frequencies will remain under our frequency resolution. (In principle the full splitting for l = 2, m = ±2 modes could be over-sampled by a factor of two with our window, but our marginal signal-to-noise seems unlikely to support such higher order interpretations.) HD 17156 has been well studied spectroscopically ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Fischer et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ammler-von Eiff et al. 2009</ref>), via transit light curve studies that determine stellar density, and augmented with stellar evolution comparisons the stellar mass and radius separately (e.g. see most recent such study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. 2009</ref>), and has a parallax from Hipparcos with a relative error of only 5% <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(van Leeuwen 2007)</ref>. <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 3</ref> will include a summary of T eff , log(g), and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref> from the spectroscopic studies, as well as the primary results from this paper. Not only is HD 17156 the best star for these HST observations in a technical sense (CVZ, high count rate possible, and 'large' predicted oscillation amplitudes), it is also near the absolute top of transiting extrasolar planet hosts in terms of intrinsic scientific interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">The Observations</head><p>Observations of HD 17156 with the Fine Guidance Sensor 2 on HST were obtained for 147 contiguous HST orbits spanning 9.67 days over <ref type="bibr">22 -31 December 2008</ref>. Use of FGS2r, which had not previously been used for science observations, and was scheduled for replacement (and now has been replaced) in servicing mission #4 was selected out of extreme caution at subjecting the photomultipliers to a summed count level of order 10 12 photons as would follow for this V = 8.172 star, since some level of lost sensitivity is expected proportional to total source exposure. In the end these observations were measured to have reduced the FGS2r sensitivity by a quite acceptable level of 0.2 -0.3%, suggesting that the better calibrated FGSs could have been safely used. HD 17156 is only 0.6 magnitudes fainter than the level at which the FGS2r digital count registers would saturate, rendering any observations of a brighter target at full aperture impossible ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland et al. 2009</ref>). Since FGS2r had not previously been used for science observations, and since none of the FGSs had been carefully calibrated for detector deadtime a few additional orbits were allocated to this project for the purpose of calibrating the FGS2r deadtime, background, sensitivity and noise properties (see results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland et al. 2009</ref>).</p><p>The Fine Guidance Sensors use photomultipliers (4 in each FGS) located behind first a beam splitter based on the two senses of linear polarization, and then behind two Koesters prisms that generate an interferometric signal. The primary use of the FGSs are to track the pointing of the telescope on guide stars and provide feedback into the pointing control system. Used as a photometer in POS mode the observing FGS (FGS2r in this case) acquires and tracks the target in Finelock, while the two guide FGSs keep the target stably positioned to start with.</p><p>The FGS data is collected at 40 Hz in each of the four PMTs per FGS. Examined at 40 Hz the relative counts from the PMTs behind each Koesters prism show strong (of order one percent) variations with characteristic timescales of about a second. The sum of the two PMTs for each polarization remains much more constant on these short timescales. We used the F583W filter covering 435 -715 nm at full aperture which provides the maximum throughput available from the FGSs.</p><p>After applying a deadtime correction averaging 11.0% the mean number of counts per 30 seconds summed over all 4 PMTs on HD 17156 is 4.96 × 10 7 . Over the 9.67 days of observing a total of 20208 time series points were extracted yielding a total count level of 1.00 × 10 12 photons for which an expected sensitivity limit of 1 ppm would follow if the observations are limited only by Poisson statistics.</p><p>The observations after summing over the 4 separate PMTs in successive blocks of 1200 samples at 40 Hz are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. The data were transformed to relative photometry by dividing each sum by the global average. There are several features in the data cadence to call attention to. The HST orbital period often results in gaps. During the central 6 days of these observations when the target was in the CVZ for HST these gaps result from passing through the South Atlantic Anomaly (SAA) when high particle-event rates require the FGS photomultiplier high voltage (HV) to be shut down. Toward the start and end of the 10 days gaps also follow from occultations from the Earth as the CVZ viewing is lost. True CVZ blocks can be seen in the 2nd through 7th days of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> with up to 9 consecutive HST orbits of unbroken data collection. A gap occurs over HJD = 27.05 -27.33 when for unknown reasons (particle hit in electronics perhaps) lock was lost and FGS2r ceased observation of HD 17156. During this 6 hour period FGS1 and FGS3 continued to track their guide stars, and FGS2 observed sky, or at least a close approximation of such about 26 arcseconds from the star -this would prove useful in calibrating corrections for sky background. Time series points for HD 17156 have only been used from periods when data quality flags show FGS2r remained in fine lock. The first data point is at HJD 22.63362 (with leading 2454800 suppressed) with the last at HJD 32.30393 for coverage of 9.67 days during which data was collected. The duty cycle (fraction of total time during which photons were usefully collected) during this interval was 72.6% reflecting the high observing efficiencies possible with HST. Clearly the data structure will introduce aliases in power spectra associated with the orbital period of HST and the one per day cycling of CVZ periods unbroken by the SAA.</p><p>The goal of this project is to detect several independent modes of oscillation on HD 17156, the highest amplitude of which is expected to be ≤ 10 ppm, and to obtain a S/N of several per mode in doing so. The simply extracted time series shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> show variations peak-to-peak at a range of 1%, or 1000 times larger than the peak intrinsic variations expected from the star. Fortunately (and by design, we would not have attempted this otherwise) the stellar oscillations for HD 17156 are expected to have periods of 6.5 -13 minutes, i.e. well separated from the bulk (but not all) of characteristic time scales reflected in the systematics apparent in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. The next section will explain the rather extreme reduction steps taken to bridge the gap between simply obtained, and necessary, noise levels in these data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">REDUCTION OF FGS2R ASTEROSEISMIC DATA</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Removal of HST Orbital Artifacts</head><p>We have experimented with starting the data reductions using the individual 40 Hz level counts from each of the four contributing PMTs. Having found no advantages in considering the highest frequencies, we have settled on analyzing 30 second (1200 samples at 0.025 second) sums. We have also explored analyzing the pairs of PMTs separately, and again no useful utility in doing so was uncovered. The only exception to working with 30 second sums over all four PMTs is that we have applied the deadtime correction for the FGS electronics separately for each PMT at the 40 Hz level, and subtracted the relatively unimportant detector background count level of ∼3 per sample per PMT ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland et al. 2009</ref>). The equation adopted for deadtime is (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland et al. 2009</ref> and references therein):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C T = C M /(1.0 − C M (T D /T I ))<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where C T is the true number of counts within the sampling interval of T I = 0.025 seconds, C M is the recorded number of counts in this interval, and the T D have values of 210.6, 306.0, 260.3 and 286.0 nano-seconds for the four PMTs. In a general sense the correction for detector deadtime is relatively unimportant in this paper, but essential for the analysis of transit depths since both the absolute count level and changes to that scale with this correction. Continuing discussion of reductions by reference to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.  1</ref>, note that after each gap in the observations there is a rapid rise in the relative intensity. The sequence within each new observation (single orbits of HST normally, up to 9 consecutive orbits when in the Continuous Viewing Zone) is that the two guide FGSs turn on and establish "fine lock" on guide stars, and only then is the High Voltage (HV) turned on for the science FGS and fine lock guiding established on HD 17156. This results in 40 Hz time series on HD 17156 starting at zero before HV is turned on, a rapid (∼0.1 second) transition from zero to ∼97% of full counts at HV turn on and an exponential ramp up to the full count level over ∼5 minutes. To facilitate correcting the data during the ∼5 minutes of stabilization at the start of each observing sequence, of which we have 101 occurrences in our 10 days, the 30 second data sums are always started the same number of 40 Hz steps after HV turn on as evidenced by rapidly rising counts. The offset between HV turn on and the start of the first 30 second sum has been chosen as 21.5 seconds, a somewhat arbitrary offset that puts the first 30 second sum at about 0.995 of the ultimate count rate. More on treating the ramp up of counts is provided later.</p><p>A first HST orbit which included brief TRANS mode observations to search for companions to HD 17156, and the start of time series observations in POS mode has been discarded, and is not shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. The TRANs mode observations show that HD 17156 appears to be a point source to the resolution of FGS2r, thus a stellar companion with a projected separation greater than about 0.015 arcsecond with a δV smaller than about 3 can be excluded. Since HD 17156 has a Hipparcos distance of ∼78 pc (van Leeuwen 2007), 0.015 arcseconds corresponds to ∼1.1 AU. The published RV data do not suggest a stellar mass body with period less than a few years, so between FGS and RV, companions with δV ≤ 3 are excluded.</p><p>A number of features are immediately obvious from inspection of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>: (a) The data values trend downward by about 0.3% over the 10 days. This has been separately established to be instrumental, at least at a precision level of ∼0.1% by observing the FGS standard Upgren 69 before and after the 10 days which showed a similar drop ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland et al. 2009)</ref>. A minor degradation of PMT sensitivity from exposure to 10 12 photons was expected. (b) The HST orbital timescale is shown by successive vertical tick marks (95.9184 ± 0.003 minutes) to guide the eye (and later reductions). Within HST orbits the time series shows similar waveforms of typical full amplitude ∼0.025%. These waveforms apparently evolve slowly over the 10 days. (Not shown -the two PMT pair sums show different orbital waveforms, with the variations in one being about twice the other, but both seem to show equally consistent orbit-to-orbit waveforms.) (c) At the start of each contiguous block of data the time series show a ramp up of full amplitude ∼0.4% following the HV turn on.</p><p>The initial approach to data reductions, as had apparently worked quite well for the more limited (and simpler orbital waveform) data during the Nov. 7, 2008 transit was based on attempting decorrelations against the x,y pointing records from all three FGSs, and the ratios of counts between PMT pairs in FGS2r itself. These are not shown; it quickly became evident that large features appear in the potential decorrelation vectors that do not appear in these times series data over 10 days.</p><p>We will next show plots similar to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> that show several decomposition terms for the obvious artifacts. These will include in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> a minor additive correction made for varying sky background. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> will document a slow variation in time, picking up time scales that are long compared to the HST orbit. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref> will show an HST orbital wave form that is allowed to evolve slowly in time.</p><p>The HV ramp up in counts will be detailed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>. The factors for the slow variation in time, the orbital waveform, and the HV ramp are solved for in an iterative, least squares procedure. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref> will show a final tweak that is derived after the above iterative solution. We next detail these corrections. These corrections are applied to the raw time series such that subtraction of the </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1.">Subtraction of sky and particle backgrounds</head><p>As noted in §2 the data gap over HJD = 27.05 -27.33 proved useful for deriving a proxy for variations in the sky background. FGS1 and FGS3 both observed stars much fainter than our target HD 17156. In order to keep the bearings in the FGSs lubricated the guide FGSs were rotated between stars -FGS1 alternated between two at V = 11.50 and 11.53 (×21.5 fainter than HD 17156) and FGS3 alternated between V = 12.97, 13.48, 14.31 stars (×83 -286 fainter than HD 17156). Changes of background occur for two reasons: (1) variations in the background light, e.g. scattered from the bright Earth limb, and (2) changes in the charged particle flux inducing counts in the PMTs. Complete discussion developing FGS1 and FGS3 count rate changes as a proxy for FGS2r need not be recounted in detail here -FGS2r is no longer on the telescope and was only used for science observations for the current program. Suffice it to note that minor differences in scaling for each of FGS1 and FGS3 to FGS2r background changes exist, and these are slightly different between contributions from light and charged particle induced counts. Also complicating this, one of the FGS1 stars was an obvious variable, but for which the intrinsic variations could be filtered out. Fortunately, the 6 hour gap while FGS2r was observing only sky provided good data for calibrating use of FGS1 and FGS3 as proxies, and the implied corrections as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> are very minor for the extremely bright HD 17156. The subtraction for sky is performed before any of the more important corrections to be detailed next are developed in an iterative sense. Only the occasional brush with outer SAA regions leads to spikes that still remain under 0.09%, and these are well determined. We believe that uncertainties in the sky subtraction are quite unimportant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2.">Slow variation of count rate</head><p>The slowly varying count rate is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> and has been derived by running a median filter of full width equal to 2.2 HST orbits over the data of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> (this is done only after sky subtraction and having accounted for the orbital wave form and HV ramp terms to be discussed next). This filtering should have virtually no impact on stellar oscillations for which we expect time scales of 5-15 minutes in HD 17156, while the filter is 211 minutes wide.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3.">HST orbit induced orbital waveform</head><p>The most interesting and important artifact in the data to be dealt with arises from highly repeatable systematics tied to the HST orbit. The source of these variations is treated as unknown for these purposes, and it is unknown. The orbital waveform derived from the data is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>. To derive this an assumed HST orbital phase is generated for all the data points (the HST orbital period is allowed to change later as needed to produce optimal results, but a good value is easily derived from inspection). The waveform is solved for on each of 1000  phase points spanning an HST orbit with weights set as exp(−(δt/10.4) 2 ) where δt is the time in seconds that the center of given 30 second sums is out of phase alignment for the orbital phase point being solved for. Essentially, one makes a stack of all the data points folded on the assumed HST orbital period and makes a weighted average at each phase point as the ratio of the dot product of data and weights divided by the sum of the weights.</p><p>In practice this solution either does not (initially) use the points impacted by HV turn on, or (later) includes these points after correction for the HV ramp. Likewise, the solution assumes the slow variation shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> has first been removed. The apparent slow variation in time of the orbital waveform is included by forming not a simple weighted sum at each phase point, but rather a quadratic fit over the 10 days in time. Later in the iteration cycle this is increased to fitting a cubic in time. Finally, with the orbital waveform in hand, which consists of the zero point, linear, quadratic and cubic polynomial terms at each of 1000 phase points, interpolation is used to provide the correction at the center of each 30 second data point. We do not claim that this nested, iterative solution for the orbital waveform provides either a unique, or optimal correction. However, inspection of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1 and 4</ref> shows that the derived orbital correction does an excellent job of matching features, and thus removing the HST-orbit induced systematics. a </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.4.">High Voltage ramp up</head><p>The correction factor for the HV ramp period is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>. As discussed earlier each 30 second sum is initiated (to ∼0.01 second rms) at exactly the same offset following HV turn on. To first order we assume that after each HV turn on successive data points experience the same suppression of count rate. But we can do better. The offsets in successive accumulated sums after HV turn on show a strong correlation against the length of time the HV was off, equivalently the length of time the PMTs and FGS electronics were not experiencing a high photon flux. After removing the linear correlation with time gap a minor dependence on time over the 10 days is also clear. In practice the solution for each successive HV turn on point is formed as a multi-linear regression over the time gap, and time (ignoring only the case following the large 6 hour time gap which is not consistently off by this amount). This solution is followed for the first 135 points in sequences, although most of the effect is restricted to the first 5-8 minutes. Following all corrections the scatter of points near the start of observing sequences is no larger than the general scatter in the time series. The HV ramp is corrected with essentially no residual error, thus restoring some 12 hours of data that would otherwise need to be dropped since the variations in these time periods contain frequency components that would directly affect the ability to cleanly detect oscillations of 5 -15 minutes. a </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.5.">Residual orbital corrections</head><p>After having applied the several correction factors discussed above, it was clear from inspection that some obvious, albeit much smaller, residuals remained. A quadratic fit to each individual data segment has been effective in dealing with much of the residuals. Before applying this correction the overall rms had been reduced to 172.22 ppm, after applying a quadratic fit over each data segment as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref> the fully corrected data are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7</ref>. This is the time series that will be used later to form power spectra and search for evidence of p-modes. The time series rms here is 163.86 ppm. The deadtime corrected count level would imply a limit of 141.93 ppm at 30 seconds. Based on these numbers the removal of artifacts has provided data within 15% of the Poisson limit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Effect on Power Spectrum Frequency Content</head><p>With the corrected time series in hand as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7</ref>, we are now ready to explore evidence for coherent oscillations. With an rms of 163.86 ppm over 20202  data points retained (dropping 6 with 4-σ deviations), the noise level is expected to be 1.15 ppm globally in amplitude, likely lower and near 1.0 ppm at frequencies beyond 1.5 mHz. A power spectrum is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref> over 0.5 to 4.0 mHz. Below about 1 mHz the reduction steps discussed above, coupled with large systematics do not provide useful information on any stellar variations. Above about 2.5 mHz inspection shows that the resulting power spectrum seems only to reflect noise. Based on published scaling relations and knowledge of the stellar parameters, we would expect oscillations peaking over 1.5-2.0 mHz at perhaps 30% higher than solar amplitude, with a large separation of some 87 µHz. The errors on stellar parameters, in particular the mean stellar density of 0.589 g cm <ref type="bibr">−3</ref> , and -0.103, +0.066 1-σ errors from <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. (2009)</ref>, project to a large separation of 87.3 µHz with a 1-σ range of 79.3-92.0 µHz. The upper panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref> shows a restricted range of 1.0 to 2.6 mHz for the power spectrum. A window function is shown as the middle panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref>. This was formed by generating a time series on the observed cadence with very low amplitude white noise and a large amplitude sinusoid at the same (1.7211 mHz) frequency as the highest peak in HD 17156. The most prominent sidelobes are at multiples of the HST orbit as expected, with smaller features reflecting the daily changes forced by SAA avoidance.</p><p>Some of our reduction steps discussed above have been rather drastic. In particular the orbital waveform correction shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref> will suppress any real oscillation frequencies that happen to coincide with HST orbital harmonics (multiples of the 173.828 µHz orbital frequency). To quantify this we have injected a test signal of 60 ppm into the raw data ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1)</ref>, then performed all of the reductions detailed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 2 -6</ref>, following this with a new power spectrum. This is done at every frequency for which the power spectrum is evaluated. The ratio of power at the injection frequency to the input value then forms the response function shown in the bottom panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref>. As expected, signals at harmonics of the HST orbit are strongly suppressed. However, the portion of frequency phase space in which signal power is suppressed by more than 20% (response function &lt;0.8) is only 4.7%. Knowledge of the response function should be taken into account in searching for evidence of p-mode oscillations. The response function is fixed in frequency, while of course the sidelobes of the window function shift in concert with source mode frequencies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">EVIDENCE FOR STELLAR OSCILLATIONS</head><p>The asteroseismic analysis of the HD 17156 data has been performed using the pipeline developed at the Kepler Asteroseismic Science Operations Center as de-  Oscillation frequencies for low-degree, p-modes are well approximated by a regular series of peaks for which the oscillation frequencies are given by the approximate asymptotic relation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ν nl ≈ ∆ν 0 (n + l/2 + ǫ) − D 0 l(l + 1)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where ∆ν 0 = (2 R 0 dr/c) −1 corresponds to the inverse of the sound travel time across the stellar diameter, and closely relates to the stellar mean density via:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">∆ν 0 ≈ 135(M * /R 3 * ) 1/2 µHz<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where M * and R * are the stellar mass and radius in solar units, and the large separation for the Sun is approximately 135 µHz.</p><p>In the above equations n is the radial order, and l the angular degree of trapped oscillation modes. D 0 is sensitive to the sound speed near the stellar core, and ǫ is a correction factor absorbing minor frequency dependent corrections sensitive to the stellar surface layers. A recent review of the theory of solar-like oscillations may be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Christensen-Dalsgaard (2004)</ref>.</p><p>Although individual peaks may be visible in the power spectrum first shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref>, guided by an expectation given the scaling relations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kjeldsen &amp; Bedding (1995)</ref> for largest amplitudes of about 7 ppm near 1.65 mHz, these results are in a low-SNR regime in which reliance on existence of evenly spaced peaks in frequency must be an inherent part of the process of coaxing information on the oscillations from the data.</p><p>A smoothed version of the power spectrum is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10</ref> which clearly shows the excess of power for HD 17156. The philosophy behind this analysis is developed in order to avoid the stochastic nature of the excitation and damping of individual oscillation modes. In order to measure the oscillation amplitude in a way that is independent of these effects, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Kjeldsen et al. (2005</ref> have suggested a method that involves heavily smoothing the power spectrum in order to produce a single hump of excess power that is insensitive to the fact that the oscillation spectrum has discrete peaks. Following  we smoothed the power spectrum by convolving (in power) with a Gaussian having a FWHM of 4 times the large separation.   <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2009)</ref> we first determine the value of the large separation that best fits the power spectrum, as was outlined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Christensen-Dalsgaard et al. (2007)</ref>. The idea is to match to the power spectrum a series of peaks described such that they follow the asymptotic relation (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref>). To suppress the effect of the last term in that equation (giving rise to the so-called small frequency separation; see below) and avoid being sensitive to the small deviations from the asymptotic description, the analysis is carried out for a smoothed power spectrum ¯ P (ν). Specifically, this is obtained from the original power spectrum through Gaussian smoothing with a FWHM of 3 µHz. We now sum the power at uniformly spaced frequencies ν k = ∆ν(k/2+ǫ 0 ) corresponding to the leadingorder asymptotic expression, by calculating</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">F (∆ν, ǫ 0 ) = 2n0−∆k k=2n0−∆k ¯ P (ν k ) ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>as a function of trial values of ∆ν and ǫ 0 , for a suitable central radial order n 0 and a suitable range ∆k. For each value of ∆ν we determine the maximum F max (∆ν) of F (∆ν, ǫ 0 ) as a function of ǫ 0 . This defines what we call the matched filter response, as a function of ∆ν. Note that the procedure essentially determines the almost uniform separation of ∆ν/2 between the nearly degenerate peaks corresponding to even and odd degrees (this will be plotted transformed to ∆ν). In our analysis we varied ǫ 0 between 1.0 and 1.5 (typical values found from stellar models), and took ∆k = 5, to include a total of 11 peaks in the analysis. The result of using trial values for the large separation between 40 and 120 µHz is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>, for n 0 = 19.5, 20, 20.5, 21 and 21.5. The maximum matched filter response is found at 83.60 µHz and clearly does not depend on n 0 within the range used. Note that sampling the spectrum at a frequency separation of ∆ν/2, and over a fixed range of radial orders, leads to a single peak in the response, unlike other types of comb analysis. The results shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref> yielding ∆ν 0 ≈ 83.6 µHz are stable and robust. In particular, the same value of the large separation can also be found by considering only the first, middle or last half of the data sets, and it also continues to be seen if the strongest peak in the power spectrum at 1721.2 µHz is arbitrarily set to zero. Thus the 9.7 days of HST observations of HD 17156 with FGS2r have provided a secure detection of solar-like pmodes. Further quantification and use of the large separation follows below.</p><p>The next stage in the analysis attempts to fix further details of the oscillation frequencies. A goal here is to determine the small separation, which would provide constraints on the stellar age if possible, and to provide individual frequencies for as many modes as possible. A necessary associated goal will be to determine mode identifications, i.e. corresponding n and l with specific frequencies. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref> shows the result of folding the amplitude spectrum at 83.5 µHz (taking into account the 83.44 µHz splitting from fits to individual mode frequencies below) over the range of 1.2-2.4 mHz. The presence of strong contrast in this figure is simply another way of demonstrating that 83.5 µHz is the correct large separation, e.g. folds at other values would show less contrast similar to the fall-off in distribution of the matched-filter response function of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref> away from 83.5 µHz. The expectation is that modes of l = 0, 1, and 2 only will be visible, with the modes at l = 0, and 2 nearly degenerate except for the small separation term of Eq. (2). This leads to the expectation that a single isolated peak in this figure will correspond to l = 1, while a doubled peak with frequencies differing by much less than the large separation will represent the l = 0 and 2 modes. Guidance from theoretical models to be further discussed in §5 has led to the identification of modes provided in the caption to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.  12</ref> and in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. One might also expect to have a higher signal from the l = 0 modes than from the l = 2 modes in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref> which is not the case. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kjeldsen, Bedding &amp; Christensen- Dalsgaard (2008)</ref> give amplitude ratios of l = 2/0 for the Sun as 0.81, 0.75, and 0.67 at wavelengths of 402, 500 and 862 nm respectively, which for the flux weighted centroid of these FGS observations at about 550 nm implies an expected ratio of 0.74. It might also be expected that the number of l = 0 modes detected would exceed l = 2; again this is not the case. In fact, due to the stochastic nature of the excitation it would not be surprising for modes with l = 2 sometimes to exceed the l = 0 mean amplitudes. Of the three stars with high S/N oscillations discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Chaplin et al. (2010)</ref>, KIC 3656476 has a ∆ν nearest HD 17156 and it shows equal numbers of detected l = 0 and 2 modes, and in 2 of the 4 jointly highest pairs of these the l = 2 amplitudes are larger than l = 0. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> provides the individual frequencies that follow from identifying the 10 highest peaks in the power spectrum. These all have a signal-to-noise ratio in excess of 4 in the power spectrum of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref>. From the asymptotic relation we identify 8 of the 10 highest frequencies. Their degree and order are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The errors in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> are estimated from simulations of the time series. We created a large number of stochastically excited modes with a mode lifetime of 3 days (similar to the lifetime of modes in the Sun) and estimated the accuracy with which we could detect the frequencies (taking peak amplitudes at same SNR as in the present data) in a time series with same sampling as the present data. A lifetime longer than 3 days would have resulted in smaller estimated frequency errors than indicated, while the errors would be larger if the mode lifetime is shorter than 3 days. The identification of the 8 frequencies that fit the comb structure should not be seen as an unbiased frequency identification since it relies on selection of the modes that fit the comb structure for l=0, 1 and 2. We also assume the existence of the asymptotic relation and the structure of stellar model frequencies to fix the identification. Another possible approach would be to use a wider frequency range when identifying the modes or use modes with lower amplitude. We have tried to use more modes and the fit to the stellar models does not depend (within the error bars) on the exact number of peaks included in the analysis. In the end we decided to use the 10 strongest peaks as a way to ensure that we only work with the most significant peaks and of those 10, 8 peaks agreed with the asymptotic relation corresponding to the comb power in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref>.</p><p>We have carried out a weighted least-squares fit of the asymptotic relation, Eq. (2), to the 8 identified frequencies, estimating the errors in coefficients from a Monte Carlo simulation. The resulting coefficients are: ∆ν 0 = 83.44 ± 0.15 µHz, D 0 = 0.90 ± 0.19 µHz, and the surface term ǫ = 1.15 ± 0.04. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> shows the power spectrum from <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref> after smoothing with a Gaussian of FWHM = 3 µHz on which the individual mode frequencies of <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> are included. Over the frequency range 1.2 -2.5 mHz 8 of the 10 highest peaks are flagged as identified.</p><p>The final step in direct analyses of the amplitude spectrum is to assess the amplitude per mode from a smoothed power spectrum, and distribution of amplitudes with frequency following the method described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kjeldsen, Bedding &amp; Christensen-Dalsgaard (2008)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Huber et al. (2009)</ref>. Converting the smoothed power spectrum <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 10)</ref> to power density by multiplying by the effective length of the observing run followed by fitting and subtracting the background noise and then multiplying by the large separation divided by the number of p-modes peaks per radial order scaled to the sensitivity of radial modes we may calculate the mean power per radial mode. The square root is then taken in order to convert to amplitude per oscillation mode (radial modes). The <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 13</ref>.-A version of power spectrum as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref> after a Gaussian smoothing of 3 µHz FWHM has been applied. Frequencies of individual modes as listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> are indicated with vertical bars at the listed frequency. The numerical label of 0, 1, or 2 provides the l value.</p><p>peak amplitude is about 7 ppm for l = 0, quite consistent with pre-observation estimates made using the published stellar parameters and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kjeldsen &amp; Bedding (1995)</ref>. The distribution of amplitudes for radial modes in HD 17156 is contrasted to those in the Sun in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 14</ref>. The extended, non-Gaussian distribution of amplitudes, albeit not well determined here, is similar to those found for Procyon ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arentoft et al. 2008</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">STELLAR EVOLUTION MODELS AND</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTERPRETATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">ASTEC -ADIPLS Analyses</head><p>The stellar evolution models are based on ASTEC (Christensen-Dalsgaard 2008a) and the associated eigenfrequency analysis code ADIPLS <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Christensen-Dalsgaard 2008b)</ref>.</p><p>Briefly, the models use the OPAL equation of state ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Rogers et al. 1996</ref>) and opacities , and the NACRE nuclear parameters ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angulo et al. 1999</ref>). The temperature gradient in the convection zone was computed using the <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Böhm-Vitense (1958)</ref> mixing-length treatment, with a mixing-length of α ML = 2.00 pressure scale heights, roughly calibrated to the corresponding solar models. In some cases convective core overshoot was included, over a distance of α ov min(r cc , H p ), where r cc is the radius of the convectively unstable region and H p is the pressure scale height at this point; the overshoot region was assumed to be fully mixed and adiabatically stratified. Diffusion and settling of helium were treated according to the simplified formulation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Michaud &amp; Proffitt (1993)</ref>. It was assumed that the initial abundances X and Z by mass of hydrogen and helium were related by X = 0.77 − 3Z, corresponding to a galactic enrichment ∆Y of helium determined by ∆Y = 2Z; the values of X and Z were characterized by the observed <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>, assuming a present solar surface composition with Z/X = 0.0253.</p><p>Evolution tracks have been computed to match the classical observed parameters as given in  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 15</ref> shows the theoretical HR diagram with selected evolutionary tracks. The associated <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table  2</ref> lists the models along the evolutionary tracks at which the computed eigenfrequencies best match the observed frequencies (see §5.2). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref>.-Theoretical HR diagram with selected evolutionary tracks, corresponding to the models defined in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. The '+' indicate the models along the full set of evolutionary sequences minimizing the difference between the computed and observed frequencies. The box is centered on the L and T eff as given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. (2009)</ref>, with a size matching the errors on these quantities (T eff error from </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Fitting the Observed Quantities</head><p>We have carried out least-squares fits of the observed frequencies in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> and the observed effective temperature to the computed grid of models. For each model in the grid we computed the mean square difference of the model frequencies ν </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">χ 2 ν = 1 N − 1 nl ν (obs) nl − ν (mod) nl σ(ν nl ) 2 ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where N = 8 is the number of observed frequencies and σ(ν nl ) is the estimated error in the frequencies. This was minimized along each evolution track, characterized by the parameters {M, Z, α ov }. We first determined the model, M min , in the evolution sequence with the smallest value of χ 2 ν . We then assumed that the best-fitting model for these parameters could be obtained from the frequencies ν (mod) nl (M min ) by scaling,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ν (mod) nl = rν (mod) nl (M min ) ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and determined r by minimizing χ 2 ν . The results presented in the following are based on these resulting minimal χ 2 ν along the evolution tracks. According to Eq. (3) the value of r so obtained determines the radius of the best-fitting model as R = r −2/3 R(M min ); the remaining model quantities, including the effective temperature T (mod) eff , were then determined by linear interpolation in radius to this value. Finally, the departure from the observed effective temperature T (obs) eff was included in the final</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">χ 2 = χ 2 ν + T (obs) eff − T (mod) eff σ(T eff ) 2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where σ(T eff ) is the standard error on the effective temperature.</p><p>The results of these fits are illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 16</ref>. A key goal of this analysis is to determine the mean stellar density ρ * of the star; thus panels a) and b) show χ 2 ν and χ 2 against ρ * for all the models in the grid. It is evident that minimizing χ 2 ν along the evolution tracks leads to a narrow range of mean density, with well-defined minima at fixed α ov . It is interesting that some preference is found for models without overshoot, although the difference between the three cases is of limited significance. Including also the constraint of the observed T eff (panel b) produces a well-defined minimum in χ 2 , shifted towards slightly higher ρ * . To quantify the location and width of this minimum we have fitted a parabola to those points that have χ 2 ≤ 3χ 2 min , where χ 2 min = 2.40 is the minimum over all the sequences in the grid. This parabola has a minimum at ρ * = 0.5301 g cm <ref type="bibr">−3</ref> , and indicates a standard error in ρ * of 0.0031 g cm −3 . Augmenting that by a factor of √ 2 to account for further possible systematic errors we arrive at our final estimate:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ρ * = 0.5301 ± 0.0044 g cm −3 .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>The error estimate in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(8)</ref> is derived from the curvature of the χ 2 surface. This estimate may also be cast in the form of a confidence interval in the manner described by, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kallinger et al. (2010)</ref>. This is done by computing the relative probability exp −χ 2 /2 for each model, and then normalizing so that the sum of the probabilities over all models is unity. The desired confidence interval is then obtained by forming the marginal distribution of these probabilities with respect to the stellar mean density, and determining the range of densities that contain the desired fraction of the total probability. In the current case, χ 2 as a function of &lt; ρ * &gt; is very well approximated by a parabola; as a result, the marginal probability distribution is almost indistinguishable from a Gaussian, and the 68% confidence interval agrees closely with the standard error in &lt; ρ * &gt; of 0.0031 g cm −3 given above. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 16</ref>.-Results of fitting the observed frequencies and effective temperature to the grid of stellar models (see text for details). Plusses, stars and diamonds correspond to models with αov = 0 (no overshoot), 0.05, and 0.1, respectively. Panel (a) shows the minimum mean square deviation χ 2 ν of the frequencies (cf. Eq. 5) along each evolution track, against the mean density ρ * of the corresponding models. Panel (b) similarly shows the combined χ 2 (cf. Eq. 7); here the dashed curve is a parabolic fit to those points that have χ 2 ≤ 7.2 (see text). Finally, panel (c) shows χ 2 against the age for the models that minimize χ 2 ν ; the different ridges correspond to the different masses in the grid, the more massive models resulting in a lower estimate of the age.</p><p>As illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 16c</ref> the fit also provides a constraint on the stellar age, although substantially affected by the spread in the mass in the grid, producing a broad nearly flat minimum in χ 2 . On the basis of the plot we estimate the age as 2.8 ± 0.6 Gyr.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref> we have indicated the models minimizing χ 2 ν for all the parameter sets in the grid. These clearly fall in a tightly confined region in the diagram, corresponding to the strongly constrained mean density. In order further to illustrate the properties of the fit we have consid- For each pair (M, Z) we selected the sequence leading to the smallest χ 2 ν . These are the evolution tracks plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref> and with properties listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p><p>To illustrate the quality of the fit of the computed frequencies to the observations, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 17</ref> compares the observed and computed frequencies in anéchelleanéchelle diagram ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Grec et al. 1983</ref>, see caption), for the model in the grid which minimizes χ 2 ν . It is evident that the fit is excellent.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>) has a mass M = 1.30 M ⊙ , [Fe/H] = 0.30 and an age of 2.67 Gyr. The horizontal axis shows frequency distribution within successive 83.6 µHz slices, starting at a frequency of 68.8 µHz, while the vertical axis shows the starting frequencies of the slices. The short horizontal lines indicate the frequency intervals where the response function drops below 50% due to orbital filtering (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref>).</p><p>As an alternative fit to the model grid, which is independent of the individual frequencies, we have selected, on each evolution track, the model that matches the large separation ∆ν. Averaging the resulting mean densities over those models where T eff differs by less than 2σ from the observed value yields ρ * = 0.5290 ± 0.0030 g cm −3 , fully consistent with the more detailed fit.</p><p>We finally note that a potential problem in fitting solar-like oscillations is the effect of the nearsurface layers on the frequencies which is not properly taken into account in the adiabatic modeling considered here. This effect is well known in analysis of helioseismic data (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Christensen-Dalsgaard et al. 1996)</ref>, where it can be isolated, owing to the availability of modes over a broad range of degree. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kjeldsen, Bedding &amp; Christensen-Dalsgaard (2008)</ref> suggested a procedure to eliminate the effect in the analysis of asteroseismic data by assuming a similar functional form as in the solar case, but a potentially different amplitude, to be determined as part of the fit; in addition, the procedure results in an estimate of the mean density of the star, through scaling from a suitable reference model. We have applied this to the observed frequencies in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>; this resulted in insignificant changes to the obtained fits and stellar parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Comparing Asteroseismic and Planet-transit Mean</head><p>Densities with Surface Gravity Asteroseismology, and transit light curve modeling when very precise relative photometry is available, can both provide very precise (even accurate) determinations of the mean stellar density of stars. Since density is a simple function of stellar mass and radius, both asteroseismology and transit light curve modeling tightly constrain allowed choices of mass and radius in individual cases. However, arriving at unique estimates of the stellar mass and radius separately, as for example are needed if one wishes to use these to provide optimal estimates of the mass and radius of hosted planets as needed to advance and challenge the theoretical study of extrasolar planet formation and evolution, requires independent input.</p><p>For both asteroseismology and transit light curve modeling the classical approach to fixing the stellar mass and radius independently, given a measured stellar density, relies on stellar evolution models that best match observed constraints, typically some combination of temperature, metallicity and surface gravity (luminosity in our case with the known parallax, although we use luminosity only as a consistency check), hence bringing in inferences from spectroscopy. Accurate estimates of stellar masses and radii then depend on correct models of both stellar evolution and stellar atmospheres. How good are these? <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 18</ref> illustrates one outstanding issue, that may perhaps exist primarily for stars in the high metallicity domain, as is the case for HD 17156, and for many exoplanet hosts given the strong correlation of high metallicity and existence of such planets . Spectroscopic studies have fixed log(g) to be 4.29 ± 0.06 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Fischer et al. 2007</ref>) and 4.33 ± 0.05 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ammler-von Eiff et al. 2009)</ref>, with very consistent determinations of T eff and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref> between the two independent studies as well; see <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 3</ref> for summaries. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 18</ref> we show the range of stellar masses and radii that jointly meet either the asteroseismic constraint for HD 17156 where M/R 3 is a constant, or the constraint imposed by published spectroscopic log(g) values which requires M/R 2 to be a constant. In this diagram an ideal result would be that the two sets of joint M, R constraints cross at the location of the preferred values obtained from other considerations. Instead, we are left with the result that there is no agreement, the asteroseismic result for radius remains nearly 3 σ away from the log(g) constraint near the preferred mass. Note that the transit light curve analyses of <ref type="bibr">Nutzman et al. (2010)</ref> also impose a constraint with the functional form of that from asteroseismology, in relative terms this would have a central value that falls near, but slightly above the preferred asteroseismic value, with error offsets about 5 times larger than those shown by asteroseismology. Clearly the spectroscopic log(g) of 4.31 is well above the asteroseismic (or transit light curve) value of about 4.19 for HD 17156. Perhaps in the high metallicity domain of interest for HD 17156, and many exoplanet hosts, the stronger lines result in biases for log(g).  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 18</ref> shows that radius estimates based on spectroscopic log(g) determinations are problematic at the 10% level, whereas estimates based on transit timing and on asteroseismology are mutually consistent. This consistency provides a necessary, but not sufficient condition for using the stellar mean density as measured from transit light curves or from asteroseismology to provide the truly desired stellar masses and radii. To verify that we can combine a mean density measurement with stellar evolution models to obtain accurate masses and radii, we must test our techniques against stars for which there are accurate and independent measures of mass and radius. Eclipsing binaries (EBs) comprise the only large set of stars for which such information exists. The mass and radius estimates derived from light curve and radial velocity measurements of EBs are almost independent of theory, and in many cases accuracies of better than 3% can be obtained for both quantities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Torres et al. (2009)</ref> have recently published the fundamental data for all known EBs meeting this standard of accuracy, a list containing 190 stars. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brown (2010)</ref> applied the meandensity analysis to 156 of these (all with masses M * satisfying 0.4M ⊙ ≤ M * ≤ 5M ⊙ ), matching Yonsei-Yale (YY) models ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yi et al. 2001</ref>) to observational estimates of mean density, effective temperature, and metallicity. Comparing radii and masses from model-matching to those measured directly showed that matching the YY models generally yielded accurate results, with systematic errors estimated to be smaller than 2% in radius and 6% in mass. Larger errors can occur for cool and rapidly-rotating stars, in which surface magnetic activity is thought to interfere with convective energy trans-port, leading to radii that are larger than the YY models predict. HD 17156 is, however, a slow rotator that is somewhat hotter than the Sun. For this star, systematic errors resulting from activity should be small, certainly less than 1% based on the expected rotation period of 19 days mentioned in §2, and the lack of any photometric variations in excess of ∼0.1% intrinsic to the star in our FGS photometry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Calibration of Stellar Mass and Radius to Eclipsing Binaries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.">Stellar Parameters from the Inferred Mean Density</head><p>To obtain an independent estimate of the values of the basic stellar parameters and their errors we have carried out a Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) fit of stellar models to the observed T eff and [Fe/H] and the asteroseismically inferred ρ * (see Brown 2010, for details). The models were obtained from the Yonsei-Yale (YY) compilation <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Yi et al. 2001</ref>). As for the ASTEC models used in the asteroseismic analysis the YY models use OPAL opacities and equation of state and include diffusion and settling of helium, although with a somewhat different formulation. Core overshoot is included, with a step-function dependence of overshoot distance on stellar mass (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Demarque et al. 2004</ref>, for details), such that for the models relevant to the present fits α ov is probably generally equal to 0.1.</p><p>The inferred parameters are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 3</ref>. The mass, radius and luminosity are very close to the values obtained from the asteroseismic analysis (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). The age inferred from the MCMC analysis, 3.2 ± 0.3 Gyr, is formally consistent with the asteroseismic value. However, the difference of 0.4 Gyr probably reflects systematic differences between the ASTEC and YY evolution codes. This deserves further investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Summary and Comparison with Previous Results</head><p>We reported the detection of the asteroseismic large separation for HD 17156, and determined the mean stellar density resulting from this to be 0.5301 ± 0.0044 g cm −3 . The best determination before these observations comes from <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. (2009)</ref> who relied on ground-based transit light curve analysis to fix ρ * at the 1 σ range of 0.486 -0.655 g cm −3 , with a preferred value of 0.589 g cm −3 . Our density is significantly different than the <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Winn et al. (2009)</ref> value, but well within their original confidence range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Comparison with Joint HST FGS Transit Analysis</head><p>Of more relevance to comparing our asteroseismic results to those from transit light curve based studies are the results from independent HST FGS observations obtained as a part of this program. <ref type="bibr">Nutzman et al. (2010)</ref> find a mean stellar density of 0.522 +0.021 −0.018 g cm −3 . This transit-based determination is 1.8 σ from the asteroseismic result, while the latter is only 0.4 σ off from the transit analysis based on its larger error allowances. Clearly of the two extreme outcomes possible from this first comparison of the two independent techniques that both yield what may be referred to as direct determinations of ρ * we are firmly in the domain of mutual confirmation, rather than a potential domain of disagreement calling for further understanding of one or both techniques. As noted in §5.3, however, the same cannot be said for consistency with the spectroscopically determined log(g) where there is a nearly 3 σ discrepancy in the sense that the spectroscopic log(g) is too large.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3.">Future Prospects from Kepler</head><p>In the near future the Kepler Mission may be expected to provide similar results in which both asteroseismology and transit light curve analysis will provide simultaneous constraints for the mean stellar density of planet host stars. The three previously known exoplanets in the Kepler field of view will be observed at short cadence (58.8 seconds) throughout the mission, thus supporting asteroseismology on these targets. "Only" 512 targets may be followed at short cadence at any time, the bulk of observations for over 150,000 stars with Kepler will use the long cadence of 29.4 minutes which suffices for detection of planets via transits. The Kepler throughput is a factor of about 5.9 higher than that for the HST FGS2r used for the observations in this paper, following from the use of back-side illuminated CCDs on Kepler, and a broad bandpass of roughly 420 -880 nm, despite the factor of 6.4 relative advantage in aperture area of HST compared to Kepler. Furthermore, Kepler should reach a duty cycle of nearly 100% during the month-long observing blocks between short breaks for telemetering accumulated data to the ground, compared to the uniquely high 72.6% duty cycle reached with HST for this observation taking advantage of a CVZ passage. This results in a net advantage in terms of Poisson statistics limit of 2.27 magnitudes for Kepler observations compared to those in this paper. What our HST observations have provided for a V = 8.17 star in 10 days, should be possible with Kepler for a V = 10.44 magnitude star in the same length of time. Also weighing in favor of Kepler asteroseismology is an expected window function without the sidelobes resulting from the orbit of HST and the daily passages through the South Atlantic Anomaly. And of course it should be routine for Kepler to devote much longer observing periods to targets than was the case for this unusually long HST observation. The initial target catalog for Kepler long cadence observations contains about 2500 targets brighter than the level which should return Poisson limited precisions per unit time as good or better than those discussed in this paper. To reach the same S/N on expected oscillations in the three previously known exoplanet hosts within the Kepler field of view, as for these HST observations of HD 17156 should take about 2 months for TrES-2 at V = 11.4, 8 days for HAT-P-7 at V = 10.5, and 20 days for HAT-P-11 at V = 9.6 taking into account the expected oscillation properties of each.</p><p>Coming at a time of significant stress on the HST project these observations required the expert assistance of many individuals to develop and execute. Especially noteworthy were the skill and tireless efforts provided by Merle Reinhart at STScI in expertly crafting the Phase II program to use all available observing time in the orbits allocated, and the efforts from Mike Wenz at Goddard Space Flight Center for shepherding the proposal through pre-flight reviews and monitoring engineering performance during execution. We thank the STScI Director, Matt Mountain, for the generous DD time award that made these results possible. We thank Matt Holman and Jeff Valenti for discussion. Financial support for this work was provided through program GO/DD-11945 from STScI.</p><p>Facilities: HST (FGS).   Note. -Models minimizing χ 2 ν (cf. Eq. 5) along the evolution tracks illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref>. The smallest value of χ 2 ν is obtained for model 8.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Time series photometry for 30 second sums over the full ten days with two days per panel shown starting at the top and progressing to the bottom. The numbers within the panels show start values for HJD days 23 -32 (-2454800). Each panel has the same 1.0% full range, which to help guide the eye is also printed at the upper left. See text for further details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>term and a point-by-point division by the four terms from Figures 3, 4, 5 and 6 will take the raw values of Fig. 1 into the corrected values of Fig. 7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2.-Sky plus counts from charged particles shown as corrections relative to the HD 17156 count level. See text for how FGS1 and FGS3 counts are used as proxies for this. The sharp, positive spikes result from grazing the South Atlantic Anomaly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-A slowly varying long-term correction factor derived by running a median filter with width of 0.15 days over the data. The 0.2 -0.3% decline overall likely follows from lost FGS PMT sensitivity, and not intrinsic variation of HD 17156.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Orbital waveform component of data corrections plotted on the same times and scale of Figure 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-The correction factor for HV ramp up, based on a bilinear regression over the preceding time gap, and overall time for each successive point in observing sequences.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-Final corrections derived after the iterative solution and application for slow-drift, orbital waveform and HV ramp changes. The solution follows from a simple quadratic polynomial fit to each data segment.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-Same as Figure 1, but after having removed all of the data artifacts discussed above. Note that relative to Figure 1 the vertical plot scale has changed by a factor of 5 to a full range of 0.2%. The rms of these 30 second sums (ignoring 6 points deviant at more than 4-σ) is 163.86 ppm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-The power spectrum for the corrected data on HD 17156 as shown in Fig. 7. The mean background noise level near 4 ppm 2 /µHz is evident above 2.5 µHz. The spectrum below 1 mHz is likely still contaminated by systematics.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.-The upper panel shows the power spectrum over a restricted range of 1.0-2.6 mHz. The adopted frequency resolution of 0.25 µHz oversamples by about a factor of 5. The middle panel shows the window function for the power spectrum from injecting a strong sinusoid at the times of observations at the frequency of the strongest peak in the upper panel. The lower panel shows the response, or transfer function of the data reduction procedure used in removing artifacts from these data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>scribed in Christensen-Dalsgaard et al.</head><label></label><figDesc>(2008). A more extended discussion of Kepler pipeline analysis tools can be found in Huber et al. (2009). The outline of analysis steps follows: (1) Calculation of the power spectrum. (2) Application of a matched filter (modified approach dif- fering from, but with similarities to the usual comb fil- ter) method to determine the large frequency separation. (3) Calculate the folded power spectrum using the large frequency separation. (4) Identify relation of l mode fre- quencies relative to the large separation. (5) Derivation of individual frequencies and fit to the asymptotic rela- tion. (6) Calculation of the oscillation amplitudes corre- sponding to the radial, l = 0 modes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10.-Smoothed power spectrum for HD 17156 shown as the solid line with a fit to the background from frequencies over 0.5 to 1.2 and above 2.6 mHz shown as a dashed line. The power excess of modes over 1.3 -2.4 mHz in the expected domain for oscillations on HD 17156 is clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Following</head><label></label><figDesc>Christensen-Dalsgaard et al. (2008) and Huber et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11.-The matched filter-response function showing the large separation ∆ν 0 for HD 17156. The curves show results of invidividual foldings of the spectra using n 0 = 19.5, 20, . . . 21.5. At 40 µHz the search range is 860 ± 200 µHz, while at 120 µHz the range is 2580 ± 600 µHz. The more precisely determined value from fits of individual frequencies to the asymptotic relation is shown at 83.44 µHz with the dashed line.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12.-The power spectrum of Fig. 9 after smoothing by 3 µHz (FWHM) and averaging over successive slices of 83.5 µHz over the domain of 1.2-2.4 mHz. The dashed lines indicate features which left to right correspond to modes of l = 2, 0, and 1 respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14.-The amplitude per radial mode distribution for HD 17156 contrasted to that for the Sun. See text for discussion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fischer et al. (2007) and Ammler-von Eiff et al. (2009), leading to T eff = 6082 ± 60 K and [Fe/H] = 0.24 ± 0.03. A grid of models was computed, varying the mass between 1.26 and 1.33 M ⊙ in steps of 0.01 M ⊙ . with composition, characterized by Z, corresponding to [Fe/H] varying be- tween 0.18 and 0.30 in steps of 0.02, and with α ov = 0, 0.05, and 0.1. All models included diffusion and settling of helium.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>mod) nl from the observed frequencies ν (obs) nl :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>ered models with masses between 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>28 and 1.32 M ⊙ and Z = 0.0299 ([Fe/H]= 0.24) and 0.0338 ([Fe/H]= 0.30), the latter case including the model minimizing χ 2 ν .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17.-The asteroseismicéchelleasteroseismicéchelle diagram comparing the observed frequencies of Table 1 (filled symbols with 1σ error bars) with values from the theoretical model minimizing χ 2 ν (cf. Eq. 5; open symbols); the model (model no 8 in Table 2) has a mass M = 1.30 M ⊙ , [Fe/H] = 0.30 and an age of 2.67 Gyr. The horizontal axis shows frequency distribution within successive 83.6 µHz slices, starting at a frequency of 68.8 µHz, while the vertical axis shows the starting frequencies of the slices. The short horizontal lines indicate the frequency intervals where the response function drops below 50% due to orbital filtering (cf. Fig. 9).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Fig. 18 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Fig. 18.-The upper curves show the allowed M * , R * values that satisfy the asteroseismology large separation constraint (solid curve prefered value of ρ * = 0.5301 g cm −3 , dashed lines the 0.0044 error offsets from this). The lower curves show the corresponding values that satisfy the spectroscopic log(g) value of 4.31, with solid and dashed curves preferred and 0.04 error offsets. The large plus symbol shows the preferred value of M * , R * , and allowed error range resulting from the transit light curves analyses (Nutzman et al. 2010) -note the excellent consistency with asteroseismology.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-Frequencies in µHz of individual modes identified in HD 17156.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Models are shown for two values of the initial heavy-element and hydrogen abundances Z 0 and X 0 , corresponding to [Fe/H] = 0.24 and 0.30. Models indicated by superscript 'a' were computed with overshoot with αov = 0.05, the remaining models had no overshoot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Note.</head><label></label><figDesc>-A: Based on asteroseismic analysis of this paper. B: Spectroscopic results averaging from Fischer et al. (2007) and Ammler-von Eiff et al. (2009). * For the purposes of deriving MCMC based errors (Brown 2010) on M * and R * we have adopted a doubling of the [Fe/H] error to ± 0.06. C: Function of A and B parameters and use of stellar evolution models. D: Derived from B and C parameters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 3 ,</head><label>3</label><figDesc>L from Winn et al. 2009).</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>TABLE 1 Individual frequencies (µHz) identified for HD 17156.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>TABLE 2 Stellar evolution models fitting the observed frequencies in Table 1.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>N o M * /M ⊙ 
Age 
Z 0 
X 0 
R * /R ⊙ 
ρ *  
T eff 
L * /L ⊙ 
χ 2 

ν 

χ 2 
(Gyr) 
(g cm −3 ) (K) 
1 a 
1.28 
2.936 0.0299 0.6803 
1.505 
0.5292 
6058 
2.74 
2.46 2.57 
2 
1.29 
2.756 0.0299 0.6803 
1.508 
0.5301 
6079 
2.79 
2.43 2.43 
3 a 
1.30 
2.557 0.0299 0.6803 
1.509 
0.5325 
6123 
2.87 
2.59 3.14 
4 
1.31 
2.389 0.0299 0.6803 
1.512 
0.5337 
6144 
2.93 
2.65 3.85 
5 
1.32 
2.215 0.0299 0.6803 
1.514 
0.5357 
6176 
2.99 
2.82 5.47 
6 
1.28 
3.069 0.0338 0.6687 
1.507 
0.5264 
5987 
2.62 
2.48 4.80 
7 
1.29 
2.865 0.0338 0.6687 
1.510 
0.5279 
6021 
2.69 
2.40 3.31 
8 
1.30 
2.670 0.0338 0.6687 
1.512 
0.5294 
6054 
2.76 
2.34 2.51 
9 a 
1.31 
2.474 0.0338 0.6687 
1.514 
0.5316 
6099 
2.85 
2.52 2.64 
10 
1.32 
2.307 0.0338 0.6687 
1.517 
0.5329 
6120 
2.90 
2.56 3.03 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>TABLE 3 System Parameters of HD 17156.</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Parameter 
Value 1-σ limits Comment 
Mean density, ρ *  (g cm −3 ) 0.5301 
±0.0044 
A 
Age (Gyr) 
2.8 
±0.6 
A 
Effective Temp, T eff (K) 
6082 
±60 
B 
Surface gravity, log(g) (cgs) 
4.31 
±0.04 
B 
Metallicity, [Fe/H]  *  
0.24 
±0.03 
B 
Mass, M *  (M ⊙ ) 
1.285 
±0.026 
C 
Radius, R *  (R ⊙ ) 
1.507 
±0.012 
C 
Age (Gyr) 
3.2 
±0.3 
C 
Luminosity, L *  (L ⊙ ) 
2.79 
±0.14 
D 
Surface gravity, log(g) (cgs) 
4.191 
±0.004 
D 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ammler-Von Eiff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Israelian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Melo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">507</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">523</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Angulo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl. Phys. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">656</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">687</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1180</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">476</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Benedict</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seifahrt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dreizler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">486</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1039</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Belle</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Böhm-Vitense</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASPC</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">309</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">709</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">169</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Gough</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">288</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1286</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Solar Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comm. Asteroseismology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">350</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second HELAS International Conference</title>
		<meeting>the Second HELAS International Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap&amp;SS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap&amp;SS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">683</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Demarque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">667</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">622</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">669</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1336</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2441</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TEL 2009-01</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>STScI</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Instrument Science Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fossat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pomerantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Solar Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-O</forename><surname>Quirion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comm. Asteroseismology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Iglesias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">943</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kallinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gruberbauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">510</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">293</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">635</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1281</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">682</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1370</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kjeldsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">683</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">175</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hipparcos, The New Reduction of the Raw Data</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Michaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Proffitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IAU Colloq. 137: Inside the stars</title>
		<editor>Baglin, A. &amp; Weiss, W. W.</editor>
		<meeting>IAU Colloq. 137: Inside the stars<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">246</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">558</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Narita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Suto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aoki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">991</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FGS Instrument Handbook for Cycle</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>STScI</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nutzman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Swenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Iglesias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">902</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mallén-Omelas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1038</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sozzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Laird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Donovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">664</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1190</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;ARev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. IAU Symp. 253, Transiting Planets</title>
		<editor>F. Pont et al.</editor>
		<meeting>IAU Symp. 253, Transiting Planets<address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guillermo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shporer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">693</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">794</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wittenmyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">632</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">141</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Demarque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lejeune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">417</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
