<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Using Dimers to Measure Biosignatures and Atmospheric Pressure for Terrestrial Exoplanets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013-12-06">6 Dec 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amit</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Univ. of Washington Astronomy Dept</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">NAI Virtual Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Univ. of Washington Astrobiology Program</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Victoria</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Univ. of Washington Astronomy Dept</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">NAI Virtual Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Univ. of Washington Astrobiology Program</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Claire</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">NAI Virtual Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Earth and Environmental Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of St Andrews</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fife</settlement>
									<country key="GB">Scotland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Blue Marble Space Institute of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">NAI Virtual Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postBox>Box 351580</postBox>
									<postCode>98195-1580</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>UW, WA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Using Dimers to Measure Biosignatures and Atmospheric Pressure for Terrestrial Exoplanets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2013-12-06">6 Dec 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Subject headings: Remote Sensing</term>
					<term>Extrasolar terrestrial planets</term>
					<term>Habitability</term>
					<term>Radia- tive transfer</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present a new method to probe atmospheric pressure on Earthlike planets using (O 2-O 2) dimers in the near-infrared. We also show that dimer features could be the most readily detectable biosignatures for Earthlike atmospheres, and may even be detectable in transit transmission with the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). The absorption by dimers changes more rapidly with pressure and density than that of monomers, and can therefore provide additional information about atmospheric pressures. By comparing the absorption strengths of rotational and vibrational features to the absorption strengths of dimer features, we show that in some cases it may be possible to estimate the pressure at the reflecting surface of a planet. This method is demonstrated by using the O 2 A band and the 1.06 µm dimer feature, either in transmission or reflected spectra. It works best for planets around M dwarfs with atmospheric pressures between 0.1 and 10 bars, and for O 2 volume mixing ratios above 50% of Earth&apos;s present day level. Furthermore, unlike observations of Rayleigh scattering, this method can-2-be used at wavelengths longer than 0.6 µm, and is therefore potentially applicable, although challenging, to near-term planet characterization missions such as JWST. We have also performed detectability studies for JWST transit transmission spectroscopy and find that the 1.06 µm and 1.27 µm dimer features could be detectable (SNR&gt;3) for an Earth-analog orbiting an M5V star at a distance of 5 pc. The detection of these features could provide a constraint on the atmospheric pressure of an exoplanet, and serve as biosignatures for oxygenic photosynthesis. We have calculated the required signal-to-noise ratios to detect and characterize O 2 monomer and dimer features in direct imaging reflected spectra and find that signal-to-noise ratios greater than 10 at a spectral resolving power of R=100 would be required.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Atmospheric pressure is a fundamental parameter for characterizing the environment and habitability of an extrasolar planet. Water's stability on a planetary surface as a liquid depends on both the surface temperature and pressure. While the freezing point of water is not strongly dependent on pressure, pressure does affect water's boiling point and sublimation. Thus, a reliable estimate of the surface pressure is an important part of the measurement suite required to determine the habitability of an exoplanet.</p><p>Despite the importance of atmospheric pressure, current proposed methods for measuring pressure using remote-sensing techniques that could be applicable to exoplanet atmospheres are challenging. The existing techniques include the use of Rayleigh scattering ( <ref type="bibr">Kasting et al. 2010)</ref> or the widths of individual absorption lines ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kaplan et al. 1964;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gray 1966)</ref> or absorption bands ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ignatiev et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Chamberlain et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Spiga et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chamberlain et al. 2013</ref>). The presence and location of a blue Rayleigh scattering tail in a spectrum can provide information about the existence and pressure of an atmosphere. However, strong blue absorbers in the atmosphere (e.g. O 3 , SO 2 , NO 2 and many others) or surface features can mask this tail ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Crow et al. 2011</ref>). Furthermore, the Rayleigh scattering tail is most prominent shortward of 0.6 µm, below the short wavelength cutoff of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) ( <ref type="bibr">Gardner et al. 2006</ref>). Lastly, planets around M dwarfs are likely to be the first to be characterized ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Deming et al. 2009)</ref>, and M dwarfs have relatively less visible-flux to Rayleigh scatter than solar-type stars. The Rayleigh tail would be more difficult to detect and characterize for planets orbiting stars of this stellar class.</p><p>It is also possible to use the widths of absorption features to estimate pressure. Pressure increases the widths of vibration rotation lines of gases. This method has been successful for the Earth using high-resolution spectra of the O 2 A band ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barton and Scott 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Mitchell and O'Brien 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Crisp et al. 2012</ref>), for Mars using CO 2 features near 2 µm (Gray 1966; <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Chamberlain et al. 2006</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Forget et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Spiga et al. 2007</ref>) and the cloud tops of Venus using the 1.6 µm CO 2 band ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ignatiev et al. 2009</ref>). This method provides unambiguous results when the spectral resolution is sufficiently high to resolve the profiles of individual spectral lines. It can also be used at lower spectral resolution, but requires prior knowledge of the mixing ratio of the absorbing gas.</p><p>Here we explore the feasibility of a new method to directly measure the pressure of an Earthlike atmosphere that combines the absorption features of dimers with those of monomer vibrationrotation bands to yield estimates of the atmospheric pressures even when the mixing ratio of the monomer is uncertain. Previous pressure estimates using dimer absorption have been made for the cloud tops of Earth, but these techniques have required prior knowledge of the gas mixing ratio profile ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Acarreta et al. 2004</ref>). Dimers are bound or quasi-bound states between two molecules driven together by molecular interactions. For example, the O 2 -O 2 or O 4 dimer consists of two O 2 molecules temporarily bound to each other by Van der Waals forces. This dimer has its own rotational and vibrational modes, and produces spectral features distinct from its constituent O 2 monomers. Additionally, absorption from dimer molecules is more sensitive to pressure than that of monomers. The optical depth (how much absorption occurs) for dimers and monomers can be expressed by the following equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">dτ monomer = σρdl = σP/T dl<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">dτ dimer = kρ 2 dl = kP 2 /T 2 dl<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where dτ monomer and dτ dimer are the monomer and dimer differential optical depths, σ is the monomer cross section, ρ is the number density of the gas, k is the dimer cross section, P is the pressure, T is the temperature, and dl is the path length. While the monomer (e.g. O 2 ) optical depth is directly proportional to pressure, the optical depth of the dimer (e.g. O 2 -O 2 ) is dependent on the square of the density (and hence square of the pressure). This difference in pressure dependence allows us to estimate atmospheric pressure by comparing the dimer and monomer absorption features</p><p>For an oxygen-rich, Earth-like atmosphere, the best combination of bands to use for pressure determination at near infrared wavelengths (&gt;0.6 µm) would be the (O 2 ) A band at 0.76 µm, and the 1.06 µm O 4 dimer band. The 0.76 µm O 2 A band is the strongest O 2 feature in the visiblenear-infrared spectral region, and is found in a relatively clean region of the spectrum between two water vapor bands. We have chosen the dimer feature at 1.06 µm as the likely best option, due to its combination of band strength and its location in a relatively uncluttered region of the planetary spectrum. Other O 4 features overlap with water features (dimer feature between 5.5 and 7 µm) or O 2 vibration-rotation bands (0.63 µm, 0.76 µm and 1.27 µm dimer features) or are weaker than the 1.06 µm dimer feature (0.477 µm and 0.57 µm dimer features). Nevertheless, some other features, in particular the strong 1.27 µm feature, could be used if the 1.06 µm dimer feature is not detectable.</p><p>In the proposed technique, the O 2 0.76µm (monomer) band is used to provide an estimate of the atmospheric concentration of O 2 , and combined with the O 4 1.06 µm (dimer) band to constrain the atmospheric pressure. This method can be used with either transmission spectroscopy, or directlydetected reflection or emission spectra, and serves as a complement to pressure determination techniques such as Rayleigh scattering, which only work in the visible. Although the proof of concept is shown here with oxygen, this technique is not limited to the oxygen dimer in an Earth-like atmosphere in the visible to near-infrared. The same technique is applicable to pairs of monomer and dimer absorption features across a wider range of planetary atmospheric composition and spectral wavelength range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head><p>In this paper we generated transit transmission and direct imaging reflected spectra for cloud and aerosol-free Earthlike exoplanets. The models we have used to do this are described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Transmission Spectroscopy Model</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Model Overview</head><p>When an extrasolar planet transits or occults its host star, the planetary atmosphere is backlit and some of the star's light traverses the planet's atmosphere on limb trajectories. This transmitted light can be used to characterize the planet's atmosphere <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Seager and Sasselov 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Brown 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Hubbard et al. 2001</ref>). This has been done for a number of Jupiter-and Neptune-sized planets (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Charbonneau et al. (2002)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Vidal-Madjar et al. (2003)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pont et al. (2008)</ref>) and the superEarth/mini-Neptune GJ1214b (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bean et al. (2010)</ref>) The transmission spectroscopy model used here is based on SMART (Spectral Mapping Atmospheric Radiative Transfer) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Meadows and Crisp 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Crisp 1997)</ref>, which is a spectrum resolving (line-by-line), multi-stream, multiple scattering radiative transfer model. We have modified SMART to generate transit transmission spectra by combining the monochromatic absorption and scattering opacities for each atmospheric layer calculated by SMART with the limb path lengths inherent in a transit transmission event. The transmission model included gas absorption, Rayleigh scattering, interaction-induced absorption, extinction from clouds and aerosols, refraction and limb darkening. Because multiple scattering was not included in the transit transmission component of the model, we have considered only cloud and aerosol-free atmospheres for this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2.">Refraction</head><p>An important characteristic of the transit transmission spectroscopy model is the inclusion of refraction. As described in García <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Muñoz et al. (2012)</ref>, refraction sets a fundamental limit on the range of pressures that can be probed during a transit, independent of absorption and scattering.</p><p>Light refracts as it passes through an atmosphere, with a larger refraction angle as higher pressures and densities are probed. For every planet-star system there will be a maximum tangent pressure in the planet's atmosphere that can be probed, because at greater pressures the light will be refracted by too large of an angle to be able to reach a distant observer during the transit.</p><p>For each tangent height in each atmosphere, we calculated the total angle of refraction for a beam of light emitted from the host star using a modified version of the method described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Auer and Standish (2000)</ref>. Their method was developed for calculating refraction for astronomical observations on the Earth given a tangent altitude, apparent zenith angle and an atmospheric density profile. We calculated the angle of refraction over a range of zenith angles to determine if a path exists to connect the host star to a distant observer via the planetary atmosphere. Transit transmission spectroscopy cannot probe the tangent altitudes at which no such path exists.</p><p>The radius of the star, planet-star distance and composition of the planet's atmosphere determine the maximum tangent pressure. The radius of the star and planet-star distance control the apparent angular size of the star from the planet's perspective. The larger the angular size, the greater the range of pressures that can be probed. For an Earth-analog orbiting a Sun-like star the angular size of the star is ∼0.5 • while for an Earth-analog orbiting an M5 dwarf and receiving the same total flux, the angular size of the star is ∼2 • . Therefore, transit transmission spectroscopy can probe higher pressures, i.e. see deeper into the atmosphere, for the planet orbiting an M dwarf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 1</ref> shows this effect by comparing all possible paths at one tangent height for a planet around an M dwarf and a planet around a Sun-like star, with each planet receiving the same total flux. The composition of the atmosphere determines the refractivity (index of refraction -1) of the atmosphere. Atmospheres with greater refractivities will have lower maximum tangent pressures. The refractivity at STP (standard temperature and pressure) can vary from ∼1.5 times the refractivity of air for CO 2 to slightly less than half the refractivity of air for H 2 , when considering only the common bulk atmospheric gases in the solar system. Therefore, in general it will be possible to probe higher pressures for an H 2 atmosphere than a CO 2 or air atmosphere.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Direct Imaging (Reflected) Spectroscopy Model</head><p>The reflected spectra were generated using the standard version of SMART, which can include multiple scattering from clouds and aerosols. However, to maintain consistency with the transmission spectrum model, clouds were not included in this study. The reflected spectra were generated assuming a surface with a constant albedo of 0.16, which is the average albedo of the cloud-free Earth (Pierrehumbert 2010). We also assumed the surface is a Lambertian scatterer. Other surface types could have introduced an error into any quantitative estimates in this paper, unless explicitly included in a retrieval attempt. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows the wavelength-dependence of a variety of surface types from the ASTER (Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection Radiometer) spectral library ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baldridge et al. 2009</ref>) and the USGS (United States Geological Survey) digital spectral library <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Clark et al. 2007</ref>). Surface albedos are nearly constant in the bands considered here, though, for example, snow fluctuates by ∼20% within the 1.06 µm dimer band. We modeled a test case with SMART with the snow surface to determine the error different surfaces can introduce. We found a difference of 15% between the seawater and snow cases when measuring the equivalent width (defined in Section 2.4) of the 1.06 µm dimer band. This difference was significantly less than the difference in measured equivalent widths for the cases considered in this paper. Therefore, we have considered any discrepancies due to variations in surface albedo to be minimal for the present work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Model Inputs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Model Atmospheres</head><p>The cloud-free model atmospheres were generated by a one-dimensional (altitude) photochemical code with an extensive history in early Earth ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Zerkle et al. 2012</ref>), modern Earth ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Catling et al. 2010</ref>) and exoplanet ) research. The planetary radius and surface gravity used were the radius of the Earth (6371 km) and surface gravity of the Earth (9.87 m/s 2 ). The vertical grid consists of 200 plane-parallel layers that are each 0.5km thick in altitude, in which radiative transfer, atmospheric transport, and photochemical production and loss are solved simultaneously, subject to upper (stellar flux, atmospheric escape) and lower (volcanos and biology) boundary conditions. The model calculates the mixing ratios of each species in each layer by solving the coupled mass-continuity/flux equations with the reverse Euler method (appropriate for stiff systems) and a variable time-stepping algorithm. Dimer concentrations were computed using estimations from quantum mechanical calculations. First, we fit the temperature dependence of the equilibrium constant for O 2 -dimer formation using the following equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Kp = (p(O 2 ) 2 /(pO 2 ) 2 )/atm −1 (3) Kp(T ) = 2428 * T (−3.518)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where p(O 2 ) 2 and pO 2 are the dimer and monomer partial pressures and T is the temperature ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Uhlik et al. 1993</ref>). The dimer mixing ratio was then computed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">p(O 2 ) 2 = Kp(T ) * (pO 2 ) 2 * P (5)</formula><p>where P is the pressure in atmospheres. The choice of quantum parameters in our fit of equation 4 ensures that our calculation is a lower limit to the dimer concentrations, an assumption which matches modern atmospheric data well ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Slanina et al. 1994</ref>).</p><p>The model atmospheres used in this study started with boundary conditions that reproduce Earth's modern atmospheric chemistry. We then replaced the solar spectrum with the M dwarf spectrum described in 2.3.3 and decreased the surface albedo to 0.16 to account for cloud-free conditions. This "modified Earth around an M dwarf" model was then perturbed to examine changes to both total pressure and oxygen concentrations. Total atmospheric pressures of 0.1, 0.5, 1.0, 3.0, 5.0 and 10.0 bar were examined. At each of these total pressures, lower boundary conditions on O 2 mixing ratios were set at 0.1, 0.5, 1.0 and 2.0 times Earths present level. This corresponds to oxygen mixing ratios from 2% to 42%, which is roughly the range of oxygen concentrations experienced throughout the past 2.5 Gyr of Earths history <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Kump 2008)</ref>. Boundary conditions for all other species were held fixed at modern values. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the pressure-temperature profile and volume mixing ratio profiles for the 1.0 times the present atmospheric level (PAL) O 2 cases for spectrally active gases in the wavelength region examined here. Stable steady-state solutions were analyzed in all but the three cases with the highest O 2 surface partial pressures. For those three cases, we extrapolated from our converged results at lower O 2 mixing ratios by increasing O 2 concentrations, scaling the dimer concentrations with the square of the O 2 mixing ratio, and keeping all other gas mixing ratios constant.</p><p>For all tests presented here, we assumed Earth-like temperature and water vapor profiles, precluding the need for costly climate simulations. More specifically, we took the modern Earth temperature profile as a function of altitude, and computed the corresponding pressure levels assuming hydrostatic equilibrium. This simplification provides a useful baseline, but limits the range of validity of these results somewhat because the gas absorption cross sections and number densities depend on these atmospheric properties. The impact of this assumption is assessed in Section 3.4. For pressure/temperature regions corresponding to Earth's mesosphere, we adopted a temperature of 180 K which likely overestimates the temperature in these regions. Dimer absorption preferentially occurs in higher pressure regions and so is insensitive to assumed conditions in the tenuous upper atmosphere. Our model grid was capped at 100km altitude ensuring optically thin conditions for nearly all species, and made allowances for CO 2 and N 2 photolysis above the upper boundary. We used the modern measured eddy-diffusion profile to simulate convective motion for all atmospheres regardless of pressure. While this simplification would affect the prediction of trace gas concentrations, all species analyzed here are either well-mixed (CO 2 , O 2 , N 2 ) or short-lived (dimers) so are not sensitive to changes in turbulent mixing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Absorption Line Lists and Cross Sections</head><p>We used the HITRAN 2008 database line lists ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Rothman et al. 2009</ref>) to generate opacities in SMART. The dimer absorption cross sections for O 2 were taken from <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Greenblatt et al. (1990)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Maté et al. (1999)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">Stellar Properties</head><p>In this paper we have assumed that the planet orbits an M5V star, or an M dwarf with stellar radius of 0.20 R ⊙ and a luminosity of 0.0022 L ⊙ (Kaltenegger and Traub 2009). The planet was placed at a distance of 0.047 AU, so that the total integrated incoming stellar flux was equal to the total flux the Earth receives from the Sun today. An M5 dwarf was chosen for these tests because there is a high probability that the terrestrial planets which will be the most easily characterized in the near future will be orbiting this class of star ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Deming et al. 2009</ref>). Additionally, transit transmission spectroscopy can probe pressures up to the ∼1 bar level in an atmosphere for an Earth analog around an M dwarf while for the Earth around the Sun, it can only probe pressures as great as ∼0.2 bars. At these pressures and lower, the 1.06 µm dimer feature is very weak, even at 200% PAL O 2 . Thus, using Earth-like atmospheres around an M dwarf instead of around the Sun provides a better demonstration of the pressure-dependence of dimer features.</p><p>To simulate the spectrum of the star, we used a Phoenix NextGen synthetic spectrum ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Hauschildt et al. 1999</ref>) for all wavelengths greater than ∼300 nm. For the shorter wavelengths we used the UV spectrum of AD Leo ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Segura et al. 2005</ref>). The Phoenix spectrum was normalized so that the total integrated flux was equal to 1373 W/m 2 , which is the integrated flux the Earth receives from the Sun. The AD Leo spectrum from <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Segura et al. (2005)</ref> was left unchanged, as it was already normalized to equal the amount of flux a planet near the inner edge of the habitable zone would receive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4.">Spectral Resolution</head><p>We have used a spectral resolving power of 100 to provide relevance to the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), which will provide new opportunities for characterizing the atmospheres of transiting exoplanets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lafreniere et al. 2013</ref>). Once the JWST is launched, the Near-Infrared Spectrograph (NIRSPEC) will provide spectra with a spectral resolving power (R= λ ∆λ ) of ≃100 between 0.6 and 5.0 µm in single prism mode <ref type="bibr">(Köhler et al. 2005</ref>). We examine the effect of varying the spectral resolution in Sections 3.6 and 4.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Absorption Strength Measurements</head><p>To make a quantitative estimate of absorption strengths we measured equivalent widths for the reflected spectra and measured parts per million (ppm) differences in flux for the transmission spectra. Equivalent widths were calculated using the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">W = (1 − F λ /F 0 )dλ (6)</formula><p>where W is the equivalent width, F λ is the flux at each wavelength λ, and F 0 is the continuum flux at each wavelength. To obtain the equivalent widths, we first measured the area of the spectral band below the continuum. For each absorption band, we define the continuum by hand. For the O 2 A band, the continuum was assumed to be linear with wavelength, and for the 1.06 µm feature the continuum was assumed to be constant with wavelength because in several of the cases the continuum at the longer wavelengths was difficult to define due to H 2 O absorption. The equivalent width is the width, in units of wavelength, of a rectangle measured from the continuum to the level of zero flux with the same total area as the spectral band. We could not use this type of measurement for the transmission spectra because of the difficulty in defining the zero flux level. Therefore, we quantified the absorption strengths for the transmission spectra by measuring the change in flux from the continuum to the point of greatest absorption within a band.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Detectability Calculations</head><p>We performed detectability studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kaltenegger and Traub 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Deming et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Belu et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Rauer et al. 2011</ref>) for the model spectra, assuming the exoplanet-star system is at a distance of 5 pc. We calculated the expected signal-to-noise ratio (SNR star ) using the JWST Exposure Time Calculator (ETC) 1 . The JWST ETC includes background noise from sky, dark, thermal and zodiacal sources along with read-out noise and photon noise. The estimates provided are expected to be within 20% of the mission requirements. We note that for all the cases considered, the noise is dominated by photon noise. We do not include noise from detector intrapixel variations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Deming et al. 2009</ref>), but in principle calibration time could be devoted to mapping the pixels, as has been done with Spitzer Space Telescope Infrared Array Camera ( <ref type="bibr">Carey et al. 2012</ref>). We also note that noise levels within ∼20% of the photon noise limit have been obtained for transit transmission spectra with HST in spatial scan mode, wherein the target star is trailed during each exposure by telescope motion perpendicular to the direction of dispersion ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Deming et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wakeford et al. 2013</ref>). Spatial scan mode is being considered for JWST, and so assuming photon-limited noise in our calculations, while optimistic, provides a reasonable estimate of the detectability of absorption features (Drake Deming, private communication, <ref type="bibr">October 13, 2013</ref>).</p><p>We assumed that every possible transit is observed in JWST's 5 year mission lifetime, ignoring decreases in integration time due to non-zero impact parameters (where the planet does not traverse the center of the stellar disk and therefore has a lower transit duration) and limits on visibility based on the ecliptic latitude of the exoplanet (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Belu et al. (2011)</ref>). For the Earth-Sun analog, this corresponds to a total integration time of ∼2.3*10 5 seconds, and for the Earth-M5V analog, an integration time of ∼10 6 seconds. We normalize the Solar spectrum (using the Phoenix G2V model available on the site) to a Johnson V magnitude of 3.32 and the M5V spectrum to 2.1*10 −13 erg cm −2 s −1 ˚ A −1 at 1 µm.</p><p>At each wavelength within an absorption band we measured the signal as the magnitude of the difference from the continuum flux. The noise is expressed in parts per million (ppm, 10 6 /SNR star ) at each wavelength. The final SNR of the transit transmission spectrum is the square root of the sum of the squares of the SNR at each wavelength in the absorption band divided by √ 2, which is included because the transit transmission spectrum must be calibrated against the out of transit spectrum of the star.</p><p>We also performed detectability studies for the direct imaging reflected spectra that could be relevant to proposed direct imaging planet detection and characterization missions. For these calculations, we did not use an instrument simulator because the exact specifications for these missions are not currently defined. For each absorption band, we calculated two SNRs, one for detecting the spectral feature (SNR D ) and one for measuring the flux at the center of the band to a precision of 3σ (SNR P ). We calculated two SNRs because obtaining information about pressure from a spectral feature requires more than detection; it also requires a quantitative estimate of the strength of that spectral feature. To calculate SNR D , we divided the reflected flux by the stellar flux, defined a continuum and calculated the signal as the difference between the continuum and the normalized reflected flux. We assumed the noise is constant over the entire absorption band, and then calculated the noise level required to detect the spectral feature with a SNR band of 3 in the absorption band. The final SNR D is the mean of the continuum reflected flux level divided by the calculated noise. To calculate SNR P , we selected the wavelength within the band with the lowest radiance. We set the value of a second noise level as the lowest radiance divided by 3. SNR P is the continuum flux level divided by the noise required to obtain a SNR of 3 at the lowest radiance in the absorption band.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Transit Transmission Spectra</head><p>We have generated transit transmission spectra and direct imaging spectra for atmospheres with O 2 concentrations of 10%, 50%, 100% and 200% of the PAL and pressures of 0.1, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 and 10 bars. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows the resulting transit transmission spectra for 100% PAL O 2 . Transmission spectra of atmospheres with pressures ≥1 bar are nearly identical for a given O 2 concentration because refraction limits to depth of penetration to &lt;1 bar. The dimer feature is weak for pressures of 0.1 and 0.5 bars.</p><p>Figures 5, 6, and 7 show the resulting transit transmission spectra for O 2 concentrations of 10%, 50% and 200% PAL. The 1.06 µm dimer feature is very weak at all pressures for O 2 concentrations at 10% PAL and weak for 50% PAL O 2 , while it is very strong for pressures above 0.1 bars at 200% PAL O 2 . <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows the reflected spectra for modern O 2 mixing ratios in atmospheres with a range of total pressure from 0.1 to 10 bars. The 0.5 and 5.0 bar cases are omitted from the plots to increase clarity, but are still included in the equivalent width and SNR calculations. The 1.06 µm dimer feature is extremely weak for the present-day atmosphere, but in contrast to its behavior in the transmission spectra, it is a very prominent feature for the 3, 5 and 10 bar atmospheres.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Reflected Spectra</head><p>Figures 9, 10 and 11 show the reflected spectra at pressures between 0.1 and 10 bars for 10%, 50%, and 200% PAL of O 2 , respectively. In the 10% PAL case, the O 2 dimer feature at 1.06 µm is very weak because the total amount of O 2 is very low, even for a 10 bar atmosphere. The 1.06 µm dimer feature is stronger in the 3, 5 and 10 bar cases for atmospheres with 50% PAL O 2 . Finally for the 200% O 2 atmospheres, the 1.06 µm dimer feature is one of the strongest spectral features, even in the 1 bar atmosphere. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 12</ref> shows the flux change for the transmission spectra and equivalent widths for reflected spectra at different pressures and O 2 concentrations for the O 2 A band and the 1.06 µm dimer feature. For a given O 2 concentration the transit transmission flux differences for the O 2 A band are roughly constant for pressures ≥1 bar due to refraction. The 1.06 µm dimer feature flux differences increase slightly with pressure but are also constant for pressures ≥1 bar for a given O 2 concentration. The dimer feature does not appear in transmission for cases with 10% PAL O 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Quantitative Absorption Measurements</head><p>For the direct imaging (reflected) spectra, both the O 2 A band and 1.06 µm dimer feature equivalent widths increase with pressure and increased O 2 concentrations. However, the dimer feature equivalent widths are much more sensitive to pressure. At higher pressures the dimer feature is strong except for cases with 10% PAL O 2 , in which the 1.06 µm dimer feature is too weak to quantify. <ref type="bibr">Figures 13-15</ref> show the relationships between the quantitative absorption measurements described above and atmospheric quantities including the O 2 mixing ratio and the O 2 partial pressure at the surface. The ppm flux difference measured in transit transmission for the O 2 A band could be used to constrain the O 2 mixing ratio, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 13B</ref>. The O 2 partial pressure at the surface can be estimated using the ratio between the 1.06 µm dimer and O 2 A band absorption measurements. These ratios are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 13a</ref> using ppm flux differences, and in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  14</ref> using equivalent widths. The O 2 mixing ratio and O 2 partial pressure at the surface can be combined to provide a unique estimate of the surface pressure of the planet. A more detailed description of the pressure measurement technique is given in Section 4.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Sensitivity Tests</head><p>To quantify the errors introduced by assuming the modern day temperature profile, we generated spectra to test the sensitivity of our models to changes in the temperature profile and in changes to the water vapor profiles. We compared our 1.0 bar, 1.0x PAL O 2 spectra to a spectrum generated using the same volume mixing ratio profiles but with an isothermal atmosphere at 250 K. We also compared our 1.0 bar, 1.0x PAL O 2 transit transmission spectrum to spectra generated with atmospheres with 0.1 and 10.0 times the H 2 O levels. We perform a similar comparison for the 1.0 bar, 2.0x PAL O 2 reflected spectrum. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 16</ref> shows the sensitivity of the spectra to the temperature profile, with our Earthlike profile and an isothermal approximation profile compared. Both the transit transmission and reflected spectra show little sensitivity to the temperature profile. The 1.06 µm dimer band also shows little sensitivity to the temperature profile, despite the dependence of the dimer optical depth on the square of the temperature because the isothermal temperature profile approximates the average temeprature of the troposphere, where the majority of dimer absorption occurs. For the transit transmission spectra, the change in the total ppm flux difference (across the entire band) is less than 20% between the 0.1 and 10.0x H 2 O cases. For the reflected spectra, the change in the equivalent width of the 1.06 µm dimer feature is less than 20%. For the reflected spectra, the equivalent widths can be much greater than that for the 1.0 bar, 2.0x O 2 case. For these greater equivalent widths, the effect of increasing or decreasing H 2 O levels will diminish as the difference from the continuum flux (affected by H 2 O) and the flux within the absorption band will increase. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> shows the SNRs for observations by JWST for the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm feature and the 1.27 µm feature for the range of pressures and O 2 concentrations considered here for an Earth analog at a distance of 5 pc. The SNR are calculated assuming that every transit of an Earth analog orbiting an M5V star is observed over JWST's 5 year mission lifetime. In transit transmission, the O 2 A band SNRs are no greater than 1.1. The 1.06µm dimer feature is detectable at a SNR of &gt;3 for many of the 2.0x PAL O 2 cases. The 1.27 µm feature is the most detectable O 2 feature in this wavelength range, with SNRs greater than 5 for many of the 1.0x PAL O 2 cases and greater than 7 for many of the 2.0x PAL O 2 cases. JWST will not be able to detect O 2 species for Earth-like exoplanets in secondary eclipse in the visible and near-infrared, as shown by the secondary eclipse SNR levels. Even for the highest pressure cases, the SNRs are no greater than ∼0.2. <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows the SNRs necessary to detect and characterize the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm band and the 1.27 µm feature for the range of pressures and O 2 concentrations considered here for the direct imaging reflected spectra at R=100. The SNRs in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> would be relevant to a direct imaging characterization mission. While these SNRs were calculated for an Earth analog orbiting an M5V star, the results should be independent of stellar spectral type because we divided out the stellar flux in our calculations. The O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and 1.27 µm feature are detectable at an average SNR D of 14, 9 and 14, respectively, for the cases when the features are strong enough to identify in the model spectra. The average required SNR P to use the features for pressure estimation are 11, 31 and 34.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Detectability of Spectral Features</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Effect of Spectral Resolving Power</head><p>We examined the effect of spectral resolving power on the detectability of spectral features by generating transit transmission spectra for the 1.0 bar, 1.0x PAL O 2 case with spectral resolving powers of 500, 200, 100, 80, 60, 40, 30 and 20. <ref type="figure">Figure 20</ref> shows the spectra for each of these cases. We also measured the SNR of each feature at each resolving power. The SNRs were calculated assuming a noise profile equivalent to the JWST NIRSPEC noise profile, but with the noise level at each wavelength divided by (100/R) 2 , so that the noise at each wavelength decreased as the resolving power decreased. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 21</ref> shows how the total SNR in each absorption band changes with resolving power. In general, the SNRs drop off rapidly as resolving power decreases for R&lt;60.</p><p>We also generated direct imaging reflected spectra for the 1.0 bar, 2.0x PAL O 2 case at resolving powers of 500, 200, 100, 80, 60, 40, 30 and 20, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 22</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figures 23 and 24</ref> show how the SNR for detection and precision vary with resolving power for the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature. The SNR required to detect each feature increases as resolving power decreases. At R=20, the SNRs are not shown because no spectral features could be identified, and at R=30 only the O 2 A band was identified. The SNR required to quantify the flux at the center of each spectral feature decreases as resolving power decreases, because the lowest radiance level increases as the spectral resolving power decreases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>The 1.06 µm dimer feature is prominent in transit transmission for atmospheres with ≥50% PAL O 2 and surface pressures ≥0.5 bars. It is a prominent feature in the reflected spectra for atmospheres with ≥50% PAL O 2 and surface pressure ≥3 bars. For the reflected spectra, the dimer feature equivalent width is highly dependent on surface pressure when compared to the O 2 A band and therefore the dimer feature can be used to constrain pressure. Here we discuss how to do this for the cases investigated here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Pressure Measurement Technique</head><p>Figure 12 confirms that dimer absorption features are more strongly dependent on pressure than monomer features. Therefore dimer features can be combined with monomer features to determine pressure, even if the mixing ratio of the absorbing gas is not known. With only transit transmission spectroscopy, it is impossible to probe pressures over ∼1 bar for the cases examined here, but it may be possible to constrain the O 2 mixing ratio and set a lower bound for pressure. In reflected spectra, it is possible to determine the surface partial pressure of O 2 and set a lower bound for pressure using the 1.06 µm dimer feature as an on/off pressure gauge. With both a transit transmission spectrum and a reflected spectrum, it should be possible to determine total atmospheric surface pressure for an Earth-like exoplanet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1.">Transmission Spectra Pressure Measurement</head><p>Transmission spectroscopy provides only a lower bound on the atmospheric pressure because refraction provides a fundamental limit to which pressures can be probed using this technique. For the spectra presented here, a lower limit of ∼1 bar can be set for the high pressure atmospheres. For a given O 2 concentration a unique estimate of the pressure can be retrieved from the ratio between the ppm flux differences of the 1.06 µm dimer feature and the O 2 A band. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 13a</ref> shows the relationship between this ratio and the total amount of O 2 above 0.9 bars, which is the highest pressure that can be probed in this particular case. There is a clear trend between this ratio and the amount of O 2 in the atmosphere. When combined with an O 2 mixing ratio this relationship can provide a quantitative estimate of a lower level of the surface or cloud-top pressure.</p><p>The O 2 mixing ratio can be estimated from the flux difference of the O 2 A band in transmission. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 13B</ref> shows the relationship between the O 2 mixing ratio (which is constant throughout the atmosphere) and the O 2 A band flux difference. For pressure ≥0.1 bars the O 2 flux difference is roughly constant for a given O 2 concentration, meaning that a measurement of the O 2 A band flux difference should correlate with the O 2 mixing ratio.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2.">Reflected Spectra Pressure Measurement</head><p>Reflected spectra alone can provide an estimate of the surface partial pressure of O 2 by examination of the ratio of the 1.06 µm dimer equivalent width and the O 2 A band equivalent width. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 14</ref> shows the relationship between this ratio and the surface partial pressure of O 2 . The strength of the 1.06 µm dimer feature could also be used as an on/off gauge to set a lower bound for pressure. Determining total atmospheric pressure with only a reflected spectrum is difficult due to degeneracies between the O 2 concentration and total atmospheric pressure, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  15</ref>. For large equivalent widths of the dimer feature, the pressure will certainly be above 1 bar.</p><p>However, it is difficult to differentiate between atmospheres with the same O 2 surface partial pressure. Nevertheless, it appears that it is possible to set a lower limit on pressure by measuring the 1.06 µm dimer feature equivalent width. For example, a 1.06 µm dimer feature equivalent width greater than ∼10 nm would imply a surface pressure &gt;1 bar.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3.">Pressure Measurement with both transit transmission and reflected spectra</head><p>If both a transit transmission spectrum and a reflected spectrum are available, it should be possible to directly measure the total atmospheric surface pressure in the absence of clouds. Transit transmission spectroscopy can provide an estimate of the O 2 mixing ratio as described previously. A reflected spectrum can theoretically probe to the reflecting surface and therefore can be used to constrain the O 2 partial pressure at the surface. By combining the O 2 mixing ratio and O 2 partial pressure we can determine the total pressure at the reflecting surface, which could either be a reflective cloud layer or the physical surface of the planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Relevance to Planet Characterization</head><p>The methods described here could be used in the near future by the JWST NIRSPEC instrument, which will potentially be able to characterize transiting planets between 0.6 and 5.0 µm. The O 2 A band will likely not be detectable for a nearby Earth-analog with JWST. Although this feature is strong in the spectrum, the sensitivity of NIRSPEC is poor at shorter wavelengths. The 1.06 µm dimer feature is detectable at the 3σ level in transit transmission for cases with 2.0x PAL O 2 and high surface pressures. Thus, the detection of the 1.06 µm dimer feature would imply a surface or cloud-top pressure greater than or equal to 1.0 bars. For cases in which the 1.06 µm dimer feature is not detectable, the 1.27 µm feature could be used to constrain the pressure. This feature is not as strongly dependent on pressure as the 1.06 µm dimer feature, but it is more detectable in all cases explored here.</p><p>TPF, Darwin or a similar direct imaging mission will be required to characterize the reflected spectra of nearby Earth analogs in the visible and near-infrared. The SNR values for secondary eclipse using JWST are all less than 1, so JWST will not be able to characterize the reflected spectra of Earth-analogs in secondary eclipse. <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows the necessary SNRs to detect and characterize spectral features for a direct imaging planet characterization mission. While the SNRs were calculated for an Earth analog orbiting an M5V star, the results should be largely independent of spectral type because we have divided the reflected flux by the stellar flux in our calculations. The required SNR values suggest that a SNR of &gt;10 would be necessary to detect and quantify the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and 1.27 µm feature for a true Earth analog. However, because continuum brightness changes with pressure, a different SNR criteria would be necessary for higher pressure atmospheres. For example, the continuum brightness near the O 2 A band is three times lower for the 10.0 bar cases than it is for the 0.1 bar cases. For most cases, a SNR of &gt;7 would likely be sufficient to set a lower limit on the surface pressure using the 1.06 µm dimer feature.</p><p>Clouds and aerosols will also affect the detectability of absorption features. In transit transmission, clouds can effectively mask the highest pressures of the atmospheres at which dimer absorption is most prominent. However, in partially cloudy atmospheres some of the paths will probe pressures as high as the maximum tangent pressure, and thus the planetary transmission spectrum could show evidence of dimer absorption. Furthermore, absorption in the 1.27 µm dimer band can be detected with SNR&gt;1 in even some 0.1 bar cases, meaning that there could be a detectable dimer absorption signal for even a completely cloud-covered planet if the cloud deck pressure was ≥0.1 bars. For reflected spectra, clouds will truncate paths before they reach the surface and limit the dimer absorption for those paths. However, for partially cloudy atmospheres, dimer absorption could be detectable in the paths that do reach the surface. Additionally, because cloud albedos are typically greater than surface albedos, the presence of clouds will increase the continuum brightness levels and the brightness in the center of absorption bands. The increase in brightness has been shown to decrease the required SNR to detect and characterize O 2 monomer absorption in cloudy atmospheres when compared to cloud-free cases ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Evans et al. 2011</ref>), though the effect of cloud albedo on the detectability of dimer absorption features has not been heretofore examined. Therefore, while clouds will impact the detectability of dimer features, using dimers to determine pressure and as biosignatures may still be feasible for cloudy atmospheres.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Detectability at Different Resolving Powers</head><p>Figures 21 shows the SNRs for spectral features at varying resolving powers for transit transmission spectra of a 1.0 bar, 1.0x PAL O 2 atmosphere. The SNRs for each band are greatest at the highest resolving powers, and then gradually decrease until R∼60 or 80, at which the SNRs decrease strongly. This dramatic decrease with resolving power occurs because at the lowest resolving powers, the absorption bands are indistinguishable from the continuum. Additionally, the highest flux levels in the continuum cannot be resolved at lower spectral resolving powers, decreasing the total signal. This effect can be seen most easily for the spectra with R=20, in which no absorption features can be identified. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figures 23 and 24</ref> show the SNRs for the direct imaging reflected spectra. In contrast to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  21</ref>, these two figures show the required SNR to detect and characterize an absorption band, not the SNR that could be obtained with JWST. The required SNR to detect spectral features increases as resolving power decreases. However, this effect would be mitigated because the expected noise at each wavelength should decrease as resolving power decreases. The SNR required to quantify each absorption band decreases as resolving power decreases because the lowest radiance level increases. At R&lt;40, however, spectral features are very difficult to identify, making these resolving powers unsuitable for detecting and characterizing O 2 -related absorption features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">O 2 Dimer Biosignatures</head><p>In addition to their utility as pressure probes, the 1.06 µm dimer feature and 1.27 µm feature could potentially be detectable biosignatures for nearby Earth-like planets. The O 2 A band has long been considered the most viable O 2 biosignature, but it is unlikely to be the most detectable biosignature for an Earth-like planet in transit transmission. As initially described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Pallé et al. 2009</ref>), lunar eclipse observations show that the 1.06 µm and 1.27 µm dimer features are more detectable than O 2 monomer features like the A band, which is corroborated by our model spectra and detectability calculations. The 1.27 µm O 2 feature has been examined as a potential biosignature for ground-based telescopes by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Kawahara et al. (2012)</ref>, but to our knowledge detectability studies of neither the 1.06 µm dimer feature nor the 1.27 µm feature have been undertaken for JWST. Our results show that the 1.27 µm feature would be detectable with a SNR of 5 for a cloud-free Earthanalog at 5 pc. Therefore, we conclude that O 2 features, especially the 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature, could be detectable biosignatures for oxygenic photosynthesis with JWST.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Challenges to Observations</head><p>Clouds and aerosols will make estimating pressure using dimer features more difficult. A direct imaging observation of a partially cloud-covered planet will be able to probe to the surface for a fraction of the paths, such that the dimer feature will be weaker than for a cloud-free planet. Cloud and aerosol extinction can also be wavelength dependent, which may complicate using equivalent widths or ppm flux differences to determine pressure. Nevertheless dimer features can still provide a lower bound for pressure if clouds and aerosols cannot be explicitly included in the retrieval method.</p><p>Higher H 2 O or CO 2 abundances in an atmosphere could also make this method more challenging. Higher H 2 O abundances will make it more difficult to define a continuum for the 1.06 µm dimer feature, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 18 and 19</ref>. However, as discussed in Section 3.4, the magnitude of this error should typically be less than 20% for most cases in which the 1.06 µm dimer feature could be detectable. CO 2 has an absorption feature near 1.06 µm ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Segura et al. 2007</ref>), which could make using the 1.06 µm dimer feature difficult. This could be overcome by modeling out absorption from H 2 O and CO 2 or by using other dimer features to supplement information from the 1.06 µm dimer feature, such as the 1.27 µm dimer feature.</p><p>Lastly, not knowing the mixing ratio of O 2 will make estimating pressure difficult when only a reflected spectrum is available. This is similar to the problem in using the absorption widths of rotation-vibration features to constrain pressure. However, the 1.06 µm dimer feature is more sensitive to pressure than a monomer feature, and therefore can provide a better estimate of pressure than a monomer feature alone. Furthermore, monomer features cannot be used as an on/off pressure gauge, while dimer features can.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>Spectrally resolved observations of O 2 dimer absorption can be combined with observations of the absorption by O 2 vibration-rotation bands to provide independent constraints on the O 2 concentration and the surface or cloud-top pressure in oxygenated atmospheres for planets around M dwarfs, and with low levels of CO 2 . Even if a precise estimate for the pressure is not possible, the presence of dimer absorption is indicative of pressures greater than ≃0.5 bars in transmission spectroscopy, and greater than ≃1 bars in reflected spectra.</p><p>We have shown that this method is feasible in the absence of clouds for oxygenated atmospheres. For transmission spectroscopy this method can be used to estimate the surface or cloudtop pressure for O 2 concentrations ≥ 100% PAL and for pressures &gt;0.5 bars. For reflected spectra this method will work if the O 2 partial pressure at the surface is &gt;0.3 bars. Clouds will reduce the absorption strength of dimer features by limiting the paths that can probe the highest pressures in transit transmission, and by truncating paths before they reach the surface in the reflected spectra.</p><p>JWST may be able to detect the 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm O 2 feature for an Earth analog orbiting an M dwarf in transit transmission. Thus, while not all the techniques described here will be applicable to JWST observations, a lower bound on pressure could be set for an exoplanet using an O 2 dimer feature. Furthermore, we showed that a direct imaging mission operating in the visible and near-infrared like TPF would require a spectral resolving power of R&gt;40, and preferably higher. At R=100, a SNR of &gt;30 would be required to not only detect O 2 related absorption features, but to also provide an estimate of an exoplanet's atmospheric pressure. 9.0e-03 2.1e-01 5.0e-02 <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>: SNRs for the O 2 A band, the 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature for all the cases considered in both transit transmission and secondary eclipse. The calculations were done for an Earth analog orbiting an M5V star at a distance of 5 pc. The total integration time was assumed to be 10 6 s, equal to the total amount of time spent in transit for this case over JWST's 5 year mission lifetime. The 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature could be detectable, allowing a lower limit for atmospheric pressure to be set.   <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>: SNRs for detection (SNR D ) and to obtain precision of 3σ in the center of the band (SNR P ) for the O 2 A band, the 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature at pressures ranging from 0.1 to 10.0 bars and O 2 concentrations ranging from 0.1 to 2.0 times PAL O 2 for direct imaging reflected spectra. Only paths that lie exactly on that dashed line will be observed. For the M dwarf case, there will be a path connecting the star to the observer through the atmosphere at this particular tangent height. However, there is no path in the Sun-like star case. This means that a transit transmission spectrum of the planet around the M dwarf can theoretically probe higher pressures of the atmosphere than in the Sun-like star case. 06 µm dimer feature is strong only in the spectra corresponding to atmospheric pressures greater than ∼0.5 bar. The spectra for atmospheres with pressure ≥1 bar are nearly identical except for an offset because there is a fundamental limit on which heights in an atmosphere can be probed using transmission spectroscopy. For an Earth-like atmosphere around the M5V used here, only the top 0.9 bars can be probed for all atmospheres at all wavelengths. This pressure corresponds to an altitude of ∼1 km above the surface for a 1 bar atmosphere, and 19 km above the surface for a 10 bar atmosphere. The offset is due to the flux blocked by layers in the atmosphere with pressure greater than 0.9 bars. In the reflected spectrum there is no fundamental limit to which pressures can be probed in an atmosphere. Assuming a cloud-free case, it is possible to probe the surface layers of the atmosphere. The 1.06 µm dimer feature is fairly weak in the present day Earth's atmosphere, but it is a very strong feature in atmospheres with greater pressures. The 1.27 µm feature is very strong in most of the spectra.   In transmission, for the Earth-like planet orbiting an M5V star considered here, only the top 0.9 bars can be probed, meaning the dimer and A band equivalent widths are roughly constant with pressure above 1.0 bars for a given O 2 concentration. In comparison to the reflected spectra, the dimer equivalent widths are extremely sensitive to pressure.    <ref type="figure">Figure 20</ref>. The SNRs decrease as resolving power decreases because the absorption bands can no longer be resolved from the continuum. For R=30 and R=20 it is very difficult to identify any of the O 2 spectral features.  <ref type="figure">Fig. 23</ref>.-SNRs needed to detect the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature for direct imaging reflected spectra. As resolving power decreases, the required SNR to detect each feature increases because the continuum level decreases, resulting in a lower overall signal in the absorption band. Furthermore, at the lowest resolutions the absorption bands cannot be resolved. Thus, this decreases the measurable signal even more, leading to an increase in the required SNR. </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">SNR P SNR D SNR P SNR D SNR P 0.1 0.1 &gt;100 3.1 - - - - 0.1 0.5 50.0 3.2 - - &gt;100 3.0 0.1 1.0 35.0 5.4 - -<label>&gt;100 5</label></formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figures 17 ,</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Figures 17, 18 and 19 show the results for the H 2 O sensitivity tests. The O 2 A band equivalent widths and ppm flux differences are not strongly affected by changes in the H 2 O profiles. However, changes in the H 2 O mixing ratios affect the continuum flux in the wings of the 1.06 micron dimer feature, complicating measurements of the equivalent width of this feature. For the transit transmission spectra, the change in the total ppm flux difference (across the entire band) is less than 20% between the 0.1 and 10.0x H 2 O cases. For the reflected spectra, the change in the equivalent width of the 1.06 µm dimer feature is less than 20%. For the reflected spectra, the equivalent widths can be much greater than that for the 1.0 bar, 2.0x O 2 case. For these greater equivalent widths, the effect of increasing or decreasing H 2 O levels will diminish as the difference from the continuum flux (affected by H 2 O) and the flux within the absorption band will increase.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A band O 2 -O 2 1.06 µm O 2 1.27 µm O 2 A band O 2 -O 2 1.06 µm O 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Comparison of the effect of refraction on (a) an exoplanet around an M dwarf and (b) a planet around a Sun-like star with both planets receiving the same total flux. The dashed circles are the planetary atmospheres. The solid lines represent different refracted paths through the atmosphere, and the dashed lines are the hypothetical paths to a distant observer observing the planet in transit transmission. Only paths that lie exactly on that dashed line will be observed. For the M dwarf case, there will be a path connecting the star to the observer through the atmosphere at this particular tangent height. However, there is no path in the Sun-like star case. This means that a transit transmission spectrum of the planet around the M dwarf can theoretically probe higher pressures of the atmosphere than in the Sun-like star case.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .Fig. 3 .Fig. 4 .</head><label>234</label><figDesc>Fig. 2.-Wavelength-dependent albedos for a variety of surfaces. The shaded regions correspond to O 2 monomer and dimer bands. For any absorption band, as long as the albedo does not vary widely within the band's wavelength range it should be possible to measure an accurate equivalent width for each feature. The maximum variation within a band is no more than ∼20%. Therefore we do not consider surface albedo variations important for this work.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .Fig. 7 .Fig. 8 .</head><label>5678</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Same as Figure 4 but for 10% of the present day level of O 2 . The dimer features do not appear at all because the O 2 concentration is too low.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .Fig. 11 .</head><label>91011</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.-Same as Figure 8 but for an O 2 concentration of 10% PAL. For this amount of O 2 , the 1.06 µm dimer feature is very weak. However, the 1.27 µm feature is still quite strong.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 13 .Fig. 14 .Fig. 15 .Fig. 16 .</head><label>13141516</label><figDesc>Fig. 13.-This plot shows how one could determine a lower limit on the surface or cloud-top pressure using only a transmission spectrum.(a) O 2 partial pressure at maximum tangent pressure vs. the ratio of the dimer feature and O 2 A band flux difference ratio. The ratio can be used to determine the O 2 partial pressure. (b) fO 2 (or O 2 mixing ratio) vs A band flux difference. The A band flux difference is roughly constant for a given O 2 mixing ratio.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 18 .Fig. 19 .Fig. 20 .Fig. 21 .</head><label>18192021</label><figDesc>Fig. 18.-The 1.06 µm dimer feature in transit transmission with different amounts of H 2 O. The spectra have been artificially offset for ease of viewing. The black dashed lines are spectra that do not include any O 2 dimer absorption and are included to help show the continuum flux level. The total ppm flux difference and SNR for the dimer band vary by less than 20% with respect to the 1.0xH 2 O case.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 22 .</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Fig. 22.-Direct imaging reflected spectra generated at spectral resolving powers from 500 to 20. The y-axis is the planetary albedo with an arbitrary offset added for ease of viewing. The O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and 1.27 µm feature are highlighted. At resolving powers of R=30 and R=20 it is difficult to identify any O 2 absorption features.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 24 .</head><label>24</label><figDesc>Fig. 24.-SNRs required to quantify the flux within 3σ in the center of the absorption band (defined as the lowest flux level) for the O 2 A band, 1.06 µm dimer feature and the 1.27 µm feature. The SNR required for this level of precision decreases as resolving power decreases because the flux is averaged over fewer wavelength bins, leading to an increase in the lowest flux. This decrease in required resolving power occurs for all three absorption features, though the trend is most apparent for the O 2 A band, as it has the narrowest spectral shape of the three features considered here.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> http://jwstetc.stsci.edu</note>

			<note place="foot">This preprint was prepared with the AAS L A T E X macros v5.2.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We thank Drake Deming for helpful dscussions on the detectability calculations, and the two anonymous reviewers for their thorough and helpful reviews that greatly improved the paper. This work was performed by the NASA Astrobiology Institute's Virtual Planetary Laboratory, supported by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration through the NASA Astrobiology Institute under Cooperative Agreement solicitation NNH05ZDA001C. This work has also been supported by a generous fellowship from the ARCS Seattle chapter and funding from the Astrobiology program at the University of Washington under an NSF IGERT award. Some of the work described here was conducted at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, under contract with NASA.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Disclosure Statement</head><p>No competing financial interests exist.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloud pressure retrieval using the O 2 -O 2 absorption band at 477 nm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Acarreta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>De Haan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stammes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research (Atmospheres)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Astronomical Refraction: Computational Method for All Zenith Angles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Standish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astronomical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2472" to="2474" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The ASTER Spectral Library Version 2.0. Remote Sensing of Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baldridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Grove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="715" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remote measurement of surface pressure using absorption in the oxygen A-band</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Optics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3502" to="3507" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A ground-based transmission spectrum of the super-Earth exoplanet GJ 1214b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Miller-Ricci Kempton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">468</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="672" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primary and secondary eclipse spectroscopy with JWST: exploring the exoplanet parameter space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Belu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-C</forename><surname>Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cossou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission Spectra as Diagnostics of Extrasolar Giant Planet Atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1026" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absolute photometric calibration of IRAC: lessons learned using nine years of flight data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric origins of perchlorate on Mars and in the Atacama</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Catling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Claire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zahnle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kounaves</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planets) 115, 0</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based near-infrared observations of water vapour in the Venus troposphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chamberlain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping Martian Atmospheric Pressure with Ground-Based Near Infrared Spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chamberlain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of an Extrasolar Planet Atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">568</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Swayze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Livo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoefen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kokaly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>USGS digital spectral library splib06a: U.S. Geological Survey, Digital Data Series 231</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absorption of sunlight by water vapor in cloudy conditions: A partial explanation for the cloud absorption anomaly</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysical Research Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="571" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">and 33 colleagues 2012. The ACOS CO 2 retrieval algorithm -Part II: Global X CO 2 data characterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atmospheric Measurement Techniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="707" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Views from EPOXI: Colors in Our Solar System as an Analog for Extrasolar Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Crow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcfadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Livengood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hewagama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lisse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wellnitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">729</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery and Characterization of Transiting Super Earths Using an All-Sky Transit Survey and Follow-up by the James Webb Space Telescope. Publications of the</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomical Society of the Pacific</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="952" to="967" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infrared Transmission Spectroscopy of the Exoplanets HD 209458b and XO-1b Using the Wide Field Camera-3 on the Hubble Space Telescope</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Biogenic Sulfur Gases as Remotely Detectable Biosignatures on Anoxic Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Domagal-Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Claire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring The Detectability of Terrestrial Exoplanet Characteristics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Domagal-Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>#343.09</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remote sensing of surface pressure on Mars with the Mars Express/OMEGA spectrometer: 1. Retrieval method</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Forget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Spiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vinatier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Melchiorri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Drossart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gendrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Bibring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Langevin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gondet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planets) 112, 8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glancing Views of the Earth: From a Lunar Eclipse to an Exoplanetary Transit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Montañés-Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">755</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">and 22 colleagues 2006. The James Webb Space Telescope</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Space Science Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="606" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission of the Atmosphere of Mars in the Region of 2 µm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">390</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absorption measurements of oxygen between 330 and 1140 nm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Greenblatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Orlando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Burkholder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ravishankara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18577" to="18582" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The NextGen Model Atmosphere Grid for 3000&lt;=T eff&lt;=10,000 K</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hauschildt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of Extrasolar Giant Planet Transits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sudarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">560</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altimetry of the Venus cloud tops from the Venus Express observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ignatiev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Titov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Piccioni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Drossart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Markiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Cottini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Roatsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Manoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planets) 114, 0</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transits of Earth-like Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaltenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Traub</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">698</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="527" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of the Spectrum of Mars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Münch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Spinrad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanet characterization and the search for life</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Traub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://sites.nationalacademies.org/BPA/BPA_050603#planetarysystems" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics Decadal Survey</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can Ground-based Telescopes Detect the Oxygen 1.27 µm Absorption Feature as a Biomarker in Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kawahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Takami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fujii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kotani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Murakami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">758</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical design of the nearinfrared spectrograph NIRSpec</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Köhler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Melf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Posselt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Holota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Te Plate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5962</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="574" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rise of atmospheric oxygen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kump</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">451</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Science Potential of JWST for Exoplanet Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lafreniere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Fgs/Niriss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Miri</forename><surname>Nircam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nirspec</forename><surname>Science</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>#135.06</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">221</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absolute intensities for the O 2 1.27 µm continuum absorption</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Maté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lugez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30585" to="30590" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based near-infrared observations of the Venus nightside: The thermal structure and water abundance near the surface</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4595" to="4622" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Error Estimates for Passive Satellite Measurement of Surface Pressure Using Absorption in the A Band of Oxygen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Atmospheric Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1981" to="1990" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Earth&apos;s transmission spectrum from lunar eclipse observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Montañés-Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="814" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of Planetary Climate. Principles of Planetary Climate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pierrehumbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>R. T Pierrehumbert</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">9780521865562</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of atmospheric haze on an extrasolar planet: the 0.55-1.05 µm transmission spectrum of HD 189733b with the Hubble Space Telescope</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential biosignatures in super-Earth atmospheres. I. Spectral appearance of super-Earths around M dwarfs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gebauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Paris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Godolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Grenfell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Belu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hedelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schreier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HITRAN 2008 molecular spectroscopic database</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Spectroscopy and Radiative Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theoretical Transmission Spectra during Extrasolar Giant Planet Transits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sasselov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">537</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="916" to="921" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Biosignatures from Earth-Like Planets Around M Dwarfs</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="706" to="725" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abiotic formation of O 2 and O 3 in high-CO 2 terrestrial atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">472</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computational thermodynamic evaluation of the altitude profiles of (N 2 ) 2 , N 2 -O 2 and (O 2 ) 2 in the Earth&apos;s atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Slanina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Uhlk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>De Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hinchliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thermochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">231</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remote sensing of surface pressure on Mars with the Mars Express/OMEGA spectrometer: 2. Meteorological maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Spiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Forget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vinatier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Melchiorri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Drossart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gendrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Bibring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Langevin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gondet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planets) 112, 8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gas-phase association of O2: a computation thermodynamic study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Uhlik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Slanina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hinchliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thermochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An extended upper atmosphere around the extrasolar planet HD209458b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ballester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ferlet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">and 15 colleagues 2013. HST hot Jupiter transmission spectral survey: detection of water in HAT-P-1b from WFC3 near-IR spatial scan observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3481" to="3493" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bistable organic-rich atmosphere on the Neoarchaean Earth</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zerkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Claire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Domagal-Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Farquhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Poulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Geoscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
