<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-11T13:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanet phase curves at large phase angles. Diagnostics for extended hazy atmospheres</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Zentrum für Astronomie und Astrophysik</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Technische Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-10623</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institut für Planetenforschung</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deutsches Zentrum für Luft-und Raumfahrt</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-12489</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanet phase curves at large phase angles. Diagnostics for extended hazy atmospheres</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">MNRAS</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">September 2017. Accepted for publication in MNRAS.</note>
					<note>Preprint 2 October 2018 Compiled using MNRAS L A T E X style file v3.0</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>planets and satellites: atmospheres -techniques: photometric -scatter- ing</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>At optical wavelengths, Titan&apos;s brightness for large Sun-Titan-observer phase angles significantly exceeds its dayside brightness. The brightening that occurs near back-illumination is due to moderately large haze particles in the moon&apos;s extended atmosphere that forward-scatter the incident sunlight. Motivated by this phenomenon, here we investigate the forward scattering from currently known exoplanets, its diagnostics possibilities, the observational requirements to resolve it, and potential implications. An analytical expression is derived for the amount of starlight forward-scattered by an exponential atmosphere that takes into account the finite angular size of the star. We use this expression to tentatively estimate how prevalent this phenomenon may be. Based on numerical calculations that consider exoplanet visibility, we identify numerous planets with predicted out-of-transit forward scattering signals of up to tens of parts-per-million provided that aerosols of 1 µm size form over an extended vertical region near the optical radius level. We propose that the interpretation of available optical phase curves should be revised to constrain the strength of this phenomenon that might provide insight into aerosol scale heights and particle sizes. For the relatively general atmospheres considered here, forward scattering reduces the transmission-only transit depth by typically less than the equivalent to a scale height. For short-period exoplanets the finite angular size of the star severely affects the amount of radiation scattered towards the observer at mid-transit.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Given the limited possibilities that exist for the remote sensing of exoplanet atmospheres, it is crucial to understand the information contained in each observing technique and the synergies between them. In that setting, this work aims to show that brightness measurements at large starplanet-observer phase angles potentially inform on atmospheric properties such as the scale height and scattering properties of aerosols in the uppermost atmospheric layers. Our investigation is motivated by recent work on Saturn's moon Titan <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(García Muñoz et al. 2017)</ref> showing that Titan brightens up at phase angles α&gt;150 • and that, when backilluminated, it becomes brighter than in full illumination by a wavelength-dependent factor of 10-200. The presence of forward-scattering haze in Titan's extended atmosphere is key to the occurrence of this optical phenomenon. Its E-mail:</p><p>garciamunoz@astro.physik.tu-berlin.de; tonhingm@gmail.com prospective detection at an exoplanet will allow us to infer the occurrence of haze and, more importantly, will provide insight into its vertical distribution and particle size near the optical radius level. <ref type="figure">Figure (</ref>1) sketches the phenomenon.</p><p>The effect of forward scattering on the measured radius of transiting planets has been considered before <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Brown 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Hubbard et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">De Kok &amp; Stam 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Robinson 2017</ref>). In particular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">De Kok &amp; Stam (2012)</ref> note that it may bias the transit radius by up to a few scale heights in specific cases, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Robinson (2017)</ref> observes that the bias can be of hundreds of partsper-million (ppm) for hot Jupiters. None of these works provide an easy way to quantitatively estimate the effect, or its connection with the stratification and size of the dominating atmospheric particles. As shown later, the finite angular size of the star as viewed from the planet limits the amount of starlight forward-scattered towards the observer during the transit, and forward scattering will affect the measured transit radius by less than a scale height in typical configurations with scattering particles of up to a few µm in size.</p><p>Our treatment here differs from the above works in that we focus preferentially on orbital phases immediately before or after transit. This configuration is better suited to identify the forward scattering contribution.</p><p>To date, the best evidence for forward scattering from exoplanets comes from ultra-short period planets on orbits of less than one day. In a few such systems, the shape of the pre-/post-transit brightness curve is attributed to starlight scattered from dust clouds surrounding the planets (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Bu- daj 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">DeVore et al. 2016)</ref>. Since the dust is plausibly of planetary origin, these planets are thought to be disintegrating. Refraction may also produce shoulders in the pre-/post-transit brightness curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Hui &amp; Seager 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Sidis &amp; Sari 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">García Muñoz &amp; Mills 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Misra &amp; Meadows 2014)</ref>. Refraction lensing of starlight by the planet atmosphere competes with extinction within the atmosphere. As a result, a brightness surge due to refraction will be prominent only on planets with clear, aerosol-free envelopes <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(García Muñoz &amp; Mills 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Misra &amp; Meadows 2014</ref>). Contrary to forward scattering, refraction lensing becomes significant for planets on relatively longperiod orbits <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Sidis &amp; Sari 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Misra &amp; Meadows 2014)</ref>. This distinction should make it posible to identify whether the brightness surge is due to refraction or to forward scattering.</p><p>The paper is structured as follows. In §2 we summarize the findings on Titan that motivate this study and generalize them for application to exponential atmospheres. In §3 we describe, through combined analytical and numerical work, the planet properties more favourable for forward scattering. Based on a zeroth-order characterization, we attempt to classify the known exoplanets according to their potential for forward scattering. In §4 we elaborate further on the detectability of this phenomenon out of transit. In §5 we comment on the blending with the brightness modulation due to stellar tides, and on the impact upon the measured transit radius. Finally, §6 summarizes the main conclusions and presents avenues for follow-up studies. In the appendices, we derive an analytical expression for the amount of starlight forward scattered by a planet with an exponential atmosphere, comment on the accuracy of the single scattering approximation, and describe the modifications to our numerical radiative transfer model to take into account the finite angular size of the star.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">FORWARD SCATTERING</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Titan</head><p>The brightness phase curve of Titan is quite unique. Titan dims as it passes from phase angles α=0 to α∼120 • due to the decreasing area of the dayside visible to the observer <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Tomasko &amp; Smith 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">West et al. 1983</ref>). For larger phase angles, however, the diminishing size of the visible dayside is compensated by forward scattering from the abundant upper-atmosphere haze and the whole-disk brightness increases again. Observations made with the Cassini Imaging Science Subsystem have revealed that at α∼165 • Titan becomes as bright as in full illumination <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(García Muñoz et al. 2017</ref>). An empirically-constrained prediction of that study is that for α→180 • , Titan's twilight appears brighter than α αI,IV <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Top. Orbit sketch. α is the star-planet-observer phase angle and α I,IV the angle at first or fourth contacts, i.e. immediately before or after transit. The arrows indicate the direction towards the observer. Bottom. Titan's phase curve from Cassini/ISS white-light photometry (effective wavelength of 650 nm) (black symbols) and best-fit model based on solving the radiative transfer problem with a realistic description of the atmosphere (red curve) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(García Muñoz et al. 2017</ref>). The two grey intervals span an identical range ∆α of phase angles, and indicate the forward scattering and control intervals (see text). The observable O is defined as the difference in the mean values of the planet brightness over the two intervals. In the example, α D =170 • and ∆α=20 • . In the examples with real planets, we always assume α D =α I,IV .</p><p>its dayside by a factor of ∼10 at wavelengths of ∼1 µm and by factors of up to 200 at wavelengths of ∼300 nm. This behaviour is due to the facts that Titan has an atmosphere that is both extended and hazy, and that the haze particles are moderately large (equal-projected-area radii ∼2-3 µm) and thus efficient at forward scattering ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Rages et al. 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">West &amp; Smith 1991)</ref>. The haze is produced photochemically through reactions initiated in the upper atmosphere ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Lavvas et al. 2010</ref>). Forward scattering from Titan originates within a few scale heights from the level at</p><p>Exoplanet phase curves at large phase angles. Diagnostics for extended hazy atmospheres. 3 which the atmosphere is optically thick when viewed through the limb. This is similar to the optical radius level probed during a hypothetical transit of Titan across the solar disk ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Karkoschka et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Lecavelier des Etangs et al. 2008)</ref>. Near that level, the number densities of the gas and haze drop in altitude with comparable scale heights, H∼H a ∼45 km. If R T stands for Titan's optical radius (∼3,000 km, dependent on wavelength), H a /R T ∼1.5×10 −2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Exponential atmospheres</head><p>Next, we identify the key planet properties that result in strong forward scattering. Appendix A elaborates on exponential atmospheres described in terms of an average scattering particle and a single scale height. We will refer to the average scattering particles as aerosols, although they may actually represent a mix of gases and condensates in the atmosphere. For an exponential atmosphere, the aerosol number density decays as n a (r)=n a (R 0 )exp (−(r − R 0 )/H a ), where r is the radial distance to the planet centre and R 0 is a reference level. H a is the aerosol scale height.</p><p>In this idealized scenario and α→180 • , single scattering dominates (Appendix B) and the planet-to-star contrast is approximately (Appendix A):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F p F (α = 180 • ) ≈ 2πp a (θ = 0) 0,a H a R p R p a 2 .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Here, p a (θ=0) and 0,a refer to the aerosol scattering phase function in the forward direction (scattering angle θ=0) and the aerosol single scattering albedo, respectively. (p a (θ=0) is the relevant phase function when the angular size of the star as viewed from the planet is small, i.e. in the point-like star limit; otherwise a generalized form &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) should be used, Appendix A.) H a /R p is the ratio of the aerosol scale height to the planet radius, and R p /a the ratio of the planet radius to the orbital distance. The geometrical terms in Eq. (1) can be re-arranged into 2πR p H a /a 2 , the numerator of which is the projected area of a ring of radius R p and width H a . This ring, which concentrates most of the forwardscattered starlight, is seen in large phase angle images of Titan <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(García Muñoz et al. 2017</ref>). Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> is analogous to the usual representation of the planet-to-star brightness contrast in full illumination (α=0) if the underlined terms are replaced by the geometric albedo, A g (see Eq. 2 below). Equation (1) enables the direct comparison of the brightness of a planet when it is fully illuminated (α=0) and backilluminated (α=180 • ). The single scattering albedo 0,a is of order one for many plausible condensates in exoplanet atmospheres ( <ref type="bibr">Bu- daj et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Wakeford &amp; Sing 2015)</ref>. However, both p a (θ=0) and H a /R p are likely to differ by orders of magnitude amongst different planets depending on the specifics of their atmospheres. (However, for short-period planets the finite angular size of the star will limit the effective scattering phase function to &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0), which may be much smaller than p a (θ=0); Appendix A.) H a /R p is a measure of how puffy the atmosphere is, meaning that large (∼10 −2 ) values are associated with extended envelopes. It is seen from Eq. (1) that for a given R p /a (measurable for transiting systems), the strength of forward scattering depends <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Refractive indices of condensates at λ eff =0.65 µm, based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Budaj et al. (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Wakeford &amp; Sing (2015)</ref> on p a (θ=0)H a /R p . Also according to <ref type="bibr">Eq. (1)</ref>, the strength of this effect depends on orbital distance as a −2 . This interpretation is however likely oversimplistic as the orbital distance will foreseeably affect the planet temperature and therefore p a (θ) through the microphysics that enables aerosol formation. Also, for small orbital distances, the finite size of the star tends to reduce the relevant &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) with respect to p a (θ=0).</p><p>To illustrate how forward scattering affects the planet brightness at configurations other than α=180 • , we produced numerical solutions to the problem of multiple scattering in spherical, exponential atmospheres. We generally assumed that the aerosols scatter following Mie theory, and that the photon wavelength is λ eff =0.65 µm. For the aerosol particles we assumed a power law size distribution with effective radii r eff ranging from 0.01 to 10 µm and a fixed effective variance v eff =0.1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Hansen &amp; Travis 1974)</ref>. We adopted refractive indices (n=n r +in i ) specific to a few plausible condensates listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (1)</ref>. The selection of condensates does not rank them by relevance in the context of exoplanet atmospheres. Rather, it simply tries to include a variety of refractive indices. In Mie theory, p a (θ) depends on all three properties: x eff =2πr eff /λ eff , v eff and n. More specifically, p a (θ=0) depends strongly on x eff but weakly on v eff and n, and typically increases as x eff increases, which establishes a diagnostic connection between the particle size and the strength of forward scattering. The implemented single scattering albedos 0,a were also calculated from Mie theory. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure (2)</ref> shows the calculated p a (θ=0) and 0,a . For comparison, we also produced phase curves based on atmospheres with Titan-like haze at an effective wavelength λ eff =600 nm. In these cases, we adopted p a (θ) as reported in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tomasko et al. (2008)</ref>, and for 0,a we simply experimented with values between 0.2 and 1.</p><p>For the smaller orbital distances, the star appears as an extended object as viewed from the planet, a fact that must be considered in the implementation of the aerosols scattering phase function going into the multiple scattering calculations. The way to deal with this is to convolve p a (θ) with the star disk brightness ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Budaj et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">DeVore et al. 2016</ref>) in the evaluation of the starlight entering the atmosphere ( §4.1, and Appendices A and C). The result-ing effective scattering phase function &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) depends on the limb-darkening law and the angular size of the star. For p a (θ) functions associated with strong forward scattering, the effective scattering phase function for deflections larger than the angular radius of the star, i.e. Θ&gt;θ =arcsin R /a, is usually larger than the non-convolved p a (θ) <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Bu- daj et al. (2015)</ref>; <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. A2</ref> in Appendix A). The opposite is generally true for Θ&lt;θ . In contrast, for p a (θ) functions associated with mild forward scattering, the convolution process has little impact on the effective scattering phase function &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3</ref>  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(2016)</ref>). For simplicity, as the convolution process is specific to each planet-star system, we have omitted this effect from most of the multiple scattering calculations done here. Its omission will tend to increase the forward scattering signal towards the observer at out-of-transit orbital phases. Therefore, the calculations presented here in the point-like star limit for pre-/post-transit configurations generally underestimate the actual forward scattering signal received by the observer. In §4.1, we provide examples of how the finite angular size of the star will impact the brightness phase curve in the specific case of the exoplanet CoRoT-24b.</p><p>It is convenient to present the planet-to-star contrast in a manner that separates the various geometric and nongeometric factors:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">F p F (α) = A g Φ(α) R p a 2 .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Here, A g is the geometric albedo and Φ(α) (Φ(α≡0)=1) the planet phase law. The definition of R p is somewhat arbitrary for planets with extended atmospheres. Because we are mainly interested in gas planets with large scale heights, we will use for R p the optical radius, which is based on the limb-viewing optical thickness of the atmosphere, τ limb . The optical radius at an effective wavelength λ eff is calculated from the condition ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Karkoschka et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Lecavelier des Etangs et al. 2008)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">τ limb (R p ) = τ nadir (R p → TOA)(2πR p /H a ) 1/2 = 0.56,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>and the optical thickness from the optical radius level R p to the top of the atmosphere (TOA):</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">τ nadir (R p → TOA) = τ nadir,0 exp (−(R p − R 0 )/H a ).<label>(4)</label></formula><p>The square root term in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref> is the approximate conversion factor between limb-and nadir-integrated columns in exponential atmospheres. τ nadir,0 is the nadir optical thickness upwards of the R 0 reference level. We could take R 0 deep enough into the planet and τ nadir,0 large enough so that the exponential description of the atmosphere effectively reaches to all depths. Instead, and to alleviate the computational cost of the calculations, we implemented finite values for R 0 (equal to a Jupiter radius, R J ) and τ nadir,0 (=10). Also, the atmosphere below the R 0 level was replaced by a black surface. The truncation of the atmosphere at R 0 will affect the planet's overall reflectance at the smaller phase angles, but not at large phase angles because in the latter viewing configuration the stellar photons will not penetrate to such depths. R p (&gt;R 0 ) can be solved numerically from Eqs. (3)-(4) for a given scale height H a . In total, we produced about 800 phase curves for different combinations of aerosol composition, particle radius and ratio of the aerosol scale height to the planet optical radius. <ref type="figure">Figure (</ref>3) shows a subset of them in the dimensionless form A g Φ(α). From top to bottom, the graphs are arranged by increasing H a /R p . It is apparent that puffy planets with large H a /R p ratios exhibit stronger forward scattering. A g Φ(α)&gt;1 is possible at large phase angles, especially for puffy atmospheres rich in large aerosol particles. This physically consistent result confirms that the overall planet brightness mimics to some extent the behaviour of the aerosols scattering phase function when the planet is back-illuminated.</p><p>The graphs in the left and central columns show the impact of particle size for two compositions that result in more reflective (Mg 2 SiO 4 ) or absorbing (FeO) aerosols. The effective radius of the particles r eff affects both p a (θ) and 0,a . Larger r eff values typically lead to p a (θ) functions with a stronger diffraction peak focused on a narrower range of scattering angles. This behaviour is mimicked by the planet phase curve, which tends to exhibit a brightness surge closer to α=180 • . The finite angular size of the star, an effect omitted in the calculations of <ref type="figure">Fig. (3)</ref>, will smear the forward scattering peak and leak it into smaller angles (see §4.1).</p><p>At small phase angles, the planet brightness is strongly dependent on 0,a . The simulations show that atmospheres with Mg 2 SiO 4 aerosols ( 0,a ∼0.997 for r eff =1 µm) result in brighter planets than if they are rich in FeO aerosols ( 0,a ∼0.555 for r eff =1 µm). At large phase angles however the dependence of the planet brightness with the assumed 0,a is almost linear (Eq. 1) and the difference between the Mg 2 SiO 4 -and FeO-aerosol atmospheres is reduced.</p><p>The graphs in the right column of <ref type="figure">Fig. (3)</ref> show phase curves calculated with Titan-like haze scattering phase functions p a (θ) at λ eff =600 nm ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tomasko et al. 2008)</ref>. To explore the impact of 0,a , we ran this set of simulations with 0,a values between 0.2 and 1, as indicated in the graphs. This battery of simulations confirms that the planet brightness is very sensitive to 0,a at the small phase angles, but much less so at large phase angles.</p><p>As a corollary, the analytical expression of Eq. (1) (and its generalization to finite angular size stars) together with the phase curves of <ref type="figure">Fig. (3)</ref> indicate that: extended hazy atmospheres result in significant forward scattering at large phase angles; the aerosol size partly dictates the strength of the phenomenon and whether it occurs on either a narrow or broad range of phase angles (at least in the point-like star limit); the aerosol composition is not critical at large phase angles. The arguments presented above suggest that the detection of such an optical phenomenon at an exoplanet will lead to a joint constraint on its aerosol scale height and particle size.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EXTENDED HAZY ATMOSPHERES</head><p>Diverse theoretical approaches to the formation of condensates in exoplanet atmospheres of different complexity and scope have been presented in the literature (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Marley et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Sudarsky et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ackerman &amp; Marley 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mor- ley et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Helling &amp; Fomins 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Parmentier et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lee et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Lavvas &amp; Koskinen 2017)</ref>. Their predictive capacity however remains uncertain. In an attempt to develop a few guidelines, <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Sudarsky et al. (2000)</ref> proposed five broadly-defined regimes in the formation of condensates on substellar gas objects depending on the objects temper-ature. This classification is not comprehensive, but is useful because reveals part of the complexity of the problem. Specifically, the authors indicate that the low-gravity (g&lt;10 m s −2 ), very hot (&gt;1,500 K) planets of their Class V are likely to have silicate condensates lofted high in their (extended) atmospheres and therefore appear as highly reflective during occultations and hazy during transits. If the prediction is correct, these planets would be potential candidates for strong forward scattering provided that the condensate particles are of the appropriate size. The increasing number of exoplanet data has also led to phenomenological approaches that seek to correlate the empirical evidence for condensates with properties such as planet gravity or temperature (Stevenson 2016), water absorption ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Sing et al. 2016)</ref>, or the muting of alkali features in the visible and near infrared <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Heng 2016</ref>). In particular, Stevenson (2016) suggests on the basis of near-infrared observations for 14 exoplanets that condensates form preferentially in low gravity (g&lt;16 ms −2 ), low temperature (T eq &lt;750 K) environments. On the other hand, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barstow et al. (2017)</ref> note that from their sample of 10 hot Jupiters the planets with T eq &lt;1,300 or &gt;1,700 K seem to exhibit Rayleigh extinction at short wavelengths attributable to small condensates. In contrast, the planets of their sample with temperatures in the 1,300-1,700 K range seem to exhibit wavelengthindependent extinction suggestive of larger condensates. The predictive capacity of phenomenological approaches remains to be confirmed with additional targets and tested with robust interpretation tools ( <ref type="bibr">Stevenson et al. 2016</ref>).</p><p>The uncertainties in the occurrence of condensates in exoplanet atmospheres translate into uncertainties in their vertical distribution, composition and particle size. <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Sing et al. (2016)</ref> note that if the pressure-temperature profile of an atmosphere runs (nearly) parallel to the condensation curve of a potential condensate, disturbances in the temperaturepressure profile may cause that the planet atmosphere shows itself as either hazy or essentially clear. The condensate composition will depend on the material available for condensation and on the local chemistry if the haze is formed photochemically. The particle size will depend on these effects, but also on competing microphysical processes that may either favour or disrupt the growth of small aerosols onto larger ones. Atmospheric dynamics, and its capacity to keep the particles suspended against gravitational settling, will also play a role.</p><p>A number of exoplanets reveal continuum extinction that increases towards ultraviolet wavelengths. The usual interpretation of this behaviour is that the wavelengthdependent extinction cross sections of small, weaklyabsorbing particles (σ∝λ −α with α∼4) cause the so-called Rayleigh slopes in the planet transmission spectra (Lecavelier des <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Etangs et al. 2008</ref>). Evidence for small condensates has also been found in the interpretation of reflected starlight. Planets with large-particle clouds will likely exhibit more structure in their brightness variation with orbital phase than if the particles are small <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Seager et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jenkins &amp; Doyle 2003)</ref>. This idea lies at the core of a recent analysis of Kepler-7b's optical phase curve that shows that the measurements are consistent with morning-side clouds made of poorly absorbing, submicron-size particles <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(García Muñoz &amp; Isaak 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Other planets show no detectable colour dependence in their transit depths. Two well-known cases of this grey behaviour are the sub-Neptunes GJ1214b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Kreidberg et al. 2014</ref>) and GJ436b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Knutson et al. 2014</ref>). In both cases, the bulk atmospheric composition is possibly dominated by hydrogen and thus they may have non-negligible scale heights. If so, grey transits are suggestive of moderately large particles lofted to mbar-µbar pressures. In spite of multiple degeneracies in the interpretation of grey transits, it is possible to constrain the location of the effective cloud level, defined as an artifical cutoff between two distinct altitude ranges: one opaque and one aerosol free. It has not been possible though to gain insight into the vertical profile of the condensates. Achieving this calls for more elaborate treatments of the aerosol vertical distribution that may not be justifiable given the multiple degeneracies already identified in the interpretation of transmission spectra. Regardless of the various uncertainties that exist in the nature of condensates and their distribution, grey transits suggest the possibility of atmospheres containing moderately large particles. If the condensates are distributed over a sufficiently broad range of altitudes, such planets might exhibit forward scattering to some extent. The fact that some exoplanets have anomalously large radii for their age is well documented. Such inflated, lowdensity planets occur amongst the population of hot Jupiters <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Demory &amp; Seager 2011</ref>) and sub-Neptunes ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lammer et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cubillos et al. 2017</ref>). The inflation mechanisms that sustain their interior structure have not been fully elucidated ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Spiegel et al. 2014</ref>), but it is possible that there are multiple at play ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Tremblin et al. 2017</ref>). Low-density exoplanets may represent good candidates for showing forward scattering provided that their extended atmospheres are accompanied by extended aerosol layers. In what follows, we derive expressions that allow us to guess when an exoplanet has suitable conditions for forward scattering. These expressions incorporate a few necessary simplifying assumptions on the envelopes.</p><p>For that purpose, we first write H/R p in terms of measurable quantities. H=kT/µg is the gas pressure scale height, where k is the Boltzmann constant, T stands for temperature, µ is the atmospheric molecular mass, and g the gravitational acceleration. The relevant H must be estimated near the optical radius level, which is also the level probed during transit. Since g=GM p /R 2 p , where G is the gravitational constant, and M p is the planet mass, we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">H R p = kT/µ GM p /R p .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>In our treatment we assume that the atmospheric pressure scale height and the aerosol scale height are equal, i.e. H=H a . This is very approximately the case for Titan ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tomasko et al. 2008</ref>). For other solar system planets, H a is a fraction of H (Sánchez- <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Lavega et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Pérez-Hoyos et al. 2016</ref>), with the exact H a /H ratio depending on the range of altitudes being considered and on whether the aerosols include the high-altitude haze that occur in most atmospheres. If the conditions in the atmosphere are such that H a H, forward scattering will be negligible and therefore undetectable.</p><p>Measurements of temperature at the optical radius level are not available. Instead, we will use for our estimates the planet equilibrium temperature T eq =T eff (R /2a) 1/2 that as-sumes that the incident stellar flux (effective temperature T eff ) is balanced by thermal radiation from a rapidly-rotating dark planet. T eq does not pertain to a specific altitude and thus it is possible that the temperature at the optical radius level will differ from it.</p><p>Re-arranging Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(5)</ref> with the expression for T eq :</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">H R p = 4.69 × 10 −6 T eq [K]R p /R J µ[a.m.u.]M p /M J = = 2.26 × 10 −7 T eff [K] R /R a[AU] 1/2 R p /R J µ[a.m.u.]M p /M J .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Finally, if Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(6)</ref> are combined:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">F p F = 3.23 × 10 −13 T eff (R /R ) 1/2 p a (θ = 0) 0,a µ[a.m.u.]ρ p /ρ J (a[AU]) 5/2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where ρ p /ρ J is the planet density relative to Jupiter's and R /R is the stellar radius relative to the Sun's. The appeal of Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> is that the information needed for its evaluation is available for many systems. It suggests that low-density planets at small orbital distances are good candidates for the occurrence of forward scattering. The reality may be more complex than that, because it is unclear how these and other parameters will affect the occurrence of aerosols and their optical properties. In a zeroth-order approximation, the amount of forward scattering from a planet can be ranked on the basis of the planet-to-star contrast at α=180 • . This simplified treatment avoids elaborate calculations such as those presented in <ref type="figure">Fig.  (3)</ref>. According to Eq. (1), the amount of forward-scattered starlight depends on the product of 2πH a /R p (R p /a) 2 , which is essentially a geometric factor, and p a (θ = 0) 0,a , which depends on the aerosol optical properties (and possibly, the star angular size).</p><p>We have searched the exoplanets.org ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Han et al. 2014</ref>) and exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu archives and collected the information needed in Eqs. (1), (6)-(7). As of the time of writing (April 2017), this information is available for a total of 462 exoplanets. Then, we calculated</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">H/R p , (R p /a) 2 , T eq , ρ p /ρ J , g/g J and 2π(H/R p )(R p /a) 2 .</formula><p>For simplicity, a is taken to be the semi-major axis, also for planets on eccentric orbits. Since most planets of interest have densities consistent with hydrogen-helium envelopes, we adopted µ=2.3 a.m.u.  <ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. (2015)</ref>.</p><p>The estimated H/R p , (R p /a) 2 , T eq and 2π(H/R p )(R p /a) 2 are displayed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. (4)</ref>. The dashed lines in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. (4, Top)</ref> divide the region of the parameter space with 2π(H/R p )(R p /a) 2 &gt; or &lt; 5, 10, 15, 20 and 25 parts per million (ppm). According to Eq. (1), on top of each dashed line, aerosols with p a (θ=0) 0,a =1 (or more generally &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) 0,a =1) will produce the quoted planet-to-star contrast at α=180 • . This is not an unrealistic situation, as the aerosol optical properties graphed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (2)</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (A2)</ref> suggest.</p><p>Atmospheric temperature will surely play a key role in the occurrence and optical properties of aerosols. It is thus interesting that the equilibrium temperature of planets with 2π(H/R p )(R p /a) 2 &gt;1 ppm covers a broad range from 410 to 2600 K. The main conclusion of Table <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. (4)</ref> is that there is a significant number of exoplanets with sufficiently extended atmospheres to potentially exhibit strong forward scattering. Many of these planets have been targets of transit observations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DETECTABILITY OF FORWARD SCATTERING</head><p>To assess how feasible it is the detection of forward scattering, one must also consider the favourable range of phase angles from the observer's vantage point, in addition to the detailed shape of the planet phase curve and the stellar brightness. To simplify this task, we will assume that: 1 ) All orbits are circular of radius equal to the orbital semi-major axis;</p><p>2 ) The planet phase curve is binned over two equal-size intervals:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">[α A , α B ] and [α C , α D ], with ∆α = α D − α C = α B − α A (Fig. 1). Forward scattering is strongest over the [α C , α D ]</formula><p>bin, and we take</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">α D = α I,IV ≈ π − (R p + R )/a ≈ π − R /a, and α C =160 • .</formula><p>The scattering signal is weak over the properly selected [α A , α B ] control bin, which sets a valid comparison baseline. With these simplifications, we calculated the time elapsed over each interval, t ∆α = P∆α/2π, where P is the orbital period;</p><p>3 ) The stellar radiation is approximated by a black body at the star effective temperature T eff between two wavelengths [λ 1 , λ 2 ]. Note that the planet does not need to transit in order to produce forward scattering. However, only planets that reach closer to the star than α∼160 • will produce a measurable effect (see <ref type="figure">Figs. 1 and 3</ref>). Highly inclined orbits will have maximum phase angles α&lt;160 • resulting in negligible forward scattering towards the observer. For each planet (and specific H a , R p and a; <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>), we calculated the planet-tostar contrast F p /F over all phases by interpolating in H a /R p from our battery of synthetic phase curves. Since the aerosol size is a key parameter that we prescribe but do not predict, we explored the sizes r eff =0.5, 1 and 2 µm. We define the observable O as the difference in the average planet-to-star contrast over the forward scattering and control bins: O= &lt;F p /F &gt; C→D −&lt;F p /F &gt; A→B (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>).</p><p>Photon noise (PN) sets a floor for the detection of the forward scattering signal, and it will be the only term considered in our noise budget. We estimate PN=1/ √ N ∆α , where N ∆α is the number of photons collected at the telescope over t ∆α . The expression for PN takes into account two canceling √ 2 and 1/ √ 2 factors, one arising from the differential definition of O and one arising from the assumption that the pre-and post-transit observations can be phase-folded to improve PN. We base our calculation of the number of photons at the telescope from an m V -magnitude star on the stellar radiated power per unit of area and time.  <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. Partial list of discovered exoplanets ordered by decreasing 2π H a R p /a 2 . The full list is available through the journal website. The list excludes KOI-55 b and KOI-55 c, both with T eq ∼7000 K, but densities ρ p /ρ J ∼4.5 incompatible with hydrogen-helium envelopes. For simplicity, we assumed that the atmospheres of all planets are dominated by hydrogen-helium, although this is not necessarily the case for many of them, including the well-studied GJ1214b. The observable O has been estimated from phase curves calculated in the point-like star limit. Therefore, the quoted Os likely underestimate the starlight forward-scattered and reaching the observer. Missing fields are due to the absence of the stellar magnitude from the consulted catalogues, or because α D &lt;160 • . The ratio (2π H a R p /a 2 )/PN is an indicator of the potential forward scattering strength vs. photon noise.</p><p>Planet This ensured that PN could be estimated for all planets with a priori better conditions for forward scattering.) We integrate the Planck function over the specified spectral interval [λ 1 , λ 2 ], and divide by the energy at the given wavelength. Then, using as reference the measured flux of an m V =0 star, we estimate the rate: Planet Here, h is the Planck constant and c the speed of light. The flux calibration factor f (m V =0; λ=550 nm)=3.6182×10 −12 W cm −2 µm −1 is taken from <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Casagrande &amp; VandenBerg (2014)</ref>. As a check, we confirmed the validity of our estimated photon rates by comparing them to those calculated from star distances and temperatures. Finally, the number of photons received at the telescope over a time t ∆α between λ 1 =400 nm and λ 2 =900 nm is calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">H a /R p (R p /a) 2 T eq 2π H a R p /a 2 ρ p /ρ J g/g J α D t ∆α m V PN 2π H a R p /a 2 O 0.5µm O 1µm [ppm] [K] [ppm] [ • ] [s] [ppm] /PN [ppm] [</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">H a /R p (R p /a) 2 T eq 2π H a R p /a 2 ρ p /ρ J g/g J α D t ∆α m V PN 2π H a R p /a 2 O 0.5µm O 1µm O 2µ [ppm] [K] [ppm] [ • ] [s] [</formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">N ∆α = Nt ∆α η tel A tel .</formula><p>For the telescope collecting area, we adopt A tel =π/4 m 2 , and include an overall instrument efficiency η tel =0.75 that accounts for the CCD quantum efficiency and possible tranmission/reflection losses. This instrument configuration is loosely related to the Kepler telescope ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Borucki et al. 2003</ref>).</p><p>In our feasibility analysis, we also assumed that the composition of the prevailing aerosols is FeO. This condensate absorbs significantly at wavelengths between 0.5 and 2 µm <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 2)</ref>. The motivation for this choice is to show that planets that appear dark at small phase angles may result in strong forward scattering. For this optical phenomenon to occur, particle size is more critical than the single scattering albedo. Thus, FeO may be regarded as a proxy for the effect of dark haze particles that might exist in the upper atmosphere of some exoplanets.</p><p>Setting α D =α I,IV , the optimal ∆α depends on the tradeoff between the brightness curve shape and associated PN. In the point-like star limit considered in the preparation of <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (</ref>2), large aerosols tend to focus most of the scattered starlight on a narrow range of phase angles near α=180 • . In turn, small particle sizes generally result in forward scattering that is less pronounced but spreads over a broader range of phase angles. Implementing a small ∆α enhances the planet-to-star contrast over the forward scattering bin at the cost of reducing the integration time and therefore worsening PN. For simplicity, we adopted ∆α=α I,IV −160 • (i.e. α C =160 • ) in all cases, but note that this choice may be sub-optimal and therefore leaves room for improvement of the O/PN ratio. The choice of α A and α B is such that &lt;F p /F &gt; A→B ≈0. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (</ref>2) summarizes the estimated O 0.5µm , O 1µm and O 2µm (each exploring the quoted aerosol particle radius) and PN. A few comments are due. Obviously, the process of averaging over ∆α and having α D &lt;180 • dilutes the observable O below the predicted forward scattering peak at α=180 • . Particles that are small result in little forward scattering. Particles that are large result in significant forward scattering, but most of the scattered starlight focuses on phase angles that are unobservable (at least in the pointlike star limit) and therefore do not contribute towards O. As a result, the highest Os often occur for the intermediate r eff ∼1 µm. In a few cases, O∼20-30 ppm values are predicted. We emphasize that, as shown below for the specific case of CoRo-T-24b, considering the finite angular size of the star will tend to increase the predicted Os by factors of up to a few from the values quoted in Tables (2)-(3). The comparison of O and PN shows that photon noise should not be critical for a number of planets provided that multiple orbits can be stacked to improve the O/PN ratio. Some of the planets listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (2)</ref> have been observed at out-oftransit phases with precisions comparable to the quoted Os, in particular the Kepler planets <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Table 3)</ref>. It is left for future work the re-analysis of their phase curves in the specific search for forward scattering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Low-mass, low-density planets</head><p>We next turn our attention to the low-mass, low-density, sub-Neptune CoRoT-24b (T eq =935 K, M p /M J &lt;0.018, ρ p /ρ J &lt;0.5). Recent work ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lammer et al. 2016</ref>) has proposed that the measured transit radius probes a low-pressure region high in the atmosphere, and that the opacity is due to an undetermined condensate capable of continuum extinction. The hypothesis of high-altitude aerosols is in line with some of the interpretations for the transmission spectra of e.g. GJ1214b and GJ436b. What makes CoRoT-24b stand out with respect to better characterized sub-Neptunes is its large H/R p ∼0.035. CoRoT-24b may be one of a population of planets in similar conditions ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cubillos et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fossati et al. 2017</ref>).</p><p>The ratio H/R p (as given by Eq. 5) is the inverse of the parameter X that appears in thermal evaporation theory and represents the squared ratio of the escape velocity and the most probable velocity of the gas Maxwellian distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chamberlain &amp; Hunten 1987)</ref>. Small X values represent favourable conditions for escape. In thermal evaporation theory, though, X is evaluated at the exobase and thus well above the optical radius level at which H/R p is evaluated. The coincidental structure of H/R p and X −1 suggests that puffy planets also offer good conditions for thermal escape.</p><p>We have explored the possibilities offered by CoRoT24b's large H/R p for its characterization at large phase angles. We estimate (R p /a) 2 =7.6 ppm, 2πR p H a /a 2 =1.7 ppm, and α I,IV =175.9 • . At small phase angles, assuming a geometric albedo A g ∼0.3 (Demory 2014) (which would preclude an envelope dominated by a dark condensate), the planet-to-star contrast is ∼2.3 ppm. Correspondingly, at α=180 • the contrast can be as high as 1.7×&lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0) 0,a ppm, thereby exceeding the contrast at small phase angles if micron-size or larger aerosols prevail at the optical radius level <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. A2)</ref>.</p><p>We produced synthetic phase curves for CoRoT-24b with H/R p =0.035. To emphasize the possibilities of large versus small phase angles, we adopted a dark condensate (FeO), and tested r eff values of 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 5 and 10 µm. As usual, we adopted α D =α I,IV but unlike in the preparation of <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (</ref>2) we explored various bin sizes ∆α. Again, the control bin was defined at phases for which the planet appears dark and &lt;F p /F &gt; A→B ≈0. A set of phase curves was calculated in the point-like star limit. We produced another set of phase curves that consider the finite angular size of the host star. The needed modifications to the original radiative transfer algorithm (García Muñoz &amp; Mills 2015) are described in Appendix C.</p><p>Figure <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(5)</ref> shows the two sets of curves with emphasis on the large phase angles. At the top, we show simulations for the various particle sizes in both the point-like star limit (solid) and in the finite angular size star approach (dashed) for the stellar angular radius specific to CoRoT24b, θ ≈4.1 • . To convert from A g Φ(α) to planet-to-star contrasts, the scaling factor is 7.6 ppm. For illustration purposes, the Middle and Bottom plots show additional calculations for θ ≈10 and 20 • , and H a /R p =0.035 as in the initial configuration.</p><p>The most obvious effect of considering the finite angular size of the star is that the out-of-transit brightness of the planet (α180 • −θ ) tends to become larger than in the point-like star limit. This a direct consequence of the convolution of p a (θ) over the stellar disk brightness to produce &lt;p a &gt;(Θ). Thus, near transit the planet terminator forwardscatters photons with deflection angles within a ±θ range as for photons coming from the stellar centre. At mid-transit (α≡180 • ) the amount of starlight forward scattered by the atmosphere is lower in the finite angular size limit because the planet sees stellar photons arriving from a range of directions, some of them not overlapping with the peak of the p a (θ) function <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. A2)</ref>. The attenuating effect of the finite angular size of the star for radiation scattered at α≡180 • is more pronounced for the large scattering particles associated with a narrow forward scattering peak p a (θ=0). <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (</ref>4) summarizes our estimates for the observable O, in both the point-like (regular typeface) and finite angular size (bold typeface) treatments of the star. Their intercomparison indicates that the point-like star treatment can underestimate the observable by factors of up to a few depending on the combination of α C , θ and r eff . For CoRoT24b, O reaches up to ∼10-20 ppm when ∆α is small enough that the steepest part of the brightness surge is resolved. The table also shows the photon noise PN per orbit, which goes from ∼64 ppm for α C =160 • to ∼186 ppm for α C =174 • . Thus, O/PN&lt;&lt;1 over the ∆α bin sizes explored. Although signals weaker than ∼10 ppm have been detected with Kepler, improving the O/PN ratio to detectable levels calls for one or more of the following strategies: accumulating data from numerous orbits; focusing on planets around bright stars; stacking observations from multiple planets with similar characteristics (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Sheets &amp; Deming 2014)</ref>. Ultimately, <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (</ref>4) suggests that there is a chance for low-density exoplanets that are too small or dark for detection in occultation to be detected through forward scattering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Pre-ingress and post-ingress forward scattering</head><p>A number of Kepler planets exhibit brightness peaks that occur at phases somewhat displaced from full illumination (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Demory et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angerhausen et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. 2015</ref>). For the less strongly irradiated planets, this finding is often explained as caused by clouds forming on the nightside that move onto the dayside and then evaporate, thereby causing an asymmetry in the phase curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(García Muñoz &amp; Isaak 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Shporer &amp; Hu 2015)</ref>. If the non-uniform cloud reaches to the altitudes probed by forward scattering, it is conceivable that the pre-ingress and post-ingress brightness curves will have dissimilar slopes. We can estimate the importance of this with the simplified model sketched in <ref type="figure">Fig. (6, Top)</ref> as applied to a CoRoT24b-like planet. In this model, one of the terminators (L) is aerosol-free and therefore forward scattering from it is inefficient, whereas the other terminator (R) contains aerosols that scatter efficiently in the forward direction. The aerosols are vertically distributed with a scale height H a,R /R p =0.035 and have effective &lt;p a,R &gt;(Θ) as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (A2)</ref> for various particle sizes and θ =4.1 • .</p><p>Figure (6, Bottom) shows the synthetic phase curves. The most remarkable characteristic is that the ingress is brighter than the egress. The reason for this is that at ingress the hazy terminator is seen with a local phase angle that is larger (and the scattering angle smaller) than the aerosolfree terminator. The difference in phase angles between terminators roughly scales as 2R p /a. The magnitude of this angular resolution element and the details of &lt;p a,R &gt;(Θ) dictate the differences in the ingress/egress curves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5</head><p>BLENDING WITH OTHER PHOTOMETRIC EFFECTS</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Modulations from stellar tides</head><p>The measured brightness from a close-in planet-star system includes the contribution from the planet atmosphere together with modulations due to Doppler beaming and tidal ellipsoidal distortion of the star. The magnitude, period and lag with respect to the orbital motion of these modulations are sources of information on both the planet and the star (e.g. Shporer 2017, for a recent review).</p><p>Assuming that the planet is on a circular orbit and the planet-star system is seen edge-on, the brightness modulation from Doppler beaming is ∝sin(α), whereas the modulation due to ellipsoidal distortion is ∝cos(2α) with additional correcting terms ∝cos(α) and cos(3α). The theoretical treatment of these phenomena provides expressions for the coefficients of each term, which depend on e.g. a, R , M p and M <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Morris &amp; Naftilan 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Loeb &amp; Gaudi 2003)</ref>. The planet atmosphere modulates the planet-star system brightness in two different ways. Thermal radiation prevails when the atmosphere is hot and/or the observations are made at long wavelengths. Reflected starlight dominates at low temperatures and/or short wavelengths. With enough photometric precision and multi-wavelength observations, it is possible to disentangle these phenomena, also the two atmospheric terms ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Placek et al. 2016)</ref>, by fitting the observations to models (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angerhausen et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. 2015</ref>).</p><p>The photometric effects described above may blend in the observed brightness signal and cause degeneracies in the interpretation of the inferred physical properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Mislis &amp; Hodgkin 2012)</ref>. Aggravated by moderate signal-to-noise ratios and a possibly incomplete understanding of each photometric effect, these difficulties may be at the heart of the mass discrepancy reported for some planet-star systems <ref type="bibr">(Sh- porer 2017)</ref>. Indeed, it has become apparent that the planet masses inferred from photometric measurements (through Doppler beaming or tidal ellipsoidal distortions) and from radial velocities are at times mutually inconsistent.</p><p>Figure <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> suggests that forward scattering from a horizontally uniform planet will leak into cos(2α) and higher order even cosine harmonics, thereby blending with the stellar tide modulation. The overall effect is a partial cancellation of the ellipsoidal effect, particularly at large phase angles and if the angular size of the star is also large, and in turn a reduced planetary mass as estimated from this photometric effect. We have briefly explored to what extent forward scattering affects the photometric mass inferred from the stellar tide modulations in the cases of TrES-2b ( <ref type="bibr">Bar- clay et al. 2012</ref>) and <ref type="bibr">Kepler-76 b (Faigler et al. 2013</ref>), with quoted ellipsoidal semi-amplitudes of 2.8 and 21.5 ppm, respectively. We find that 2πR p H a /a 2 ∼5 (TrES-2b) and ∼10 (Kepler-76b) ppm, which means that blending of forwardscattered starlight with the tidal brightness modulation is a priori possible. The fact that the masses retrieved from stellar tide modulations (M ell p /M J =1.06 +0.28</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">−0.23</formula><p>for TrES-2b, and 2.1±0.4 for Kepler-76b) and radial velocities for both planets (M RV p /M J =1.206±0.045 for TrES-2b, and 2.00±0.26 for Kepler-76b) are in good agreement ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Barclay et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Faigler et al. 2013</ref>) suggests that neither of these planets exhibit significant forward scattering, which puts an additional constraint on their atmospheres.</p><p>It is worth noting the cases of Kepler-12b and -412b, listed on Tables (2)-(3), whose phase curves have been published by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angerhausen et al. (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. (2015)</ref>. Kepler-12b's curve is distinctly asymmetric with respect to occultation, a fact likely attributable to a horizontally nonhomogeneous atmosphere. Other Kepler planets also show asymmetric atmospheric contributions ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angerhausen et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. 2015</ref>). According to our estimates, both planets might exhibit forward scattering signals of up to 10-20 ppm. A look at the corresponding curves in <ref type="bibr">Esteves et al. (2015)</ref> however does not reveal clear evidence for forward scattering in the case of Kepler-412b, although it hints at a tentative brightness surge at orbital phases close to one in the case of <ref type="bibr">Kepler-12b</ref>. A thorough analysis incorporating the data from all Kepler quarters might provide a more definitive answer.</p><p>Clearly, further work is needed to quantify these contributions and extend the analysis to all planets with accurate photometric data available. Because the forward scattering signal scales as M −1 p and a −5/2 (Eq. 7), and the amplitude of the ellipsoidal tidal distortion scales as M p and a −3 , each effect will likely dominate in a different region of the M p -a parameter space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Transits</head><p>During a transit, the host star dims by an amount that depends on the planet size and its atmospheric structure. For an exponential atmosphere described by a single absorber (the conditions explored here), and omitting the scattering towards the observer of photons having one or more collisions in the atmosphere, the planet appears effectively opaque up to the so-called equivalent height h eq (λ). To a good approximation, the equivalent height occurs where the limb opacity of the atmosphere τ limb =0.56 <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Karkoschka et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Lecavelier des Etangs et al. 2008)</ref>.</p><p>Part of the starlight that is intercepted by the atmosphere during the transit is restored into the forward direction and scattered towards the observer <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Brown 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hub- bard et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">García Muñoz &amp; Mills 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">De Kok &amp; Stam 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Robinson 2017)</ref>. Under the assumption of an exponential atmosphere, Eq. (A13) quantifies how many of these photons reach the observer, thereby reducing the transit depth by 2R p ∆/R 2 or the equivalent to an annulus area of radius R p and width ∆:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">∆ H a = π R a 2 &lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0) 0,a .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>This is also akin to diminishing the transmission-only equivalent height, h eq , by ∆, which means that the measurable equivalent height during the transit is h eq =h eq −∆ rather than h eq . ∆ depends on wavelength through the aerosol properties &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) and 0,a . Typically, the larger the particle radius r eff the larger the effective &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig.  A2)</ref>, and in turn the impact of forward scattering on the transit depth. In an aerosol-rich atmosphere, 0,a will depend strongly on wavelength if there are strong gas absorption bands in the spectral range of interest. Within the gas absorption band, 0,a can become significantly smaller than in the continuum, and in turn h eq ≈h eq at the specific wavelengths.</p><p>Interestingly, the angular size of the star enters into Eq. (8) both directly (θ ≈R /a) and indirectly through &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) (Eq. A5, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. A2</ref>). The two effects partially cancel out. For large orbital distances, the a 2 term in the denominator of Eq. (8) dominates and ∆/H a becomes small; for small orbital distances, the convolution of p a (θ) over an extended solid angle results in a reduced &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) with respect to p a (θ=0). <ref type="figure">Figure (9)</ref> incorporates the information presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (A2)</ref> for &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) and shows that forward scattering will reduce the equivalent height of the atmosphere by typically less than one scale height, even for the more extreme configurations (θ =20 • , r eff =10 µm). The connection of ∆ with the particle size is more direct through the analytical expression of Eq. (8) than in the treatments by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">De Kok &amp; Stam (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Robinson (2017)</ref>, who base their analyses on Henyey-Greenstein parameterizations of the aerosols scattering phase function.</p><p>For completeness, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. (8)</ref> shows the transit depth as a function of orbital phase for both CoRoT-24 b and Kepler-76 b. For CoRoT-24 b (θ ≈4.1 • ), it is shown the case with aerosols of particle size r eff =10 µm, which results in a correction of the transit depth at mid-transit due to forward scattering of about 50 ppm. For Kepler-76 b (θ ≈12.8 • ), the corresponding graph shows the case with r eff =2 µm, which results in a correction of about 36 ppm. Both corrections correspond to a change in the equivalent height of less than their estimated gas pressure scale heights.</p><p>We have assumed throughout this work an effective wavelength λ eff =0.65 µm. Because in Mie theory the diffraction peak of the aerosols is largely dictated by the size parameter x eff =2πr eff /λ eff , <ref type="figure">Fig. (9)</ref> can be reworked at other wavelengths by appropriately selecting the particle radius. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">DeVore et al. (2016)</ref> have shown that forward scattering can significantly modify the transit light curve of ultra-short period planets surrounded by dust clouds. The difference with our treatment is that these authors assume that the entire (and sizable) cloud is uniform in its dust content, and thus every element of it can scatter the incident starlight towards the observer. In our treatment, the exponential variation of the optical properties reduces the effective scattering area to a relatively narrow ring around the planet of width about an atmospheric scale height.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">SUMMARY</head><p>A main goal of this work is to raise awareness about the diagnostics possibilities of exoplanet brightness measurements at large phase angles. As for Saturn's moon Titan, a brightness surge when the planet approaches back-illumination will provide joint information on atmospheric stratification and aerosol optical properties. This is valuable insight difficult to gain by other means. It is unclear how common this optical phenomenon is, but its possibility justifies a dedicated search with existing and future observations.</p><p>In the framework of exponential atmospheres, we derived an analytical expression for forward-scattered starlight in the single-scattering limit. The expression incorporates the effects of the angular size of the star, one of which is to convolve the aerosols scattering phase function with the brightness distribution over the stellar disk. Based on this expression, we estimate that there are a number of exoplanets with a priori suitable conditions for forward scattering. We have refined these predictions with a more elaborate assessment that considers the shape of the phase curve and the time elapsed during the brightening phase. Some of these planets potentially exhibit brightness surges of up to tens of ppms.</p><p>At out-of-transit phases, considering the finite angular size of the star tends to increase the amount of starlight forward-scattered towards the observer with respect to the treatment in the point-like star limit. On the contrary, during the transit the finite angular size of the star reduces the amount of starlight that reaches the observer with respect to the point-like star limit. Once the latter effect is considered, it is seen that forward scattering will modify the equivalent height of the atmosphere by less than one scale height in most configurations. For future reference, we show how to take into account the finite angular size of the star in Backward Monte Carlo radiative transfer models. Our study raises the possibility that, given the appropriate atmospheric structure, some low-density planets may be easier to detect at large phase angles than in occultation.</p><p>Throughout our treatment, we assumed that aerosols dominate the atmospheric opacity at the optical radius level. Two additional key assumptions are that the aerosols are vertically distributed with a scale height equal to the gas scale height, and that the aerosols are described as having a single particle size that we prescribe but do not predict. This simplified treatment is similar to the way transit spectra are often interpreted within retrieval algorithms. The reality of exoplanet atmospheres will surely be more complex, but our simplified approach at least enables a direct comparison with observations from which to draw physical conclusions. It may well happen that some of the planets that are ranked higher as candidates for strong forward scattering will have no detectable signal because their atmospheres do not form aerosols or the aerosol particles at the optical radius level are not large enough. Even then, and if observations of high enough precision exist, a non-detection will provide constraints on the atmospheric structure that can be tested against microphysical models. This possibility should motivate further studies on the microphysics of aerosols in the diverse range of conditions found in exoplanet atmospheres (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Helling &amp; Fomins 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Lavvas et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Lavvas &amp; Koskinen 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lee et al. 2016</ref>). Helpful information that could be obtained from such investigations includes: the aerosol scale height at the optical radius level, and the particle size of the condensates dominating the continuum opacity at the corresponding altitudes.</p><p>Last, we emphasize that the starlight reflected by exoplanets varies with phase in manners that are not necessarily well described by simple formulations such as Lambert's law. It is challenging to decide when more elaborate descriptions are justified, but it is equally important to realize that oversimplified descriptions will likely wash out unique information on the planet atmosphere. the integral of p a (θ) over all directions equal to 4π. In our normalization, for isotropic scattering p a (θ)=1/4π, and for Rayleigh scattering p a (θ)=1/4π (1+cos 2 θ).</p><p>For evaluating the second integral of Eq. (A1), we adopt I(x a , s )≈B t(x a , x b ), which assumes that the opacity from x a to x b is representative of the opacity from x a in any of the possible −s directions towards the star. Also, we take dΩ≈2πd(cos θ), which tacitly assumes that all points x a are near the planet-star axis. With this, the integral becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">2πB t(x a , x b ) 1 cos θ d(cos θ)p a (θ), (A2)</formula><p>where cos θ = 1 − (R /a) 2 . As usual, R and a are the stellar radius and planet orbital distance, respectively. The integral of Eq. (A2) has the meaning of an aerosol scattering phase function averaged over the angular size of the star and, in general, requires numerical evaluation. We term this general treatment the finite angular size star approach, and is relevant when the angle θ subtended by the star from the planet is not small. In contrast, the so-called point-like star approach is appropriate when the planet-star orbital distance is large enough that all stellar photons reaching the planet can be assumed to be collimated and θ →0. In this latter approach, Eq. (A2) can be simplified further into:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">π R a 2 B t(x a , x b )p a (θ = 0). (A3)</formula><p>For convenience, we introduce an aerosol scattering phase function averaged over the stellar angular size:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">&lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0) = 2 a R 2 1 cos θ d(cos θ)p a (θ),<label>(A4)</label></formula><p>and rewrite Eq. (A2) as:  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(2016)</ref> shows that all three treatments seem equivalent.</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">π R a 2 B t(x a , x b )&lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0)<label>(</label></formula><p>For a spherically symmetric atmosphere, the transmittance t(x, x b ) (=t(x, x a )t(x a , x b )) can be reduced to a function of the the minimum distance r from the line of sight to the planet centre (SA(i)). If τ(r) is the optical thickness along that chord, t(x, x b )=exp (−τ(r)). And from the definition of optical thickness:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">τ = x x b d a γ(x a ).</formula><p>Following the above, Eq. (A1) can be rewritten as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">I(r) = B exp (−τ(r))+B π R a 2 0,a τ(r) exp (−τ(r))&lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0).<label>(A6)</label></formula><p>Deep into the atmosphere, τ(r) is large whereas exp (−τ(r)) is small. The reverse is true high up in the atmosphere. The irradiance measured by the observer from a starto-Earth distance d is obtained by integration of I(r) over the solid angle subtended by the whole planet-star system:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">F = IdΩ = 2π I(r) r dr d 2 .<label>(A7)</label></formula><p>According to Eq. (A6), F contains the contributions from both unscattered photons and from photons that have undergone one scattering collision. For the unscattered component:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">F 0 = 2πB d 2 R R 0 exp (−τ(r))r dr,<label>(A8)</label></formula><p>where R 0 is a somewhat arbitrary altitude level in the atmosphere such that τ(R 0 )&gt;&gt;1. Or, if we introduce the planet equivalent cross section to transmission, πr 2 eq :</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">F 0 = πB d 2 R 2 − r 2 eq (A9)</formula><p>For exponential atmospheres, Lecavelier des <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Etangs et al. (2008)</ref> have shown that r eq (=R 0 +h eq ) matches the atmospheric level where τ(h eq )=0.56 that defines the optical radius of a planet, R p . Correspondingly, for the single-scattering component:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">F 1 = B π R a 2 0,a &lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0) 2π d 2 R R 0 τ(r) exp (−τ(r))r dr.<label>(A10)</label></formula><p>The occurrence of τ(r) exp (−τ(r)) suggests that the main contribution to the integral arises from τ(r)∼1. From SA(i) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">SA(iii), τ(r) = τ(R 0 ) exp (−(r − R 0 )/H a )</formula><p>. By virtue of SA(v), the integral of Eq. (A10) converges rapidly in r, and it is acceptable to take r≈R p outside of the integration <ref type="figure">(Fig. A3)</ref>.</p><p>The resulting integral is easy to evaluate after realizing that H a dτ = −τdr, and results in:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">R R 0 τ(r) exp (−τ(r))dr = H a (1 − exp(−τ(R 0 ))) ≈ H a .<label>(A11)</label></formula><p>Introducing these results into F 1 and normalizing by the irradiance of the unimpeded star at the observer's vantage point:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">F = B π R d 2 ,<label>(A12)</label></formula><p>leads to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">F 1 F ≈ 2π&lt;p a (Θ = 0)&gt; 0,a H a R p R p a 2 , (A13)</formula><p>which is the analytical expression for starlight forwardscattered towards the observer by an exponential atmosphere under the assumption of single scattering, relative to the net stellar brightness. The orbital distance enters Eq. (A13) in two competing ways. Since the amount of starlight intercepted by the planet varies as a −2 , close-in planets will in principle appear brighter in reflected starlight. However, as the ratio R /a becomes larger &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) samples scattering angles that differ from the strict forward scattering configuration, and &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) will typically become much smaller than p a (θ=0). The decrease in &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) with respect to p a (θ=0) is more pronounced when R /a (or θ ) is large and/or the aerosols exhibit a strong forward scattering peak.</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">APPENDIX B: MULTIPLE SCATTERING FOR CLOSE-IN PLANETS. THE α=180 • CONFIGURATION.</formula><p>García <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Muñoz et al. (2017)</ref> show that the number of collisions contributing to Titan's brightness decreases as the star-object-observer phase angles increases (their <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>). We confirm that for the phase curves presented in our <ref type="figure">Fig. (3)</ref> the difference between the numerical multiple scattering solution at α=180 • and the single-scattering estimate based on Eq. (A13) remained below 30%. Also, for the phase curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. (5)</ref> motivated by the study of CoRoT-24b, in both the point-like and finite angular size treatments of the star, single scattering contributed ∼70% or more to the multiple scattering solution. Using the case of CoRoT-24b, we ran a few additional simulations in which we forced the aerosols to be fully conservative, i.e. 0,a =1. In those cases, single scattering contributed at least ∼50% of the multiple scattering solution at α=180 • . Together, these conclusions suggest that Eq. (A13) generally approximates the planet-tostar contrast in forward scattering to within a factor of two or better.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX C: BACKWARD MONTE CARLO CALCULATIONS WITH A FINITE ANGULAR SIZE STAR</head><p>The radiative transfer calculations presented in this work were done with a Backward Monte Carlo algorithm that has been described elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(García Muñoz &amp; Mills 2015)</ref>, and used to investigate the phase curves of exoplanets, Venus and Titan <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(García Muñoz &amp; Isaak 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">García Muñoz et al. 2014</ref>. These previous studies omitted the consideration of the finite angular size of the star, which can modify the effective scattering geometry at the particle level. The effect is likely important for close-in planets at large phase angles because atmospheric aerosols can be efficient at scattering in the forward direction. Referring to Figs. (A1) and (C1), a scattering particle sees the incident starlight enter the atmosphere from a range of directions s rather than from a single direction. This distinction is important since the probability that the incident photon is re-scattered into another direction can be a strong function of the relative angle between the two directions. For instance, in the configuration of <ref type="figure">Fig. (A1)</ref>, which assumes a perfect star-planetobserver alignment, the angle between s and s ranges from 0 to θ (the angular size of the star as viewed from the planet). For very close-in exoplanets, θ can be as large as 20 • .</p><p>Our Backward Monte Carlo algorithm builds the solution to the radiative transfer problem by tracking simulated photons (or photon packages) from the observer's vantage point through the atmosphere. At the outset of the simulation, each photon is assigned a 'weight' of one. As the simulation proceeds and the photon interacts with the medium, its weight is progressively reduced by amounts that account for the probabilities that the photon is either absorbed within or escapes from the atmosphere. The simulated photon trajectory is terminated when the weight falls below a user-defined threshold. A tentative photon trajectory is sketched in <ref type="figure">Fig.  (C1)</ref>. The arrows show the directions for the photon displacements, which are the reverse of the directions actually simulated in the Backward algorithm. At each photon scattering collision, either within the atmosphere or at the planet surface, the algorithm evaluates an integral over solid angle that results into two separate contributions. Mathematically, these contributions are expressed as the two terms on the right hand sides of Eqs. (9)-(10) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">García Muñoz &amp; Mills (2015)</ref>.</p><p>The first contribution accounts for diffuse radiation, i.e. radiation associated with photons that have had at least one previous collision. The relevant scattering phase function to quantify the diffuse radiation re-scattered into the s direction is the local p a (θ) because the change in photon directions from s to s is independent of the star location. The corresponding implementation in the algorithm is as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">García Muñoz &amp; Mills (2015)</ref>. The second contribution accounts for stellar photons having their first scattering collision. Mathematically (Eqs. (9)-(10) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">García Muñoz &amp; Mills (2015)</ref>, and assuming that all stellar rays are attenuated by the same amount), this involves an integral over the solid angle Ω subtended by the star at the collision location: ∂Ω p a (s · s )dΩ(s ) which can be pre-calculated and re-written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">Ω &lt;p a &gt;(Θ),</formula><p>where Θ is the angle between the s ray passing through the star centre (s in the sketch) and s . This definition generalizes to Θ&gt;0 the &lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0) of Eq. (A5). Examples of effective scattering phase functions &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (A2)</ref>.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table (1)</ref>. (The finite angular size of the star reduces the effective scattering phase function &lt;p a (Θ=0)&gt; with respect to p a (θ=0); see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. (A2)</ref>.) We normalize p a (θ) so that its integral over 4π is equal to one (Appendix A). Bottom. For the same condensates, their corresponding single scattering albedo, 0,a . <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Reflected starlight phase curves for spherical, exponential atmospheres. Three types of scattering aerosols are considered: Mg 2 SiO 4 (left), FeO (middle) and Titan-like haze (right). From top to bottom, the graphs explore increasing values of H a /R p . The phase curves are normalized as in Eq. (2), with R p being the optical radius. The simulations are based on the point-like star limit, thereby assuming that the angular size of the star is small. A non-negligible angular size will modify the phase curves by leaking some of the forward-scattered radiation to smaller phase angles (see §4.1).  Top. Phase curve simulations of CoRoT-24b (H a /R p ∼0.035, see text). Taking into account the finite angular size of the star in &lt;p a (Θ)&gt; <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. (A2)</ref>) results in the leakage of brightness from the larger to the smaller phase angles. To convert to planet-to-star contrasts, the quoted A g Φ(α) should be multiplied by (R p /a) 2 =7.6 ppm. Middle and Bottom. Phase curves for H a /R p ∼0.035, but with the star spanning larger fractions of the sky as viewed from the planet.  <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. Top. The cartoon depicts a transiting planet at 1st and 4th contacts. The planet's R terminator scatters the incident starlight in the forward direction much more efficiently than the L terminator. This is potentially due to a more extended aerosol layer and/or larger aerosol particles at the R terminator. Bottom. Phase curves for a CoRoT-24b-like planet with a hazy terminator (R) and an aerosol-free terminator (L). Both ingress and egress curves are shown. Contact I and IV are at α∼175.9 • . The simulations take into account the finite angular size of the star.  For the transit light curve, we assumed the brightness is uniform over the stellar disk. Forward scattering reduces to some extent the transit depth. In the two examples shown here, the reduction amounts to ∼50 ppm (CoRoT-24 b) and ∼36 ppm (Kepler-76 b), which is less than the equivalent to a gas pressure scale height.  . Aerosols scattering phase function in the pointlike star limit, p a (θ) (black); and in the finite angular size star approach, &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) (red). Each graph considers aerosols of a specific particle size anf FeO composition. Note the different vertical scales for each of the graphs. The various red curves correspond to different star angular radii. p a (θ) is calculated from Mie theory. For &lt;p a &gt;(Θ), we convolve p a (θ) with the scattering angle for stellar rays from each visible element of the stellar disk. Accounting for the finite angular size of the star decreases the effective scattering by the aerosols at small scattering angles (typically, angles &lt;θ ) but increases it at scattering angles somewhat larger. For sufficiently large scattering angles, both p a (θ) and &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) merge. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, Budaj et al. (2015); Figs. 3 and A2, DeVore et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A5) which encompasses both Eqs. (A2) and (A3). Obviously, in the point-like star limit, &lt;p a &gt;(Θ = 0)→p a (θ = 0), and Eq. (A5) reduces to Eq. (A3). Both Budaj et al. (2015) and DeVore et al. (2016) present formulations to calculate &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) for conditions other than Θ=0, using either Mie theory or Airy functions in the description of the scatter- ing phenomenon. Using &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) rather than p a (θ) in the radiative transfer problem when evaluating the contribution from the star at each photon-atmospheric particle scattering collision (through integrals like the second one in Eq. (A1)) reduces the radiative transfer problem with a finite angular size star to the simpler problem of a point-like star. Figure (A2) demonstrates p a (θ) and &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) for FeO particles of a few effective radii r eff at an effective wavelength λ eff =0.65 µm. For &lt;p a &gt;(Θ), we adopted star angular radii θ of 1, 5, 10, and 20 • . The comparison of our Fig. (A2) to Fig. 3 of Budaj et al. (2015) (dividing their results by 4π) and Fig. 3 of DeVore et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Top. Scattering phase function in forward scattering p a (θ=0) for the condensates of Table (1). (The finite angular size of the star reduces the effective scattering phase function &lt;p a (Θ=0)&gt; with respect to p a (θ=0); see Fig. (A2).) We normal-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Estimated parameters for the sample of 462 exoplanets considered in the study. In the top graph, the dashed lines divide the parameter space with 2π H/R p (R p /a) 2 &gt; or &lt; the quoted ppms. From left to right, the dashed lines represent 5, 10, 15, 20 and 25 parts per million. The planet and stellar parameters were extracted from exoplanets.org and complemented from exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Top. Phase curve simulations of CoRoT-24b (H a /R p ∼0.035, see text). Taking into account the finite angular size of the star in &lt;p a (Θ)&gt; (Fig. (A2)) results in the leakage of brightness from the larger to the smaller phase angles. To convert to planet-to-star contrasts, the quoted A g Φ(α) should be multiplied by (R p /a) 2 =7.6 ppm. Middle and Bottom. Phase curves for H a /R p ∼0.035, but with the star spanning larger fractions of the sky as viewed from the planet.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Photometric modulations for a Kepler-76b-like planet. The Doppler beaming and ellipsoidal distortion contributions are based on Esteves et al. (2015). We model the thermal emission component as (1+cos(α))/2, premultiplied by a coefficient of 58 ppm consistent with integrated blackbody radiation between 0.45 and 0.85 µm for an estimated T eq =2551 K. The reflected starlight calculations are based on a FeO aerosol, which explains the low reflectance at small phase angles. As in the case of CoRoT-24 b (Figs. 5-6), the multiple scattering simulations were done considering the finite size of the star, and θ ≈12.8 • . The symbols in the bottom plot are the measurements reported by Esteves et al. (2015) in their Fig. 3, shifted in the vertical by 30 ppm. The vertical lines in the two bottom graphs represent the positions for [α A , α B ] (dotted) and [α C , α D ] (dashed) as described in the preparation of Table (2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Transit depth as a function of orbital phase. For the transit light curve, we assumed the brightness is uniform over the stellar disk. Forward scattering reduces to some extent the transit depth. In the two examples shown here, the reduction amounts to ∼50 ppm (CoRoT-24 b) and ∼36 ppm (Kepler-76 b), which is less than the equivalent to a gas pressure scale height.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 .Figure A1 .</head><label>9A1</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Forward scattering contribution to the equivalent height of the atmosphere, normalized by the scale height and adopting 0,a =1, according to Eq. (8). Each curve assumes aerosols of a specific particle radius. The values of &lt;p a &gt;(Θ=0) are from Fig. (A2). According to these curves, forward scattering will reduce the measured equivalent height of the atmosphere by less than one scale height, even in the most extreme conditions of particle size and star angular radius explored here.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure A2</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A2. Aerosols scattering phase function in the pointlike star limit, p a (θ) (black); and in the finite angular size star approach, &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) (red). Each graph considers aerosols of a specific particle size anf FeO composition. Note the different vertical scales for each of the graphs. The various red curves correspond to different star angular radii. p a (θ) is calculated from Mie theory. For &lt;p a &gt;(Θ), we convolve p a (θ) with the scattering angle for stellar rays from each visible element of the stellar disk. Accounting for the finite angular size of the star decreases the effective scattering by the aerosols at small scattering angles (typically, angles &lt;θ ) but increases it at scattering angles somewhat larger. For sufficiently large scattering angles, both p a (θ) and &lt;p a &gt;(Θ) merge.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure A3 .Figure C1 .</head><label>A3C1</label><figDesc>Figure A3. Most of the contribution to the starlight forwardscattered by an exponential atmosphere arises from within a few scale heights above and below the optical radius level, defined by the limb opacity τ(r = R p )=0.56. In the example, τ(r) = 10 exp(−(r − R 0 )/H a ). Because, H a /R p &lt;&lt;1, the curves for rτ(r) exp (−τ(r)) and τ(r) exp (−τ(r)) are nearly undistinguishable in the scale of the plot; only the latter is graphed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table ( 2</head><label>(</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>) shows a selection of the planets investigated ar-
ranged by decreasing 2π(H/R p )(R p /a) 2 . Table (3) shows the 
same information specific to the Kepler planets discussed in 
Angerhausen et al. (2015) and </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Table 3 . Same as Table (2) for the planets discussed in Angerhausen et al. (2015) and Esteves et al. (2015).</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><head>Table 4 . Forward scattering from CoRoT-24b. We have varied both ∆α (by varying α C ) and r eff . The tabulated values provide the estimated photon noise PN and the observable O for each aerosol size. The quoted Os in regular typeface refer to calculations</head><label>4</label><figDesc>in the point-like star limit. Bold typeface refers to calculations taking into account the finite angular size of the star.</figDesc><table>α C 
PN 
O 0.5µm 
O 1µm 
O 2µm 
O 3µm 
O 5µm 
O 10µm 
[ • ] 
[ppm] 
[ppm] 
[ppm] [ppm] [ppm] [ppm] 
[ppm] 

160. 
64.3 
1.4 
2.7 
3.0 
2.3 
1.5 
0.8 
1.4 
2.6 
3.3 
3.5 
3.4 
3.7 
162. 
68.8 
1.5 
3.0 
3.4 
2.6 
1.7 
0.9 
1.4 
2.9 
3.7 
3.9 
3.9 
4.2 
164. 
74.2 
1.6 
3.4 
3.9 
3.0 
1.9 
1.0 
1.5 
3.3 
4.3 
4.6 
4.5 
4.9 
166. 
81.4 
1.6 
3.8 
4.6 
3.6 
2.3 
1.2 
1.6 
3.7 
5.1 
5.4 
5.3 
5.8 
168. 
91.1 
1.7 
4.4 
5.5 
4.4 
2.8 
1.4 
1.7 
4.2 
6.1 
6.6 
6.5 
7.2 
170. 
105.4 
1.8 
5.0 
6.9 
5.6 
3.5 
1.8 
1.7 
4.7 
7.5 
8.4 
8.5 
9.5 
172. 
129.6 
1.9 
5.7 
8.9 
7.6 
4.7 
2.4 
1.8 
5.3 
9.3 
11.2 
11.8 
13.8 
174. 
185.6 
1.9 
6.5 
12.2 
11.3 
7.4 
3.5 
1.9 
5.9 
11.7 
15.4 
17.7 
23.3 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">MNRAS 000, 1-16 (2017)</note>

			<note place="foot">N(m V ) = 10 −0.4m V f (m V = 0; λ = 550 nm)× MNRAS 000, 1-16 (2017)</note>

			<note place="foot">This paper has been typeset from a T E X/L A T E X file prepared by the author. MNRAS 000, 1-16 (2017)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AGM gratefully acknowledges conversations with Agustín</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: STARLIGHT FORWARD-SCATTERED BY A PLANET. AN ANALYTICAL EXPRESSION FOR EXPONENTIAL ATMOSPHERES.</head><p>We derive an expression for the starlight forward-scattered by an exponential atmosphere at a phase angle of 180 • . In its general form, the expression considers the finite angular size of the star. A few simplifying assumptions (SAs) enable us to treat the problem analytically:</p><p>(i) The atmosphere is horizontally uniform but vertically stratified.</p><p>(ii) The optical properties of the atmosphere are determined by ubiquitous particles that are referred to as aerosols (subscript a ) but that may actually be a mix of gases and condensates.</p><p>(iii) The aerosols extinction and scattering coefficients, γ a and β a , drop exponentially in the vertical with the scale height H a . The single scattering albedo 0,a =β a /γ a is altitude-independent.</p><p>(iv) The aerosols scattering phase function p a (θ) is also altitude-independent. θ is the scattering angle between the incident and exit directions of a photon being scattered by an aerosol particle.</p><p>(v) The ratio of the aerosol scale height H a and the planet radius R p satisfies H a /R p &lt;&lt;1.</p><p>(vi) The starlight forward-scattered by the atmosphere is dominated by singly-scattered photons. The validity of this assumption is tested a posteriori in Appendix B by comparison with numerical solutions to the multiple-scattering problem.</p><p>Figure (A1) sketches the star-planet-observer configuration at mid-transit for an impact parameter equal to zero, when α is identically equal to 180 • . The radiance at x in direction s due to stellar photons that either go through the atmosphere without scattering (and without altering their trajectories by atmospheric refraction) or that are scattered once is:</p><p>Here, t(x, x a ) and t(x, x b ) are the atmospheric transmittances between x and x a , and between x and x b , respectively. I(x b , s) is the outgoing radiance in direction s from the stellar surface element at x b . For simplicity, we assume that the star emits as a blackbody of radiance B , and omit limb darkening, which means that I(x b , s)=B . d a is the differential arc-length along s at x a , and β(x a ) is the scattering coefficient of the medium at x a . The second integral represents the starlight that is scattered at x a into direction s from all directions s emerging at the stellar surface. The scattering angle θ is locally defined by the dot product of the s and s directions, cos θ=s · s , and is equal to zero in forward scattering. dΩ is the differential solid angle subtended by the star from x a , and p a (x a , s ) is the corresponding aerosol scattering phase function. We normalize p a (θ) (SA(iv)) so that its integral over the 4π solid angle is one. This normalization differs from the more conventional approach of making</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precipitating condensation clouds in substellar atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ackerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/321540</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">556</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="884" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A comprehensive study of Kepler phase curves and secondary eclipses: Temperatures and albedos of confirmed Kepler giant planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Angerhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Delarme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">1113-1130.doi:10.1086/683797</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<publisher>Publications of the Astronomical Society of Pacific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photometrically derived masses and radii of the planet and star in the TrES-2 system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Morley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.53.doi:10.1088/0004-637X/761/1/53</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">761</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consistent retrieval analysis of 10 hot Jupiters observed in transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Barstow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aigrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.50.doi:10.3847/1538-4357/834/1/50</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">834</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Kepler mission: a wide-field-of-view photometer designed to determine the frequency of Earth-size planets around solar-like stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Caldwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1117/12.460266</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the SPIE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4854</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission spectra as diagnostics of extrasolar giant planet atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/320950</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1026" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light-curve analysis of KIC 12557548b: an extrasolar planet with a comet-like tail</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Budaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.A72.doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201220260</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">557</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tables of phase functions, opacities, albedos, equilibrium temperatures, and radiative accelerations of dust grains in exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Budaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kocifaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Salmeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hubeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/mnras/stv1711</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">454</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthetic stellar photometry -I. General considerations and new transformations for broad-band systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vandenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/mnras/stu1476</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of planetary atmospheres. An introduction to their physics and chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chamberlain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hunten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Geophysics Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<publisher>Academic Press Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Orlando</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of forward-scattered light in transmission measurements of (exo)planetary atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cubillos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Juvan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/mnras/stw3103</idno>
		<idno>doi: 10.1016/j.icarus.2012.08.020</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">466</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Icarus</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The albedos of Kepler&apos;s close-in superEarths</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B.-O</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.L20.doi:10.1088/2041-8205/789/1/L20</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">789</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of inflated radii for Kepler giant planet candidates receiving modest stellar irradiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B.-O</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.12.doi:10.1088/0067-0049/197/1/12</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Supplement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference of inhomogeneous clouds in an exoplanet atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B.-O</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zsom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.L25.doi:10.1088/2041-8205/776/2/L25</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">776</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the detection of non-transiting exoplanets with dusty tails</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Devore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanchís-Ojeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/mnras/stw1439</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2453" to="2460" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changing phases of alien worlds: Probing atmospheres of Kepler planets with high-precision photometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Esteves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J W</forename><surname>De Mooij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jayawardhana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.150.doi:10.1088/0004-637X/804/2/150</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">804</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">BEER analysis of Kepler and CoRoT light curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Faigler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tal-Or</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of Kepler-76b: A Hot Jupiter with evidence for superrotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.26.doi:10.1088/0004-637X/771/1/26</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">771</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aeronomical constraints to the minimum mass and maximum radius of hot low-mass planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cubillos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Odert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.A90.doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201629716</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">598</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">transit of Venus. Framework for interpretation of observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201219738</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">547</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pre-conditioned backward Monte Carlo solutions to radiative transport in planetary atmospheres. Fundamentals: Sampling of propagation directions in polarising media</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201424042</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">573</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glory revealed in disk-integrated photometry of Venus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pérez-Hoyos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sánchez-Lavega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201423531</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probing exoplanet clouds with optical phase curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Isaak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1073/pnas.1509135112</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the National Academy of Sciences</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13461" to="13466" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glancing views of the Earth: From a lunar eclipse to an exoplanetary transit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Montañés-Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/0004-637X/755/2/103</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">755</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Titan brighter at twilight than in daylight</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lavvas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.0114.doi:10.1038/s41550-017-0114</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Astronomy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exoplanet Orbit Database. II. Updates to Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/678447</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>org. Publications of the Astronomical Society of Pacific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="837" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light scattering in planetary atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Travis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1007/BF00168069</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Space Science Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="610" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the formation of atmospheric dust in brown dwarfs and planetary atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Helling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fomins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1098/rsta.2011.0581</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cloudiness index for transiting exoplanets based on the sodium and potassium lines: Tentative evidence for hotter atmospheres being less cloudy at visible wavelengths</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.L16.doi:10.3847/2041-8205/826/1/L16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">826</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studying atmosphere-dominated hot Jupiter Kepler phase curves: Evidence that inhomogeneous atmospheric reflection is common</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shporer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.112.doi:10.1088/0004-6256/150/4/112</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astronomical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of extrasolar giant planet transits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sudarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/322490</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">560</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric Lensing and Oblateness Effects during an Extrasolar Planetary Transit. The Astrophysical</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/340017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">572</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="540" to="555" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting reflected light from closein extrasolar giant planets with the Kepler photometer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Doyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/377165</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">595</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="445" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical constants of transition metals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Christy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Cr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Mn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Fe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ni</forename><surname>Co</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pd</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.9.5056</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5056" to="5070" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latitudinal variation of aerosol sizes inferred from Titan&apos;s shadow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Karkoschka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lorenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1006/icar.1996.5621</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="379" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A featureless transmission spectrum for the Neptune-mass exoplanet GJ436b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1038/nature12887</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extinction spectra of corundum in the wavelengths from UV to FIR</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kaito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shivai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Suto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1006/icar.1995.1055</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clouds in the atmosphere of the super-Earth exoplanet GJ1214b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kreidberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1038/nature12888</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying the &apos;true&apos; radius of the hot subNeptune CoRoT-24b by mass-loss modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Juvan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Odert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">10.1093/mnrasl/slw095</idno>
		<ptr target="doi:10.1093/mnrasl/slw095" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society: Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Titan&apos;s vertical aerosol structure at the Huygens landing site: Constraints on particle size, density, charge, and refractive index</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lavvas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/j.icarus.2010.07.025</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="832" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aerosol properties in exoplanet atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lavvas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koskinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>European Planetary Science Congress</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aerosol properties in the atmospheres of extrasolar giant planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lavvas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koskinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press. astroph</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rayleigh scattering in the transit spectrum of HD 189733b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1051/0004-6361:200809388</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">481</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic mineral clouds on HD 189733b. I. 3D RHD with kinetic, non-equilibrium cloud formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dobbs-Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Helling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bognar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Woitke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.A48.doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201628606</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">594</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periodic flux variability of stars due to the reflex Doppler effect induced by planetary companions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">L117-L120.doi:10.1086/375551</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reflected Spectra and Albedos of Extrasolar Giant Planets. I. Clear and Cloudy Atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gelino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stephens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Freedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">513</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">879</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A massive exoplanet candidate around KOI-13: independent confirmation by ellipsoidal variations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mislis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hodgkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1512" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discriminating between cloudy, hazy, and clear sky exoplanets using refraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/2041-8205/795/1/L14</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neglected clouds in T and Y dwarf atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Morley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Visscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Saumon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Leggett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.172.doi:10.1088/0004-637X/756/2/172</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">756</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The equations of ellipsoidal star variability applied to HR 8427</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Naftilan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/173488</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">419</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3D mixing in hot Jupiters atmospheres. I. Application to the day/night cold trap in HD 209458b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Parmentier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Showman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.A91.doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201321132</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">558</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Saturn&apos;s tropospheric particles phase function and spatial distribution from Cassini ISS 2010-11 observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pérez-Hoyos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sanz-Requena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sánchez-Lavega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/j.icarus.2016.04.022</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Combining photometry from Kepler and TESS to improve shortperiod exoplanet characterization. Publications of the Astronomical Society of Pacific</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Placek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Knuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Angerhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/1538-3873/128/965/074503</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74503</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Size estimates of Titan&apos;s aerosols based on Voyager high-phase-angle images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rages</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pollack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1029/JA088iA11p08721</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8721" to="8728" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of exoplanet transits with light scattering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.236.doi:10.3847/1538-4357/aa5ea8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">836</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clouds in planetary atmospheres: A useful application of the ClausiusClapeyron equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sánchez-Lavega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pérez-Hoyos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hueso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1119/1.1645279</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="774" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photometric Light Curves and Polarization of Close-in Extrasolar Giant Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Whitney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sasselov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/309292</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">540</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="504" to="520" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical Eclipses of Close-in Kepler Sub-Saturns</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sheets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.133.doi:10.1088/0004-637X/794/2/133</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">794</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The astrophysics of visible-light orbital phase curves in the space age</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shporer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/1538-3873/aa7112</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publications of the Astronomical Society of Pacific</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transits of transparent planetsatmospheric lensing effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/0004-637X/720/1/904</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">720</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="904" to="911" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A continuum from clear to cloudy hot-Jupiter exoplanets without primordial water depletion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nikolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kataria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1038/nature16068</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sotin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1073/pnas.1304206111</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<meeting>the National Academy of Sciences</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12622" to="12627" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying and predicting the presence of clouds in exoplanet atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.3847/2041-8205/817/2/L16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">817</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Transiting exoplanet studies and community targets for JWST&apos;s Early Release Science program</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beichman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fraine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1088/1538-3873/128/967/094401</idno>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Publications of the Astronomical Society of Pacific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94401</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Albedo and reflection spectra of extrasolar giant planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sudarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/309160</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">538</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="903" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photometry and polarimetry of Titan -Pioneer 11 observations and their implications for aerosol properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tomasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/0019-1035</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90030" to="90036" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model of Titan&apos;s aerosols based on measurements made inside the atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tomasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Doose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dafoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/j.pss.2007.11.019</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PSS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advection of potential temperature in the atmosphere of irradiated exoplanets: a robust mechanism to explain radius inflation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tremblin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mayne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Amundsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baraffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1704.05440</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission spectral properties of clouds for hot Jupiter exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">id.A122.doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201424207</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">573</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Voyager 2 photopolarimeter observations of Titan</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hord</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Esposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1029/JA088iA11p08699</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8699" to="8708" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for aggregate particles in the atmospheres of Titan and Jupiter</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/0019-1035(91</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90113" to="90121" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
