<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T15:58+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TIDAL EVOLUTION OF THE PLANETARY SYSTEM AROUND HD 83443</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2001-08-31">31 Aug 2001 Draft version October 25, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yanqin</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TIDAL EVOLUTION OF THE PLANETARY SYSTEM AROUND HD 83443</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2001-08-31">31 Aug 2001 Draft version October 25, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Draft version October 25, 2018</note>
					<note>Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: celestial mechanics -(stars:) binaries: spectroscopic -(stars:) planetary systems</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Two planets with orbital period ratio approximately 10:1 have been discovered around the star HD 83443. The inner and more massive planet, HD 83443b, has the smallest semi-major axis among all currently known exoplanets. Unlike other short period exoplanets, it maintains a substantial orbital eccentricity, e 1 = 0.079 ± 0.008, in spite of efficient tidal damping. This is a consequence of its secular interactions with HD 83443c whose orbital eccentricity e 2 = 0.42 ± 0.06. Dissipation, associated with tides the star raises in the inner planet, removes energy but not angular momentum from its orbit, while secular interactions transfer angular momentum but not energy from the inner to the outer planet&apos;s orbit. The outward transfer of angular momentum decreases the tidal decay rate of the inner planet&apos;s orbital eccentricity while increasing that of the outer planet. The alignment of the apsides of the planets&apos; orbits is another consequence of tidal and secular interactions. In this state the ratio of their orbital eccentricities, e 1 /e 2 , depends upon the secular perturbations the planets exert on each other and on additional perturbations that enhance the inner planet&apos;s precession rate. Tidal and rotational distortions of the inner planet along with general relativity provide the most important of these extra precessional perturbations, each of which acts to reduce e 1 /e 2. Provided the planets&apos; orbits are coplanar, the observed eccentricity ratio uniquely relates sin i and C ≡ (k 2 /k 2J)(R 1 /R J) 5 , where the tidal Love number, k 2 , and radius, R 1 , of the inner planet are scaled by their Jovian equivalents.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Parameters of the HD 83443 planetary system as given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mayor et al. (2000)</ref> are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The substantial eccentricity of the inner planet's orbit, e 1 = 0.079 ± 0.008, is surprising since other exoplanets with comparable semi-major axes have circular orbits. In the absence of other interactions, tidal dissipation would erode e 1 as d ln e 1 /dt = −1/τ with ( <ref type="bibr">Goldreich 1963</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">, Hut 1981</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">τ ≈ 2 27 Q k 2 a 3 1 GM * 1/2 m 1 M * a 1 R 1 5 .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Adopting values appropriate for Jupiter: radius R 1 ≈ 7 × 10 4 km, mass m 1 ≈ 2 × 10 30 g, tidal Love number k 2 ≈ 0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Yoder 1995)</ref>, and tidal quality factor, Q ∼ 3×10 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Goldreich &amp; Soter 1966</ref>), yields τ ∼ 3 × 10 8 yr. This is in striking contrast to the old age of the star. Isochrone fitting suggests an age of about 6.5 Gyr (N. Murray, private communication), which is consistent with the absence of chromospheric activity and the small projected rotational velocity, v sin i &lt; 2 km/ s. Secular interactions with HD 83443c are undoubtedly responsible for the persistence of HD 83443b's orbital eccentricity <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Mayor et al. 2000)</ref>. Results from calculations by Lasker and Benz displayed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mayor et al. (2000)</ref> show that secular interactions between the inner and outer planets induce anti-correlated oscillations in the two planets' orbital eccentricities. The anti-correlation results because secular interactions transfer angular momentum, J, but not energy, E, and e is related to E and J by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">e 2 = 1 + 2J 2 E m 3 (GM ) 2 .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Similar phenomena are noted in the hierarchical triple star systems HD 109648 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Jha et al. 2000)</ref>, HD 284163 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Griffin &amp; Gunn 1981)</ref>, and Algol (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kiseleva et al. 1998</ref>).</p><p>We argue that eccentricity oscillations were tidally damped a long time ago, and that currently the planets maintain apse alignment ( §3). In this state the orbital eccentricity of the inner planet is proportional to that of the outer planet, and both are steady on the secular timescale. On the much longer tidal time-scale, the individual eccentricities decay, with the decay rate being faster for the inner planet.</p><p>We utilize the properties of this system to constrain parameters that are not directly measurable. From the ratio of the two eccentricities, we place bounds on the inclination angle, i, of the planets' orbit plane and on the radius of the inner planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">CONSEQUENCES OF APSE ALIGNMENT</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Assumptions</head><p>We study secular interactions in HD83443's planetary system under the assumptions that the planets share a common orbital plane and that their apsides remain aligned. The former assumption seems reasonable for planets formed in a gaseous disk. The latter assumption is consistent with the currently observed approximate apse alignment (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>) and is justified by the analysis in  <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mayor et al. (2000)</ref>. Planet masses are in unit of Saturn mass M Sat ≈ 5.68 × 10 29 g. The host star M * = 0.79M ⊙ . §3. These assumptions allow us to infer parameters of the planetary system from the observed eccentricity ratio.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Secular Dynamics</head><p>Mutual secular perturbations of the planets' orbits are calculated following a method devised by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Gauss (1818)</ref> as outlined in the appendix. Equation (A3) describes the resulting periapse and eccentricity variations. However, as a result of inner planet's proximity to the star, it is subject to additional precessional perturbations of which the most important arise from its related tidal and rotational distortions (Sterne 1939) 3 , and from general relativity <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Einstein 1916)</ref>. Expressions for these precession rates are,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">d̟ 1 dt tide = 7.5n 1 k 2 1 + 3 2 e 2 1 + 1 8 e 4 1 (1 − e 2 1 ) 5 M * m 1 R 1 a 1 5 , (3a) d̟ 1 dt J2 = 0.5n 1 k 2 (1 − e 2 1 ) 2 Ω 1 n 1 2 M * m 1 R 1 a 1 5 , (3b) d̟ 1 dt GR = 3n 1 GM * a 1 c 2 (1 − e 2 1 )</formula><p>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(3c)</formula><p>Note that in equation (3b) the planet's spin rate, Ω 1 , is scaled by its mean motion, n 1 , since we expect that tidal dissipation has produced approximate spin-orbit synchronization. We neglect smaller precessional contributions due to the rotational oblateness of the star and to the tidal distortion of the star by the planet.</p><p>Numerically, the total rate of extra precessions amounts to,</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">∆ ≡ d̟ 1 dt tide + d̟ 1 dt J2 + d̟ 1 dt GR = (7.79 C sin i + 1.52) × 10 −11 s −1 ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where we set Ω 1 = n 1 and introduce the dimensionless number <ref type="bibr">5</ref> , with R J and k 2J assigned values appropriate for Jupiter. Observations determine k 2J = 0.494, close to that of an n = 1 polytrope, k 2 ≈ 0.51, whereas Saturn has a smaller Love number, k 2 = 0.317 (Yoder 1995) because it is more centrally condensed as a result of possessing a relatively larger core of heavy elements. We incorporate the additional precessional terms into the secular perturbation equations (see eq. <ref type="bibr">[A1]</ref>). In a state of apse alignment, there is no secular exchange of angular momentum between the planets. Therefore, their orbital eccentricities are constant on the secular timescale. Moreover, the eccentricity ratio, e 1 /e 2 , is a monotonically decreasing function of ∆. To match the observationally determined value of e 1 /e 2 = 0.19 requires ∆ ≈ 9.1 × 10 −11 sin −1 i s −1 . This value is greater than the precession rate due to general relativity and provides evidence for the tidal and rotational distortion of the inner planet. Because the inner planet is not observed to transit, sin i &lt; 0.99, which implies C ≥ 0.9. Nearly pole-on orbits, sin i &lt; 0.20, are excluded if we accept that R 1 &lt; 2R J , a conservative upper-limit as judged from <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Burrows et al. 2000</ref>. This implies m 1 &lt; 5.45M sat . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows e 1 as a function of C for different values of sin i with e 2 fixed at its observed value. </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">C ≡ (k 2 /k 2J )(R 1 /R J )</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Tidal Dynamics</head><p>Tidal dissipation in the approximately synchronously rotating inner planet decreases its orbital energy without significantly changing its orbital angular momentum. It follows from equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> that this causes a 1 to vary as d ln a 1 /dt ≈ −2e 2 1 /τ . Since secular interactions transfer angular momentum but not energy between the planets' orbits, a 2 remains constant. Conservation of total angular momentum leads to,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">dJ 1 dt = J 1 1 2 d ln a 1 dt − e 2 1 1 − e 2 1 d ln e 1 dt = − dJ 2 dt = J 2 e 2 2 1 − e 2 2 d ln e 2 dt ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where J i = 1 − e 2 i m i n i a 2 i . Apse alignment implies e 1 = f (a 1 , e 2 ), from which we deduce that</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">d ln e 1 dt = − 1 τ f e2 (1 − e 2 1 ) + 2e 2 2 f a1 J2(1−e 2 1 ) J1(1−e 2 2 ) f e2 + J2 J1 ( 1−e 2 1 1−e 2 2 ) ( e2 e1 ) 2 , d ln e 2 dt = − 1 τ (1 − e 2 1 ) − 2e 2 1 f a1 f e2 + J2 J1 ( 1−e 2 1 1−e 2 2 ) ( e2 e1 ) 2 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where f a1 ≡ ∂ ln f /∂ ln a 1 and f e2 ≡ ∂ ln f /∂ ln e 2 . Numerically, f a1 ≈ 8 and f e2 ≈ 1, so currently e 1 and e 2 are damping on time-scales of 8.6τ and 40τ , respectively; e 1 damps faster than e 2 because the inner planet's semimajor axis is shrinking.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">LINEAR APPROXIMATION</head><p>In §2 we assumed that tidal dissipation had delivered the planets' orbits into a state of periapse alignment. Here we justify this assumption by studying the secular dynamics and tidal evolution under the somewhat inaccurate approximation of small orbital eccentricities.</p><p>Our starting point is the expansion of the secular disturbing function to second order in e 1 and e 2 . Substituting the expanded disturbing function into Lagrange's equations for the variations of the e's and the ̟'s, and adding a term to represent tidal damping of e 1 , yields the following set of linear equations (MD2000)</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">dI 1 dt = iA 11 I 1 + iA 12 I 2 − I 1 /τ, dI 2 dt = iA 21 I 1 + iA 22 I 2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>for the complex variable I i ≡ e i exp(i̟ i ). The coefficients A ij read:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A 11 = α 2 4 m 2 M * n 1 B 1 + ∆, A 12 = − α 2 4 m 2 M * n 1 B 2 , A 21 = − α 4 m 1 M * n 2 B 2 , A 22 = α 4 m 1 M * n 2 B 1 ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>with α = a 1 /a 2 , B 1 = b</p><p>3/2 , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">B 2 = b (2) 3/2 ; b (j) s</formula><p>is the usual Laplace coefficient. The symbols ∆ and τ retain their definitions from §2.</p><p>In the absence of tidal damping (τ → ∞), the general solution of equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(7)</ref> can be expressed as a super-position of two eigenvectors I * with</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">I * = [e 1 * exp(i φ 1 * ), e 2 * exp(i φ 2 * )] exp(i g * t),<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">g * = (A 11 + A 22 ) ± (A 11 − A 22 ) 2 + 4A 12 A 21 2 , (10a) e 1 * e 2 * = g * − A 22 A 21 = A 12 A 11 − g * ,<label>(10b)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">φ 1 * = φ 2 * + π 2 [1 + sgn(g * − A 22 )] .<label>(10c)</label></formula><p>We distinguish the two eigensolutions by * = p and * = m according to the plus or minus sign that appears before the square root in the expression for g * . Since (e 1p /e 2p ) (e 1m /e 2m ) = A 12 /A 21 ≈ 1.0, one solution satisfies e 1 &lt; e 2 and the other e 1 &gt; e 2 . If we take ∆ = 5 × 10 −11 s −1 , the * = m solution reproduces the observed eccentricity ratio e 1m /e 2m = 0.19 and apse alignment. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> The other solution has e 1p /e 2p = 5.26 and antialigned apses. If both eigenvectors have non-zero lengths, the orbital eccentricities oscillate out of phase on timescales of thousands of years (∼ 1/g * ) as depicted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Mayor et al. (2000)</ref>.</p><p>When τ is finite, a 1 and therefore A ij vary with time. Since τ ≫ 1/g * , the solution for the eigenvectors given by equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(10)</ref> remains valid. However, the eigenvector components, e i * , decay slowly with time as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">γ 1 * = 1 τ 1 + 2e 2 2 * f a1 J2 J1 1 + J2 J1 ( e2 * e1 * ) 2 , γ 2 * = 1 τ 1 − 2e 2 1 * f a1 1 + J2 J1 ( e2 * e1 * ) 2 ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where γ i * ≡ −d ln e i * /dt. In the limit of small eccentricity, the expressions for the nonlinear damping rates given by equation (6) reduce to those in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(11)</ref> provided f e2 = 1 as is appropriate for the linear problem. Each of the four eigenvector components has its individual damping rate. Both components of the p eigenvector decay more rapidly than those of the m eigenvector. If the current state consists mostly the m eigenvector with a small admixture of the p eigenvector, both components in the latter would decay on time-scale ≈ τ , while the dominant components e 1m and e 2m would decay much more slowly, as γ −1 1m ≈ 7τ and γ −1 2m ≈ 32τ . It is notable that the asymmetry in damping rates between the aligned and the anti-aligned solutions only applies if the inner planet has an orbital period ≤ 5 days. For longer periods, the additional precession rates (eqs.</p><p>[3a] - <ref type="bibr">[3c]</ref>) are unimportant and (e 1m /e 2m ) ∼ (e 1p /e 2p ) ∼ 1.</p><p>Apse alignment indicates that a minimum amount of tidal dissipation has occurred over the life-time of the system, taken to be N Gyrs. By requiring that this is at least 3 times longer than τ , we deduce that Q &lt; 5×10 5 N C sin i. It may also be possible to infer a lower limit for Q by integrating the orbits backward in time.</p><p>At the present time n 1 /n 2 = 9.99 ± 0.06, suggestive of a 10 : 1 mean motion resonance. This is probably just a coincidence. Moreover, no physically important effects would be associated with this resonance should it exist.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">, d̟ 1 dt = d̟ 1 dt 2 + d̟ 1 dt tide + d̟ 1 dt J2 + d̟ 1 dt GR ,<label>(A1)</label></formula><p>where the subscript 2 denotes effects arising from secular interactions with the outer planet. Similar equations apply to the evolution of ̟ 2 and e 2 but the only significant perturbations are those from the inner planet. Expressions for the precession rates due to the tidal and rotational distortion of the inner planet and to general relativity are given in the main body of the text. We obtain d̟ 1 /dt| 2 by applying a method devised by Gauss (1818) as outlined below. Consider a pair of coplanar rings formed by spreading the mass of each planet along its orbit such that the line density is inversely proportional to the orbital velocity. We decompose into radial, R, and tangential, T , components the gravitational force exerted on a line element of length r 1 df 1 by a line element of length r 2 df 2 , where f denotes true anomaly and r distance from the star; R = Gρ 1 ρ 2 r 1 r 2 df 1 df 2 |r 1 − r 2 | 2 cos θ, T = Gρ 1 ρ 2 r 1 r 2 df 1 df 2 |r 1 − r 2 | 2 sin θ,</p><p>with θ the angle between r 1 and r 2 − r 1 . We remove θ in favor of φ, the angle between r 1 and r 2 (φ = f 2 + ̟ 2 − f 1 − ̟ 1 ), by applying the geometric relations, |r 1 − r 2 | sin θ = r 2 sin φ and |r 1 − r 2 | cos θ = r 2 cos φ − r 1 . Then we integrate over df 2 to obtain the components of the total force due to planet 2 on the mass of planet 1 in the line element r 1 df 1 . When this result is substituted into Gauss' form of the perturbation equations (Gauss 1818) and integrated over f 1 , we obtain We have verified that when integrating these equations with parameters appropriate to HD 83443's planetary system, we obtain results that agree well with those obtained by direct integration of the orbits using the SWIFT package <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Levinson &amp; Duncan 1991</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Values of the inner planet eccentricity, e 1 , as a function of C for different values of sin i. The ten solid lines are for sin i varying in equal increments from 0.1 to 1.0. The horizontal band is centered on the measured value of e 1 and its vertical width spans a 1 − σ error bar in each direction. Relevant parameters are taken from Table 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 Parameters for the two planets of HD 83443. a</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Planet 
P (d) 
e 
̟( • ) 
a (AU) 
m sin i 

HD83443b 2.9853 ± 0.0009 0.079 ± 0.008 300 ± 17 
0.0376 
1.14 
HD83443c 
29.83 ± 0.18 
0.42 ± 0.06 337 ± 10 
0.175 
0.53 

a Data taken from </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> Canadian Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Toronto, 60 St. George Street, Toronto, ON M5S 3H8, Canada, wu@cita.utoronto.ca 2 Division of Geophysics and Planetary Sciences, Caltech, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA, pmg@gps.caltech.edu 1</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> The symbol k 2 also appears as the apsidal motion constant in stellar literature in which case it is a factor 2 smaller than the Love number.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4">. CONCLUSIONS Both the survival of HD 83443b&apos;s orbital eccentricity and the locking of its apse to that of HD 83443c are straightforward consequences of secular and tidal dynamics. The ratio e 1 /e 2 provides compelling evidence for the tidal and rotational distortion of HD 83443b. It constrains unknown system parameters by relating C ≡ (k 2 /k 2J )(R 1 /R J ) 5 to sin i. In particular, we find C &gt; 0.9. 4 This value of ∆ is different from that required in §2.2 because the linear approximation is inaccurate for e 2 = 0.42.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> Our derivation is slightly different from that given in MD2000, but the results are identical.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SECULAR PERTURBATIONS</head><p>Secular changes of the inner planet's periapse angle, ̟ 1 , and eccentricity, e 1 , are described by</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Saumon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sudarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">534</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Einstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annalen der Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1916" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Collected Works</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1818" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">257</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>MNRAS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">588</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stefanik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kiseleva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Eggleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mikkola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">292</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planetary Systems in the Universe, Observation, Formation and Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burnet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASP Conf. Series</title>
		<editor>Penny, A.J., Artymowicz, P., Lagrange, A.-M. &amp; Russell, S.S.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Solar System Dynamics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sterne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">451</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1939" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Handbook of Physical Constants: Global Earth Physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Ahrens, T. J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
