<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:05+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Vol. 3 On homogeneous statistical distributions exoplanets for their dynamic parameters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mushailov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Sternberg Astronomical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Moscow State University Universitetsky pr</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13</addrLine>
									<postCode>119992</postCode>
									<region>Moscow</region>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ivanovskaya</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Sternberg Astronomical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Moscow State University Universitetsky pr</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13</addrLine>
									<postCode>119992</postCode>
									<region>Moscow</region>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Teplitskaya</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Sternberg Astronomical Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Moscow State University Universitetsky pr</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>13</addrLine>
									<postCode>119992</postCode>
									<region>Moscow</region>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Vol. 3 On homogeneous statistical distributions exoplanets for their dynamic parameters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>exoplanets</term>
					<term>orbital resonances</term>
					<term>statistical distributions</term>
					<term>orbital parameters</term>
					<term>extra solar systems</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Correct distributions of extrasolar systems for their orbital parameters (semi-major axes, period, eccentricity) and physical characteristics (mass, spectral type of parent star) are received. Orbital resonances in extrasolar systems are considered. It is shown, that the account of more thin effects, including with use of wavelet methods, in obviously incorrectly reduced distributions it is not justified, to what the homogeneous statistical distributions for dynamic parameters of exoplanets, received in the present work, testify. Introduction During dynamic evolution extrasolar planets pass a number of regular stages which have universal character. Revealing of these general laws, certainly, will promote better understanding of an origin and evolution of planetary systems. At October, 2009 outside Solar system it was discovered about 400 candidates for major planets (extrasolar planets). A large number of extrasolar planets comparable in mass to Jupiter, but apparently this is a consequence of the selective effect of detection-giant planets easier to detect. In connection with the improvement of the observation base, development of new methods of detection, the number of candidates for extrasolar planets is steadily increasing. The most effective are the methods of searching candidates for extrasolar planets:-The measuring of radial velocity. The star having a planet, tests fluctuations of velocity &quot; to us-from us &quot; which can be measured by observing the Doppler shift of the spectrum of the star.-The photometric method, is connected with an opportunity of passage of a planet on a background of a star. The planet eclipses a part of a surface, and brightness of a star decreases.-Astrometric method. It is based on taking into account of gravitational influence of planets on a star. If very precisely to measure a trajectory of a star it is possible to see its easy tortuosity caused by gravitation of planets.-Microlensing. When one star passes another on a background, light of a distant star is bent by gravitation near star and its brightness varies. If the nearest star has planets it will affect a curve of change of brightness.-A number of the methods based on obtaining of the direct image-In addition, the method for ultra precise photometric monitoring of stars and method for a method of measurement of a curve of shine, but not due to transit of a planet, and in view of tidal influence from a planet (planets) (Gerasimov I.A. et al., 2003) is developed also. Currently, there are six specialized discusses space projects to find extrasolar planets (PEGASE, New Worlds Mission, IRSI/ DARWIN (ESA), Space Interferometry Mission SIM, Terrestrial Planet Finder TPF, Kepler (NASA), GAIA (ESA)) are discussed. The statistical distribution of exoplanets. Till now the conventional and consistent theory of formation of planetary systems and multiple stellarr systems is not created. It is considered, that stars with rather small mass, located more to the right of the main sequence, could be members of multiple stellar systems, and that the most part of these dynamic systems has broken up under action of tidal forces. But due to capture interstellar gas-dust matters, these stars were capable to form the planetary systems. On the other hand, stars can lose the planets being far from them and having with a central star weak gravitational connection. Except for major planets, around of stars can exist a minor planets (asteroids, comets, etc.). Configuration of large and minor planets of the solar system suggests that their dynamic evolution is strongly influenced</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution of exoplanets for eccentricity</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Given that the dominant role in the dynamical evolution of planetary systems are parameters (and, above all, mass) of the central star, the correct comparison of the dynamic characteristics of exoplanets is possible only in a system of units adapted (self-consistent) to the parameters of the central star. Such approach considers their hierarchy -a dominating role of the central star in evolution of planetary system within the limits of n-bodies problem, instead of all statistical sample of planets. While use of not self-consistent parameters leads to distortion of results and does not allow correctly identify the general laws of evolution of exoplanets systems. As consequence, in distributions in not adapted system of units the harmonics connected with not considered dynamic influence of the central stars are shown.</p><p>Distributions in the reduced (self-consistent) system of units are exponential. The precise distribution of extrasolar planets by the masses, as well as on the orbital period suggests expressly selective effect.</p><p>For each statistical distribution the correlation coefficient between corresponding values of parameters in the self-consistent and not adapted systems of units has been calculated. Divergences between the values of the same name in different systems of units are substantial, and the homogeneity of the distributions is broken when the correlation coefficient smaller than 0.97. As expected, the correlation coefficients of samples for the spectral types of stars are much higher than for the entire sample.</p><p>Presence of the common laws proves to be true existence of resonant systems, and, in particular, two-frequency resonances. From 44 multiple systems 17 -are connected by two-frequency orbital resonances of lower orders.</p><p>Revealing of more thin effects, including with use "wavelet methods" (Baluyev R.V. 2006.), in obviously incorrectly reduced distributions, certainly, is not justified, to what the homogeneous statistical distributions of dynamic parameters of exoplanets received in the present work testify.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The orbital periods of 17 alleged resonance exoplanets. We give the size of extrasolar planets in proportion to their masses, with the exception of three planetary systems, which are displayed as a points with shadow, in view of the smallness of their masses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>upper0</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The histogram distribution of extrasolar planets in semi-major axes . The correlation coefficient values in the self-consistent and not adapted systems of units is equal to 0.821.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Distribution exoplanet for central strar's stellar spectral type.Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. The histogram distribution of extrasolar planets by the stellar spectral type.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Distribution of exoplanet for semi-major axes for central stars of spectral typeFig. 6 .of exoplanet for semi-major axes for central stars of spectral typeFigure 7 .of exoplanet for semi-major axes for central stars of spectral typeFig. 8 .of exoplanet's mass for central stars of spectralFig. 9 .Fig. 10 .Fig. 11 .of exoplanets for orbital period for central stars of spectral type</head><label>67891011</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. The histogram distribution of exoplanets for semi-major axes of the planets for the stars of stellar spectral type F. The correlation coefficient values in the self-consistent and not adapted systems of units is equal to 0.957.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig.13. The histogram distribution of extrasolar planets for the orbital period for stars of the stellar spectral type G. The correlation coefficient values in the self-consistent and not adapted systems of units is equal to 0.863. Distribution of exoplanets for orbital period for central stars of spectral type K</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. The histogram distribution of extrasolar planets for the orbital period for stars of the stellar spectral type K. The correlation coefficient values in the self-consistent and not adapted systems of units is equal to 0.883.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15. Histogram of the predicted distribution of the eccentricity of extrasolar planets (in dimensionless units).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistics of masses and orbital parameters of extrasolar planets using continuous wavelet transforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Baluyev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the international colloquium held at the observatories de Haute Provence</title>
		<editor>L. Arnold, F. Bouchyand, C. Moutou</editor>
		<meeting>the international colloquium held at the observatories de Haute Provence<address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gerasimov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mushailov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. and Astrophis. Transaction</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanet orbital evolution under the influence of nearby stars. Fewbody problem: Theory and computer simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kuteeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sokolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annales Universitatis Turkuensis. Ser.1A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="134" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clearing of statistics extrasolar planets from effects of observant selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Baluyev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>30.01-3.02</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of space. 35-international stud. Conf. Ekaterinburg</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Publishing house Urals State University.2006. P.214</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probability theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wentzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>M. Publishing Center &quot;Academia</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">About some general common laws of dynamic evolution exoplanets and planets of Solar system&quot;. Theses of reports. International conf</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mushailov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ivanovskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>100 years to the Tungus phenomenon: the past, present, the future&quot;. Moscow, 26.06-28.06.2008. P.139</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">15 figures; International Conference &quot;100 years since Tunguska phenomenon: Past, present and future</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Russia, Moscow</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Moscow State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Lomonosov readings</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
