<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:05+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Fast Inversion Method for Determination of Planetary Parameters from Transit Timing Variations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2009-11-30">30 Nov 2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">Nesvorn´y</forename><surname>Nesvorn´y</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Space Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southwest Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1050 Walnut St., Suite 400</addrLine>
									<postCode>80302</postCode>
									<settlement>Boulder</settlement>
									<region>Colorado</region>
									<country>USA (</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cristián</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional de Córdoba</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Laprida 854</addrLine>
									<postCode>X5000BGR</postCode>
									<settlement>Córdoba</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Fast Inversion Method for Determination of Planetary Parameters from Transit Timing Variations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2009-11-30">30 Nov 2009</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: Stars: planetary systems -celestial mechanics</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Transit Timing Variation (TTV) method relies on monitoring changes in timing of transits of known exoplanets. Non-transiting planets in the system can be inferred from TTVs by their gravitational interaction with the transit-ing planet. The TTV method is sensitive to low-mass planets that cannot be detected by other means. Here we describe a fast algorithm that can be used to determine the mass and orbit of the non-transiting planets from the TTV data. We apply our code, ttvim.f, to a wide variety of planetary systems to test the uniqueness of the TTV inversion problem and its dependence on the precision of TTV observations. We find that planetary parameters, including the mass and mutual orbital inclination of planets, can be determined from the TTV datasets that should become available in near future. Unlike the radial velocity technique, the TTV method can therefore be used to characterize the inclination distribution of multi-planet systems.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In Nesvorn´y <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Nesvorn´y &amp; Morbidelli (2008)</ref> and Nesvorn´yNesvorn´y (2009) (hereafter NM08 and N09) we developed and tested a fast inversion method that can be used to characterize planetary systems from the observed Transit Timing Variations (TTVs; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agol et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Holman &amp; Murray 2005)</ref>. See NM08 and N09 for a technical description of the method. Here we use this new method to solve the TTV inversion problem for an arbitrary planetary system. The results provide a baseline for studies of real exoplanetary systems for which TTVs will be detected. Examples of past work that would greatly benefit from the application of the fast inversion algorithm discussed here include , , <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Miller-Ricci et al. (2008)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gibson et al. (2009)</ref>.</p><p>In §2, we briefly describe the TTV inversion method. In §3, we apply it to a case with coplanar planetary orbits. Inclined planetary orbits are discussed in §4. We show, for example, that the mutual inclination of planetary orbits can be determined from TTVs. This important parameter, which may be used to test planet-migration theories (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Rasio &amp; Ford 1996</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">, Goldreich &amp; Sari 2003</ref>, is not typically available from other existing planetdetection methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Inversion Method</head><p>Our TTV inversion method, hereafter TTVIM, has two parts. The first part is a fast algorithm for the computation of transit times, (δt j ) trial , 1 ≤ j ≤ N, for specified planetary parameters. This algorithm is based on perturbation theory (NM08, N09). It calculates the short-period TTVs as these have been shown to be the most diagnostic (NM08). The long-term effects such as the apsidal precession produced by the perturbing planet are more difficult to detect if transit observations span only a few years <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Miralda-Escudé 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Heyl &amp; Gladman 2007</ref>).</p><p>The second part of TTVIM is an adaptation of the Downhill Simplex Method (DSM; <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Press et al. 1992</ref>). The DSM is used to search for the minima of</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">χ 2 = N j=1 (δt j ) trial − (δt j ) obs σ j 2 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where (δt j ) trial are the transit times produced by the first part of the algorithm for a trial planetary system, (δt j ) obs are the observed mid-transit times, and σ j are the measurement errors. It is assumed here (as indicated by δ's) that the period of the transiting planet, P , has been removed from transit observations. Thus, (δt j ) obs = (t j ) obs − C j P , where (t j ) obs are the actual transit times and integer C j denotes the transit cycle.</p><p>The best-fit planetary parameters correspond to the global minimum of χ 2 , denoted by χ 2 min in the following. A large number of initial trials must be used to assure that the DSM method finds χ 2 min . The confidence levels for the normally distributed data can be defined as ∆χ 2 = χ 2 − χ 2 min &lt; (∆χ 2 ) cut , where the (∆χ 2 ) cut values are properly chosen for N and the required confidence level (NM08).</p><p>Here we assume that the mass and orbit of the transiting planet are known from transit and radial velocity (RV) measurements as this should be the most common case in practice.</p><p>If so, χ 2 is a function of seven unknown parameters of the perturbing planet, χ 2 = χ 2 (m 2 , a 2 , e 2 , i 2 , Ω 2 , ̟ 2 , λ 2 ), where m 2 is the mass, a 2 semimajor axis, e 2 eccentricity, i 2 inclination, Ω 2 nodal longitude, ̟ 2 periapse longitude, and λ 2 the mean orbital phase at t = 0 (arbitrarily defined here to correspond to cycle C 0 ). <ref type="bibr">1</ref> The parameters of the transiting planet will be denoted by index 1. DSM must therefore search in 7D space for the global minimum of χ 2 . This is not a trivial task because χ 2 often has many deep and narrow local minima . Fortunately, several simplifications can be made.</p><p>First, as the amplitude of the short-period TTVs scales linearly with m 2 , we can calculate the TTV profile for the selected a 2 , e 2 , i 2 , Ω 2 , ̟ 2 , λ 2 values and obtain m 2 by the linear least-square fit. Second, the determination of χ 2 for a new set of the Ω 2 , ̟ 2 and λ 2 values is computationally cheap in the perturbation algorithm, if χ 2 was determined previously for the required a 2 , e 2 and i 2 values. <ref type="bibr">2</ref> The code can thus efficiently search for the minimum of χ 2 (a 2 , e 2 , i 2 ) for any value of Ω 2 , ̟ 2 and λ 2 . In practice, we use 5 to 20 values between 0 and 360 • to resolve each of these parameters. This effectively reduces the number of dimensions to 3. Once the interval of estimated a 2 , e 2 and i 2 values is narrowed down, the solution can be refined by using the full DSM search in 7D.</p><p>The tricky part of TTVIM is the choice of the initial guess in the (a 2 , e 2 , i 2 ) space. By trials and errors we found that fine (and non-linear) sampling of a 2 is generally needed for a successful convergence of the algorithm. The best results were obtained with uniform sampling in 1/α 2 , where α = a 1 /a 2 &lt; 1. Parameters e 2 and i 2 require less care since DSM usually finds the right minimum even in the high-e 2 and/or high-i 2 case if at least one corner of the initial simplex is stretched to e 2 &gt; 0.2 and i 2 &gt; 30 • .</p><p>With the nominal setup, our TTVIM code (ttvim.f) requires about 2 minutes of CPU time 3 for a coplanar fit with i 2 = 0 and about 50 minutes for the full 7D fit. In the absence of measurement errors, the success rate in finding χ 2 min is better than 95%. Thus, ttvim.f is a robust code that can reliably solve the TTV inverse problem at a low computational cost.</p><p>1 These are the actual parameters used in DSM. The boundary at e 2 = 0 does not need a special treatment because (e 2 , ̟ 2 ) is formally equivalent to (−e 2 , ̟ 2 + π/2). Similar rules apply to (i 2 , Ω 2 ) and (m 2 , λ 2 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results for Coplanar Orbits</head><p>We used a random number generator to define different sets of parameters m 2 , a 2 , e 2 , i 2 , Ω 2 , ̟ 2 and λ 2 . Typically, 1000-2000 different planet parameter sets were used in tests. In each case, the orbital evolution of the two planets was followed for a fixed timespan, 0 &lt; t &lt; T int , with the Bulirsch-Stoer integrator ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Press et al. 1992)</ref>. During this timespan we interpolated for and recorded all transit times of the inner planet. This data mimics the real observations, (δt j ) obs . They were used in a blind test where we applied the TTVIM code to each of these cases in an attempt to recover the original mass and the orbital elements of the non-transiting planet.</p><p>We start by discussing the case with star's mass m 0 = M Sun , where M Sun = 2 × 10 33 g is the mass of the Sun, m 1 = 10 −3 m 0 , a 1 = 0.1 AU, e 1 = i 1 = 0 and N = 100 consecutive transits. Since NM08 and N09 showed that the behavior of the inversion method is insensitive to m 1 , we will not test different m 1 values in this work. To distinguish between the issues related to the intrinsic limitations of ttvim.f and those arising from the finite precision of the real measurements, we first discuss an idealized case with zero measurement noise.</p><p>For coplanar orbits and σ j = 0, the TTVIM code finds the correct planetary parameters with a high rate of success <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1)</ref>. The typical precision in the successful cases is |m 2 − m * 2 |/m 2 &lt; 0.2, |a 2 −a * 2 |/a 2 &lt; 0.02, |e 2 −e * 2 | &lt; 0.02, |̟ 2 −̟ * 2 | &lt; 10 • and |λ 2 −λ * 2 | &lt; 10 • , where the asterisk denotes the values determined by the TTVIM code. 4 This is very satisfactory. In the absence of measurement errors, the result of the TTVIM code illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> with m 2 = 10 −4 m 0 is insensitive to the actual value of m 2 .</p><p>The main failure mode of the TTVIM code occurs near mean motion resonances between planets, because resonant perturbations are not (yet) taken into account in TTVIM. While the resonant signal can improve our chances of the TTV detection for (near-)resonant planets, it seems less useful in helping us estimate the mass and orbit of the planetary companion. Specifically, the amplitude and period of the resonant signal can be fit by a number of different planetary setups corresponding to different resonances. Thus, without an apriori knowledge of the mean motion resonance that is responsible for the observed behavior, the inversion problem from resonant frequencies alone is strongly degenerate.</p><p>Fortunately, the short-period TTVs underlying the resonant signal can still be used to determine the planetary parameters without much ambiguity. As shown in NM08, probably the best strategy is to isolate short-period frequencies in the signal by Fourier filter and apply the inversion method to the filtered signal. The application of this procedure is straightforward in individual cases (see NM08), where the resonant period, and thus the appropriate frequency cutoff, can be estimated from (t j ) obs . We verified that this procedure works quite well in &gt;75% of cases shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> in which the resonant variations are an issue.</p><p>The remaining &lt;25% unsuccessful cases (representing &lt;5% overall) correspond to the very large values of e 2 for which the Laplacian expansion of the perturbing function in TTVIM is not convergent (NM08), and/or planetary configurations that are not Hill stable. Direct N-body integrations can be used to address the TTV inversion problem in the veryhigh-eccentricity domain, but the CPU cost of these tests is likely to be substantial and lies beyond the scope of this letter.</p><p>The measurement errors have a profound effect on the uniqueness of the inverse problem <ref type="figure">(Fig. 2)</ref>. For m 2 = 10 −4 m 0 , N = 100 and σ j = σ = 3 s, corresponding to the Keplerlike precision of timing measurements for a Sun-like star with a 2 Neptune-mass planet, unique determination of planetary parameters can be achieved for most stable systems with q 2 = a 2 (1 − e 2 ) &lt; 3.3a 1 , while for σ j = σ = 10 s (Corot-like precision), it is required that q 2 &lt; 2.6a 1 . These limits approximately correspond to the planetary parameters for which the amplitude of the short-period TTVs is comparable to σ. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 3</ref> shows the result of the TTVIM code for an Earth-mass planet. The region of parameter space in which unique determination can be achieved from TTVs is relatively small even with σ = 1 s. Thus, an Earth-mass planet detection and characterization of its orbit will require a rather fortuitous setup of the planetary system, in which (q 2 − a 1 )/a 1 2 (for external perturber).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results for Inclined Planetary Orbits</head><p>We applied the TTVIM code to mock planetary systems with 0 &lt; i 2 &lt; 50 • . As in §3, we assumed that m 0 = M Sun , m 1 = 10 −3 m 0 , a 1 = 0.1 AU, e 1 = 0 and used N = 100 consecutive transits. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 4</ref> shows the result for σ j = σ = 0. The (a, e) plot does not differ much from the coplanar case although it may be noted that the quality of fits slightly degraded for the large e 2 values. This is probably related to the convergence problems of the perturbation algorithm in TTVIM. A precise N-body integrator should perform better for high e 2 , although it has yet to be shown that an N-body integrator can be applied to the inclined inverse problem in practice due to the large CPU cost.</p><p>Probably the most exciting result obtained in this work is that it was possible to determine the mutual inclination of planets for most planetary systems <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 4b)</ref>. Unlike the radial velocity technique, the TTV method can therefore be used to characterize the inclination distribution of multi-planet systems. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5</ref> shows the detailed statistic of TTVIM errors in i 2 . In most cases, |i 2 − i * 2 | &lt; 2 • . The tail of larger |i 2 − i * 2 | values corresponds to the high-eccentricity cases. If the statistic is limited to q 2 = a 2 (1 − e 2 ) &gt; 0.25 AU ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 5a</ref>; dashed line), the fraction of successful cases with |i 2 − i * 2 | &lt; 2 • increases to &gt;90%. In the succesful cases, orbital angles Ω 2 , ̟ 2 and λ 2 are generally correctly determined to within a better than 5 • precision.</p><p>We also studied how the uniqueness of the inclined inverse problem is affected observational errors. The trends seen in these tests are very similar to those described in §3. Namely, the instrumental noise sets an upper limit on q 2 beyond which the determination of planetary parameters from TTVs is ambiguous. Again, we see that these limits approximately correspond to the planetary parameters for which the amplitude of the short-period TTVs is comparable to σ. The results in <ref type="bibr">N08 and Payne et al. (2009)</ref> can therefore be used to estimate whether (or not) a unique characterization of the specific inclined planetary system may be achieved from TTV observations with given σ.</p><p>We find that TTVs obtained in the coplanar case represent a good approximation of the TTVs for planetary orbits with i 2 &lt; 20 • . The planar version of the TTVIM algorithm can therefore be used in these cases to estimate the a 2 and e 2 values of the perturbing planet. This helps to narrow the range of initial guesses for the 7D fit and represents a factor of ∼20 speed up of the inversion. The full 7D algorithm needs to be used for i 2 &gt; 20 • .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>The method developed here can be used to analyze TTVs found for any of the potentially hundreds of planets expected to be discovered by <ref type="bibr">Kepler (Beatty &amp; Gaudi 2008)</ref>. Kepler should be able to detect transit timing variations of only a few seconds <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Holman &amp; Murray 2005)</ref>, which should easily exist in many systems, extrapolating from the radial velocity planets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agol et al. 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">, Fabrycky 2008</ref>).</p><p>Perhaps the most interesting result that comes out of this work is that the shape of the TTV signal is generally sensitive to the orbital inclination of the non-transiting planetary companion. Thus, the TTV method can provide means of determining mutual inclinations in systems in which at least one planet is transiting. This parameter cannot be determined by other planet-detection methods.</p><p>TTVIM algorithm can be easily extended to incorporate uncertainties in the transiting planet's parameters. This can be done by sampling dimensions that correspond to the additional parameters. For example, in N09 we extended the NM08 method to the case with e 1 = 0. This may be especially relevant to the transiting planets that will be discovered by Kepler because these planets are expected to have wider orbits, which are less susceptible to the circularizing effects of tides. The low CPU cost of the TTVIM algorithm is the key element which will make such studies possible. This work was supported by the NSF AAG program. <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>.-TTVIM code results for planetary systems with m 0 = M Sun , m 1 = 10 −3 m 0 , a 1 = 0.1 AU, e 1 = 0 and i 2 = 0. Planetary parameters for which the TTVIM code converged to the correct solution were denoted by blue ×'s. Incorrect solutions were denoted by red dots. We defined the correct solution as having |m 2 − m * 2 |/m 2 &lt; 0.5, |a 2 − a * 2 |/a 2 &lt; 0.05 and |e 2 −e * 2 | &lt; 0.05, where m 2 , a 2 and e 2 are the original planetary parameters for which the TTV signal was computed by N-body integration, and m * 2 , a * 2 and e * 2 are the values determined by the TTVIM code. In the majority of cases corresponding to correct solutions, the TTVIM code determined the original orbital parameters with a better than 2% precision and mass with a better than 20% precision. The two bold solid lines show the planet-crossing (upper) and Hill-stability limits (lower). We also show the location of the principal mean motion resonances between the planets (e.g., 2:1 at a 2 = 0.16 AU). There are two lines per resonance corresponding to the left and right separatrices of resonant motion. The V-shaped profiles are characteristic for mean motion resonances that become wider with eccentricity.    <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 4</ref>. We show the total distribution (solid line) and the one for q 2 &gt; 0.25 AU (dashed). In the later case, the erroneous determinations with |i 2 − i * 2 | &gt; 5 • are reduced because the algorithm does not need to deal with the difficult case when q 2 ∼ a 1 . Most cases correspond to |m 2 − m * 2 |/m 2 &lt; 0.2 (i.e., &lt;20% precision of mass determination) and |i 2 − i * 2 | &lt; 2 • .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-TTVIM code results for an Earth-mass planet (m 2 = 3 × 10 −6 M Sun ) and two different levels of the measurement error, σ. See caption of Fig. 1 for a description of different lines and symbols. With σ &gt; 3 s, the TTVIM code can only characterize the Earth-mass planets with very specific orbits.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-The same as Fig. 1 but with i 2 = 0. Most correct solutions (blue ×'s) have |a 2 − a * 2 |/a 2 &lt; 0.015, |e 2 − e * 2 | &lt; 0.02, |i 2 − i * 2 | &lt; 2 • and |m 2 − m * 2 |/m 2 &lt; 0.2. In (b), the dashed lines denote the libration centers of the principal mean motion resonances.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Distribution of TTVIM errors in i 2 (left) and m 2 (right) for the case shown in Fig. 4. We show the total distribution (solid line) and the one for q 2 &gt; 0.25 AU (dashed). In the later case, the erroneous determinations with |i 2 − i * 2 | &gt; 5 • are reduced because the algorithm does not need to deal with the difficult case when q 2 ∼ a 1 . Most cases correspond to |m 2 − m * 2 |/m 2 &lt; 0.2 (i.e., &lt;20% precision of mass determination) and |i 2 − i * 2 | &lt; 2 • .</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> This is because all Fourier terms can be pre-computed for a 2 , e 2 and i 2 and need only to be assembled with the specific Ω 2 , ̟ 2 and λ 2 values. The assembling procedure itself is computationally inexpensive. 3 On a single 2.7-GHz Opteron processor.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Except for very small values of e 2 for which the errors in ̟ 2 can be large.</note>

			<note place="foot">This preprint was prepared with the AAS L A T E X macros v5.2.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">941</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Clarkson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">567</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Beatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1302</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">IAU Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">173</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1684</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1024</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Heyl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gladman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1511</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">307</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1288</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Miller-Ricci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">682</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">586</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Miralda-Escudé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1019</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nesvorn´ynesvorn´y</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">688</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">NM08</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">636</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nesvorn´ynesvorn´y</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">701</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">N09</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Numerical recipes in FORTRAN. The art of scientific computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rasio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">954</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">96</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:astro-ph/0612442</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transiting Extrasolar Planets Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">158</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">TTVIM code results for a planet with m 2 = 10 −4 m 0 and different levels of the measurement error, σ. See caption of Fig. 1 for a description of different lines and symbols</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
