<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Direct detection of exoplanet host star companion γ Cep B and revised masses for both stars and the sub-stellar object</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-11-14">14 Nov 2006 July 6, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Neuhäuser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astrophysikalisches Institut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Schillergässchen 2-3</addrLine>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Mugrauer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astrophysikalisches Institut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Schillergässchen 2-3</addrLine>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Misato</forename><surname>Fukagawa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Spitzer Science Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91125</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Particle and Astrophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nagoya University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Furo-cho, Chikusa-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>464-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Nagoya</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guillermo</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>60 Garden Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>02138</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astrophysikalisches Institut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Schillergässchen 2-3</addrLine>
									<postCode>07745</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Direct detection of exoplanet host star companion γ Cep B and revised masses for both stars and the sub-stellar object</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-11-14">14 Nov 2006 July 6, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received 17 Oct 2006; accepted 27 Oct 2006</note>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. 6581 c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>instrumentation: adapive optics -binaries: spectroscopic -binaries: visual -planetary systems -star: individual: γ Cep</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. The star γ Cep is known as a single-lined spectroscopic triple system at a distance of 13.8 pc, composed of a K1 III-IV primary star with V = 3.2 mag, a stellar-mass companion in a 66-67 year orbit (Torres 2006), and a substellar companion with M p sin i = 1.7 M Jup that is most likely a planet (Hatzes et al. 2003). Aims. We aim to obtain a first direct detection of the stellar companion, to determine its current orbital position (for comparison with the spectroscopic and astrometric data), its infrared magnitude and, hence, mass. Methods. We use the Adaptive Optics camera CIAO at the Japanese 8m telescope Subaru on Mauna Kea, Hawaii, with the semi-transparent coronograph to block most of the light from the bright primary γ Cep A, and to detect at the same time the faint companion B. In addition, we also used the IR camera Ω Cass at the Calar Alto 3.5m telescope, Spain, to image γ Cep A and B by adding up many very short integrations (without AO). Results. γ Cep B is clearly detected on our CIAO and Ω Cass images. We use a photometric standard star to determine the magnitude of B after PSF subtraction in the Subaru image, and the magnitude difference between A and B in the Calar Alto images, and find an average value of K = 7.3 ± 0.2 mag. The separations and position angles between A and B are measured on 15 July 2006 and 11 and 12 Sept 2006, B is slightly south of west of A. Conclusions. By combining the radial velocity, astrometric, and imaging data, we have refined the binary orbit and determined the dynamical masses of the two stars in the γ Cep system, namely 1.40 ± 0.12 M ⊙ for the primary and 0.409 ± 0.018 M ⊙ for the secondary (consistent with being a M4 dwarf). We also determine the minimum mass of the sub-stellar companion to be M p sin i = 1.60 ± 0.13 M Jup .</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction: γ Cep</head><p>The bright star γ Cep (also HD 222404 or HIP 116727) located near the north celestial pole (α = 23 h 39 m 20.8 s and δ = +77 • 37 ′ 56.2 ′′ for J2000.0) is known as a single-lined spectroscopic triple: The primary star has spectral type K1 III-IV, is visible to the naked eye (V = 3.2 mag) and is located at a distance of 13.8 pc. A low-mass stellar companion with an orbital period of several decades was discovered spectroscopically by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Campbell et al. (1988)</ref>, but until now it has never been imaged directly (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hatzes et al. 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">, Mugrauer et al. 2006</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Campbell et al. (1988)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Walker et al. (1992)</ref> discussed the evidence for additional radial velocity variations indicative of a very low-mass, possibly planetary companion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hatzes et al. (2003)</ref> confirmed that there is indeed a third object in the system with a minimum mass of M p sin i = 1.7 M Jup , i.e., probably</p><p>Send offprint requests to: Ralph Neuhäuser, e-mail: rne@astro.uni-jena.de a planet, with a semi-major axis of 2 AU and a 900-day eccentric orbit (e = 0.12).</p><p>Several investigators have attempted to constrain the orbit as well as the mass of γ Cep B (the stellar companion) on the basis of available spectroscopic data. The estimated period of the binary from these studies has ranged from about 30 to 66 yr ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Walker et al. 1992</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, Griffin et al. 2002</ref>. Most recently, Torres (2006) put together not only the spectroscopic data (dating back to 1902), but also Hipparcos and groundbased astrometric data (dating back to 1898) and obtained new results for the primary star (γ Cep Aa), the secondary (B), and the sub-stellar companion (Ab): B orbits A in an eccentric orbit (e = 0.4085 ± 0.0065) with 66.8 ± 1.4 year period and a semi-major axis of 19.02 ± 0.64 AU; the primary has a mass of 1.18 ± 0.11 M ⊙ , temperature of 4800 ± 100 K, and an age of 6.6 Gyrs; the unseen stellar companion should have a mass of 0.362 ± 0.022 M ⊙ , i.e. spectral type about M4; the minimum mass of the lowest-mass component in the system is then M p · sin i = 1.43 ± 0.13 M Jup ; the astrometric data yield an upper mass limit of 17 M Jup (at the 3 σ confidence level), i.e. certainly sub-stellar, probably planetary; all values above are from <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref>. The predictions for γ Cep B can be tested by direct imaging.</p><p>In this paper, we present the first direct imaging detections of γ Cep B (sect. 2), compare the parameters observed with the predictions (sect. 3), and newly determine the masses of γ Cep Aa, Ab, and B (sect. 4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Imaging observations</head><p>We observed γ Cep first on 15 July 2006 with the Coronagraphic Imager for Adaptive Optics (CIAO) on the Japanese 8m telescope Subaru on Mauna Kea, Hawaii, in the K-band. The night was photometric with ∼ 0.7 arc sec natural seeing. We took ten images (always 30 times 0.1 sec each, i.e. 30 sec total integration time) through a semi-transparent coronographic mask (0.6 arc sec diameter, a chrome spot on a sapphire substrate) in order to block most of the light of γ Cep A, but still to be able to detect B.</p><p>The data were reduced in the normal way: Dark subtraction, flat-field devision, and adding up the individual images. The resulting image is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>.</p><p>The semi-transparent coronograph has a transmission of between about 1% and 6%, thus still allowing the primary star to shine through. We subtracted the point spread function (PSF) of remaining light of γ Cep A, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> for the result. γ Cep B is clearly detected in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 and 2</ref>.</p><p>Because the throughput of the coronograph is not well known and because the star A may still be in the non-linear regime, we cannot derive the magnitude of B with respect to A from the image itself. A photometric standard star is needed. We therefore observed the standard star FS 150 (9.94 ± 0.01 mag, UKIRT web page) in the same night (8 × 3 sec) to obtain the magnitude of γ Cep B by aperture photometry (after PSF subtraction). The result for B is K = 7.32 ± 0.11 mag. Hence, the magnitude difference between γ Cep A and B is 6.28 ± 0.24 mag (A has K s = 1.04 ± 0.21 mag, 2MASS Catalog, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Skrutskie et al. 2006</ref>).</p><p>By Gaussian centering, we can determine the position of B relative to A, i.e. to measure the separation and position angle. For a companion (or candidate) to a very bright primary, it is very useful to observe with a semi-transparent coronograph, so that the primary star is still visible together with the companion (for separation measurement). For the astrometric analysis, we use the most recent pixel scale for CIAO, namely 21.3 ± 0.1 mas/pixel ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mayama et al. 2006</ref>) and the orientation of the detector being 0.81 ± 0.25 deg from north as measured by us from images of three sources in the V1686 Cyg region taken in the same night.</p><p>The resulting separation and position angle are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>.</p><p>After our detection with Subaru we observed γ Cep with the Ω Cass IR imager on the Calar Alto 3.5m telescope in Spain. Due to the fact that our instrument of choice, the AO system ALFA, was not functioning at the time, we observed γ Cep in a backup programme by taking several thousand short (0.1 sec) integration images (speckle), which we then combined by shift+add, after background correction and flatfielding. We detected γ Cep B on both 11 Sept (7391 images) and on 12 Sept 2006 (18140) using the K ′ (K-prime) filter together with Br γ. In addition to measuring the separation between B and A from  the resulting images in each night, we determined also the magnitude difference relative to the primary, which was neither saturated nor in the non-linear regime of the detector. See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> for the final images of the two nights and <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> for the results of our measurements. We used the Hipparcos multiples HIP 109474, HIP 91115, HIP 92961, HIP 104536, observed in the same two nights, for astrometric calibration of the pixel scale (38.681±0.059 mas/pixel) and the detector position angle (21.362 ± 0.037 • ).</p><p>Our measurements may indicate a small change in the position angle of 0.63 ± 0.36 deg between July and September 2006, and a more significant increase in separation of 19 ± 6 mas, consistent with the predictions for orbital motion, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.  4</ref>.</p><p>For the secondary star γ Cep B, imaged for the first time here, we obtain a magnitude of K = 7.3 ± 0.2 mag, the average of the Subaru and the two Calar Alto data points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Comparison with predictions</head><p>Our new measurements of the relative position of γ Cep B with respect to the primary star allow us to test the predictions from the orbital solution for the binary produced recently by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref>. That study combined all available measurements of the radial velocity of the primary from a variety of sources (including the high-precision studies that uncovered the sub-stellar companion, along with classical measurements from the literature and from new observations) and used also the intermediate astrometry from the Hipparcos mission ('abscissa residuals') as well as ground-based astrometry reaching back more than a century. This enabled the scale and orientation of the binary orbit to be established for the first time, in a combined solution that included also the perturbing effects of the sub-stellar companion.</p><p>A comparison of our measurements with the published orbit <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Torres 2006</ref>) indicates systematic (observed minus computed) O − C residuals of ∼ 8 • in position angle and 50-60 mas in separation (positive in both cases). These are many times larger than the measurement errors, although the predicted positions themselves have uncertainties of about 3.1 degrees in position angle and 34 mas in separation for the dates of our observations. These reflect the uncertainty in the orbital elements as well as the estimated error of the adopted primary mass, which was external to the orbital solution of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref> and was established from stellar evolution considerations. Therefore, the residuals correspond to 1.5-2.5σ, which, while not overly large, may nevertheless indicate the need for some adjustment in the orbit given that they are systematic in nature. The new O − C values given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> (this paper) are computed for the new orbit <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Table 2)</ref> after taking into account our three imaging observations. They are much smaller than in Torres (2006), i.e. a clear improvement as expected, which was the motivation for the imaging observations. The relative brightness of the secondary was predicted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref> to be ∆K ∼ 6.4 mag, which is not far from the values we measure (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Improved masses</head><p>The assumption of a value for the primary mass in the Torres (2006) solution was necessary because of the lack of direct measurements of the relative position between γ Cep A and B, since the secondary had never been imaged. With our present results this assumption can now be dropped, and this allows for a direct measurement of the dynamical masses of both stars with no need for external constraints. In order to update the orbital solution and solve for the masses we have added to the data considered by Torres (2006) our 3 measurements of the separation and position angle of γ Cep with their corresponding uncertainties. We have modified the procedures to include the relative semimajor axis of the binary, a ′′ AB , as an adjustable parameter in addition to the other variables considered in the original solution. The results are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, which includes the most relevant elements of the inner and outer or- bits and several derived quantities. The notation follows that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref>. Most of the orbital elements change very little (well within the errors). The most significant change is in the position angle of the ascending node (Ω AB ), which increases by about 5 • . This accounts for a large fraction of the residuals in P.A. noted above. The other significant change is in the scale of the orbit, which increases by about 6%. This in turn accounts for the residuals in the angular separation. The residuals from this new orbit are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, and are now all within 1σ, indicating a satisfactory fit.</p><p>The resulting masses of the two stars are M Aa = 1.40 ± 0.12 M ⊙ and M B = 0.409 ± 0.018 M ⊙ . Both the primary and secondary are somewhat more massive than assumed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref>. Consequently the minimum mass of the substellar companion also increases to M p sin i = 1.60 ±0.13 M Jup , a value intermediate between those proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Torres (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Hatzes et al. (2003)</ref>, and the upper mass limit from Torres (2006) changes from 17 M Jup to 19 M Jup . The brightness of the stellar companion B is fully consistent with a single M4-type dwarf, neither multiple itself nor a white dwarf.</p><p>Given the new parameters in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, the critical semimajor axis for long-term stability of planets according to the <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Holman &amp; Wiegert (1999</ref>) criterion is at only 3.85 ± 0.38 AU. The size of a planet-forming circumstellar disk in the close binary is not larger than 3.4 AU according to the <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pichardo et al. (2005)</ref> criteria. The planet candidate γ Cep Ab orbits around Aa between 1.8 and 2.3 AU, which is inside the stable region, so that it is not neccessary to invoke migration after its formation.</p><p>Continued measurements of the relative position between γ Cep A and B over the coming years, which we intend to carry out, should further improve the stellar mass determinations and help establish also the true mass of the sub-stellar companion. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Subaru CIAO K-band image of γ Cep A and B, where A is below the semi-transparent coronograph. The total integration time was 30 sec, obtained on 15 July 2006.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Subaru CIAO K-band image of γ Cep A and B, now after subtraction of the PSF of γ Cep A. The stellar companion γ Cep B is now clearly detected 0.87 arc sec west of A (slightly south of west).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Orbit and orbital motion of γ Cep B around A as already observed by our imaging within two month. The inlay shows our three imaging data points of B in orbit around A.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Ω Cass IR speckle images of γ Cep A and B, obtained on 11 Sept 2006 (left) and 12 Sept 2006 (right) with the Calar Alto 3.5m telescope with ∼ 12 to 30 min total integration time (through K ′ and Br γ filters).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Astrometry and photometry for γ Cep A and B</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Obs date 
Telescope 
PA 
O-C 
separation 
O-C 
∆K 
HJD 
instrument 
[ • ] 
[ • ] 
[arc sec] 
[mas] 
[mag] 
2453932.046 Subaru 8.3m CIAO 256.91 ± 0.27 −0.20 0.870 ± 0.005 −0.005 6.28 ± 0.24 
2453989.520 
CA 3.5m Ω Cass 
256.16 ± 0.35 +0.09 0.891 ± 0.006 +0.005 6.28 ± 0.13 
2453990.514 
CA 3.5m Ω Cass 
256.39 ± 0.34 +0.33 0.887 ± 0.005 +0.001 6.12 ± 0.11 
Remark: Observed minus computed (O-C) residuals are explained in sect. 3. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Global orbital solution for γ Cep Parameter and value</figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot">Ralph Neuhäuser et al.: Direct detection of γ Cep B</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">902</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hatzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Paulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">599</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1383</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Carquillat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ginestet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wiegert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">621</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mugrauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Neuhäuser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Broeg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">321</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pichardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sparke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aguilar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">521</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Skrutskie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cutri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stiening</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>astro-ph/0609638</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bohlender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
