<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:04+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Optical Images of an Exosolar Planet 25 Light Years from Earth *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2008-11-19">19 Nov 2008</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astronomy Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astronomy Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Astronomy Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth &amp; Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Geophysics &amp; Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory Livermore</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94551</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Clampin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Exoplanets &amp; Stellar Astrophysics Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Goddard Space Flight Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20771, 91109</postCode>
									<settlement>Greenbelt, Caltech, Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>MD, CA</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kite</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth &amp; Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karl</forename><surname>Stapelfeldt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Herzberg Institute for Astrophysics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V9E2E7</postCode>
									<settlement>Victoria</settlement>
									<region>BC</region>
									<country key="CA">CANADA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Krist</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Optical Images of an Exosolar Planet 25 Light Years from Earth *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2008-11-19">19 Nov 2008</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>5 MS 183-900, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, * Accepted for publication in Science</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fomalhaut is a bright star 7.7 parsecs (25 light years) from Earth that harbors a belt of cold dust with a structure consistent with gravitational sculpting by an orbiting planet. Here, we present optical observations of an exoplanet candidate , Fomalhaut b. In the plane of the belt, Fomalhaut b lies approximately 119 astronomical units (AU) from the star and 18 AU from the dust belt, matching predictions. We detect counterclockwise orbital motion using Hubble Space Telescope observations separated by 1.73 years. Dynamical models of the interaction between the planet and the belt indicate that the planet&apos;s mass is at 1</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detection of Fomalhaut b</head><p>Coronagraphic observations with the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) in 2004 produced the first optical image of Fomalhaut's dust belt, and detected several faint sources near Fomalhaut (6). Fomalhaut's proper motion across the sky is 0.425 arcsecond per year in the southeast direction, which means that objects that are in the background will appear to move northwest relative to the star. To find common proper motion candidate sources, we observed Fomalhaut using the Keck II 10-m telescope in <ref type="bibr">with HST in 2006 (SOM)</ref>. In May, 2008, a comprehensive data analysis revealed that Fomalhaut b is physically associated with the star and displays orbital motion. Follow-up observations were then conducted at Gemini Observatory at 3.8 µm (SOM).</p><p>Fomalhaut b was confirmed as a real astrophysical object in six independent HST observations at two optical wavelengths (0.6 µm and 0.8 µm; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 1</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref>). It is co-moving with Fomalhaut, except for a 0.184 ± 0.022 arcsecond (1.41 ± 0.17 AU) offset between <ref type="bibr">2004</ref> and 2006 (∆T = 1.73 yr), corresponding to 0.82 ± 0.10 AU yr −1 projected motion relative to Fomalhaut (SOM). If Fomalhaut b has an orbit that is coplanar and nested within the dust belt, then its semimajor axis is a ≃ 115 AU, close to that predicted by Quillen <ref type="bibr">(7)</ref>. An object with a = 115 AU in Keplerian motion around a star with mass 2.0 M ⊙ has an orbital period of 872 years, and a circular speed of 3.9 km s −1 . The six Keplerian orbital elements are unconstrained by measurements at only two epochs; however, by comparing the deprojected space velocity (5.5 +1.1 −0.7 km s −1 ) with the circular speed we find a lower limit on the eccentricity of 0.13 (95% confidence) by assuming that Fomalhaut b is at periastron. Thus, our observations are consistent with bound Keplerian motion, although the exact range of allowable eccentricity depends sensitively on poorly known uncertainties in orbital inclination, apsidal orientation, and host stellar mass.</p><p>Fomalhaut b is located near the faint half of the belt seen in stellar light backscattered by dust grains. Therefore it lies behind the sky plane (the Earth-Fomalhaut-Fomalhaut b angle is 126 o ), at approximately 51 o past conjunction as it orbits counter-clockwise. Though faint, Fomalhaut b is still one hundred times brighter than reflected light from a Jupiter-like planet at that radius from Fomalhaut (SOM).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dynamical Models of Planet-Belt Interaction</head><p>We constrain the mass of Fomalhaut b by modeling its gravitational influence on the dust belt, reproducing properties of the belt inferred from the HST scattered light images. Our model assumes that Fomalhaut b is solely responsible for the observed belt morphology. This assumption implies that the orbits of the belt and of Fomalhaut b are apsidally aligned. The deprojected space velocity of Fom b is nominally inconsistent with this expectation. Apsidal misalignment may imply the existence of additional perturbers; then the mass estimates derived from our single planet models are upper limits.</p><p>Our modeling procedure takes four steps. First, for a given mass and orbit of Fomalhaut b, we create a population of several thousand parent bodies stable to gravitational perturbations from the planet. These parent bodies, modeled as test particles, do not undergo close encounters with Fomalhaut b over 100 Myr. Initial parent body orbits have semimajor axes between 120 and 140 AU, and eccentricities and longitudes of periastron that are purely secularly forced by the planet (9). Initial inclinations of parent bodies are randomly and uniformly distributed within 0.025 radian of Fomalhaut b's orbital plane, and remaining orbital angles are drawn at random. After 100 My, parent body orbits differ somewhat from these initial conditions; most survivors have semimajor axes &gt; 130 AU. The forced orbits thus constructed are nested ellipses of eccentricity ≈ 0.11 that approximate the observed belt morphology. Forced orbits are expected to result from interparticle collisions, which dissipate random motions and compel planetesimals to conform towards closed, non-intersecting paths (10).</p><p>This elliptical annulus of parent bodies is termed a "birth ring" (11); erosive collisions among parent bodies give birth to smaller sized but more numerous dust grains. The observed scattered stellar light arises predominantly not from parent bodies but rather from their dust progeny. Thus the second step of our procedure is to track dust trajectories. We take each parent to release a dust grain with the same instantaneous position and velocity as its parent's. The trajectory of a grain of given β (force of radiation pressure relative to that of stellar gravity; β scales inversely as grain radius) is then integrated forward under the effects of radiation pressure and Poynting-Robertson drag. We carry out integrations for β ∈ (0, 0.00625, 0.0125, . . . , 0.4).</p><p>For β approaching the radiation blow-out value of ∼1/2, grains execute highly elongated orbits whose periastra are rooted within the birth ring. Integrations last 0.1 Myr, corresponding to the collisional lifetime of grains in Fomalhaut's belt, as estimated from the inferred optical depth of the belt.</p><p>Third, we superpose the various β-integrations to construct maps of optical depth normal to the belt plane. To reduce the shot noise associated with a finite number of grains, we smear each grain along its orbit: each grain is replaced by an elliptical wire whose linear density along any segment is proportional to the time a particle in Keplerian motion spends traversing that segment. We compute the optical depth presented by the collection of wires, weighting each β-integration according to a Dohnanyi (12) grain size distribution. This distribution, which reflects a quasi-steady collisional cascade in which parent bodies grind down to grains so small they are expelled by radiation pressure, is assumed to hold in the birth ring, where dust densities are greatest and collision rates highest.</p><p>The final step is to compare the optical depth profile of our dynamical model with that of a scattered light model adjusted to fit the 2004 HST image of Fomalhaut's belt (6). We focus on the one belt property that seems most diagnostic of planet mass and orbit: the belt's inner edge, having a semimajor axis of a inner = 133 AU according to the scattered light model. This edge marks the outer boundary of the planet's chaotic zone (7). The chaotic zone is a swath of space enclosing the planet's orbit which is purged of material because of dynamical instabilities caused by overlapping first-order mean-motion resonances <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(13)</ref>. For a given planet mass M, we adjust the planet's semimajor axis a until the dynamical model's optical depth attains half its maximum value at a inner <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig. 2, bottom panel)</ref>. Applying this procedure, we find that</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">a inner − a = 2.0(M/M * ) 2/7 a (1)</formula><p>where M * is the central stellar mass.</p><p>Two trends that emerge from our modeling imply that the mass of the planet should be low.</p><p>First, as M increases, the planet more readily perturbs dust grains onto eccentric orbits, and the resultant optical depth profile becomes too broad at distances &gt; ∼ 140 AU <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig. 2</ref>, bottom panel). Second, to not disrupt the belt, larger mass planets must have smaller orbits, violating our estimate for the current stellocentric distance of Fomalhaut b <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig. 2</ref>, top two panels). Together, these considerations imply that M &lt; 3M J . This upper limit supersedes those derived previously (7), as the quantitative details of our model are more realistic [see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(14)</ref>]: the belt as a whole is modeled, not just its inner edge; parent bodies are handled separately from dust grains, and only the latter are used to compare with observations; stellar radiation pressure is accounted for; parent bodies are screened for dynamical stability over the system age; and grain-grain collisions are recognized as destructive, so that dust particle integrations are halted after a collision time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model Planet Atmospheres</head><p>Comparison between our photometric data and model planet atmosphere spectra indicate that Fomalhaut b may be a cooling Jovian-mass exoplanet with age 100-300 Myr <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 3)</ref>. A planet atmosphere model with effective temperature T eff = 400 K and radius 1.2 R J , for which the bolometric luminosity is 3.4 × 10 −7 L ⊙ (15-16), reproduces the observed 0.8 µm flux.</p><p>This model implies that the luminosity of Fomalhaut b is lower than any other object observed outside the solar system, and thus that it is not a young brown dwarf or a more massive object.</p><p>Theoretical cooling tracks of objects with T eff = 400 K and ages &gt;100 Myr are insensitive to uncertain initial conditions (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">figure 1</ref> of 15). The luminosity on these tracks is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">L ∼ 2 × 10 −7 (M/2M J ) 1.87 (t/200Myr) −1.21 L ⊙ ,</formula><p>implying that the mass of Fomalhaut b is 1.7-3.5 M J . The error in the mass is dominated by the age uncertainty.</p><p>Relative to the models of planet atmospheres, the flux of Fomalhaut b is too faint by at least a factor of a few at 1.6 µm, and the upper limit set by observations at 3.8 µm is only marginally consistent with the models. However, the various models disagree with each other by similar factors at 1.6 µm, partly because of theoretical uncertainties associated with the strengths of the CH 4 vibrational bands. Moreover, our hypothesized effective temperature is near the condensation temperature of water clouds, and such clouds are a large source of uncertainty in planet atmosphere models. Nevertheless, our observations at 1.6 µm and 3.8 µm exclude a warmer (more massive) planet.</p><p>Choosing a 400 K, 46 m s −2 , 5× solar abundance model from <ref type="formula">(15)</ref> as a baseline, we can investigate the effects of gravity and composition using theoretical exoplanet model spectra <ref type="bibr">(15- 16)</ref>. The elevated abundance set is chosen to be representative of solar system gas giants. The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other Sources of Optical Emission</head><p>From 0.6 to 0.8 µm, Fomalhaut b is bluer than the models predict ( As remarkably distant as Fomalhaut b is from its star, the planet might have formed in situ.</p><p>The dust belt of Fomalhaut contains three Earth masses of solids in its largest collisional parent bodies. Adding enough gas to bring this material to cosmic composition would imply a minimum primordial disk mass of 1 M J , comparable to the upper mass limit of Fomalhaut b.</p><p>Alternatively, the planet might have migrated outward by interacting with its parent disk (20), or by gravitationally scattering off another planet in the system and having its eccentricity mildly damped by dynamical friction with surrounding disk material (21 are then rotated to a common orientation and combined. Technique 2 is known in the literature as roll deconvolution or angular difference imaging (ADI; S2-S4). <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table S1</ref> catalogs our observations. Fomalhaut b is detected independently in each row with an F606W and F814W observations. For each of these rows, Fomalhaut b is detected using both PSF subtraction techniques outlined above. False-positives are defined as apparent point sources that cannot be consistently confirmed among these data sets. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Astrometry</head><p>The astrometric reference frame is established relative to the star Fomalhaut as there are The fact that Fomalhaut b is orbiting Fomalhaut is robust because the apparent orbital motion of 7.3 pixels between epochs is significantly greater than these uncertainties, as well as the PSF full-width at half-maximum of ∼2.7 pixels. Fomalhaut b cannot be a background objects as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. S1</ref>. The empirical RMS accuracy in the position angle achieved in ACS data is 0.003 degrees (S5), which corresponds to an insignificant uncertainty of 0.03 pixel at the radial position of Fomalhaut b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Photometry</head><p>In the cases where Fomalhaut b was detected (HST), we report photometry corrected to an infinite aperture using DAOPHOT and an empirical curve of growth derived from the data <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table   S2)</ref>  to a common signal level using background star observations prior to combination. For the multi-night combination of H-band data, we use the July 17 observations for photometric calibration because of that night's exceptional conditions. The peak brightness of Fomalhaut was measured through the partially transmissive occulting spot in short exposure images. These measurements were used to determine an on-axis sensitivity calibration using the 2MASS photometry of Fomalhaut and the previously measured occulting spot transmission. We derived a sensitivity curve by measuring the standard deviation of fluxes in apertures of 3 pixel diameter and measured the value at the predicted angular separation of Fomalhaut b. Finally, we noted that the Strehl ratio at the location of Fomalhaut b is degraded due to anisoplanatism. We estimated a decrease in sensitivity of 0.75 mag, which corresponds to an isoplanatic angle of 13 ′′ at</p><p>1.6 µm.</p><p>Calibration of the Gemini L ′ -band data was performed using observations of a standard star, HR 9016A, which were obtained in the middle of the observing sequence each night. The unsaturated exposures of the standard were used to derive a photometric zero point and aperture correction for each night. The data from the different nights were scaled to the same throughput in apertures of 0.3 ′′ diameter prior to combination. The upper limit to Fomalhaut b was obtained by measuring the standard deviation of flux in 0.3 ′′ apertures in an arc along ±45 degrees of the predicted position of Fomalhaut b. We adopt a factor of 2 in decreased sensitivity due to the estimated Strehl degradation from errors in centroiding the saturated images of Fomalhaut.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bolometric luminosity</head><p>In this section and following, we consider various possibilities for the origin of the detected optical flux. Here, we assume that the F814W flux is pure thermal emission from the planet, which consistent with the model atmosphere from (S7) where T ef f = 400 K; g = 46 m s −2 ;</p><p>and 5× solar metallicity. With this effective temperature, and with a planet radius 1.2 R J , the bolometric flux at Earth is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">F = r p d p 2 σ SB T 4 ef f = 1.86 × 10 −13 erg s −1 cm −2<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where r p is the the radius of Fomalhaut b, d p is the heliocentric distance, and σ SB is the Stefan- </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">F ν dν = 1.80 × 10 −13 erg s −1 cm −2<label>(3)</label></formula><p>The smaller value is expected because the model is tabulated over a finite frequency range and some power is missing in the numerical integration. The corresponding luminosity is ∼ 3×10 −7</p><p>L ⊙ , which indicates that Fomalhaut b is the faintest known object outside of the solar system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hα Emission</head><p>Photometry efficiency). If we assume that the efficiency is ∼1%, then the total gas accretion is 0.2 M J .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dust Cloud Model</head><p>We explore the possibility that Fomalhaut b represents reflected light from an unresolved dust cloud that is not gravitationally bound and therefore not associated with a planet. In this scenario the cloud arises from the stochastic, catastrophic collision of two parent bodies analogous to Kuiper Belt Objects or short-period comets in the solar system. The event is improbable at the location of Fomalhaut b compared to regions closer to the star where the collision timescales are significantly shorter, or farther from the star where the number density of parent bodies is enhanced in order to replenish the visible belt with fresh dust.</p><p>Since Fomalhaut b appears as a point source in the HST data, the maximum size of the dust cloud corresponds to the full-width at half-maximum of the PSF, which is 69±6 mas or 0.53 ±0.05 AU (compared against the background star shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. S1</ref>, which has FWHM = 68 ± 4 mas). A dust cloud could originate from a catastrophic collision between two planetesimals, but the event must be recent because even in the absence of stellar radiation pressure and Poynting-Robertson drag, the different orbital period of a dust grain located at the inner boundary of the cloud (i.e. closest to Fomalhaut) versus the outer boundary of the cloud would shear the cloud into an arc, ultimately becoming a ring of material orbiting Fomalhaut.</p><p>The dust cloud will contain a size distribution of grains, though the scattered light images are predominantly sensitive to grain sizes with x = 2πa/λ ∼ 1, where a is the grain radius. In our model of a dust cloud we assume a size distribution with a min &lt; a &lt; a max following a differential size distribution dn/da = n o (a/a o ) −3.5 . We note that due to radiation pressure from Fomalhaut, grains smaller than 3−8 µm (depending on porosity) are ejected from the system on free-fall timescales (S9). We therefore use Mie theory to calculate the apparent magnitude and scattered light color of a dust cloud with a min = 0.01 µm and a max = 1000 µm (m 0.01 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table S3</ref>) and a min = 8 µm and a max = 1000 µm (m 8 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table S3</ref>). These values represent two extremes of a fresh dust cloud with small grains still present within the cloud, and a later epoch where only grains larger than the radiation pressure blowout size of ∼8 µm have survived. We test grains composed of water ice (density = 1.0 g cm −3 ; m ice in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table S3</ref>) and refractory carbonaceous material (density = 2.2 g cm −3 ; S10; m LG in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table S3</ref>). The results for these two calculations are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table S3</ref>. The total grain mass (and hence the total scattering surface area) is adjusted such that the integrated light in F814W from the model matches the observations. In the case of m 8 ice , the total mass is 1.24×10 21 g, which corresponds to the disruption of a 67 km water ice body. However, the total grain mass depends strongly on the value selected for a max . Perhaps a more useful calculation is the minimum grain mass assuming the grain size distribution is nearly monodisperse and peaks where the scattering efficiency is highest. For these optical observations, the scattering efficiency is highest for grains 0.1 − 0.2 µm in size, giving a minimum dust mass in the cloud M d = 4.1 × 10 18 (ρ g /1.0 g cm −3 ) g. Therefore, for water ice, the minimum grain mass is 4.1 × 10 18 g, corresponding to the disruption of a 10 km radius object.  In <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S4</ref> we give the apparent optical colors. The dust cloud model explains the Fomalhaut b observations with respect to the non-detections in H and L ′ . Otherwise, the dust cloud model is inconsistent with the Fomalhaut b photometry because: (1) A dust cloud should have been detected in the F435W data (except in the case of m 8</p><p>LG in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S4</ref>), and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(2)</ref> The color of a dust cloud is significantly bluer than the observed red color of Fomalhaut b <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">(Table S3)</ref> years. This scenario demands that we have observed the cloud at a fortuitous time right after it has been produced, but before all of the small grains are blown out.</p><p>Taking all four arguments together -the low probability of the stochastic collision at the position of Fomalhaut b, the fortuitous timing to explain variability, the non detection in the F435W filter, and the somewhat discrepant observed optical colors compared to a model -the dust cloud hypothesis appears inadequate to explain the observed properties of Fomalhaut b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reflected light from a planet surrounded by an extended dust disk</head><p>We consider the hypothesis that the Fomalhaut b observations are explained by reflected light from a Jovian planet surrounded by a large ring system. First, we consider reflected light from the planet alone. The flux received at Earth from the star (Fomalhaut) is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">f ⋆ = L ⋆ 4π D 2 = 6.34 × 10 27 4π (2.379 × 10 17 ) 2 = 8.914 × 10 −9 Wm −2 (4)</formula><p>where L ⋆ is the stellar luminosity in watts (W; S12), and D is the heliocentric distance (7.688 pc = 2.379 × 10 17 m). The stellar flux received by a planet at d=115 AU radius from Fomalhaut is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">f o = L ⋆ 4π d 2 = 6.34 × 10 27 4π (115 × 1.5 × 10 11 ) 2 = 1.70 Wm −2 (5)</formula><p>The flux received at earth:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">f p = f o 4π D 2 = σ p Q s × 1.70 Wm −2 4π (2.379 × 10 17 ) 2 = σ p Q s × 2.390 × 10 −36 Wm −2 (6)</formula><p>where σ p [m 2 ] is the projected geometric surface area of the planet and Q s is the scattering efficiency, such as the product of the geometric albedo and the scattering phase function at the observed phase. It is useful to consider these values as a relative contrast in apparent magnitude:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">∆m = m p −m ⋆ = −2.5 log f p f ⋆ = −2.5 log σ p Q s × 2.39 × 10 −36 8.91 × 10 −9 = −2.5 log(σ p Q s )+69 (7)</formula><p>The V band (F606W) apparent magnitude of Fomalhaut is m V = 1.2 mag, giving m p = −2.5 log(σ p Q s ) + 70.2. If we ignore the reduction in brightness due to viewing phase, the geometric cross section of a 1.2 R J planet is σ p = π × (1.2 × 7.15 × 10 7 m) 2 = 2.31 × 10 16 m 2 . For Q s = 0.5, the apparent magnitude of this planet m p = 30.0 mag. Thus, the observed apparent magnitude of Fomalhaut b at optical wavelengths <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table S2)</ref>  If Fomalhaut b also harbored a ring system extending to its Roche radius, then σ p would be replaced by the ring cross section σ pr ∼ σ p × 2 2 × cos(66 o ) ∼ 1.6σ p . Assuming again Q s = 0.5, the apparent magnitude of the system would be m pr = 29.5 mag, or about 4.5 mag too faint compared to what is actually observed.</p><p>To make up for this shortcoming, the scattering surface area of the planet+ring system would have to increase by yet another factor of ∼60. This would correspond to about ∼16 planetary radii. If the effective albedo of the ring particles is closer to 0.1-and in fact outer solar system albedoes are typically this low-then the rings must extend to ∼35 planetary radii. An optically thick ring system that is 16-35 planetary radii large is better described as a protosatellite, The existence of a planet permits a system of dust to be spatially confined rather than dispersed due to shearing or radiation pressure.  . Gaps open at the planet's resonances, akin to the solar system's Kirkwood gaps. Black circles and bars mark the range of stellocentric distances spanned by the model orbits for Fomalhaut b. The apocentric distance for 10 M J is inconsistent with the observed stellocentric distance of Fomalhaut b (green line). The 1 M J model is consistent. Bottom panel: Vertical optical depth profiles of dust generated from parent bodies. The planet orbit is tuned so that the optical depth is at half maximum at 133 AU, the location of the inner edge of the scattered light model from (6) (red curve), which itself is an idealized and non-unique fit to the HST data. While the dynamical and scattered light models do not agree perfectly, lower planet masses are still inferred because they do not produce broad tails of emission at a &gt; ∼ 140 AU. At a &gt; ∼ 160 AU, the HST data are too uncertain to constrain any model. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>: Photometry on Fomalhaut b shows the F435W 3-σ upper limit (yellow square), two F606W measurements (blue square=2006, blue circle=2004), the F814W photometry (green square), 3-σ upper limits for Keck observations in the CH 4 passband (purple solid star) and the H band (red solid star), and a 3-σ upper limits for Gemini observations at L ′ (light blue star). This is a log-log plot. If we first assume that the F606W variability is due to Hα emission and the F814W detection is due to planet thermal emission, we then proceed to fit a planet atmosphere model from (15) to the F814W flux. The heavy solid line represents that planet atmosphere model smoothed to R=1200 with planet radius 1.2 R J , gravity 46 m s −2 , and T=400K (roughly 1-3 M J at 200 Myr). The horizontal colored lines mark the equivalent broad-band flux found by integrating the model spectrum over the instrumental passband. Other models from (16) give a similar spectrum (light solid line), though a factor of 3 -4 brighter in CH 4 and H band. The model predicts that the planet candidate should have been detected with Keck in the H band, though this prediction is only a factor of a few above our limit. The discrepancy could arise from uncertainties in the model atmosphere (which has never been tested against observation), or from the possibility that the F606W and F814W detections include stellar light reflected from a circumplanetary dust disk or ring system. The solid blue line intersecting the optical data represents light reflected from a circumplanetary disk with radius 20 R J , a constant albedo of 0.4, and with stellar properties adopted from (22). </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>temperature and gravity of this model are a good match to a 200 Myr, 2.5 M J exoplanet. As previously noted, this model accounts for the 0.8 µm flux, but over predicts the 1.6 µm band flux by a factor of three. Cooler models (350 K) cannot simultaneously reproduce the 0.8 µm flux without violating the long wavelength flux limits, while for hotter models (500 K) the 1.6 µm upper limit becomes particularly problematic. If there is a significant thermal photospheric contribution to the 0.8 µm flux, then 400 K is a rough upper limit to the temperature of the object. The 400 K, solar abundance model has reduced methane opacity which causes it to be unacceptably bright in the H band. The colors and fluxes also depend on the surface gravity. Models from (15) for 10 m s −2 and 215 m s −2 are also available: the colors of the low gravity model are too red in both [0.8 µm − 1.6 µm] and [0.8 µm − 3.8 µm] to be acceptable. Thus, if the gravity is lower than our nominal assumption, corresponding to approximately a 0.5 M J object, then we estimate that the upper limit on temperature is raised by about 50 K. The colors of the high-gravity 400 K model are similar to those of the 46 m s −2 one.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 )</head><label>3</label><figDesc>. Furthermore, between 2004 and 2006 Fomalhaut b became fainter by ∼0.5 mag at 0.6 µm . Photometric vari- ability and excess optical emission cannot be explained by exoplanet thermal radiation alone. The 0.6 µm flux might be contaminated by Hα emission (SOM) that is detected from brown dwarfs (17, 18). Variable Hα emission might arise from a hot planetary chromosphere heated by vigorous internal convection, or trace hot gas at the inner boundary of a circumplanetary accretion disk, by analogy with magnetospheric emission from accreting T Tauri stars (e.g., 19). If a circumplanetary disk is extended, the starlight it reflects might contribute to the flux detected at 0.6 and 0.8 µm. To explain our observed fluxes requires a disk radius ∼ 20 − 40 R J , comparable to the orbital radii of Jupiter's Galilean satellites (SOM). The need for additional sources of luminosity implies that the mass inferred from the 0.8 µm flux alone is an upper limit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>no other adequately bright stars contained within the ACS/HRC field of view. The signif- icant source of astrometric uncertainty is determining the position of Fomalhaut behind the ACS/HRC occulting spots. Successive frames may be registered at the sub-pixel level relative to each other by mutual subtraction, but a fiducial frame is required where the pixel position of Fomalhaut behind the occulting spot is estimated. This is achieved by minimizing the residuals when a frame is subtracted from a copy of itself rotated by 180 o . The residuals are minimized when the assumed center of rotation is nearest the position of the star behind the spot. The self-subtraction center positions can be compared to the relative center positions determined by subtracting images of Fomalhaut obtained in successive orbits. We thus estimate the accuracy of determining the location of Fomalhaut behind the occulting spots using 180 o self-subtraction technique as ±0.5 pixel (12.5 mas, or 0.10 AU at the distance to Fomalhaut). This value is an upper limit to the possible difference between the true and estimated positions of Fomalhaut. The centroid position of Fomalhaut b were measured in three versions of the final F606W processed images in 2004, and seven versions from the 2006 F606W processed data. All images were rotated to the orientation shown in Fig. 1. We find a standard error of 0.31 and 0.55 pixel along the x and y directions in the 2004 data. In the 2006 measurements the corresponding standard errors are 0.09 and 0.32 pixel. Adding these uncertainties in quadrature to the uncer- tainties in the position of Fomalhaut at each epoch gives 0.87 pixel for the 1-σ uncertainty in the estimated motion of Fomalhaut b between epochs. This translates to 0.022 arcsecond or 0.169 AU.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>.</head><label></label><figDesc>Zeropoints for the HST data are obtained from (S6). The error bars quoted are statistical only. The standard error derived from multiple versions of the F606W data with different PSF subtraction techniques is 0.10 mag and 0.05 mag for the 2004 and 2006 data, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in the F606W filter varies between 25.1 and 24.3 mag (0.36 and 0.75 µJy, re- spectively). Assuming that the flux is due to a single, narrow emission line, the equivalent line flux would be ∆νF ν = 0.7 − 1.5 × 10 −14 erg s −1 cm −2 . The fractional luminosity would be L Hα /L bol = 0.4−0.8%. The Hα emission from Fomalhaut b would be similar to that suggested for GQ Lup b, where L Hα /L bol = 2% (S8). The Hα emission hypothesis can be tested with an optical spectrum of Fomalhaut b. If con- firmed, then a key problem is explaining the origin of gas around a 200 Myr yr old star (two orders of magnitude older than GQ Lub b). Equating the Hα luminosity to accretion luminosity, the accretion rate is 10 −11 M J yr −1 , or 0.002 M J over the age of the system (assuming 100%</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. A third significant problem with the dust cloud model is explaining the F606W variability observed over two epochs. The cumulative scattering surface area would have to drop by 63% over 1.73 year to account for the 0.5 mag decrease in optical magnitude. One possible mechanism is that the 2004 data show Fomalhaut b with a small grain component, but in 2006 the small grains have dispersed due to radiation pressure. Removing all grains &lt; 8 µm in size from the first model without renormalizing the F814W flux results in a brightness decrease of 2.23 mag in F606W. Thus an 0.5 mag decrease is possible by tuning the removal of small grains over 1.73</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is ∼5 mag brighter than light reflected from a Jupiter. Now we consider that the planet is surrounded by dust grains analogous to circumplanetary rings. Since this is a flattened disk, the geometric cross section scales as cos(i), where i is the inclination to the line of sight (i = 0 o is a face-on orientation). Consider that the main, optically thick rings of Saturn extend out to Saturn's Roche radius, or about 2 planetary radii.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>circumplanetary disk.</head><label></label><figDesc>For example, the outermost Galilean satellite of Jupiter, Callisto, has a planetocentric distance of about ∼27 Jupiter radii. Regular satellites have prograde motion that indicates formation in situ around the planet. Though in some respects this is similar to the pure dust cloud model, the planet+disk hypoth- esis has several advantages: (1) The presence of a planet allows for a wider range of physical phenomena to account for the F606W variability, such as the Hα hypothesis. (2) The location of Fomalhaut b just inside the dust belt is consistent with the predicted location of a planet gravitationally sculpting the belt's inner edge. (3)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: HST coronagraphic image of Fomalhaut at 0.6 µm showing the location of Fomalhaut b (white square) 12.7 ′′ radius from the star and just within the inner boundary of the dust belt. All the other apparent objects in the field are either background stars and galaxies or false-positives. The fainter lower half of the dust belt lies behind the sky plane. To obtain an orientation with north up and east left, this figure should be rotated 66.0 o counterclockwise. The yellow circle marks the location of the star behind the occulting spot. The yellow ellipse has a semimajor axis of 30 AU at Fomalhaut (3.9 ′′ ) that corresponds to the orbit of Neptune in our solar system. The inset is a composite image showing the location of Fomalhaut b in 2004 and 2006 relative to Fomalhaut. Bounding Fomalhaut b are two elliptical annuli that are identical to those shown for Fomalhaut's dust belt (6), except that here the inner and outer annuli have semimajor axes of 114.2 and 115.9 AU, respectively. The motion of Fomalhaut b therefore appears to be nested within the dust belt.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Dynamical models of how Fomalhaut b gravitationally sculpts the belt [see also (14)]. Top two panels: Histograms of time-averaged semimajor axes of parent bodies that survive 100-Myr-long integrations with Fomalhaut b, whose parameters are chosen to reproduce the belt's inner edge at 133 AU and ellipticity of 0.11. Parent bodies are evacuated from Fomalhaut b's chaotic zone (yellow region). Gaps open at the planet's resonances, akin to the solar system's Kirkwood gaps. Black circles and bars mark the range of stellocentric distances spanned by the model orbits for Fomalhaut b. The apocentric distance for 10 M J is inconsistent with the observed stellocentric distance of Fomalhaut b (green line). The 1 M J model is consistent. Bottom panel: Vertical optical depth profiles of dust generated from parent bodies. The planet orbit is tuned so that the optical depth is at half maximum at 133 AU, the location of the inner edge of the scattered light model from (6) (red curve), which itself is an idealized and non-unique fit to the HST data. While the dynamical and scattered light models do not agree perfectly, lower planet masses are still inferred because they do not produce broad tails of emission at a</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Fig. S1: Two enlarged sub-regions (at the same scale) from Figure 1 centered on Fomalhaut b and a background star (located at the 8 o'clock position relative to Fomalhaut in Fig. 1, just outside the dust belt). We show relative motion by registering the 2004 and 2006 data to Fomalhaut and producing the difference image. Background objects are easily distinguished from the planet candidate in terms of the magnitude (0.7 arcsecond) and direction of their motion. In 2004, Fomalhaut b is detected at separation ρ = 12.61 ′′ and position angle, PA = 316.86 o relative to Fomalhaut. In 2006, Fomalhaut b is at ρ = 12.72 ′′ and position angle, PA = 317.49 o (recall that the orientation shown here is rotated 66.0 o clockwise from one that gives north up and east left).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table S1 :</head><label>S1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Fomalhaut Observing log 
Observatory 
Instrument 
UT Date 
Filter 
Exp. Time (s) 
HST 2.4-m 
ACS/HRC 1.8 ′′ spot 2004 Oct. 25 
F606W 1320 
................. 1.8 ′′ spot 2004 Oct. 26 
F606W 1320 
................. 1.8 ′′ spot 2006 July 14 
F435W 6525 
................. 3.0 ′′ spot 2006 July 15-16 F435W 6525 
................. 1.8 ′′ spot 2006 July 17-19 F606W 7240 
................. 3.0 ′′ spot 2006 July 19-20 F606W 7240 
................. 1.8 ′′ spot 2006 July 18 
F814W 5430 
................. 3.0 ′′ spot 2006 July 19 
F814W 5430 
Keck II 10-m NIRC2 2.0 ′′ spot 
2005 July 17 
H 
3790 
2005 July 27 
H 
4320 
2005 July 28 
H 
4890 
2005 Oct. 21 
H 
5310 
2005 Oct. 22 
CH4 
4774 
Gemini N 8-m NIRI 
2008 Sep. 17-18 L ′ 
6006 

Keck II observations with adaptive optics used the NIRC2 near-infrared camera located at 

the Nasmyth of the telescope where the sky rotates relative to the instrument focal plane. We 

used a camera scale of 0.04 ′′ per pixel and a 2.0 ′′ diameter, semi-transparent occulting spot. 

Though the instrument has reimaging optics to fix the sky angle relative to the detector refer-

ence frame, we permit the sky to rotate in order to employ PSF subtraction technique 2 (ADI). 

Gemini South observations at L ′ , without adaptive optics correction, were executed in a similar 

manner to employ the ADI technique. We used the NIRI F/32 camera with 22 mas pixels, giv-

ing a 22.4 ′′ × 22.4 ′′ field of view. Fomalhaut b is not detected in either the Keck II or Gemini 

North data. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table S2 :</head><label>S2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Photometry on Fomalhaut b 
UT Date 
Filter 
λ c (µm) Magnitude Error (mag) Detection? 
2004-10-25 
F606W 0.606 
24.43 
0.08 
Yes 
2004-10-26 
... 
... 
24.29 
0.09 
Yes 
2005-07-21 
H 
1.633 
&gt;22.9 
3σ limit 
No 
2005-10-21 
CH 4 S 
1.592 
&gt;20.6 
3σ limit 
No 
2006-07-14/20 F606W 0.606 
25.13 
0.09 
Yes 
... 
F814W 0.814 
24.55 
0.13 
Yes 
... 
F435W 0.435 
&gt;24.7 
3σ limit 
No 
2008-09-17/18 L ′ 
3.78 
&gt;16.6 
3σ limit 
No 

Photometric calibration of the Keck upper limits is a multi-step process. Data were scaled 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Table S3 :</head><label>S3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Dust cloud model for Fomalhaut b 
Filter 
m ⋆ 
m Fom−b 
m 0.01 

ice 

m 0.01 

LG 

m 8 

ice 

m 8 

LG 

F435W 1.25 &gt;24.7 3-σ 
24.37 24.59 24.50 24.83 
F606W 1.16 25.13 ± 0.09 24.46 24.57 24.67 24.68 
F814W 1.08 24.55 ± 0.13 24.55 24.55 24.55 24.55 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table S4 :</head><label>S4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Colors of the dust cloud model 
Filter 
∆m ⋆ ∆m Fom−b ∆m 0.01 

ice 

∆m 0.01 

LG 

∆m 8 

ice 

∆m 8 

LG 

F435W -F606W 0.09 &lt;0.43 
-0.09 
0.02 
-0.17 0.15 
F606W -F814W 0.08 0.58 
-0.09 
0.02 
0.12 
0.13 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Backman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gillett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cool Stars, Stellar Systems and the Sun</title>
		<editor>J. L Linsky and R.E. Stencel</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="350" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mouillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Larwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">896</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wyatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">527</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">918</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stapelfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl. Ser</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Clampin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1067</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Quillen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Barrado Y Navascues</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">839</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Solar System Dynamics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Paczynski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">216</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">822</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Strubbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">648</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">652</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dohnanyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2531</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wisdom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Clampin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">683</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">H C</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SOM References 1</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4584</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">641</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">556</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Duchene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pinte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><forename type="middle">J R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">670</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">536</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lafrenì Ere</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">670</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1367</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Van Der Marel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kozhurina-Platais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ACS 2007-007</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Space Telescope Science Institute; Baltimore</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Instrument Science Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sirianni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1049</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">683</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">654</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Artymowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp; M</forename><surname>Clampin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">863</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Nachr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">326</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
