<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:11+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On the Formation Age of the First Planetary System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-04-03">3 Apr 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tetsuya</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shuhei</forename><surname>Kunitomo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Masanobu</forename><surname>Shigeyasu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daigo</forename><surname>Kajiura</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On the Formation Age of the First Planetary System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-04-03">3 Apr 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Recently, it has been observed the extreme metal-poor stars in the Galactic halo, which must be formed just after Pop III objects. On the other hand, the first gas clouds of mass ∼ 10 6 M⊙ are supposed to be formed at z ∼ 10, 20, and 30 for the 1σ, 2σ and 3σ, where the density perturbations are assumed of the standard ΛCDM cosmology. Usually it is approximated that the distribution of the density perturbation amplitudes is gaussian where σ means the standard deviation. If we could apply this gaussian distribution to the extreme small probability, the gas clouds would be formed at z ∼40, 60, and 80 for the 4σ, 6σ, and 8σ where the probabilities are approximately 3 × 10 −5 , 10 −9 , and 10 −15. Within our universe, there are almost ∼ 10 16 (∼ 10 22 M⊙/10 6 M⊙) clouds of mass 10 6 M⊙. Then the first gas clouds must be formed around z ∼ 80, where the time is ∼ 20 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1 + z) 3/2 Gyr). Even within our galaxy, there are ∼ 10 5 (∼ 10 11 M⊙/10 6 M⊙) clouds, then the first gas clouds within our galaxy must be formed around z ∼ 40, where the time is ∼ 54 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1 + z) 3/2 Gyr). The evolution time for massive star (∼ 10 2 M⊙) is ∼ 3 Myr and the explosion of the massive supernova distributes the metal within a cloud. The damping time of the supernova shock wave in the adiabatic and isothermal era is several Myr and stars of the second generation (Pop II) are formed within a free fall time ∼ 20 Myr. Even if the gas cloud is metal poor, there is a lot of possibility to form the planets around such stars. The first planetary systems could be formed within ∼ 6 × 10 7 years after the Big Bang in the universe. Even in our galaxies, the first planetary systems could be formed within ∼ 1.7 × 10 8 years. If the abundance of heavy elements such as Fe is small compared to the elements of C, N, O, the planets must be the one where the rock fraction is small. It is interesting to wait the observations of planets around metal-poor stars. For the panspermia theory, the origin of life could be expected in such systems.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>§1. Introduction</head><p>Recently it has been reported that the detection of the metal poor stars: HE0107-5240 is a giant star (36, 000 lyr, M ≃ 0.8M ⊙ ), having just 1/200, 000 of the solar metal abundance 1) : HE1327-2326, discovered in 2005, is a star (≥ 1, 500 lyr, M ≃ 0.7M ⊙ ), having just 1/300,000 of the solar metal abundance (the lowest known iron abundance to date). <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref> It has been speculated that these stars are the second generation, born out of the gas clouds which were polluted by the primordial Population III stars.</p><p>In the following we estimate the formation age of the first stars and consider the formation of the first planetary systems. If we consider the panspermia theory seriously, it could be speculated that first life began in such primordial planetary systems.</p><p>There has been established that rocks can be ejected from planetary surface by colliding asteroids and comets. The Chicxulub crater event 65 Myr ago provides evidence of the collisional ejection process. The meteorites size is estimated about 10 km in diameter.</p><p>However it is not certain that the micro-organisms within the size ( ≥ 1cm) of meteorites are still viable for several Myr, the Earth origin meteorites could be transferred to the nearby stellar systems. If we take it is viable, we should consider the panspermia theories more seriously. §2. Gaussian Distribution It is now understood that the first luminous stars are formed through the contraction of gas cloud due to cooling into the dark matter potential where the amplitudes of density perturbation become order one. Without the density perturbation of dark matter, baryonic gas could not contract due to background homogeneity. The formation of primordial gas clouds has been investigated <ref type="bibr">(Matsuda, Sato and Takeda 1969, 3</ref> The first gas clouds of mass ∼ 10 6 M ⊙ are supposed to be formed at z ∼ 10, 20, and 30 for the 1σ, 2σ and 3σ, where the density perturbations are assumed of the standard ΛCDM cosmology (Nishi and Susa 1999). 7) Usually the distribution of the perturbation amplitudes is approximated as gaussian where σ means the standard deviation.</p><p>If we could apply this gaussian distribution to the extreme small probability, the gas clouds would be formed at z ∼40, 60, and 80 for the 4σ, 6σ, and 8σ where the probabilities are approximately 3 × 10 −5 , 10 −9 , and 6 × 10 −16 . Within our universe, there are almost ∼ 10 16 (∼ 10 22 M ⊙ /10 6 M ⊙ ) clouds of mass 10 6 M ⊙ . Then the first gas clouds must be formed around z ∼ 80, where the time is ∼ 20 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1+z) 3/2 Gyr). Even within our galaxy, there are ∼ 10 5 (∼ 10 11 M ⊙ /10 6 M ⊙ ) clouds, then the first gas clouds within our galaxy must be formed around z ∼ 40, where the time is ∼ 54 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1 + z) 3/2 Gyr). The probability for each sigma is displayed in the Although the probability will increase if we take into account the non-gaussianity of the density perturbations ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bartolo et al. 2004</ref>), 8) we did not consider the effect. §3. Formation of Population III stars</p><p>It is now understood that the first luminous stars are formed through the following stages such as Jean's instability, free fall and Kelvin contraction. Comparing the free fall time and cooling time (mainly H 2 cooling), the gas clouds of ∼ 10 6 M ⊙ become Jean's instability and contracts into the dark matter potential as stated before.</p><p>In the following, we take z ∼ 80 as the representative age for the first gas cloud formation, where the time includes the contraction of the gas cloud <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Susa, 2002)</ref></p><note type="other">. 10) The age at z ∼ 80 is t z ∼ 13.7Gyr (1 + z) 3/2 ≃ 1.91 × 10 7 z 80 −3/2 yr. (3 . 1)</note><p>During the contraction of gas cloud, the central part contracts almost free fall and becomes opaque (Omukai and Nishi 1998). 9) The massive star of ∼ 10 2 M ⊙ is formed there. In the opaque stage where the configuration becomes stable, radiation radiates the gravitational potential energy. The time scale of Kelvin contraction is</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">t K ∼ GM 2 2R /L ≃ 2 × 10 7 M 100M ⊙ 2 R 10R ⊙ −1 L L ⊙ −1 yr. (3 . 2)</formula><p>Although the formation age is a little bit different, the detailed contraction process of primordial gas clouds are numerically investigated and the results are not so much different <ref type="bibr">(Omukai and Nishi 1998, 9</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Formation of Planetary System</head><p>The damping time of the supernova shock wave in the adiabatic and isothermal era is several Myr. Here we assume it takes the time scale of the following free fall time.</p><p>The contraction and the free fall time of the cloud around z ∼ 80 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">t f f ∼ 1 √ πGρ ≃ 2 × 10 7 z 80 −3/2 yr. (4 . 1)</formula><p>(the gas cloud is assumed to collapse at z ∼ 80 so the mean density at turn around is two times of the background density at z ∼ 1.6 × 80 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Susa, 2002)</ref>). 10) If the mass of gas cloud is smaller than ∼ 10 6 M ⊙ , the explosion energy of SN is greater than the gravitational binding energy. So the mass of the gas cloud must be greater than ∼ 10 6 M ⊙ . Then the increase of metal abundance δZ in the cloud is order of</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">δZ ∼ 10 −5 ∼ 10M ⊙ /10 6 M ⊙ .</formula><p>After the contraction of metal contaminated gas cloud, the stars of the second generation (Pop II) are formed within a free fall time ∼ 20 Myr. Then the first planetary systems could be supposed to be formed within ∼ 6 × 10 7 years after the Big Bang.</p><p>The same arguments could be applied to the case of z ∼ 40 for 4σ where the collapsed time is ∼ 54 Myr. After the explosion of the gas cloud, the expected elapsed time for the adiabatic, isothermal expansion and the free fall time is t f f ∼ 6 × 10 7 (z/40) −3/2 yr. So the first planetary systems for this case could be supposed to be formed within ∼ 1.7 × 10 8 years after the Big Bang.</p><p>The Population II stars reside in Halos and globular clusters. Even stars in globular clusters could take planetary systems for enough time (several Gyr), it is expected the life could start there.</p><p>The fragmentation of the supernova shocked shell is investigated by Salvaterra, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ferrara and Schneider (2004)</ref> 11) and they estimated the instability of the shell sets in 0.2 ∼ 50 Myr after the explosion, depending on the explosion energy and the density of the surrounding medium. If we adopt their estimation of the short time scale ∼ 0.2 Myr, the formation age of the first planetary system will become as fast as ∼ 43 Myr after the Big Bang. They also discussed the metallicity of the fragments through the mixing of the heavy elements into the swept up matter in the shell. Although there are many uncertainty mechanism, they estimated the mean metallicity of the fragments 10 −3.5 Z ⊙ ≤ Z ≤ 10 −2.6 Z ⊙ . If we include their estimation, the metallicity of the secondary stars will much increase and the formation of the planetary systems around the secondary stars will be much expected in the earlier stage of the cosmography. §5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions and Discussion</head><p>The formation of the first planetary system is related to gaussian distribution of dark matter perturbation. Within our universe, there are almost ∼ 10 16 (∼ 10 22 M ⊙ /10 6 M ⊙ ) clouds of mass 10 6 M ⊙ . Then the first gas clouds must be formed around z ∼ 80, where the time is ∼ 20 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1 + z) 3/2 Gyr). Considering the evolution, SN explosion, expansion, and contraction, the first planetary systems with metals could be supposed to be formed within ∼ 6 × 10 7 years after the Big Bang.</p><p>Even within our galaxy, there are ∼ 10 5 (∼ 10 11 M ⊙ /10 6 M ⊙ ) clouds. As stated before the first gas clouds within our galaxy must be formed around z ∼ 40, where the time is ∼ 54 Myr (∼ 13.7/(1 + z) 3/2 Gyr). The first planetary systems for this case could be supposed to be formed within ∼ 1.7 × 10 8 years after the Big Bang.</p><p>It is interesting to wait the observations of planets around metal-poor stars in the halos and globular clusters. For the panspermia theory, the origin of life could be expected in such systems. The ejected rocks from such planets could transfer microorganism within galaxies ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wallis and Wickramasinghe 2004</ref>). 12) Even in our solar system, there must be many types of life in Mars, Europa, Ganymede, Io, Uranus, Neptune, Pluto, and Titan. It is interesting to wait the investigation of these planets and satellites.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>table .</head><label>.</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>σ 
probability 
σ 
probability 

1 
0.158 
6 
9.90 × 10 −10 
2 
2.27 × 10 −2 
7 
1.28 × 10 −12 
3 
1.35 × 10 −3 
8 
6.25 × 10 −16 
4 
3.17 × 10 −5 
9 
1.13 × 10 −19 
5 
2.87 × 10 −7 
10 
7.66 × 10 −24 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">* ) E-mail:hara@cc.kyoto-su.ac.jp</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chrtlieb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">904</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Frebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">871</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Theor. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">219</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Palla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salpeter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stahler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">632</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bromm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Coppi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Abel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hernquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sugiyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">544</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Susa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">523</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bartolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Komatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Matarrese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rept</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Omukai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">508</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">141</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Susa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Theor. Phys. Sup</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Salvaterra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ferrara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wallis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
