<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:11+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Transfer of Life-Bearing Meteorites from Earth to Other Planets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-04-08">8 Apr 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tetsuya</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kazuma</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daigo</forename><surname>Kajiurafirstname</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kyoto Sangyo University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>603-8555</postCode>
									<settlement>Kyoto</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Transfer of Life-Bearing Meteorites from Earth to Other Planets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-04-08">8 Apr 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>§1. Introduction</head><p>A number of scientists now believe that micro-organisms can be transferred to and from various planets and moons, including from Earth to other worlds <ref type="bibr">(Joseph and Schild 2010a,b ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Napier and Wickramasinghe 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Wainwright et al., 2010)</ref>. To determine the probability of the transfer of viable organisms between planets, we have used Earth as the origin of these life-bearing rocks and have determined the likelihood that viable life could be deposited on those stellar objects in this Solar System which are believed capable of sustain life, i.e. Enceladus, Europa, Ceres and dwarf planets Eris. Recently it has been reported that the detection of the super-Earth planets in the Gl 581 system which reside at the warming edge of the habitable zone of the star <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Udry et. al. 2007</ref>). Therefore, we also investigate the probability of successful transfer to extra solar planets, such as Gl 581. The propagation distances of life-bearing rocks are also estimated, and we have determined that under some circumstances, life originating in one stellar system could propagate throughout Galaxy. §2. Seeding Other Planets With Life</p><p>Super-Earth planets have been recently detected, including in the Gl 581 system where planet orbits are at the warming edge of the habitable zone of the star ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Udry et al. 2007)</ref>. Whether this planet or other super-Earth's may harbor life or not is completely unknown. On the other hand, if microbial life were to be deposited on a super-Earth through mechanisms of panspermia <ref type="bibr">Schild 2010a,b, Napier and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Wickramasinghe 2010)</ref>, then it could be predicted that these microbes flourish and reproduce.</p><p>The only planet, which we know has life, is Earth. Therefore, Earth would be a likely source to seed other planets with life. This could take place following solar storms which eject microbes from outer atmosphere into space, or from bolide impacts which eject stones, rocks, and oceans of water into space <ref type="bibr">(Joseph and Schild 2010a, b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Napier and Wickramasinghe 2010)</ref>. Naturally, those meteors, asteroids or comets which strike with the strong force, would eject the most material into space. Thus it could be prediced that the asteroid or meteor which struck this planet 65 million years ago, and which created the Chicxulub crater <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alvarez. et al. 1979)</ref> would have ejected substantial amount of rock, soil, and water into space, some of which would have fallen onto other planets and moons, including stellar bodies outside our stellar system, Kuiper belt objects, Oort cloud objects, and possibly extrasolar planets. That meteorite was estimated to be about 10km in diameter <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alvarez, et al. 1979</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">, Bralower et al. 1998</ref>). @@ Here, we investigate the transfer probability of Earth origin rocks to our Solar System. We put parameters as following that N 0 rocks are ejected from Earth, s(cm) is the distance to the object, and the cross section of the rock capture by the object is σ (cm 2 ). Then the impact rock number is estimated that N 0 times σ over the surface of sphere of radius s as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">N impact = N 0 σ 4πs 2</formula><p>When the Chicxulub meteorite collided to the earth, it could be estimated that almost the same amount mass could be ejected from Earth, where we have taken the optimistic value ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wallis and Wickramasinghe, 2004</ref>). Then it is assumed that the ejected mass from Earth is f 1 × M 0 , where M 0 is the mass of the Chicxulub meteorite and the factor f 1 (∼ 0.3) denotes the fraction of the mass ejected from Earth. Taking that the mean diameter of rocks is r 1 (cm) and the estimated diameter of the Chicxulub meteorite is R 1 , the number N 0 of ejected rocks from Earth is estimated as f 1 times of the cubic of (R 1 /r 1 ).</p><p>If we take R 1 and r 1 as 10(km) and 1(cm), the number N 0 of ejected rocks is the order of</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">N 0 = f 1 R 1 r 1 3 ∼ 3 × 10 17 f 1 0.3 R 1 10 km 3 r 1 1 cm −3 .</formula><p>This is a rather crude approximation. To be precise, we have to include the size distributions of rock fragments. Here we only tentatively want to estimate the number of rocks. If we take r 1 ∼ 1mm, the above value has increased factor ∼ 10 3 . However the cosmic radiation in space will damage the micro-organism within the fragments of size ∼ 1 mm, unless it is covered by molecules such as ice or other elements. The distance to the interesting objects within our Solar System is the order of astronomical unit. So we take the representative value as s ∼ 1AU ∼ 1.5 × 10 8 km. The problem is the cross section σ. So we consider the following two models.</p><p>Model A : The cross section σ for the direct collision to the object is the order σ ∼ πR 2 0 where R 0 is the radius of the object. Then the number of impact rocks is estimated for the case R 0 ∼ 10 3 km and s ∼ 1 AU as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">N A ∼ N 0 σ 4πs 2 ∼ 3 × 10 6 f 1 0.3 R 1 10km 3 r 1 1cm −3 R 0 10 3 km 2 s 1AU −2 .</formula><p>This model corresponds to the high velocity case of ejected rocks.</p><p>Model B : After rocks are ejected from Earth, they are orbiting around Earth and then ejected to orbits around Sun through swing-by. If rocks could be decelerated by gravitational interaction, rocks are captured to objects. After a few My, some fraction of rocks could fall into objects. The gravitational infall to the object could be inferred by the gravitational accretion radius R g ∼ Gm 0 /v 2 0 where m 0 is the mass of the object. Then the cross section σ is estimated as σ ∼ R 2 g which is proportional to the mass square m 2 0 . As the dominant planet is Jupiter, the infalling rate is roughly proportional to (m 0 /M J ) 2 where M J is Jupiter's mass. Then the number of falling rocks is estimated for the case of m 0 ∼ 10 20 kg as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">N B ∼ N 0 m 0 M J 2 ∼ 10 3 f 1 0.3 R 1 10km 3 r 1 1cm −3 m 0 10 20 kg 2 M J 2 × 10 27 kg −2 .</formula><p>This model corresponds to the low velocity case of ejected rocks. The values for Enceladus, Europa, Ceres, Eris, Moon and Mars are presented in the  For every object, the number N A and N B are much greater than one. Although it is uncertain how rocks enter the presumed sea under the surface, for example, of Enceladus and Europa, the probability may be high that micro-organisms transferred from Earth would be adapted and growing there. The orbital calculations of meteorite transfer among planets within our Solar System are estimated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Melosh (2003)</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. §3. Probability of reaching Gl 581 and extra solar planets</head><p>To extend the above consideration to the extra solar planets is almost straightforward. We introduce the factor f 2 (∼ 0.3) which denote the fraction of rocks ejected from our Solar System. As the distance to Gl 581 is 20 light years, we take the representative value for s as s ∼ 10 19 (cm). The problem is the cross section σ. So we consider the following model A and C, where model A is the almost the same in section 2.</p><p>Model A : The cross section σ for the direct collision to the planet in the Gl 581 system is of the order σ ∼ πr 2 ∼ π(m/m ⊕ ) 2/3 r 2 ⊕ where m and m ⊕ are the mass of the planet and Earth, respectively. Then the cross section factor becomes σ/(4πs 2 ) ∼ (m/m ⊕ ) 2/3 (r ⊕ /s) 2 /4 ∼ 3 × 10 −21 (m/5m ⊕ ) 2/3 (s/10 19 cm) −2 , and the impact number becomes as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">N impact ∼ N 0 σ 4πs 2 ∼ 3 × 10 −4 f 1 f 2 0.1 R 1 10km 3 r 1 1cm −3 m 5m ⊕ 2/3 s 10 19 cm −2 .</formula><p>The probability for the direct collision is small.</p><p>Model C: The cross section σ could be enlarged including the effect of the gravitational interaction such as swing-by. If rocks could be deaccelerated by gravitational interaction, rocks are captured to the stellar system. Although the velocity dependence of the cross section is pointed out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Melosh (2003)</ref>, it is difficult to include this effect here. Then we simply assume the cross section as σ ∼ f 3 πR 2 , where R is the orbit radius of the planet and the uncertainty factor f 3 is included. The number of impacted rocks, N impact , becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">N impact ∼ N 0 f 2 f 3 4 R s 2 ∼ 10 4 N 0 f 2 10 17 f 3 0.1 R 1AU 2 s 10 19 cm −2 .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Due to the estimation of numerical simulations by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Melosh (2003)</ref>, the factor f 1 , and f 2 are roughly 0.3. We take f 3 tentatively as ∼ 0.1. Even though there are many uncertainty factors, the probability could increase by considering the small rocks which are smaller than 1cm . If we consider the possibility that the fragmented ejecta (smaller than 1cm ) are accreted to comets and other icy bodies in the 'EdgeworthKuiper Belt', the securely buried fertile material could make the interstellar journey through Galaxy ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Wallis and Wickramasinghe, 2004</ref>). The above estimated number N impact is the captured number of rocks in the Gl 581 system. If we consider the falling probability f 4 to the appropriate planet and the landing probability f 5 to the appropriate circumstances of the planet, the probability for the proliferation of the life must be decreased. Then the numbers of rocks for the proliferation becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">N proli ∼ 10 2 f 1 f 2 f 3 10 −2 f 4 f 5 10 −2 R 1 10km 3 r 1 1cm −3 × R 1AU 2 s 10 19 cm −2 .</formula><p>If we take the mean velocity of meteorites in the interstellar space as ∼ 10 km/s, the elapsed time to travel to GI 581 system is</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">T ∼ s v ∼ 10 6 s 20ly 10kms −1 v years.</formula><p>Then the time to be ejected from our Solar System through swing-by (several Million years) and the orbiting time to fall in the planet through swing-by after captured to Gl 581 system (several Million years) are longer than the travel time to Gl 581 system. §4. Transfer Distance and Velocity of Rocks with Micro-Organisms</p><p>In this section, we estimate the distance and velocity of rocks with microorganism through the interstellar space.</p><p>Model I: The number of ejected rocks from our Solar System is</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">N ej ∼ 10 17 f 1 f 2 0.1 R 1 10km 3 r 1 1cm −3 .</formula><p>To apply the estimate to general stellar systems, we change the size of the system from ∼ 1 AU to ∼ 10 AU where the orbits of Jupiter and/or Saturn like planets are considered. If the radius of the planet orbit is taken as R , the cross section σ is given by σ ∼ πR 2 . The number of accumulated rocks to the system is</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">N impact ∼ N ej πR 2 4πL 2 ,</formula><p>where L is the distance between the origin and the system. For the propagation of the micro-organism, N impact must be greater than N crit (∼ 1). From the criterion</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(N impact ≥ N crit ), the distance L is limited as L ≤ L crit ∼ N ej N crit 1/2 R 2 ∼ 3 × 10 4 N ej 10 17 1/2 (N crit ) −1/2 R 10AU</formula><p>ly.</p><p>The propagation time T to the L crit is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">T ∼ L crit v mean ∼ 10 9 L crit 3 × 10 4 ly 10km s −1 v mean years,</formula><p>where we take the mean velocity of rocks as 10 kms −1 . Then, by 10 9 years, rocks could reach each stellar system within the distance 3 × 10 4 light years. The above estimate is rather optimistic. We must consider the uncertainty factor such as f 3 , f 4 and f 5 . If we include these factors, the value of N crit must be greater than 10 3 . Then the above critical length decreased to</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">L crit ∼ N ej N crit 1/2 R 2 ∼ 10 3 N ej 10 17 1/2 10 3 N crit 1/2 ly.</formula><p>The propagation time T to L crit is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">T ∼ L crit v ∼ 3 × 10 7 L crit 10 3 ly 10km s −1 v years.</formula><p>Then, by 3 × 10 7 years, the many rocks (∼ 10 3 ) could reach each stellar system within the distance 10 3 light years. To estimate the longer distance than L crit , we consider the following model.</p><p>Model II: The Chicxulub crater event is 65 My ago and such event is happened roughly per every 100 My, which is consistent of the accretion rate of crater forming bodies (∼ 10 11 g/y, Sephton <ref type="formula">(2003)</ref>). Then the mean number of ejected rocks per year N mean is estimated as N mean ∼ N ej /(10 8 y) ∼ 10 9 /y. The number N acc (t) of accumulated rocks in the system of the distance L after t year is</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">N acc (t) ∼ N mean × t × πR 2 /(4πL 2 ).</formula><p>Then the distance (L crit (t)) which satisfies the criterion that N acc (t) is greater than N crit (∼ 10 3 ) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">L crit (t) ∼ (N mean × t × R 2 4N crit ) 1/2 ∼ 10 3 N mean 10 9 1/2 t 10 8 y 1/2 10 3 N crit 1/2 R 10AU ly.</formula><p>As the radius of Galaxy (R G ) is about 5 × 10 4 ly, it takes 3 × 10 11 years for L crit (t) ≥ R G , which is much greater than the age of our Galaxy.</p><p>Model III: If we assume that the propagated system becomes the place where the micro-organisms adapt, multiply and proliferate, the system becomes the source of the rocks with micro-organisms. If it takes t 0 time to propagate to such a system with distance L and t 1 time to proliferate there enough, the propagation velocity</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">v prop is v prop ∼ L t 0 + t 1 ∼ 10 3 ly 10 8 y ,</formula><p>where we take L ∼ L crit ∼ 10 3 ly, t 0 ∼ 3 × 10 7 years and t 1 ∼ 10 8 years, respectively.</p><p>PjIf the multiplication factor m of such descendants for each generation is high (m ≫ 1) , the propagated distance L prop would be proportional to the time as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">L prop ∼ v prop × t.</formula><p>It takes 5 × 10 9 years for L prop ≥ R G , which means that if origin of life has begun within our Galaxy 10 10 years ago, it has propagated through Galaxy, as our Galaxy age is almost 1.3 × 10 10 years. The problem may be that many types of life which evolved differently from the same origin are falling to Earth nowadays.</p><p>2) If the multiplication factor m of such descendants for each generation is not high (m ≃ 1) and they eject rocks with micro-organism only one time after t 1 , the propagated distance L prop would be proportional to the square root of time for its random walk property, as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">L prop ∼ L crit × t 10 8 y 1/2 .</formula><p>If we take L crit ∼ 10 3 ly, it takes 2.5 × 10 12 years for L prop ≥ R G . It means that, if origin of life has begun within our Galaxy 10 10 years ago, it has propagated only 10L crit ∼ 10 4 ly. If there are X ∼ 25 sites where the life began 10 10 years ago in our Galaxy, the propagated surface is about the same of our Galaxy by the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">π(10L crit ) 2 X ∼ πR 2 G .</formula><p>Then the probability is almost one that our solar system is visited by the microorganisms originated in extra solar system. §5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions and Discussion</head><p>Although there are many uncertain factors, the probability of rocks originated from Earth to reach nearby star system is not so small. The rough estimation is given by Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(1)</ref>  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table .</head><label>.</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Object 
s (AU) 
R0(km) 
m0 (kg) 
NA 
NB 

Enceladus 
10 
2.5 × 10 2 
7 × 10 19 
2 × 10 3 
5 × 10 2 
Europa 
5 
1.6 × 10 3 
5 × 10 22 
3 × 10 5 
3 × 10 8 
Ceres 
3 
5 × 10 2 
9 × 10 20 
10 5 
10 5 
Eris 
100 
1.2 × 10 3 
2 × 10 22 
4 × 10 2 
4 × 10 7 
Moon 
3 × 10 −3 
1.7 × 10 3 
7 × 10 22 
10 12 
5 × 10 8 
Mars 
1.5 
3.4 × 10 3 
6 × 10 23 
2 × 10 7 
4 × 10 10 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table I .</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The values of s, R0, m0, NA, NB for Enceladus, Europa, Ceres, Eris, Moon and Mars 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomalous iridium levels at the Cretaceous/Tertiary boundary at Gubbio, Italy : Negative results of tests for a supernova origin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Asaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cretaceous/Tertiary Boundary Events Symposium</title>
		<editor>Christensen, W.K., Birkelund, T.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Copenhagen</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological Cosmology and the Origins of Life in the</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Universe Journal of Cosmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1040" to="1090" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origins, Evolution, and Distribution of Life in the Cosmos: Panspermia, Genetics, Microbes, and Viral Visitors From the Stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cosmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1616" to="1670" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Napier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mechanisms for Panspermia. Journal of Cosmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1671" to="1691" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary cocktail: Chicxulub impact triggers margin collapse and extensive sediment gravity flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bralower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Paull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leckie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exchange of Meteorites (and Life?) Between Stellar Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Melosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origin of Life</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sephton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">An Introduction to Astrobiology</title>
		<editor>Gilmour, I. Sephtons, M.A.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets XI. Super-Earths (5 and 8 M ⊕ ) in a 3-planet system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>astro-ph/0704.3841</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are Microbes Currently Arriving to Earth from Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wainwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Alshammari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Alabri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cosmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1692" to="1702" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interstellar transfer of planetary microbiota</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wallis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
