<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:21+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Statistical analysis of narrow-band signals at setilive.org</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Igor</forename><surname>Nikitin</surname></persName>
							<email>igor.nikitin@scai.fraunhofer.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of High Performance Analytics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fraunhofer Institute for Algorithms and Scientific Computing Schloss Birlinghoven</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>53757</postCode>
									<settlement>Sankt Augustin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Statistical analysis of narrow-band signals at setilive.org</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>SETILive is a web project forwarding radio signals from SETI Institute&apos;s Allen Telescope Array (ATA) for the analysis of volunteers. It contains a large archive with more than 1.5 millions observations for more than 7.5 thousands observation targets, including directions to exoplanets discovered by telescope Kepler and other sources. It also supports various tools for signal collection and classification. Till recent time it supported live feeds of signals from ATA together with a feedback loop, a possibility to interrupt the schedule and repeat the observation of an interesting signal registered by sufficiently many viewers. Unfortunately, since 12-Oct-2014 the live feeds have been discontinued. We hope that the project will persist, taking into account the importance of the search subject, the worldwide interest to the topic and the value of already collected data. In this paper we present the results of statistical analysis of data stored in SETILive archive, using Radon transform and specially constructed filter for selection of single beams, potential signals of ET origination. We will also estimate statistical significance of signals depending on their signal-to-noise ratio using Monte Carlo simulation and select 28 strong signals and totally 1072 statistically significant signals in the archive. Fig.1. Synthetic signal of different strength and its Radon transform.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Signal analysis at SETI <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> uses so called waterfall plots, representing a moving window Fourier decomposition of the signal with frequency taken as horizontal axis and time as vertical axis. Especially interesting features on the waterfall plots are straight lines, corresponding to narrow signals with slowly drifting frequency. Given a source signal of a fixed frequency, Doppler effect will produce a frequency shift, while the rotation and orbital motion of the Earth and similar motions of the signal source will make this shift varying in time. If the observation period is much less than the periods of these motions, the drift will be approximately linear in time and will produce straight lines on the waterfall plots. Earlier it has been proposed to use Radon transform for searching straight lines on the waterfall plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>. Radon transform performs an integration of a signal along straight lines in various directions, accumulating lines to points. In this way signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) can be increased. An example on <ref type="figure">Fig.1</ref> shows a synthetic signal of the form s(f,t) = SNR exp(-((f-f 0 -kt)/b) 2 ) + N(f,t) where f denotes frequency, t -time, f 0 +kt represents a line on waterfall plot, b adjusts signal bandwidth and N(f,t) is Gaussian random field with zero mean and identity covariance matrix. Radon transform recovers the signal as a bright spot with a characteristic hourglass profile. For the plots of n x n pixel resolution Radon integration amplifies the signal by a factor ~n and noise by a factor ~sqrt(n), resulting to typical increase of SNR by a factor ~sqrt(n) relative to the original signal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods of the analysis</head><p>In this paper we will apply Radon transform for the analysis of waterfall plots available at setilive.org. The general scheme of the analysis is shown on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.2</ref>. The main component, Radon transform is defined by the formula:</p><p>r(x,a) =  dy s(x cos a -y sin a, x sin a + y cos a)</p><p>In numerical estimation the integral has been replaced by a sum over corresponding pixels restricted to the bounds of the waterfall plot. The resulting distribution has been normalized by subtracting the average and dividing to rms. The normalization maps rms1, so that the resulting 2D plot directly represents Radon transform in SNR units. Prescaling step is needed to remap the original waterfall plots to the size appropriate for Radon transform. The original plots are 8-bit grayscale PNG images, coming in two resolutions: 768x384 and 758x410. Since the above described version of Radon transform is suitable for square images, the original plots have been rescaled to 256x256 resolution, using ImageMagick 'convert' tool. In this paper we use direct O(n 3 ) algorithm for Radon transform. As an improvement, one can replace it with fast O(n 2 log n) Radon transform and its versions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. They are designed for the images, whose dimensions are either integer powers of two or prime numbers. The prescaling step will be also necessary for fast transform. Signal selection is the most important step in the chain. The input waterfall plots come in groups, corresponding to simultaneous signal observations in several directions on celestial sphere. Only the signals highly localized on the sphere are interesting, i.e. the signals present in one observation from the group and absent in others, so called 'single beams'. As the first step, only the groups containing 3 observations have been selected, reducing the total number of groups from 6.73e5 to 2.53e5. Then the signals with small Doppler drift were eliminated. Such signals are produced by the sources which don't move (or have a constant radial speed) relative to the receiver and most probably correspond to terrestrial radio sources or geostationary satellites. These signals are represented as vertical lines on waterfall plots, i.e. as nearly zero angles on Radon plots and can be easily eliminated. Further, the signals were selected on Radon plots using a method shown on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.3</ref> left. Two rectangular contours around a given point were defined. The point is selected if a logical AND of the following conditions took place:</p><p>• in the given beam in the given point SNR 0 &gt;4</p><p>• in the given beam everywhere between two contours SNR&lt;SNR 0 /2 • in the other two beams everywhere inside external contour SNR&lt;4</p><p>This allows to select narrow signals appearing in a single beam. On <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.4</ref> left the signals are presented using as coordinates SNR in main beam and maximum of SNR in two other beams. In more detail, in the main beam SNR 0 in the given point is taken, while in two other beams the maximum SNR inside the external contour around the given point is taken. The grid step on this plot equals 1. The diagram can be separated to random background, a region of radio frequency interference and a region for potential extraterrestrial signals. The latter region corresponds to strong signal in main beam and weak signals in the other beams. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.4</ref> right shows a cumulative distribution plot, where the vertical axis presents the number of selected events possessing SNR in the main beam greater than a value given on the horizontal axis. In appropriate normalization this plot presents an empirical distribution function, a finite sample approximation to cumulative distribution function (CDF), characterizing the probability P(SNR&gt;val) in its tail region. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Monte Carlo simulation</head><p>For comparison, we show on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.4</ref> the results of Monte Carlo simulation, where Radon transform and the same selection criteria were applied to purely random field. Significant difference of these distributions starts at about SNR~6, which can be used as a threshold separating signals from the background.</p><p>In more detail, Radon integral contains lines with different number of pixels e.g. comparing locations in central region and corners of waterfall plots. To compensate this effect, the result of Radon transform before global normalization has been divided to sqrt(k), where k is the actual number of pixels counted along the integration line. For Gaussian random field with uncorrelated pixels this will correct SNR for integration lines of different lengths. However, detailed look into original waterfall plots <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.3</ref> right shows a presence of vertical correlation. Namely, p consequent pixels in vertical direction share the same value, where p varies between 2-4 and most often equals 3. The reason for this correlation could be in the details of measurement procedure, data processing or final representation of images. We will not speculate, but introduce a correction for this effect. For this purpose we assume the groups of p=3 input vertical pixels strongly correlated, count the number of uncorrelated pixels k' along integration lines and multiply the result of Radon transform to sqrt(k'/k) before global normalization. The same pattern of p=3 vertically correlated random pixels has been also used in MC simulation.</p><p>We note also that vertical correlation of Radon plots is not directly related to vertical correlation of waterfall plots. E.g. taking Gaussian random field with identity covariance matrix on input cov(s(x,y),s(x',y'))=(x-x')(y-y') we obtain the following covariance matrix on output of Radon transform:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">cov(r(x,a),r(x',a'))=|sin(a-a')| -1 (x,a;x',a')</formula><p>Here  equals 1 if two straight lines defined by (x,a) and (x',a') have intersection inside the domain of random field definition and 0 otherwise. For the random field defined on a square <ref type="bibr">[-1,1]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">2 = (|sin(a-a')|-|x sin a'-x' sin a|) (|sin(a-a')|-|x cos a'-x' cos a|)</formula><p>where  is Heaviside step function. In particular, we have</p><p>• cov(r(x,a),r(x',a'))=0 at a=a', xx', in horizontal direction of Radon plot;</p><p>• cov(r(x,a),r(x',a'))~ |a-a'| -1 at a-a'0, x=x', |x|&lt;1, in vertical direction.</p><p>Simulation of random fields with a given covariance matrix can be performed with the methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> using principal component analysis (PCA). There are also methods for simulation of random fields with unknown covariance matrix based on numerically efficient singular value decomposition (SVD) of a representative set of samples from the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. These methods can be used as an improvement of MC technique used here for estimation.</p><p>In our analysis the processing of real data and MC simulation used the same number of waterfall plots, they were performed on parallel CPUs and were accomplished in the same time. Although such synchronization is not obligatory, since the simulated cumulative distribution could be scaled to the size of real data with an appropriate factor. The results of MC simulation with SNR~6 have a form of bright spots on Radon plots and faint lines on original waterfall plots. They are visually indistinguishable from weak signals we are looking for. The only difference is that for MC results we know definitely that they have random origin. Their small probability was amplified by a large statistics and a narrow filter tuned to the signals of such shape. Although such weak signals cannot be distinguished from random events by their shape, the number of observed signals at SNR~6 should be considered as statistically significant, since it prevails over the estimated number of signals randomly adopting the shape of straight lines.</p><p>Thus we leave in selection all signals with Radon's SNR&gt;6. This threshold separates ~1500 events. Our selection algorithm can trigger several events per one signal, because several neighbor pixels of Radon plot can pass selection criteria. In the list below the duplicates will be eliminated, all events originating from the same observation will be represented by only one observation code, comprising 1072 signals in total.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The results</head><p>The figures below show the brightest signals from the selected set, while the Appendix contains all selected signals. We see that the algorithm works stable also in the presence of several straight lines on the waterfall plot, since they become separable on Radon plot. The lines on the waterfall plots can be reconstructed from selected pixels on Radon plots, actually applying inverse Radon transform to them. As a further improvement of the algorithm, one can apply the inverse transform not to single pixels but to a group of pixels near selected signal on Radon plot or perform non-linear transforms like contrast corrections rr  on Radon plot and apply the inverse Radon transform to the result.</p><p>The signals in Appendix are selected 'with a margin' and can require further filtration:</p><p>• Many selected signals possess only a slight slope to the vertical on waterfall plots. Their selection depends on the threshold for vertical lines elimination. Currently this threshold has been selected to 2 pixels in vertical direction from the center of 256x256 Radon plot, corresponding to 2° slope to the vertical on original waterfall plots. • Many selected signals have a periodical structure combined in parallel lines, e.g. ed9f on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.7</ref>. This implies the same source for several related frequencies. The signals of this kind can be attributed to terrestrial or satellite RFI. On Radon plane they create a sequence of spots located on the same horizontal line. Currently all such signals are preserved in the list. Further the algorithm can be upgraded for automatic recognition of such sequences and their identification as multiple components of the same signal.</p><p>• The signals with SNR&lt;7 are almost impossible to recognize on waterfall plots. Their presence is important nevertheless. Firstly, one can see them on Radon plots and this gives enough evidence for their existence. Secondly, the number of reconstructed signals at this level in real data prevails over MC results. These signals should be subjected to further analysis to identify the reason of such excess.</p><p>Finally, selected single beams can be subjected to more sophisticated analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, involving the tests for reproducibility of the signal in repeating observations in a given beam, the absence of signal with similar parameters in other beams, not only for simultaneous observations but also in all observations within a certain time frame, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>We have performed statistical analysis of data stored in SETILive archive, using Radon transform and specially constructed filter for selection of single beams. 28 strong signals and 1072 signals in total were selected at the level SNR&gt;6 in the main beam on Radon plot. This level corresponds to the point where CDF of the signals changes its behavior and starts to differ from the results of Monte Carlo simulation of Gaussian random field.</p><p>We will greatly appreciate continuation of SETILive project, which will also make meaningful further developments of the described methods including   Appendix: observation codes for all selected signals in SNR descending order <ref type="table">58fv_1 4kjr_1 4xpv_1 4xq3_1 5812_1 4xrh_1 2r7d_1 4xri_1 4bag_2 4xq5_1 4w6w_3 580w_1 4sly_1 ed55_1 3zmc_2 ed58_1  3xfa_2 ee5l_1 4qds_3 4x06_2 2m46_1 4xej_2 4tme_3 e6pa_1 1y6e_3 4pux_2 4umi_1 4w4a_3 4wvx_2 4xhj_3 4gke_2 3ylb_3  3zqo_1 4x07_2 56ri_2 4djp_2 4qkj_3 4m59_3 4wt6_2 4qe1_3 43y2_2 47wb_2 4va8_2 1x6w_1 4slx_1 47us_3 18jb_1 45c4_3  4uz4_2 3w8g_1 4vkb_3 4xsd_1 41j6_3 4ai4_1 5295_2 580l_1 30z4_1 451y_2 4u5z_3 4q7r_3 3xzq_3 4h65_1 3y8a_3 4hjt_1  4u5x_3 4l4p_3 45c9_3 4lkx_1 4slu_1 4pzj_3 4xhd_3 4kfo_2 2535_2 40ag_2 4pz4_3 3xzp_3 e5fe_2 4is7_1 3unw_2 2rcm_1  42dz_2 1ift_3 45m0_2 4vcz_2 4ko6_1 4wwg_2 4kg3_2 48gd_1 49m7_2 3yhh_2 4x05_2 47xl_3 4uq1_3 3wh5_1 4l9m_2 4pz1_3</ref> ed54_1 432m_2 3zmt_3 4x0l_3 3xzx_1 3eio_1 4qtb_3 1x70_1 1jkj_3 41re_2 4v3x_1 ed9f_1 45my_1 4bzi_2 3aun_2 4q7p_3 4ypf_2 47t8_3 4kfk_2 4e9b_1 4l1d_3 4iqo_2 3ylc_3 3zqv_1 e6tf_1 4v57_3 4aps_3 430y_3 4dp0_2 1cnx_3 4i8m_2 3w5h_1 4l5u_2 4fob_1 3tpp_2 4ahh_3 3yly_1 4uh6_3 4g2q_2 4jxw_2 4ph9_2 4jq4_1 4jdc_2 4mhi_2 4pqw_3 45bz_3 57ne_1 4avh_3 1img_2 3y7p_2 4wvw_2 42a1_3 4isf_2 4c7i_1 32dl_2 3xzr_1 4tlv_3 agwm_3 3zm8_1 4tar_2 4xcl_1 4grv_3 cc7n_1 0wyn_1 4s8a_2 40ks_1 48ga_2 3vvn_3 4l8z_3 42ag_1 4ad1_3 40zu_1 45eu_1 4qky_2 48g7_2 40kl_1 ed4u_3 4xc5_2 4kg1_2 2nzv_1 4myw_3 4l11_1 4n2e_3 4wwe_2 edx0_2 4l5c_2 432s_1 edw6_1 3wt4_2 4fqu_2 ed8d_3 4999_3 4g5s_3 1osp_3 49v8_1 4v8y_2 428d_3 dwlt_2 4myv_3 3xzs_3 4ipq_3 47r1_2 3zm9_1 42lg_2 4g2t_1 3zxc_3 4rv4_2 4pvg_2 3uzi_3 4qdr_3 4kfr_2 3zqz_1 40kq_1 42e5_3 4t6c_1 4e9z_2 4eq1_3 4ktc_3 4foe_3 4wzz_2 4l5q_2 4j0w_1 4q5z_2 0tr6_3 4ph9_1 4bwz_1 4wqr_1 4pjk_2 56ud_3 1hxz_1 42sd_1 4ktq_3 4g5z_1 3tpo_2 1uct_1 3zsq_2 3zqr_1 3a9a_2 4i2g_3 4kap_3 432j_2 27nt_1 4c2m_1 3vxq_3 4l8d_1 2esf_3 2hyz_3 4th2_3 235c_3 4t1u_2 41w7_3 e5mw_2 4dos_2 42n0_3 4jzc_2 4qim_3 2in1_1 2iob_1 2ipo_1 2irq_1 2iz6_1 3w5j_1 dtps_1 42t4_2 4pxo_2 2l3x_2 4ld2_1 35o2_3 4uq6_3 45pf_3 4jt5_2 4i7z_2 3lqr_2 4e4p_1 e6wa_1 e5mw_3 432f_2 42bl_1 1l7d_2 3fhq_2 34w4_2 3aij_3 42gn_1 4327_1 160l_3 c4ht_1 1acx_3 4h4w_2 3vxt_1 1c2u_3 1quz_1 15cy_3 4jdv_2 41ny_3 aduo_3 0u3l_3 28xr_2 4308_3 4grz_3 1bsb_1 4w2u_3 2xmq_3 42vg_3 42ow_1 4pv2_2 c7qh_3 42a2_1 3dbz_3 3gin_1 2v47_3 3w8e_1 3xom_2 1put_1 11g9_3 3jdt_2 31fm_1 44du_2 4ai5_1 0waf_2 3wc1_2 496z_1 415b_3 4nu4_3 agkt_3 4ewz_3 0vnc_2 asax_3 440s_2 45og_1 1iiy_3 45fd_2 4ic0_1 4od0_3 dv5v_1 4bqx_1 249h_1 4zmg_3 as01_2 dua4_3 2zch_3 4e8l_2 4lpb_1 3jji_1 4uxq_3 3y2p_1 asph_1 2ly6_2 456c_1 3rde_2 4tko_3 4l17_3 4328_2 4frp_1 3uzo_1 1y6f_3 1jw5_2 duq1_2 1oqo_1 4ijo_1 4c2b_3 59tz_2 41nv_3 4jue_1 2mh6_2 ajso_1 30wr_3 2anr_2 2cyy_1 24ir_2 4ru8_1 1gbc_1 e0rd_1 4b7t_2 431e_3 1zx4_3 4drx_1 2rvn_3 1dl8_2 421r_2 4suz_3 3q4g_3 4grj_3 3zmu_3 49zr_1 2cvd_2 4si1_3 2uoa_3 300v_2 1i44_1 21u7_3 47zw_3 31nl_3 3e0v_3 ars2_2 3hby_2 4q9k_3 1wz1_3 3xzo_1 4242_1 4t9s_3 bs7k_2 c3ea_1 c1v7_1 24yd_2 ae5d_1 aois_3 10mh_1 4g5r_3 4j6p_3 2t09_1 2o99_3 57nm_2 1gkr_2 2kf5_1 2kfw_1 1t14_1 4306_3 4e99_1 ee1i_1 1wtc_3 50lb_3 2f7v_1 2ihs_1 2l6d_2 22ub_1 ads0_2 4voa_2 3xzu_1 11bz_3 2g5f_1 39yu_2 39xh_1 145a_2 3546_3 4hty_3 4h79_3 1lkt_1 3dsb_2 11ce_1 bqlg_2 4e4u_1 42vg_2 4pxh_2 aquk_3 4ugz_2 2obl_2 2oqg_2 1hxv_1 3zmi_1 3tim_2 21ny_1 4c80_1 1qkn_3 286w_2 1jeh_2 3rq4_2 4u6g_3 2y9t_2 2wu1_3 1hq2_3 du2d_3 196r_3 3uwn_1 e3e1_2 30wo_1 3zsr_1 4ade_3 0y58_1 4mls_3 195m_3 198n_3 0szo_3 4u9y_3 1nss_3 10wp_3 1l61_2 126g_1 511n_3 4ejp_1 4dsa_1 42lq_1 3wkt_2 1doq_3 4xfb_3 aq2o_2 2y4w_3 1re0_2 0t0l_2 4keg_1 2rys_3 523x_1 4fyq_1 4jte_3 4tr9_3 4iro_1 29b1_1 1psq_1 29ha_1 3y02_3 4e4b_2 c8ef_3 2lws_1 4mde_1 5c6y_2 2lqq_2 42cj_3 5b18_3 30x5_3 49m9_3 4n2e_1 aflm_1 4l83_2 3v2q_3 4s0d_1 dz2f_1 2gny_1 1n1q_1 2kwm_2 5919_1 dxw9_2 dnkq_1 1710_1 du6x_1 5bl6_1 3a48_2 4itj_1 2rd0_1 3v6t_1 1yvu_2 44ag_3 28uw_3 4rk8_2 c2tf_1 0us4_3 125x_3 29y1_1 176p_3 40mr_2 28tn_3 arsb_1 aqy6_2 1ftg_3 3ut0_1 atip_3 2h0l_1 45pz_2 atfr_1 3wux_3 c9ga_3 5037_1 eds8_3 3wkl_1 4tf2_3 2no2_3 1b8x_1 1kcj_3 2w0h_3 1u6p_1 42t2_3 45t9_2 321j_1 4e20_3 4974_1 0zk6_3 1ly6_3 4hjs_1 bpz6_3 1s4t_2 0u17_1 42eg_2 4mlp_3 ccfj_2 4xhn_3 2m43_1 bpt4_3 4973_1 432j_1 1jan_3 3uwl_2 29z8_3 4twe_1 2csc_3 2x4j_2 dva2_1 3sp6_1 3s9y_2 cak6_2 426h_1 4v4f_1 4lcp_2 43vx_3 4rhm_1 4uxs_3 4xlb_2 2cgr_3 42eb_3 36r3_3 5dax_1 aehz_1 edkx_3 4tgr_2 3yl8_2 dysq_2 502c_3 2h31_3 3flh_2 2rtw_2 1t3v_1 ajue_1 4b1s_1 37gt_1 akzx_2 4vl3_3 42b2_2 5b2c_1 2yd1_3 0t7u_2 1u2y_1 3hov_2 2wm5_3 1ulc_2 e1qr_2 2dl4_2 aehp_1 3wes_1 57h5_1 5e7c_2 4lf0_1 cauw_1 4x83_3 3w8f_1 4hi9_2 1aqq_3 43c1_3 426j_1 1o8e_2 e329_2 3trs_3 2to9_3 1b4j_3 4jdd_2 1acj_1 0sw7_3 31ol_1 14yn_3 4ea0_2 dyln_2 4e9x_2 51xs_3 4qt3_1 40kk_1 4rtz_2 585l_3 c5lu_3 4j5i_1 4w85_2 4rid_3 5eur_2 e20e_2 4hwb_2 3lg0_1 3ajq_3 33er_2 4x01_2 1q6d_2 2fho_1 3zxb_3 499f_3 1q5f_3 4e4c_2 10dd_2 ate2_1 4k7q_2 2yle_1 2nrv_1 294b_2 58r5_2 4sv4_3 3c5k_3 0trj_1 2z7h_3 201o_1 dk27_2 3uwx_1 bn10_2 31xr_2 cevi_2 cdyc_3 0zx5_3 2ljz_3 4l3c_1 2xk3_2 0ukb_2 2rra_3 4w9g_3 2tfc_2 agl5_3 as8a_2 e4gc_3 39gm_2 2brp_2 1g8m_2 34qu_1 4hni_2 e8cp_3 2krg_3 0wrh_1 37bb_3 5a3w_2 1adv_2 3xq3_2 3jxk_3 1s6u_2 2w5c_3 dv8e_1 5d0h_1 3021_1 22pb_1 4e9w_1 18yo_2 3c7i_2 424e_1 c8f1_2 4c0f_3 25l8_2 3wjj_2 2pm1_3 29jc_2 2kdl_2 4w2y_2 4e25_1 atux_2 5exy_1 3g65_1 0y7i_3 1ig7_2 4jq1_1 2d7g_1 bw0r_3 alcb_3 e172_3 2dy3_3 4doz_3 am57_2 2yds_1 2cof_3 5cer_3 3pjy_1 c78t_3 4u5a_1 3h5u_1 3zqq_3 anad_3 48wr_3 1tbh_1 51e4_3 0z2a_1 ee5d_2 41it_2 27np_3 ameg_1 3hlc_3 1wio_2 4iy2_1 1c9q_2 57jg_1 25ae_3 49i0_1 442j_3 27lj_1 13ox_2 2wc0_2 39gi_1 4x1a_3 1vtw_3 2giv_2 2d0g_1 41t7_3 edw9_1 2a71_3 48tf_1 438q_1 1win_2 354z_1 45pb_3 dzf5_2 aizc_3 1aqh_1 boti_1 39ql_3 1uqe_1 0zzr_3 1fpa_3 36iv_3 3rsc_1 2g2d_3 1w2t_2 1aym_1 2yt5_3 4mrc_2 4i5n_2 57kr_1 dxpt_1 4j1z_2 c68f_1 4oid_2 c17b_1 ceer_3 1xwz_1 28fo_2 28zo_2 5a41_1 djzd_1 32kz_1 2cc2_3 bpw9_1 1ns0_1 4y0f_1 430v_3 4bqx_2 2lw7_3 dmui_3 2pfw_1 0un2_3 c4rk_3 3thk_3 3ti2_3 4bgn_3 1qea_3 3nrn_2 45c1_1 2527_3 58eu_1 42c0_3 2qyt_2 58vk_1 2yya_2 40c0_3 5ct3_2 1kch_1 1wti_3 582v_1 c6hk_1 aft5_2 23ni_1 22y4_1 4hjp_1 0z8q_3 4ke7_2 5erl_1 4api_3 2xuj_1 4zaw_1 dyiw_2 artw_2 ci34_3 2orf_1 149h_1 3onc_2 3934_3 4yg0_1 1d4r_2 3bcn_2 27h5_2 adb2_2 5fce_1 5de6_2 23gc_3 2buy_3 1gyh_3 ajk3_2 2zmu_3 56ra_2 bxwc_2 4zm8_2 1xsz_2 2jbj_1 4ke8_1 26mf_3 15z9_3 cgir_1 3occ_2 3ny5_2 0uaa_3 42aw_2 32jt_1 2kjv_1 47r4_3 3kw7_3 2lgb_1 2ua2_2 bylv_2 1s77_2 1ofs_2 3587_3 dlwc_3 2y7i_2 1ok0_2 agje_2 afke_1 4c5s_1 brdu_1 2g56_2 acpi_1 3yhi_2 4306_2 4bbp_3 4zls_3 2o7r_2 bn8c_1 4ew6_3 239d_3 51tt_3 c7nn_3 2vwr_1 44ff_1 0ukn_1 3m53_1 3vvl_1 0zsc_1 3f89_3 4ry2_3 4jq5_1 1ln4_1 1aor_3 4x35_2 2cul_1 3dc7_2 2fr0_2 2tr6_3 4wk2_2 4318_3 2jff_2 3smd_1 1ipp_3 2u6h_3 36yq_2 4huj_3 2c5v_2 4u6e_3 4ka8_3 5c1w_1 0xvc_2 1wlc_3 3y9t_2 40f3_3 2r91_2 at0c_2 e8gb_2 ccrm_1 30ev_1 0ywu_1 4prx_3 dvm6_2 4ktp_3 2blk_3 29lb_1 3oa4_2 44ls_1 4dkv_3 4ujv_1 2y9n_1 2a5z_1 3zyy_1 4r5e_2 4479_2 0wzb_3 dvf6_3 4qsi_1 2o1l_3 0y12_3 ci3m_3 1jha_3 0xef_3 0sym_2 1wn8_2 45iw_3 0ts9_2 1urc_1 ac4o_2 18hi_1 3uaj_1 57on_1 4aj0_1 3e13_1 akx8_2 56uk_3 2jhu_2 2zbe_3 42c0_2 1wup_2 4nk3_2 4xa6_3 2dss_3 4et6_1 13uv_2 4ke9_1 42a0_2 28hi_3 cagh_3 121i_3 2ma6_1 1xmr_3 4ijo_3 3pb8_3 38yw_3 4l9v_3 35sz_1 anhe_1 4qp2_3 58lg_1 4phz_1 38zp_3 0szr_1 1cfn_2 3rwg_1 2t2j_2 2x7v_2 1xad_1 2v52_1 4kfu_2 4ll6_3 49xy_3 dm17_1 17ca_2 dliu_1 432a_2 3uss_1 ae56_3 4yra_1 1ibu_1 2ik3_1 2ike_1 2ilg_1 2inv_1 2iq3_1 3jlb_3 0x5s_3 1ugv_3 bnmh_3 bnaz_2 3kh7_1 3mye_1 ciq6_3 1qfi_2 11x3_2 577c_3 4n9h_1 3grr_2 edyk_2 29k5_2 3qyt_1 3xwd_1 1h5g_2 5c9t_3 4y9k_1 c51z_1 bq3k_2 48cz_1 cemx_1 2l11_2 5awe_3 2qp4_1 1btl_3 dxna_3 4u2h_1 22zg_1 4eri_3 4j5j_3 dziq_2 adub_1 4g1i_3 4sth_3 40zz_2 cgay_2 1d8p_1</p><p>Here the last digit defines beam number and the preceding 4-character code can be used to retrieve the waterfall plots from http://talk.setilive.org/observation_groups/GSL000****</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig.2. Scheme of analysis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3. On the left: selection of narrow signal on Radon plot. On the right: vertical correlation on original waterfall plot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig.4. On the left: separation of RFI and potential ET signals. On the right: distribution of selected signals in comparison with Monte Carlo simulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>•Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig.5. Selected signals with highest SNR. The plots for all 3 beams are shown. Radon plot is shown on the right of every waterfall plot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. Selected signals with highest SNR (cont'd). Reconstructed signals on waterfall plots are shown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig.7. Selected signals with highest SNR (cont'd).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 1.1 to 1.9 GHz SETI Survey of the Kepler Field: I. A Search for Narrow-band Emission from Select Targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Andrew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Siemion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>&lt;arxiv.org/abs/1302.0845&gt;</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13pp</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Deans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Seti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Radon Transforms, and Optimization, Maximum-Entropy and Bayesian Methods in Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Radon transform provides alternative waterfall plots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;setiquest.org/blog/radon-transform-provides-alternative-waterfall-plots&gt;" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete Radon Transfrom</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gregory</forename><surname>Beylkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shekhar</forename><surname>Chandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;arxiv.org/abs/1006.1965&gt;" />
		<title level="m">Fast Mojette Transform for Discrete Tomography</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finite Transform Library (FTL), &lt;finitetransform.sourceforge.net&gt;</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Non-parametric structural reliability analysis using random fields and robustness evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Veit</forename><surname>Bayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dirk</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>WOST 3.0</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>Weimar</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stochastic analysis and nonlinear metamodeling of crash test simulations and their application in automotive design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Igor</forename><surname>Nikitin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lialia</forename><surname>Nikitina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tanja</forename><surname>Clees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Browning, J.E., Ed.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Nova Science Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="74" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computational engineering: Design, development, and applications</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
