<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CRYPTOPLANET UPDATE CRYPTOPLANET UPDATE CONSERVATION OF ANGULAR MOMENTUM UNIFORMITARIANISM FORMATION OF CRYPTOPLANETS CONVECTION FORMATION OF PLANETS CRYPTOPLANET CHARACTERISTICS 3 CONSERVATION OF ANGULAR MOMENTUM 5 HOWEVER, THIS CAPTION DOES NOT EXPLAIN THE FIGURE MASSES: SKATER 50 KG, HAIR 50G, SKIRT 500G 1/1000 OF MASS MOVES OUTWARD IN HAIR 1/100 OF MASS MOVES OUTWARD IN SKIRT ADD 1 KG LEAD DRAPERY WEIGHTS TO HEM OF SKIRT. NOW 3/100 OF MASS. ENOUGH TO REDUCE SPINUP ADD TO CAPTION: A ROTATING BODY TRIES TO MINIMIZE ITS SPINUP BY MAXIMIZING ITS MOMENT OF INERTIA 7 CONVECTION 11 UNIFORMITARIANISM IN GEOLOGY 100 YEARS AGO GEOLOGISTS WERE UNIFORMITARIANS. THERE WERE SLOW UPLIFTS, SLOW EROSION, SLOW LAYERING, AND THEN THE DEPOSITS WERE UPLIFTED AND THE CYCLE WAS REPEATED ALL IMPORTANT CONSTRUCTION TOOK A LONG TIME AT MM/YEAR IN 1915 WEGENER PROPOSED CONTINENTAL DRIFT THAT REQUIRED MOTIONS OF CM/YEAR AND UNKNOWN PHYSICS THE UNIFORMITARIANS RIDICULED THE THEORY, SUPPRESSED RESEARCH ON IT, AND PREVENTED PROGRESS FOR MORE THAN A GENERATION 12 THE UNIFORMITARIANS ALSO SUPPRESSED CATASTROPHIC EXPLANATIONS FOR EVENTS, EVEN VIOLATING COMMON SENSE AND EVERYDAY EXPERIENCE UNIFORMITARIANISM AND CONTINENTAL DRIFT WERE CONSISTANT AT ONE TIME WHEN ALL THE CONTINENTS MERGED INTO ONE, PANGEA, AND THERE WAS ONE OCEAN. THE MOUNTAINS WORE DOWN. THERE WAS NOT MUCH WEATHER AND NOT MUCH WEATHERING. EVERYTHING SLOWED DOWN. FORTUNATELY, THE CORE IS RADIOACTIVELY HEATED AND CONVECTION EVENTUALLY BROKE UP PANGEA OR WE WOULD NOT BE HERE TODAY 13</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2007">FEBRUARY 15, 2007</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">HARVARD-SMITHSONIAN CENTER FOR ASTROPHYSICS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CRYPTOPLANET UPDATE CRYPTOPLANET UPDATE CONSERVATION OF ANGULAR MOMENTUM UNIFORMITARIANISM FORMATION OF CRYPTOPLANETS CONVECTION FORMATION OF PLANETS CRYPTOPLANET CHARACTERISTICS 3 CONSERVATION OF ANGULAR MOMENTUM 5 HOWEVER, THIS CAPTION DOES NOT EXPLAIN THE FIGURE MASSES: SKATER 50 KG, HAIR 50G, SKIRT 500G 1/1000 OF MASS MOVES OUTWARD IN HAIR 1/100 OF MASS MOVES OUTWARD IN SKIRT ADD 1 KG LEAD DRAPERY WEIGHTS TO HEM OF SKIRT. NOW 3/100 OF MASS. ENOUGH TO REDUCE SPINUP ADD TO CAPTION: A ROTATING BODY TRIES TO MINIMIZE ITS SPINUP BY MAXIMIZING ITS MOMENT OF INERTIA 7 CONVECTION 11 UNIFORMITARIANISM IN GEOLOGY 100 YEARS AGO GEOLOGISTS WERE UNIFORMITARIANS. THERE WERE SLOW UPLIFTS, SLOW EROSION, SLOW LAYERING, AND THEN THE DEPOSITS WERE UPLIFTED AND THE CYCLE WAS REPEATED ALL IMPORTANT CONSTRUCTION TOOK A LONG TIME AT MM/YEAR IN 1915 WEGENER PROPOSED CONTINENTAL DRIFT THAT REQUIRED MOTIONS OF CM/YEAR AND UNKNOWN PHYSICS THE UNIFORMITARIANS RIDICULED THE THEORY, SUPPRESSED RESEARCH ON IT, AND PREVENTED PROGRESS FOR MORE THAN A GENERATION 12 THE UNIFORMITARIANS ALSO SUPPRESSED CATASTROPHIC EXPLANATIONS FOR EVENTS, EVEN VIOLATING COMMON SENSE AND EVERYDAY EXPERIENCE UNIFORMITARIANISM AND CONTINENTAL DRIFT WERE CONSISTANT AT ONE TIME WHEN ALL THE CONTINENTS MERGED INTO ONE, PANGEA, AND THERE WAS ONE OCEAN. THE MOUNTAINS WORE DOWN. THERE WAS NOT MUCH WEATHER AND NOT MUCH WEATHERING. EVERYTHING SLOWED DOWN. FORTUNATELY, THE CORE IS RADIOACTIVELY HEATED AND CONVECTION EVENTUALLY BROKE UP PANGEA OR WE WOULD NOT BE HERE TODAY 13</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2007">FEBRUARY 15, 2007</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1 2</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DAVE WILNER SHOWED IMAGES OF THE</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recent landmarks since the last Cool Star meeting include the detection of planets of a few Earth masses by radial velocity and microlensing surveys, and the characterization of several transiting hot gas giants.</head><p>Transiting planets have served as the Rosetta Stone to connect the abstract language of exoplanet orbits to the detailed knowledge of solar system planets, providing an empirical foundation to the nascent field of"exo-planetology".</p><p>Precise masses and radii are known for more than a dozen transiting gas giants, some discovered by wide-field photometric monitoring, others by radial velocity surveys.</p><p>For the brightest of these, infrared emission from the planet itself could be detected at several wavelengths with the Spitzer Space Telescope.</p><p>The Corot satellite is expected to discover dozens of transiting planets, possibly including ice giants and rock giants.  Today, this temporal baseline allows us to detect exoplanets at orbital distances of ~ 5 AU including many in systems already known to harbor an inner exoplanet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PONT'S TRANSITING PLANET</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PONT SAID, IN JEST, THAT EXOPLANETS SEEM</head><p>Analysis of incomplete orbits of longer-period exoplanets allows us to peek beyond this 5 AU curtain, and recent hardware and software upgrades bring our RV precision to 1 m/s, allowing us to detect exoplanets of only a few earth masses.</p><p>Together, these achievements have helped bring the number of known multiple-planet systems up to 20 (and counting) and test theories of planet formation and migration.</p><p>Although it appears that multiplicity among exoplanets is common, the search for a true Solar System analog continues. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXOPLANETS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FORMATION OF PLANETS THERE ARE SIMPLE, LOGICAL RULES THAT ARE THE SAME FOR EVERY UNARY LATE-TYPE POP I PROTOSTAR IN THE UNIVERSE PLANETS ARE SELF-GRAVITATING BODIES &gt; 10^26 G FORMED FROM PROTOSTELLAR DISKS AFTER PROTOSTARS FORM ALL UNARY DWARF LATE-TYPE STARS ARE FORMED FROM DISKS AND HAVE PLANETARY SYSTEMS LIKE OURS UNLESS AN OB STAR, OR A SUPERNOVA, OR A COLLISION HAS DISRUPTED THE DISK BINARIES PROBABLY HAVE PLANETS AS WELL BUT I DO NOT DISCUSS THAT HERE. QUESTIONS HOW ARE BINARIES MADE? WHAT IS THE PURPOSE OF PLANETS? WHY DOES A PROTOSTAR STOP GROWING? WHAT HAPPENS TO THE DIPOLE MAGNETIC FIELD THAT COUPLES THE PROTOSTAR TO THE DISK? WHAT HAPPENS TO INFALLING GAS ONCE THE MAGNETIC COUPLING IS BROKEN? WASTE MANAGEMENT EVERY UNARY POP I PROTOSTAR HAS THE SAME WASTE MANAGEMENT PROBLEM DISK WASTE PROPERTIES: RADIOACTIVE, SELF-HEATING MAGNETIC, FE ~ SI CARBONACEOUS DAMAGE BY RADIOACTIVITY, RADIATION, AND PARTICLES FREE RADICALS, BROKEN MOLECULES, POSITIVE AND NEGATIVE CHARGES CARCINOGENIC GENERALLY STICKY FAR FROM STAR, ICY 20 DISPOSAL METHOD: DISPERSAL NEARBY OB STARS, OR SUPERNOVAS, OR COLLISIONS BLOW EVERYTHING AWAY. IT IS FREE ENERGY. DISK IS WIPED BEFORE STAR IS COMPLETED OR BEFORE PLANETS ARE COMPLETED "URANUS" AND "NEPTUNE" ARE MOST LIKELY TO BE LOST BECAUSE THEY TAKE SO LONG TO MAKE DISPOSAL METHOD: COMPACTION</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>DEG LAT SUPER-CME ILLUMINATES BOTH SIDES OF THE DISK AS WELL AS THE INNER WALL RADIATION AND PARTICLES BLOW AWAY ALL THE INFALLING GAS OUT TO ~ SNOW LINE AND PUSH INWARD ON BOTH SURFACES OF THE DISK SO THAT DUST AGGLOMERATES. VAPORIZES AT SURFACE OPTICAL DEPTH OF POPCORN IS MUCH LESS THAN THAT OF DUST FROM WHICH IT IS MADE 30 PLANETS FORM SEQUENTIALLY OUTWARD RADIATION AND WIND FROM STAR HEAT POPCORN AND PUSH IT OUTWARD ORBITS MOVING OUTWARD CROSS STATIONARY ORBITS AND ORBITS MOVING INWARD AT AT SHALLOW ANGLE SO SLOW COLLISIONS WALL OF AGGLOMERATED POPCORN (= POPCORN BALLS) FORMS THAT ABSORBS 3-5% OF THE RADIATION FROM THE STAR NEAR STAR VOLATILES ARE COOKED OUT POPCORN AGGLOMERATES AND CONSOLIDATES UNTIL PLANETESIMALS FORM AND THE WALL BECOMES OPTICALLY THIN A NEW WALL FORMS FURTHER OUT WHERE THE DISK IS INTACT AND THE PROCESS REPEATS AS THE RADIUS INCREASES THERE IS LESS "COOKING" OF THE POPCORN PLANETESIMALS FORMED IN THE WALL ARE IN NEARBY ORBITS THE DISPERSION OF THE DOTS IN THE CARTOONS IS GREATLY EXAGGERATED THEY RAPIDLY GRAVITATIONALLY COLLAPSE INTO A PLANET NOT ENOUGH MASS IN ASTEROID WALL TO FORM A PLANET. LEFT WITH PLANETESIMALS SNOW BELT ICE IS ADDED TO THE POPCORN AND DUST IN JUPITER'S WALL. A LARGE CORE FORMS THAT IS ABLE TO PULL IN GAS UNIFORMITARIANISM WORKS FOR THE OUTER PLANETS SINCE RADIATION FROM THE STAR IS SO WEAK AT THOSE DISTANCES, THEY ARE ACCRETED SLOWLY BY UNASSISTED GRAVITY REMINDER: CFA Colloquium 4 May 2006 SPEAKER: David Wilner (CfA) TITLE: Protoplanetary Disks: Analogs of the Early Solar System ABSTRACT: [edited]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Analysis of the impact crater record of the terrestrial planets and the Moon implicates two populations of impactors that are distinguishable by their size distributions. The old population, responsible for an intense period of bombardment that ended 3. 8 Gy ago, is virtually identical in size distribution to the present main belt asteroids; the second population, responsible for craters younger than ~3. 8 Gy, matches closely the size distribution of the near earth asteroids. An inner Solar System impact cataclysm occurred ~3. 9 Gy ago, Many asteroids were ejected from the main belt on a short timescale, ~10^7 y, possibly due to a major dynamical instability owed to the orbital migration of the giant planets in early Solar System history.</head><label>889</label><figDesc>20 CLOSEST "PROTOPLANETARY" DISKS THAT ARE VISIBLE THROUGH SURROUNDING GAS AND DUST THE DISKS HAD UNRESOLVED CENTRAL HOLES WITH DIAMETERS &gt; 20 AU. SMALLER HOLES ARE NOT VISIBLE IN FACT, THESE ARE "POST-PLANETARY" DISKS. PLANETS HAVE ALREADY FORMED RAPIDLY OUT THROUGH "JUPITER" SPEAKER: Renu Malhotra (University of Arizona) TITLE: Bombardment History of the Terrestrial Planets ABSTRACT: [edited]FORMATION OF OUTER PLANETS RENU MALHOTRA SHOWED THAT URANUS AND NEPTUNE TOOK ~600 MILLION YEARS TO FORM AND MIGRATE INTO PLACE THEIR FORMATION AND MIGRATION PRODUCED RESONANCES IN THE ASTEROID BELT THAT EITHER DROVE ASTEROIDS INWARD TO CRATER THE INNER PLANETS, OR EJECTED THEM FROM THE SOLAR SYSTEM 46 FORMATION OF CRYPTOPLANETS DATE: MONDAY, November 20 TIME: 11:30 ROOM: Pratt SPEAKER: Frederic Pont (Geneva Observatory) "Transiting Extra-solar Planets: Towards Exo-planetology" Abstract [edited]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>TO BE DIFFERENT FROM OUR PLANETS AND THAT OUR PLANETS WOULD TURN OUT TO BE WEIRD THAT IS WHY I DECIDED TO GIVE THIS TALK "I think we're missing something fundamental about the interior structure or atmospheres of hot Jupiters." ---Josh Winn DATE: MONDAY, October 30 TIME: 12 : 00 ROOM: Pratt SPEAKER: Jason Wright (UC Berkeley) "Characterizing Exoplanetary Systems: The Search for Solar System Analogs" Abstract [edited]For 10 years the California &amp; Carnegie Planet Search has been collecting precision radial velocities of hundreds of Sun-like stars with ever-improving precision.</head><label>1200</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>THE</head><label></label><figDesc>ONLY CONNECTION BETWEEN PLANETS AND EXOPLANETS IS THAT THEY BOTH ORBIT STARS IN GENERAL: EXOPLANETS ORBIT CLOSE TO THE STAR EXOPLANETS HAVE MORE ECCENTRIC ORBITS EXOPLANETS ARE MORE MASSIVE EXOPLANETS ARE LESS DENSE NOT A SINGLE EXOPLANET CAN BE MATCHED TO A PLANET ANYONE WITH COMMON SENSE WOULD THINK THAT THEY ARE TWO SEPARATE CLASSES OF OBJECT A NEW CLASS OF OBJECT REQUIRES AN EXPANATION AND IMAGINATION I DID NOT BELIEVE THAT THE FIRST EXTRA SOLAR GIANT PLANET WAS A PLANET. NEITHER DID DAVID BLACK. I MADE UP A NAME FOR THE CLASS: CRYPTOPLANETS WHEN OBSERVATIONS IMPROVE THERE WILL EVENTUALLY BE EXOPLANETS THAT ARE PLANETS, SO EXOPLANET IS NOT A VALID NAME FOR THE CLASS 56 CRYPTOPLANETS WHAT ARE THEY? PLANETS ARE WASTE DUMPS FROM THE DISK MAYBE THEY ARE WASTE DUMPS, BUT NOT FROM THE DISK WASTE INFALL? WASTE ANGULAR MOMENTUM? WASTE MAGNETIC FIELD? SINCE CRYPTOPLANETS ARE CLOSE TO THE STAR, THEY ARE PROBABLY ALL THREE AND FORM BEFORE PLANETS START WITH THE SAME PROTOSTAR MACHINERY AS BEFORE STANDARD SCENARIO ASSUMES ISOLATED EVOLUTION BUT STARS ARE FORMED IN CLUSTERS IF THERE IS A COLLISION WITH A DENSE CLOUD, OR WITH A STAR, OR IF AN OB STAR FORMS NEARBY, OR THERE IS A SUPERNOVA, THERE CAN BE A PULSE OF ENHANCED DENSITY LET THE COMPLEX MACHINERY NOT WORK PERFECTLY SO THAT THERE IS EXCESS INFALL THAT THE DIPOLE MAGNETIC FIELD CANNOT CONTROL INFALL GAS FLOWS OVER THE SURFACE OF THE STAR TO THE EQUATOR AND THEN OUTWARD 61 EXCESS INFALL BLOCKS CONVECTION ENVELOPE AND ATMOSPHERE OUTSIDE THE MAGNETIC CYLINDER PUFFS UP, DECOUPLES, AND SPINS UP TO INCREASE THE MOMENT OF INERTIA COMBINES WITH INFALL GAS THAT IS ALSO MOVING OUTWARD FROM EQUATOR INNER CYLINDER IS A DWARF AND OBLATE PART IS A SUBGIANT THE MATERIAL CAN NEVER GO BACK SINGLE EVENT OR MULTIPLE EVENTS THE PROTOSTAR, THE MAGNETIC FIELD, AND THE DISK CONTINUE TO EVOLVE AS BEFORE FOR PLANET FORMATION THE COUPLING BETWEEN THE STAR AND DISK WEAKENS AND THE FIELD LINES WRAP IN PLANET FORMATION, FIELD LINES PULL OUT OF THE DISK AND FORM A TORUS FILLED WITH LOW DENSITY IONS THAT COLLAPSE INTO A SUPER-CME IN CRYPTOPLANET FORMATION, THE FIELD LINES PULL OUT OF THE DISK AND FORM A TORUS FILLED WITH DENSE GAS INITIALLY THE TOROIDAL MAGNETIC FIELD ROTATES MORE SLOWLY THAN THE GAS INSIDE WHICH HAS HIGH ANGULAR MOMENTUM THE WHOLE APPARATUS MUST BE HIGHLY UNSTABLE. WHEN A THIN SPOT FORMS FROM OSCILLATIONS OR WHATEVER, THE MAGNETIC FIELD LINES CAN RECONNECT PART OF THE FIELD FALLS BACK TO MAKE TO MAKE A SUPER-CME PART FORMS A FREE-SPINNING TOROIDAL RING, A TOKAMAK RING IS HOT AND DENSE AND HAS A LARGE SURFACE AREA RING AND SUPER-CME ARE VERY LUMINOUS. SUPER-CME PRODUCES STRONG PARTICLE OUTBURSTS RADIATION AND PARTICLES BLOW AWAY ALL INFALLING GAS OUT TO ~ SNOW LINE AND PUSH INWARD ON BOTH SURFACES OF THE DISK SO THAT DUST AGGLOMERATES. VAPORIZES AT SURFACE SINCE RING IS EQUITORIAL, IT MAY DESTROY MORE OF THE INNER DISK AND REDUCE INNER PLANET FORMATION RING IS UNSTABLE AND RECONNECTS IN SECTIONS 74 HOT DENSE PLASMA BLOBS ARE ENCAPSULATED IN SPHERICAL MAGNETIC BOTTLES, SPHEROMAKS. BLOBS ARE LARGE ENOUGH AND DENSE ENOUGH TO BE GRAVITATIONALLY BOUND WHEN THEY COOL, CRYPTOPLANETS MAGNETIC BOTTLES SHIELD THE CRYPTOPLANETS FROM ABLATION BY THE STELLAR WIND THE NUMBER OF CRYPTOPLANETS IS RANDOM, UP TO A DOZEN SOME OF THE CRYPTOPLANETS ARE EJECTED FROM THE SYSTEM, OR FALL INTO THE STAR, OR EVAPORATE, OR MERGE, OR CONTINUE TO ORBIT. CRYPTOPLANETS CAN ACCRETE NEUTRAL GAS MASS CAN VARY UP TO BROWN DWARF MASS BROWN DWARFS CAN BE CRYPTOPLANETS, FREE OR BOUND SPHEROMAKS A SPHEROMAK IS A SELF-GRAVITATING SPHERE OF HOT IONS OF MOSTLY H AND HE SURROUNDED BY A SPHERICALLY WOUND MAGNETIC FIELD THAT PREVENTS IONS FROM ESCAPING OR ENTERING SPHEROMAKS DO NOT HAVE EXTERNAL MAGNETIC FIELDS DO NOT ROTATE MUCH LARGE ORBITAL ANGULAR MOMENTUM ABUNDANCES UNKNOWN, NOT FROM DUST PROBABLY SUB-SOLAR LIKE YOUNG A-STAR VEGA, LAMBDA BOO COOLS RAPIDLY BY RADIATION AND CONTRACTS PRESSURE AND DENSITY KEEP INCREASING FORMS HEH+, H2, H2+, H3, H3+, HYDRIDES CARBIDES, NITRIDES, OXIDES, AND THEIR IONS 79 CRYPTOPLANET CHARACTERISTICS SPHEROMAKS EVENTUALLY COOL AND BECOME CRYPTOPLANETS COOL FOR A CRYPTOPLANET IS STILL &gt; 1000K. FORM TYPICAL PLANETARY MOLECULES BUT WITH NON-PLANETARY ABUNDANCES OPACITY IS NOT PLANETARY INTERIOR MODELS ARE WRONG CORE NOT AGGLOMERATED BUT LOW DENSITY SURFACE MODELS ARE WRONG PREDICTED ENERGY DISTRIBUTION IS WRONG CANNOT ASSUME SED IN INTERPRETING SPITZER OBSERVATIONS 80 CRYPTOPLANETS ARE A GENERAL PHENOMENON OF POP I UNARY LATE-TYPE STAR FORMATION THEY INDICATE THAT SOMETHING WENT WRONG WITH THE FORMATION PROCESS SO THAT THERE WAS TOO MUCH INFALL THIS MUST HAPPEN MORE THAN 1% OF THE TIME THE CHANCE THAT ONE OR MORE CRYPTOPLANETS WILL CONTINUE TO ORBIT THE STAR IS RANDOM THE MASSES OF CRYPTOPLANETS ARE RANDOM 81 CRYPTOPLANETS MAKE IT DIFFICULT TO DETECT PLANETS MODULATE RADIAL VELOCITIES BRIGHTER THAN PLANETS IN ECCENTRIC ORBITS THAY MAY SWALLOW INNER PLANETS IF THE PURPOSE OF SEARCHING FOR PLANETS IS SEARCHING FOR LIFE, CRYPTOPLANETS ARE NOT GOOD CANDIDATES A1 WHEN THERE IS TOO MUCH INFALL, THE INFALL FLOWS OUTWARD AT THE EQUATOR AND HITS THE INNER WALL OF THE DISK. THERE IS AN IMMEDIATE CATASTROPHE AND PROBABLY MATTER IS FLUNG OUTWARD. FU ORI STARS? THE BIRTH OF AN FGK STAR IS DEFINED AS THE PULLOUT OF THE DIPOLE FIELD FROM THE DISK SO THAT INFALL STOPS AND THE PROTOSTAR STOPS GROWING. THE BIRTHRATE FOR FGK STARS IN OUR GALAXY IS BETWEEN 1/DECADE AND 1/CENTURY. IT IS A ONCE IN A LIFETIME EXPERIENCE. THE FORMATION OF A STAR WITH CRYPTOPLANETS HAPPENS ONCE IN A MILLENNIUM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>TABLE</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>NAME 
Mplanet 
Rplanet 
Period 
a [AU] 

OGLE-TR-10 
0.61 
1.22 
3.101278 
0.04162 
OGLE-TR-56 
1.29 
1.30 
1.211909 
0.0225 
OGLE-TR-111 
0.52 
1.01 
4.0144479 
0.0467 
OGLE-TR-113 
1.35 
1.09 
1.4324757 
0.0229 
OGLE-TR-132 
1.14 
1.18 
1.689868 
0.0299 
HD189733 
1.15 
1.156 
2.2185733 
0.031 
HD149026 
0.330 
0.726 
2.87598 
0.042 
TrES-1 
0.76 
1.081 
3.0300737 
0.0393 
TrES-2 
1.28 
1.24 
2.47063 
0.0367 
HD209458 
0.657 
1.320 
3.52474859 
0.047 
XO-1 
0.90 
1.184 
3.941534 
0.0488 
HAT-P-1 
0.53 
1.36 
4.46529 
0.0551 
WASP-1 
0.867 
1.443 
2.519961 
0.0382 
WASP-2 
0.88 
1.038 
2.152226 
0.0307 

NAME 
Mstar 
Rstar 
Teff 
[Fe/H] 

OGLE-TR-10 
1.10 
1.14 
6075 
0.28 
OGLE-TR-56 
1.17 
1.32 
6119 
0.19 
OGLE-TR-111 
0.81 
0.831 
5044 
0.19 
OGLE-TR-113 
0.78 
0.77 
4804 
0.15 
OGLE-TR-132 
1.26 
1.34 
6210 
0.37 
HD189733 
0.82 
0.753 
5050 
-0.03 
HD149026 
1.3 
1.45 
6147 
0.36 
TrES-1 
0.89 
0.811 
5250 
-0.02 
TrES-2 
1.08 
1.00 
5960 
0 
HD209458 
1.101 
1.125 
6117 
0.02 
XO-1 
1.0 
0.928 
5750 
0.015 
HAT-P-1 
1.12 
1.15 
5975 
0.13 
WASP-1 
1.15 
1.453 
6200 
? 
WASP-2 
0.79 
0.813 
5200 
? </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
