<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:43+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On the orbital evolution of a giant planet pair embedded in a gaseous disk. II. A Saturn-Jupiter configuration</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hui</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ji-Lin</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On the orbital evolution of a giant planet pair embedded in a gaseous disk. II. A Saturn-Jupiter configuration</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Subject headings: planet-disk interactions -protoplanetary disks</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We carry out a series of high-resolution (1024 × 1024) hydrodynamic simulations to investigate the orbital evolution of a Saturn-Jupiter pair embedded in a gaseous disk. This work extends the results of our previous work by exploring a different orbital configuration-Jupiter lies outside Saturn (q &lt; 1, where q ≡ M i /M o is the mass ratio of the inner planet and the outer one). We focus on the effects of different initial separations (d) between the two planets and the various surface density profiles of the disk, where σ ∝ r −α. We also compare the results of different orbital configurations of the planet pair. Our results show that: (1) when the initial separation is relatively large(d &gt; d iLr , where d iLr is the distance between Jupiter and its first inner Lindblad resonance), the two planets undergo divergent migration. However, the inward migration of Saturn could be halted when Jupiter compresses the inner disk in which Saturn is embedded. (2) Convergent migration occurs when the initial separation is smaller (d &lt; d iLr) and the density slope of the disk is nearly flat (α &lt; 1/2). Saturn is then forced by Jupiter to migrate inward when the two planets are trapped into mean motion resonances (MMRs), and Saturn may get very close to the central star. (3) In the case of q &lt; 1, the eccentricity of Saturn could be excited to a very high value (e S ∼ 0.4 − 0.5) by the MMRs and the system could maintain stability. These results explain the formation of MMRs in the exoplanet systems where the outer planet is more massive than the inner one. It also helps us to understand the origin of the &quot;hot Jupiter/Saturn&quot; undergoing high eccentric orbit.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The existence of more than 40 multiple planet systems have been affirmed so far. The observational facts show that almost one-fourth of them contain two or more planets locked in the mean motion resonances (MMRs). This ratio keeps growing as new detection methods are adopted, e.g. the transit time variation method which is particularly suitable for detecting low-mass planets locked in resonance. If we set q = M i /M o , where M i is the mass of the inner planet and M o is the mass of the outer one, the resonant systems could be simply divided into two types: (1) q &gt; 1, e.g. 55 cnc <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Fischer et al. 2003)</ref>, and (2) q &lt; 1, e.g. Gliese 876( <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Marcy et al. 2001</ref>). The establishments of MMRs when q &gt; 1 could be explained by the convergent migration of the planets <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Masset &amp; Snellgrove 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Masset &amp; Papaloizou 2003)</ref>. According to the theory of disk-planet interaction, planets embedded in a gaseous disk may undergo various types of migration depending on their masses. Low(around several Earth masses) or moderate mass(around Saturn mass) planets usually undergoes fast type I or III migration, while massive planets (comparable to Jupiter) opens a gap on the gaseous disk and undergoes slow type II migration. In the case of 55 cnc, for example, the inner planet has a minimum mass of 0.87M J and the outer one has a minimum mass of 0.17M J , where M J is the Jupiter mass. For this mass configuration, the outer planet probably migrates inward faster than the inner one and catches the inner one in the 3 : 1 MMR. These kinds of processes have been explored numerically by several classic works <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Nelson &amp; Papaloizou 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Papaloizou &amp; Szuszkiewicz 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Kley et al. 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kley et al. , 2005</ref>), as well as our previous research <ref type="bibr">(Zhang &amp; Zhou 2010, hereafter Paper I)</ref>. Although the process is complicated, the convergent migration and the establishment of MMRs are robust outcomes.</p><p>If the above-mentioned mechanism also dominates the orbital evolution when q &lt; 1, then divergent migration should occur naturally and the establishments of MMRs would become ineffective. However, observations show that the MMRs exist in exoplanet systems of this orbital configuration as well. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> shows a list of exoplanet systems that contain two planets probably locked in MMRs. In fact, one may find that more than half of the resonant systems have q &lt; 1. How do these MMRs form? There should be a mechanism that suppresses or even halts the fast inward migration of the low-mass inner planet, so that the massive outer one could catch it before it is swallowed by the star. If such a mechanism exists, it may also help us to better understand the formation of a "hot Jupiter/Saturn" which survives the inward migration.</p><p>For terrestrial planets (tens of Earth masses or below), their inward migration could be halted by the density jump on the disk ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Masset et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Morbidelli et al. 2008</ref>). Otherwise, they could be captured by the high-order MMRs of an inward migrating giants( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Zhou et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fogg &amp; Nelson 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Raymond et al. 2006</ref>). These processes explain the formation of terrestrial planets in "hot Jupiter/Saturn" systems well, but could not account for the low-order MMRs in the systems whose inner planet is as massive as Saturn or even Jupiter, e.g. Gliese 876, HD 160691 and HD 128311.</p><p>So far, few works have considered the orbital configuration in which the two giant planets have a mass ratio q &lt; 1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kley et al. (2005)</ref> studied the orbital evolution of Gliese 876, which has q ≈ 0.31. They simulated convergent migration for the two planets and successfully represented the their observed orbital configuration, especially for the right range of eccentricities. To obtain convergent migration, they assumed that there is a preformed cavity at the center of the disk. The two planets are set inside the cavity so that the outer planet keeps losing its angular momentum to the disk and migrates inward, while the inner planet barely migrates until it is trapped by MMRs with outer one. This assumption in fact implies that gas accretion onto the center star should be so vigorous that the inner part of the disk is depleted much earlier before the formation and migration of the giant planets. Other processes like the magnetic field may also account for the inner cavity at the center of the disk. However, the relatively small radii of the cavity limit this assumption to specific cases. A more general and self-consistent mechanism to bring about convergent migration is required in a whole and regular disk. To construct a full-region disk instead of a ring, we adopt the Cartesian computational domain. Details of these domain settings can be found in paper I.</p><p>As shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>, we note that most of the planet pairs trapped in MMRs have q ≈ 0.3 − 0.6. A familiar and typical planet pair in this range is a Jupiter-Saturn pair, which is most suitable for studying the dynamics of this mass configuration. Therefore, following Paper I, we continue to investigate the orbital evolution of a Saturn(inner)-Jupiter(outer) pair embedded in a gaseous protostellar disk. We focus on the effects of various surface density slopes(α = −d ln(σ)/d ln(r)) and various initial separations d between the two planets. We will show the following. (1) Although under divergent migration, when Jupiter migrates inward, it could halt the inward migration of Saturn by compressing the inner disk in which Saturn is embedded. (2) When the initial separation is smaller than the distance from Jupiter to its farthest inner Lindblad resonance d iLr and the density slope of the disk is nearly flat, the two planets may undergo convergent migration and then be trapped into MMRs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref> The eccentricity excitation of MMRs overwhelm the damping of the gas disk. Saturn may get very close to the central star(a s &lt; 1AU) preserving a very high eccentricity. (4) We also compare the results between different orbital configurations-q &gt; 1 and q &lt; 1. These results help reveal the orbital architecture formation of some resonant exoplanet systems, e.g. HD 160691 and Gliese 876, as well as the formation of the 'hot Jupiter/Saturn' undergoing high eccentric orbit. This paper is organized as follows: the model including the numerical methods and the initial settings are introduced in Section 2; our results and the analysis are presented in Section 3; some discussions are made in Section 4, and the conclusions are summarized in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Numerical setup</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Physical model</head><p>We simulate the full dynamical interaction of a system including a solar-type star, a Saturn mass giant(inner planet), a Jupiter mass giant(outer planet) and a two-dimensional (2D) gas disk. The star is fixed at the origin of the system with both the planets and the disk surrounding it; thus, the whole system is accelerated by the gravity of the planets and disk. For efficiency, we ignore the self-gravitating effect of the gas. Therefore, the gravity exerted on the gas only comes from the central star, the two giant planets and the acceleration of the origin.</p><p>For numerical convenience, the gravitational constant G is set to 1. The solar mass (M ) and the initial semimajor axis of Saturn (R s0 = 5.2 AU) are set in units of mass and length, respectively. We locate Saturn initially inside the orbit of Jupiter; thus, the mass ratio of the two planets is q ≈ 0.33. Our aim is to investigate the formation of MMRs and the consequential evolution of the system with this orbital configuration. Considering that Saturn and Jupiter would mostly undergo type II migration, we adopt a relatively large viscosity of ν = 5 × 10 −5 to accelerate the evolution, and run simulations up to 2500 − 5000 initial orbital periods of the inner planet.</p><p>We adopt a polytropic equation of state and set the disk aspect ratio to be H/r = 0.04. The evolution of the gas under the gravity of the star and planets is solved by the 2D Godunov coded Antares, which is based on the exact Riemann solution for isothermal or polytropic gas. While the dynamics of the two planets under the potential of the star and gas disk are integrated by an eighth-order Runge-Kutta integrator, the global time step is the minimum of the hydrodynamical part and the orbit integration part. Details of the numerical method as well as the computational configuration have been well described in our previous works <ref type="bibr">(Paper I)</ref>. A comparison with other well-studied codes has also been presented in paper I.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Initial condition</head><p>One of the issues that we expect to figure out is the effect of the surface density profile on the disk. In this paper, we try several typical density profiles, which are only the function of disk radii σ = σ 0 r α . As shown in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>, the initial density distribution varies from flat to very steep: σ 0 , σ 0 r −1/2 , σ 0 r −1 and σ 0 r −3/2 . σ 0 is set to be 0.0006 in our units, which corresponds to a height-integrated surface density ∼ 200g/cm 2 . The density slope on gas disk results in a pressure gradient. To ensure that there is no radial flow at the beginning, we set the radial velocity u r0 to be 0 and adjust the initial angular velocity of gas u θ0 = rΩ g to balance the pressure and central gravity, where Ω depends on α.</p><p>Another issue is the role of the initial separation between Saturn and Jupiter. As shown in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>, we choose three separations: d ≡ a J0 − a S0 = 1, 0.5, 0.25. For numerical convenience, we set the initial semi-major axis of the inner planet (Saturn) as the length unit (the initial location of Saturn is always a S0 = 1). Then we adjust the initial locations of the outer one (Jupiter) to obtain different separations. When d = 1, Jupiter initially locates at a J0 = 2. At such a large distance, the mutual interaction due to gravity is negligible, so the two planets could migrate independent of each other at the very beginning. When d = 0.5, Jupiter is initially located at a J0 = 1.5. The position of the P J : P S = 2 : 1 MMR, where P J and P S are the orbital periods of Jupiter and Saturn, respectively is now at r ≈ 0.94, which is a little bit inside the initial location of Saturn. By doing so, Saturn passes through the 2 : 1 resonance of Jupiter soon after their release if divergent migration occurs. Furthermore, the first inner Lindblad resonance (at Ω = Ω J + κ/m, where κ is the epicycle frequency and m = −2) of Jupiter is located around ∼ 0.88 − 0.94 depending on the density slope α. Now the separation between the two planets is smaller than the distance between Jupiter and its first(also the furthest) inner Lindblad resonance, d d iLr . Thus, the inner Lindblad torque of Jupiter should be reduced by the existence of Saturn at the beginning of evolution. Finally, when d = 0.25, Jupiter initially locates at a J0 = 1.25. This location ensures that Saturn passes through the P J : P S = 3 : 2 MMR of Jupiter, the location of which is at r = 0.95. More importantly, this small separation d ≤ 3r mH allows mutual scattering due to gravity between the two planets at the beginning of evolution, where r mH = 0.085 is the mutual Hill radius of Saturn and Jupiter at this configuration:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">r mH ≡ ( M J + M S 3M ) 1 3 ( a J + a S 2 ).<label>(1)</label></formula><p>The initial settings of the disk do not take into account of the gravitational perturbation of the planets. Instead, we adopt the "quiet-start" prescription to setup a dynamical equilibrium to ensure that the streamlines of the gas are always closed when the planet is growing. Basically, we set the initial masses of the planets to be negligible, then we fix their orbits and increase their masses to Saturn and Jupiter masses adiabatically. At the end of their growth we release them at the same moment and start the evolution. Details of this prescription have also been described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Zhang et al. (2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Divergent migration and suppression of inward migration</head><p>Our main results are summarized in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. There are two main variables: the density slope α and the initial separation d between the two planets. To avoid confusion, we present the results mainly according to the sequence of the initial separations d. And for each d, we present the effects of the different density slopes first and then explain these effects together.</p><p>First, we start with a relatively large initial separation (d = 1). As introduced in the previous section, the mutual interaction due to gravity between Saturn and Jupiter is now negligible (d &gt; 5r mH ). Our results show that, at large separation, Saturn and Jupiter will generally undergo divergent migration or achieve equilibrium state, depending on the surface density profile:</p><p>(1) When the disk is very steep (α &gt; 1/2), Jupiter digs a clear gap and migrates outward after the release. In the meantime, Saturn migrates inward very fast until it clears its coorbital region(type III migration). Then Saturn starts to follow the viscous evolution of the disk, and its fast inward migration is halted or even reversed. This result is consistent with our previous result that the massive planet follows the movement of the global disk and moves outward when α &gt; 1/2. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows the orbital evolutions of the two giant planets embedded in different surface density slopes when d = 1.</p><p>(2) When the disk is nearly flat (α ≤ 1/2), both planets are under inward migration. Since Saturn is still surrounded by gas at the moment of release, it migrates inward much faster than Jupiter during the first stage of evolution. As Saturn keeps clearing its vicinity, inward migration is then reduced gently. In fact, we observed an equilibrium state where Jupiter and Saturn both stop migrating inward and maintain their separation when α = 1/2, see Panel (b) in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. This is also consistent with the results of Paper I, which showed that the direction of viscous movement changes sign around α = 1/2:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">˙ r = 1 2πrσ ∂Γ ν /∂r d(r 2 Ω)/dr = −3ν( 1 2 − α)r −1 . (2)</formula><p>where Γ ν is the viscous torque,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Γ ν = 2πr 2 νσ rdΩ dr ∼ r 1/2−α ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>which stays constant over different radii r when α = 1/2, by assuming a constant viscosity ν across the disk.</p><p>According to <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, one may find that both the inward and the outward type II migration of Saturn are suppressed. After several hundred orbits evolution, the whole disk has been well separated into two parts-an inner disk and an outer disk-by the gap opened by Jupiter. Saturn has also dug a gap in the inner disk. Although it is much weaker than that of Jupiter, this gap ensures that Saturn will undergo type II migration. Because of the large initial separation and divergent migration at the beginning stage, the gaps of the two planets will not overlap soon. Thus, the inner disk and Saturn could be treated as a sub-system which is shepherded by the tidal torque of Jupiter, see Figures 2 and 3. Then the surface density profile α makes some differences.</p><p>If the disk was nearly flat (α ≤ 1/2), Jupiter migrates inward gently and pushes the gas of the inner disk toward the central star. Thus the local surface density distribution of the inner disk is changed. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref>, the surface density profile of the inner disk is changed from flat (α ≤ 1/2) to relatively steep (α ≥ 1). When the local disk mass exceeds the planet mass, πa p σ M p , the migration of the planet is then disk dominated. To exceed the mass of Saturn, the disk requires a minimum local density σ min ≥ 1.5 × 10 −4 inside the orbit of Saturn when Saturn is located at a S = 0.8, which is much smaller than the present density of the inner disk (σ &gt; 6 × 10 −4 ). This ensures that the type II migration of Saturn is dominated by the disk evolution, which means Saturn follows the movement of the inner disk. On the one hand, the gas which flows across the orbit of Saturn from outside to inside exerts an additional positive corotation torque on Saturn, see Panel (b) and (d) in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  4</ref>. On the other hand, as the inner part becomes denser, the inner disk tends to spread outward. However the outward diffusion of the inner disk is suppressed by Jupiter(as well as the disk outside Jupiter's orbit), thus this local density profile is maintained(Panel (a) and (c) of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref>). As a result, the inward migration of Saturn is slowed down or even halted.</p><p>If the disk is relatively steep (α &gt; 1/2), Jupiter tends to migrate outward. The inner disk could now expand outward, and Saturn follows the movement of the gas. However, the Hill radius of Jupiter increases as it moves outward and the expansion of the inner disk is limited by the increasing width of the gap. Thus the outward migration of Saturn is also slower than that of Jupiter, see Panel (c) and (d) in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>.</p><p>The above results indicate that Saturn could migrate slower than Jupiter under some conditions, when they are both undergoing type II migration. If the surface density of disk is steep, both Saturn and Jupiter will migrate outward and thus, results in divergent migration, while in a nearly flat disk, the inward migration of Saturn is suppressed. Due to the large initial separation, the two planets would achieve an equilibrium state(Panel (a) and (b) in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>). How could they then approach to each other further and get into MMRs? One possible way is reducing their initial separation to enlarge the interactions between them at the very beginning of the evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">convergent migration and MMR captures</head><p>Next, we try a moderate separation d = 0.5 by setting Jupiter at a J0 = 1.5 and Saturn at a S0 = 1. At this distance, the initial mutual interaction due to the gravity of the two planets is still not important (d &gt; 4r mH ). However the indirect interaction becomes significant since Saturn initially locates near the position of the 2 : 1 MMR with Jupiter, and furthermore, it is also close to the location of the farthest inner Lindblad resonance (m = −2) of Jupiter. Our results show that the surface density profile also plays a great role in the final results:</p><p>(1) When α &gt; 1/2, we get divergent migrations which are similar to the cases with d = 1. The divergent rate is higher when a larger α is adopted. An important difference is that Jupiter migrates inward for a while right after the moment of release and turns back outward while Saturn had moved far away inward, see Panel (c) in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. This phenomenon indicates that, at small separation, the total inner Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter is weakened by Saturn(at the beginning of evolution).</p><p>(2) When α ≤ 1/2, we find that Jupiter migrates inward much faster than it does in the d = 1 cases, and the inward migration of Saturn is substantially slowed down. At this condition, we observe a gently convergent migration between Saturn and Jupiter. This slow convergent migration then results in the 2 : 1 MMR of the two planets and Saturn is forced to migrate further inward by Jupiter. Their eccentricities are greatly excited and maintained by the resonance, especially for that of Saturn (e S ∼ 0.4 − 0.5), see Panel (a) and (b) in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>.</p><p>These results can be understood as follows. At the beginning of the evolution, Saturn sweeps out the gas at the positions of the inner Lindblad resonances of Jupiter. Thus, the total inner Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter is weakened. The outer Lindblad torque then dominates the migration of Jupiter for a while. When α &gt; 1/2, their orbits become divergent because Saturn migrates inward faster than Jupiter at the first stage of the evolution. When their separation becomes large enough, Saturn's effect vanishes. Thus, the inner Lindblad torque overwhelms the outer one again and Jupiter start to migrate outward. Panel (b) in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> shows the torques exerted on Jupiter versus time when α = 3/2. It is clear that the inner torque decreases for a while around the moment of release. Then the inner torque recovers and overwhelms the outer one, while Saturn is quickly dragged inward by the corotation torque at the beginning (Panel (c) of <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>). Then, as its coorbital region is cleared, Saturn follows the expansion of the inner disk and moves outward. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the semi-analysis of each mth Lindblad torque (inner and outer) exerted on Saturn(obtained by the same method in paper I). One may find that the total outer Lindblad torque decreases a lot after the release while the inner one increases a little bit, and thus the net torque becomes positive.</p><p>The situation is different when α ≤ 1/2. Although the decrease rate of the inner Lindblad torque is slowed down when the separation between Saturn and Jupiter is increasing, the outer Lindblad torque still dominates the migration of Jupiter and pushes it inward slowly. In the meantime, the inward migration rate of Saturn decreases even more. This is mainly due to three reasons. First, as we have mentioned before, the inward migrating Jupiter compresses the inner disk and the steepened local surface density profile makes the net torque exerted on Saturn vanish there. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows each mth (|m| = 2−80) Lindblad torque exerted on Saturn at different time points. It is clear that during the first 300P S0 evolution, the total outer Lindblad torque is greatly reduced to the same value as the inner one. Second, the gas outside Saturn is pushed inward by the tidal torques of Jupiter. Parts of the gas flow across Saturn's orbit and generate an additional positive corotation torque on Saturn, which drives Saturn to move outward(see <ref type="figure">Figure 9)</ref>. Third, the disk between Saturn and Jupiter is heavily weakened by the gap created by Jupiter. As Jupiter approaches Saturn, more higher order(|m| &gt; 2) inner Lindblad torques of Jupiter and outer Lindblad torques of Saturn are cleared. Thus, both parts of the disk, outside Jupiter and inside Saturn, push the two planets toward each other further. Finally, when the disk between them is swept out gently and a common gap forms finally(see <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>).</p><p>Since this convergent migration is slow, the 2 : 1 MMR is then a robust outcome. When Jupiter captures Saturn into MMR, Saturn is forced to migrate inward to the vicinity of the central star, preserving a high eccentricity e S ∼ 0.4−0.5( <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>). This result is consistent with the observations, e.g. Gliese 876 and HD 128311. Faster convergent migration and higher MMR may be achieved by reducing the initial separation between the two planets further.</p><p>At last, we try a small separation d = 0.25 by setting Jupiter initially at a J0 = 1.25 and Saturn initially at a S0 = 1. Since d &lt; 3r mH , the mutual interaction due to gravity between the giant planets becomes important at the beginning of the evolution. Our results show that, although the steep surface density prevents fast inward migration, it does not determine the direction of the migration as in the previous cases. Now, the two planets migrate inward even when α = 3/2. The results are similar to the cases that have d = 0.5 and α &lt; 1/2, but the inward migration of the planet pair becomes much faster and more unstable. As the result of this fast convergent migration, Saturn is trapped into the 3 : 2 MMR with Jupiter when the disk is flat α = 0. For the other surface density slopes α ≥ 1/2, the 2 : 1 MMR is still the preferred outcome. The eccentricity of Saturn never gets higher than 0.3 in the 3 : 2 MMR, see <ref type="figure">Figure 11</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Comparison between q &gt; 1 and q &lt; 1</head><p>As we have shown in the previous section and in Paper I, both q &gt; 1 and q &lt; 1 configurations could result in convergent migration of the two planets and the the planets being trapped in MMRs. The observations show that more than half of the exoplanet pairs trapped in MMRs are of q &lt; 1 configuration. It should be interesting to compare the results of these two configurations.</p><p>First, the major difference between the cases of q &gt; 1 and q &lt; 1 is the direction of the common migration of the planet pair after they are trapped into MMRs. When q &gt; 1, the common inward migration is halted and the planet pair starts to migrate outward. When q &lt; 1, common inward migration is preferred, see Figures 5 and 11.</p><p>Since Jupiter is much more massive, Saturn in fact follows the migration of Jupiter when they are locked in MMRs. The migration of Jupiter is dominated by the torque balance between the gas disk inside and outside its orbit. Thus, the surface density slope of the gas disk is an important issue(presented in paper I). For a density slope that could result in convergent migration, e.g. α = 0, the relative position of the two planets makes a difference: when Saturn lies outside Jupiter (q &gt; 1), the total outer Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter is weakened and the inner Lindblad torque becomes relatively stronger. Thus the inward migration of Jupiter will be slowed down, halted or even reversed; when Saturn lies inside Jupiter (q &lt; 1), the situation is also similar: the total inner Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter is reduced when Saturn sweeps out the gas inside Jupiter and the net inner Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter decreases. So, Jupiter will migrate inward and push Saturn inward as well.</p><p>Second, the eccentricity of Saturn could be excited to a higher value in the q &lt; 1 configuration. When Saturn lies outside Jupiter (q &gt; 1), its maximum eccentricity could be excited to e S ∼ 0.2 by the 2 : 1 MMR and to e S ∼ 0.15 by the 3 : 2 MMR. When e S &gt; 0.15, the 3 : 2 MMR breaks, and the eccentricity is damped by gas disk quickly. Due to the damping effect of gas, the eccentricity of Saturn never increases to e S &gt; 0.2 even in 2 : 1 MMR. However, when Saturn lies inside Jupiter, its maximum eccentricity could be excited to e S ∼ 0.4 − 0.5 by the 2 : 1 MMR and the system is still stable( <ref type="figure">Figure 5)</ref>. This difference could be understood by considering the different structures of the heavily perturbed disk. When Saturn is located outside Jupiter(q &gt; 1), the gas disk would be separated into two parts after the two gaps overlap. As the eccentricity keeps growing, Saturn gets closer and closer to the out edge of the common gap or even cuts into the disk. If the resonance is strong enough, e.g. the 2 : 1 MMR, the effect of damping and excitation will allow the system to achieve equilibrium. Otherwise the MMR would probably break at high eccentricity, e.g. in the 3 : 2 MMR(see Paper I). The situation seems to be the same in the q &lt; 1 configuration since Saturn will meet the inner edge of the common gap. However, since the two planets tend to migrate inward together after the common gap is formed, Saturn usually forms an inner cavity at the very center( <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>). With both Saturn and Jupiter located within the cavity, the damping effect of the gas is negligible. Thus the eccentricity of Saturn could be estimated by mutual dynamical analysis. Denoting e S0 , the eccentricity of Saturn before p + 1 : p resonance, and a J0 , a J the semimajor axes of Jupiter before and after resonance respectively, we can obtain the eccentricity of Saturn e S which is excited by the resonance through the following equation(Malhotra 1995):</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">e 2 S = e 2 S0 + 1 p + 1 ln( a J0 a J ).<label>(4)</label></formula><p>For the 2 : 1 MMR, when e S0 = 0.01, a J0 = 1.05 at T ≈ 1000P S0 and a J = 0.58 at T ≈ 5000P S0 , both the above equation gives e S = 0.54, and our result gives e S = 0.5, which are in good agreement with each other(see <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>).</p><p>The third difference is the frequency and stability of the planet pair in MMRs. As shown here and in Paper I, the two planets undergo convergent migration more easily in the q &gt; 1 configuration. Convergent migration and MMRs are robust outcomes for all the surface density slopes when q &gt; 1. However, when q &lt; 1, the two planets are under divergent migration in almost half of the simulations.</p><p>It seems that, most of the exoplanet pairs trapped in the MMRs should be of the q &gt; 1 configuration(where the inner planet is more massive than the outer one). However, by considering the above-mentioned differences and the migration process of the two planets, we find that the MMRs in q &lt; 1 are more stable than that in q &gt; 1. In the case of q &gt; 1, Saturn and Jupiter usually reverse their migration to outward when they are locked into MMRs. As Jupiter moves outward, Saturn is pushed outward further and their orbits are in fact divergent. As the separation between them increases, the mutual interaction due to gravity becomes weaker and Saturn is easily scattered away by the corotation torque, especially at a high eccentricity(unless the gas has already depleted). For q &lt; 1, there is no such a problem since the two planets migrate inward and form an inner cavity at the center. Our long time evolution also proves this stability (T ≥ 8000P S0 , see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 12</ref>). This explains why the relatively high frequency of exoplanet systems have the configuration of q &lt; 1 contain MMRs; see <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. This relatively high frequency may also be a result of observational bias where the massive outermost planet is easier to detect by the radial velocity method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussions</head><p>In our simulations, the onset of convergent migration is much earlier than the emergence of the inner cavity. Therefore, in our results, the cavity should not account for the suppression of the inward migration of Saturn. We would like to indicate that there are two essentials that make convergent migration happen: the steepened density slope on the inner disk(compressed by the pre-formed giant planet) and the proper separation between Saturn and Jupiter.</p><p>The disk discussed here should be gas-full, otherwise it could not support the long range type II migration of massive planets. This usually happens at the early stage of the evolution of a protostellar disk. When a massive planet is forming, say Jupiter, it will substantially change the structure of the gas disk by digging a clear gap. The gas interior its orbit will be pushed inward and accumulates on the inner disk. If the timescale of gas accretion onto the central star(and other processes leading to loss of gas at the center) is longer than the timescale of this compression, the local density slope on the inner disk will steepen. The typical gas accretion rate of T Tauri star is around ∼ 10 −7 M yr −1 , while the gap opening process is only ∼ 100 orbits if we drop a mature Jupiter in an unperturbed disk(in fact, we have already employed a 'quiet start' method in our simulations to simulate the growth of planets and avoid the unreal initial impact to the gas. The planets all start with a mass of 0.1M ⊕ Earth masses, see section 2.2 and paper I).</p><p>If we take into account the growth of the planet(core and gas accretion), the gap opening process will be prolonged. However, according to the core accretion model of giant planet formation, for the core mass stays below 15M ⊕ most of the time. Since the lowest mass required to open a gap in a typical protostellar disk(H/r = 0.04, ν = 10 −5 ) is around 30−50M ⊕ , the planet would not change the disk significantly during this stage. As soon as its core mass reaches the critical mass M core = 15M ⊕ and equals to the mass of its gas envelope, the gas accretion steps into the runaway accretion phase( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pollack et al. 1996</ref>) and the total mass of planet would increase to 1 Jupiter mass within several hundred orbits <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(d'Angelo &amp; Lubow 2008)</ref>. That means, once the planet is massive enough to dig a gap on the disk, the gap will be opened and enlarged very quickly. So the gas accumulation on the inner disk should be a natural outcome when Jupiter is forming within the disk.</p><p>Besides the surface density factor, a proper separation between the two giant planets is also required. If the separation is small, the gas disk between Saturn and Jupiter would be weakened substantially when the two planets are digging gaps on the disk. For Jupiter(Saturn), the torques that come from the gas inside(outside) its orbit are reduced and it would be pushed inward(outward) by the disk outside(inside) its orbit. And, as the two planets get closer, the torque unbalance of each planet becomes more serious and the two planets would get closer. Thus, the total effect is that the gas disk tends to keep pushing the two giant planets toward each other when the gas between their orbits becomes more and more tenuous. When the two planets get close enough(the gaps usually had already overlapped), the mutual gravitational interaction between the two planets would prevent them from further approaching, e.g. the MMRs.</p><p>Our results show that the maximum separation leading to convergent migration is approximately d ≤ 5r mH (when α = 0). According to the core accretion model, the embryos of planet will accrete all the solid mass within their vicinities and achieve their isolation masses. This isolation separation between embryos is also d iso ∼ 5r mH . If we take into account of the migration of light planets(embryos) in the gas disk, the planets may get closer before they become massive enough to open gaps on the disk. Furthermore, the massive gas giants usually form in an area a little further outside the snow line, where the surface density of disk increases significantly due to the icing of water, and the collision timescale of solid grains is not long enough to prevent the effective growth of the planet core. So, it is reasonable to expect that some giant planet cores emerge with proper separations. This means that the initial conditions leading to convergent migration should not be rare, despite q &gt; 1 or q &lt; 1(q is the mass ratio of the inner planet and the outer planet).</p><p>To focus on the effects of the surface density slope of the disk and the initial separation between the two planets, we assume the two planets form simultaneously and the gas accretions onto planets(and the growth of planet) are not taken into account in this series of works(in both paper I and II). However, this does not mean that the accretion process is negligible. In fact, the gas accretion should become more vigorous on Saturn, whose gap formation process is well prolonged by Jupiter. Thus, we add some additional discussions about the accretion processes of the planets here. Many factors need to be considered when the mass growing of the planet is included, e.g. the formation sequence of the two planets, the time required to build a critical mass core, and the proper descriptions of accretion rate and range. We find that it becomes too complicated to concentrate on the dynamic evolution of the planet pair if all the factors are taken into account. To avoid the complexity, one could take a reasonable assumption that Jupiter forms first while Saturn is still a planet core undergoing gas accretion. Although, in a multiple planet system, the accretion process of planet makes the orbit evolution more complicated by leading to mass of the planets growing and various migration rates, we believe that the it may not change our main result-the convergent migration-qualitatively.</p><p>First of all, the accretion onto Jupiter could be neglected since the clear gap prevents the effective gas accretion process. Then we only need to consider the accretion onto Saturn. One could further assume the core of Saturn is already around 15M ⊕ and it undergoes fast type I migration initially. Since the direction of type I migration is always(or in most cases) inward, the convergent migration should still be a robust outcome when the planet core(Saturn) lies outside Jupiter(q &gt; 1). Comparing to the cases we studied in this paper, the growing Saturn may get closer to Jupiter and be trapped in MMRs with higher p(p+1 : p is the orbit ratio of the two planets). As the mass of Saturn core keeps increasing, the high-p MMRs would become unstable and lead to breaks or re-captures of MMRs(the resonances may overlap easily for massive planets at high p and leads to instability, see paper I).</p><p>When the planet core lies inside Jupiter(q &lt; 1), the two planets would undergo divergent migration at the beginning. However, the accretion process is fully runaway when the core mass is above 15M ⊕ . It will take only 200 − 400 orbits to achieve 1M J for an accreting planet embedded in a disk as dense as the one we adopt here and its orbit decay is less than 20% during this process <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(d'Angelo &amp; Lubow 2008)</ref>. When the mass of the inner planet becomes massive enough to open a clear gap, its migration rate will decrease significantly. Furthermore, as it keeping accreting gas, the inner planet should become more massive(than Saturn) and dig a wider gap, which weakens the disk between the two planets further. Thus, the gas outside the planet pair(inside inner planet and outside outer planet) tends to push the two planets toward each other(the inner planet only gets angular momentum from inner disk and move outward, the outer planet only loses angular momentum to outer disk and move inward) and results in a more compacter orbital configuration. So, it may also lead to the convergent migration in the q &lt; 1 configuration, when we consider the gas accretion onto the Saturn core.</p><p>A more self-consistent simulation should include two accreting and interacting planet cores as well as the thermal evolution of the gas around planets, which would lead to much more complicated orbital evolution and thus stepping into a new aspect of orbital evolution investigation. The relational results are under preparation now.</p><p>We also note that the characteristics of resonant systems with q &lt; 1 are the relatively large eccentricity and the short orbit period of the inner giant planet, e.g. GJ 876, HD 128311, HD 45364 and HD 60532. These characteristic orbits are easier to detect by radial velocity methods. Thus, this observational bias also explains the relatively high frequency of the resonant system in the q &lt; 1 configuration. The orbital eccentricities of the planets in these real systems are all less than 0.3, which indicates that there may exist other mechanisms that restrain the planets' eccentricities when the gas damping is absent. One possible mechanism which need to be addressed further is the interaction with planetesimal disk after the depletion of gas.</p><p>The tidal dissipation that arise from the star will drive the resonant planet pair out of resonance, when they are close to the center(D.N.C. <ref type="bibr">Lin et al. 2010, in preparation)</ref>. The eccentricity of the inner planet could be damped by this tidal dissipation as well. So the 'hot Jupiter/Saturn' would probably form in the q &lt; 1 system as follows: at first, the fast inward migration of the inner planet is suppressed by the outer giant planet. Then the two planets are locked into MMRs and migrate inward together. They dig an inner cavity at the center of gas disk, and the eccentricity of inner planet is excited to a high value by the resonance. As the inner planet gets closer to the star, the tidal dissipation gently drives it out of the MMR with the outer one. After the depletion of gas, the inward migration of outer planet stops, while the inner one falls toward the center due to tidal interaction with the star. Finally, the two planets undergo divergent migration again and the inner one approaches the central star more closely with a moderate eccentricity which had been damped by the tidal dissipation of the star. To ensure the validity of this process, we need to carry out further N-body integration associated with tidal damping, by adopting the results of this work as the initial conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>Following the paper I, we continue the investigation of the orbital evolution of Saturn and Jupiter embedded in a protostellar disk by running a series of 2D high-resolution hydrodynamic simulations. The main aim of this work is to find out whether the convergent migration also happens in a system with q &lt; 1(where the more massive giant planet is initially located outside the lighter one). To do so, we switch the initial positions of Saturn and Jupiter to achieve q &lt; 1 and focus on the effects of various surface density profiles of the gas disk and different initial separations between the two planets. From our results and analysis, we summarize our conclusions as follows:</p><p>(1). The type II migration of Saturn could be suppressed by Jupiter when q &lt; 1. As Jupiter digs a deep gap, the gas disk is cut into two parts -an inner disk and an outer disk. Saturn also digs a gap on the inner disk and follows the viscous movement of gas. Being shepherded by the tidal torque of Jupiter, the expansion of inner disk is suppressed. When the surface density slope is steep α &gt; 1/2, Jupiter migrates outward and the inner disk expands. The width of gap increases as Jupiter moves outward(a J increases) and the expansion of inner disk is limited, thus the outward migration of Saturn is limited as well. When the surface density is nearly flat α ≤ 1/2, Jupiter tends to migrate inward. Being compressed by Jupiter, the inner disk becomes denser and the local surface density slope α increases. Thus the inner disk tends to spread outward and fight against the tidal compression of Jupiter. When the expansion and compression effects achieve equilibrium, the inward migration of Saturn is slowed down or even halted.</p><p>In a system of q &lt; 1, this mechanism provides a way to halt the inward migration of the inner giant planet and does not require the overlapping of gaps. In fact, this suppression happens as early as the outer massive planet starts to compress the inner disk and makes the convergent migration possible. We also note that, the inner planet should also be massive enough to open a gap on the disk, otherwise it won't follow the viscous evolution of the inner disk and this mechanism won't be valid. The lowest mass required should be 30 − 50M e , depending on the scale height and viscosity of the disk.</p><p>(2). Convergent migration could also happen in q &lt; 1 configuration under some circumstances. The two main factors that account for the occurrence of the convergent migration: are the nearly flat surface density profile and the relatively small separation between the two planets. On the one hand, as we have concluded above, when α ≤ 1/2, the inward migration of Saturn would be suppressed by the steepened local surface density slope on the inner disk. On the other hand, as the initial separation between the two planets is reduced, the total inner(outer) Lindblad torque exerted on Jupiter(Saturn) is weakened by the gap created by Saturn(Jupiter). Thus, the outer torque overwhelms the inner one and pushes Jupiter inward faster than the regular type II migration. In the meantime, the inward migration of Saturn is suppressed and it migrates more slowly than Jupiter. As a result, the net orbital movement of the two planets is convergent.</p><p>The 2 : 1 MMR is a usual outcome when Jupiter and Saturn approach to each other adiabatically. If the initial separation becomes smaller, e.g. d ≤ 0.25 ∼ 3r mH , the inward migration of Jupiter is much faster and the two planets may achieve the 3 : 2 MMR. However, because of the mutual scattering due to gravity, the migrations of both planets are unstable when the initial separation is too small. (3). In the case of q &lt; 1, after Saturn and Jupiter have been locked into MMRs, they will migrate inward together instead of migrating outward, and the eccentricity of Saturn could be excited much higher than that of the q &gt; 1 configuration. After the stage of convergent migration, the gaps of the two planets overlap. As the disk between the two planets is cleared, Saturn is pushed outward by the inner disk and Jupiter is pushed inward by the outer disk. When the two approaching planets are locked into MMR, the mutual interaction due to gravity prevents them from getting close too quickly, and the separation between them becomes steady. Since Jupiter is much more massive, Saturn is then pushed inward by Jupiter. As they move toward the center, the inner disk is swept out and forms an inner cavity.</p><p>This cavity plays a great role. First, without the damping effect of gas, the eccentricity of Saturn could be excited to e S ∼ 0.5(in the 2 : 1 MMR), which is much higher than that of q &gt; 1 configuration and is consistent with the result of the analysis of two resonant planets. Second, without the scattering triggered by the massive gas within the coorbital zone of planet, Saturn is able to maintain the high eccentricity and be pushed to the vicinity of the central star. Our long-time evolution shows that the inward migration of Saturn and Jupiter is stable at the high eccentricity for at least T ≥ 8000P S0 . Thus, this cavity in fact ensures the stability of a highly eccentric system, e.g. 'Hot Jupiter/Saturn'. <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. A summary of our simulations. </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Case Configuration Separation d σ Relative migration Resonance 1 S-J d = 1 σ ∼ r 0 Divergent - 2 S-J d = 1 σ ∼ r −1/2 Equilibrium - 3 S-J d = 1 σ ∼ r −1 Divergent - 4 S-J d = 1 σ ∼ r −3/2 Divergent - 5 S-J d = 0.5 σ ∼ r 0 Convergent 2 : 1 6 S-J d = 0.5 σ ∼ r −1/2 Convergent 2 : 1 7 S-J d = 0.5 σ ∼ r −1 Divergent - 8 S-J d = 0.5 σ ∼ r −3/2 Divergent - 9 S-J d = 0.25 σ ∼ r 0 Convergent 3 : 2 10 S-J d = 0.25 σ ∼ r −1/2 Convergent 2 : 1 11 S-J d = 0.25 σ ∼ r −1 Convergent 2 : 1 12 S-J d = 0.25 σ ∼ r −</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">(a) σ ∝ r 0 (b) σ ∝ r −1/2 (c) σ ∝ r −1 (c) σ ∝ r −3/2</formula><p>Fig. 1.-semi-major axis evolutions of Saturn and Jupiter embedded in a gas disk whose surface density slope varies from flat(σ ∝ r 0 ) to very steep(σ ∝ r −3/2 ). The dash-dot curve in Panel (a) corresponds to the migration of single Saturn, which is faster than that in planet pair case. This indicates that the inward migration of Saturn is suppressed by the existence of Jupiter. Further more the inward migration may be halt(Panel b) or even reversed(Panel c, d) as the surface density becomes steeper. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-density map of the gas disk at different evolution stages, where the initial density slope α = 0 and the initial separation d = 1. Note that, after about 500P S0 evolution from release, the inner disk is compressed and shepherded by Jupiter while Saturn is digging a gap on it. This ensures Saturn moves with the inner disk. <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>.-density map of the gas disk at different evolution stages, where the initial density profile is steeper than <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, α = 1/2 and the initial separation is still d = 1. This steeper density slope prevents the inward migration of Jupiter, as well as that of Saturn. : the associated evolution of torques exerted on Saturn when α = 1/2. Note that the surface density increases at the inner disk and its local surface density becomes steeper. The outer Lindblad torque is initially much larger than the inner one, then it decreases very quickly while the inner one increases a bit after the release. And the corotation torque changes from negative to positive as some gas is forced to flow across Saturn's orbit from outside to inside. Thus the net torque is greatly negative at beginning and soon increases to near or even equal to zero. The outer Lindblad torques decrease while the inner ones maintain. Both the maximum of inner and outer torques move toward small m, which indicates a gap around Saturn is forming(surface density decreases around Saturn). <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>.-Panel (a): surface density evolution when α = 0 and d = 0.5. The inner disk is swept out by the inward migrating planet pair and a cavity forms at T ≥ 1000P S0 . Panel (b): the evolution of torques exerted on Jupiter. Panel (c): the evolution of torques exerted on Saturn. Note that the outer Lindblad torque decreases much faster than the inner one after the release moment. <ref type="figure">Fig. 11</ref>.-orbital evolutions of Saturn and Jupiter embedded in a gas disk whose surface density slope α is 0(Panel a), 1/2(Panel b) and 3/2(Panel c). The initial separation between the two planets is reduced to d = 0.25. The convergent migration becomes faster at small initial separation and the 3 : 2 MMR is reached when α = 0(Panel a). This system is stable for at least 8000P S0 at high eccentricity of Saturn (e S ≤ 0.6) when the 2 : 1 MMR is preserving. Saturn get close to the central star at a S &lt; 1AU .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-cross sections of the gas disk at different stages and the associated torque evolutions. The initial separations are d = 1. Panel (a): density cross sections at T = 0, 200P S0 , 500P S0 and 1000P S0 , where α = 0. The light doted line shows the distribution of σ ∝ r −1 as a reference. Panel (b): the evolution of torques exerted on Saturn, when α = 0. Panel (c): density cross sections at T = 0, 200P S0 , 500P S0 and 1000P S0 , where α = 1/2. The light doted line shows the distribution of σ ∝ r −1 . Panel (d): the associated evolution of torques exerted on Saturn when α = 1/2. Note that the surface density increases at the inner disk and its local surface density becomes steeper. The outer Lindblad torque is initially much larger than the inner one, then it decreases very quickly while the inner one increases a bit after the release. And the corotation torque changes from negative to positive as some gas is forced to flow across Saturn's orbit from outside to inside. Thus the net torque is greatly negative at beginning and soon increases to near or even equal to zero.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 7 .Fig. 8 .</head><label>578</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-orbital evolutions of Saturn and Jupiter embedded in a gas disk whose surface density slope α is 0(Panel a), 1/2(Panel b) and 3/2(Panel c). The initial separation between the two planets is reduced to d = 0.5. Convergent migration happens when the disk is nearly flat α ≤ 1/2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12.-long time evolution of α = 0 and d = 0.5 case. This system is stable for at least 8000P S0 at high eccentricity of Saturn (e S ≤ 0.6) when the 2 : 1 MMR is preserving. Saturn get close to the central star at a S &lt; 1AU .</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Acknowledgement</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System</head><p>No </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">496</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">521</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Angelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lubow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">685</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">560</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">586</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1394</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1195</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gozdziewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Migaszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">657</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">546</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guillem</forename><surname>Anglada-Escud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mercedes</forename><surname>Lpez-Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">709</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hueso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">437</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">727</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bryden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">735</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">496</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">641</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">420</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">556</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">296</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">642</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="487" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">494</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Snellgrove</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">478</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Szuszkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pollack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hubickyj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Podolak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Greenzweig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>MNRAS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sigurdsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">313</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1413</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Snellgrove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1092</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R A</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Laughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Toole</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">647</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">594</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">632</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">638</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C C</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">676</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">639</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">714</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">532</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J. -L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Aarseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nagasawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">631</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">10.-density map at different stages of evolution. The right Panels zoom in the inner disk in which Saturn is embedded</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Fig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
