<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:04+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Formation of multi-planetary systems in turbulent disks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2009-04-27">27 Apr 2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hanno</forename><surname>Rein</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wilberforce Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0WA</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wilberforce Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0WA</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Formation of multi-planetary systems in turbulent disks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2009-04-27">27 Apr 2009</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Turbulence -Celestial mechanics -GJ876 -HD128311</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We summarize the analytic model and numerical simulations of stochastically forced planets in a turbulent disk presented in a recent paper by Rein &amp; Papaloizou [4]. We identify two modes of libration in systems with planets in mean motion resonance which react differently to random forces. The slow mode, which mostly corresponds to motion of the angle between the apsidal lines of the two planets, is converted to circulation more readily than the fast mode which is associated with oscillations of the semi-major axes. We therefore conclude that stochastic forcing due to disk turbulence may have played an important role in shaping the configuration of observed systems in mean motion resonance. For example, it naturally provides a mechanism for accounting for the HD128311 system for which the fast mode librates and the slow mode does not.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Of the recently discovered 336 extrasolar planets, at least 75 are in multiple planet systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. More than 10% of these are in or very close to a resonant configuration where two planets show a mean motion commensurability, with at least five systems in or near a 2:1 resonance <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>Resonant configurations can be established by dissipative forces acting on the planets which lead to convergent migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. An anomalous effective kinematic viscosity ν, but with considerable uncertainty, has been inferred from observations of accretion rates onto the central protostars. The magneto rotational instability (MRI) is thought to be responsible for this anomalous value of ν but the level of MRI turbulence and associated density fluctuations are uncertain. The density fluctuations give rise to random forces on close-by protoplanets.</p><p>The influence of stochastic forces on migrating planets was explored first by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. They considered MRI simulations directly and therefore the simulation ran only for a relatively small number of orbits. Recently [4, and see references therein] presented a parameterized analytic model which can be used to predict the lifetime of resonant systems as a function of the stochastic diffusion coefficient. We shortly summarize this model in section 2 and focus on the stability of the GJ876 system in section 3 and the formation of the HD128311 system in section 4. We refer the interested reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for a more detailed discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">ANALYTIC MODEL</head><p>Our goal is to estimate the growth rate of orbital parameters and the lifetime of resonant systems analytically without making any restrictive assumptions about the orbits or the nature of the stochastic forces. We therefore add an additional term to the full Hamiltonian of the system that is linear in a stochastic force F. The new equations of motion can be calculated by elementary means and expressed in terms of the orbital parameters such as semi-major axis a, eccentricity e, periastron ϖ, mean motion n, mean longitude λ . Thus, the additional terms due to the stochastic forces are linear in F.</p><p>We assume that each component of the force F on each planet, in cylindrical coordinates, satisfies the relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F i (t)F i (t ′ ) = F 2 i g(|t − t ′ |)</formula><p>where the autocorrelation function g(x) is such that ∞ 0 g(x)dx = τ c , with τ c being the correlation time and F 2 i the mean square value of the i component. The stochastic forces make quantities they act on undergo a random walk. The square of the change of such a quantity A occuring after a time interval t is given by (∆A) 2 = D i t, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">D i = 2 F 2 i τ c is the diffusion coefficient.</formula><p>Considering stochastic forcing on a single isolated planet when D i ≡ D is independent of i, we obtain precise statistical estimates for the growth of the orbital parameters</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(∆a) 2 = 4 Dt n 2 (∆e) 2 = 2.5 γDt n 2 a 2 (∆ϖ ) 2 = 2.5 e 2 γDt n 2 a 2 .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>When two planets are involved there are two modes of oscillation (libration) which we separate and describe as fast and slow modes with frequencies ω l f and ω ls . To summarize our results, the ultimate lifetime of a resonant configuration of planets is determined by the time taken for the fast angle to achieve circulation. We determine this lifetime using equations similar to those described above but for the libration amplitude, obtaining</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">t f = 2.4 × 10 −4 a 2 1 n 4 1 F 2 i 1 8n 1 τ c 8.5ω l f √ q GJ n 1 √ q 2 q q GJ P 1 .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Here the first quantity in brackets represents the ratio of the square of the central force to the mean square stochastic force acting on the outer planet. The other quantities in brackets are expected to be of order unity, while the last factor q/q GJ is the ratio of the planet mass to the stellar mass compared to the same quantity in the GJ876 system. P 1 is the period, with the subscript 1 denoting the outer planet. We showed that this is in very good agreement with numerical results <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">STABILITY OF GJ876</head><p>We have performed numerical simulations of two planet systems that allow for the incorporation of additional stochastic forces with the properties described above. In order to mimic the effects of turbulence it is necessary to calibrate these forces with reference to MHD simulations. The only free parameters are the mean square value of the force components per unit mass F 2 FIGURE 1. Time evolution of the resonant angles φ 1 = 2λ 1 − λ 2 − ϖ 2 (fast mode), φ 2 = 2λ 1 − λ 2 − ϖ 1 and ζ = ϖ 2 − ϖ 1 (slow mode), the period ratio P 1 /P 2 and the eccentricity, e 1 , in the GJ876 system. The vertical lines indicate when the angles enter circulation for a prolonged period. The realization illustrated in the right panel scatters shortly after the fast libration angle, φ 1 goes into circularization.</p><p>numerical noise generator that we implemented, uses a discrete first order Markov process <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to generate a correlated and continuous force. We conclude from numerical MHD simulations that the natural scale for the diffusion coefficient is specified through</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">D 0 ≈ 10 −5 r 1 AU −3/2 M * 1 M ⊙ −1/2 cm 2 s 3 .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Of course we emphasize that the value of this quantity is very uncertain. In order to illustrate the evolutionary sequence we plot results for two realizations of the GJ876 system in figure 1. For these runs we adopted a diffusion coefficient of D = 0.42cm 2 /s 3 . In this context we note that reducing D increases the evolutionary time which has been found, both analyticaly and numerically to be ∝ 1/D. The times at which the transition from libration to circulation occurs are different for the slow and fast angles and indicated by vertical lines in <ref type="figure">figure 1</ref>. The tendency for the occurrence of very small values of e 1 can be associated with transitions to circulation of the slow mode, ζ being the angle between pericenters. We have verified this by considering the results from simulations which started with a larger value of e 1 . As expected, the attainment of circulation of the slow angle takes longer in this case. Also as expected, the time when φ 1 attains circulation is not affected by the change in e 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">FORMATION OF HD128311</head><p>The ideas presented above can help us to understand the orbital configuration of the planetary system HD128311. This system is in a 2:1 mean motion resonance with the angle φ 1 librating and the angle ζ circulating (no apsidal corotation) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>It can be shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> that the planets should exhibit apsidal corotation if the commensurability was formed by convergent migration only. Accordingly, it has been suggested <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> that an additional perturbing event (a close encounter with an additional planet) could FIGURE 2. The plots show two different formation scenarios of HD128311 including turbulence and migration. We plot the observed system on the right hand side of each plot. The plots show the resonant angles φ 1 , φ 2 and ζ , the eccentricities e 1 and e 2 as well as the period ratio P 1 /P 2 .</p><p>produce orbital parameters similar to the observed ones. This perturbation is needed to alter the behaviour of ζ , so that it undergoes circulation rather than libration.</p><p>We showed above that stochastic forcing that results from turbulence driven by the MRI readily produces systems with commensurabilities without apsidal corotation. This suggests that a scenario which forms the resonance through disk induced migration might readily produce commensurable systems without apsidal corotation if stochastic forcing is included. We present such formation scenarios that do not invoke artificial perturbation events in <ref type="figure">figure 2</ref>. We indeed find that model systems with orbital parameters resembling the observed ones are formed without difficulty and we are able to obtain similar final states for a wide range of migration parameters.</p><p>With radial velocity measurements continuously improving and dedicated telescopes such as Kepler many exoplanets will be discovered within the next few years. That will allow us to assess the role of stochastic forcing on protoplanets in a statistical manner.</p></div>
			<note place="foot">i and the auto correlation time τ c . The</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete Simulation of Colored Noise and Stochastic Processes and a/ f α Power Law Noise Generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kasdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics and Origin of the 2:1 Orbital Resonances of the GJ 876 Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">567</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="596" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The interaction of giant planets with a disc with MHD turbulence -IV. Migration rates of embedded protoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="864" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the evolution of mean motion resonances through stochastic forcing: fast and slow libration modes and the origin of hd 128311</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">497</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the evolution of the resonant planetary system HD 128311</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sándor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">451</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://exoplanet.eu" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Decade of Radial-Velocity Discoveries in the Exoplanet Domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Protostars and Planets V</title>
		<editor>Reipurth, B., Jewitt, D., and Keil, K.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="685" to="699" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Laughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Johnson</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Five New Multicomponent Planetary Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">632</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="638" to="658" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
