<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:13+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Hot Moons and Cool Stars</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013-01-02">2 Jan 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">René</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz-Institut für Astrophysik Potsdam (AIP)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>An der Sternwarte 16</addrLine>
									<postCode>14482</postCode>
									<settlement>Potsdam</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rory</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98195</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Hot Moons and Cool Stars</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2013-01-02">2 Jan 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The exquisite photometric precision of the Kepler space telescope now puts the detection of extrasolar moons at the horizon. Here, we firstly review observational and analytical techniques that have recently been proposed to find exomoons. Secondly, we discuss the prospects of characterizing potentially habitable extrasolar satellites. With moons being much more numerous than planets in the solar system and with most exo-planets found in the stellar habitable zone being gas giants, habitable moons could be as abundant as habitable planets. However, satellites orbiting planets in the habitable zones of cool stars will encounter strong tidal heating and likely appear as hot moons.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The advent of high-precision photometry from space with the CoRoT and Kepler telescopes has dramatically increased the number of confirmed and putative extrasolar planets. Beyond the sheer number of detections, smaller and smaller exoplanets were found with the today record being about 0.5 Earthradii <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. This achievement is of paramount importance for astrobiological investigations, as roughly Earth-sized planets may be inhabited -provided many other requirements are met, of course.</p><p>Habitability of terrestrial planets can formally be defined as a planet's ability to allow for liquid surface water. The presence of liquid surface water will depend on the planet's distance to its host star, amongst others, with the adequate distance range spanning the stellar habitable zone, depending on the planet's atmospheric composition and surface pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>. As of today, roughly 50 extrasolar planet candidates have been confirmed in the Kepler data, most of which are much bigger than Earth. These planets are likely to be gaseous and to resemble Neptune or Jupiter, rather than Earth. While they are not likely to be habitable, their moons might be.</p><p>Referred to exomoons, Martin Still, Director of the Kepler Guest Observer Office, said in his talk on the extended Kepler project during this meeting: "They are gonna come." So how can massive extrasolar moons be detected, provided they exist in the first place? And to which extent will they possibly be characterized? a e-mail: rheller@aip.de b e-mail: rory@astro.washington.edu EPJ Web of Conferences </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Detection methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Transit timing and duration variations of the planet</head><p>Two of the most promising techniques proposed for finding exomoons are transit timing variations (TTVs) and transit duration variations (TDVs) of the host planet. Combination of TTV and TDV measurements can provide information about a satellite's mass, its semi-major axis around the planet <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, and possibly about the inclination of the satellite's orbit with respect to the orbit around the star <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The first dedicated hunt for exomoons in the Kepler data is now underway <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and could possibly detect exomoons with masses down to 20% the mass of Earth <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. This corresponds to roughly 10 times the mass of the two most massive moons in the solar system, Ganymede and Titan.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Direct observations of the moon</head><p>Observations of an exomoon transit itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> as well as planet-satellite mutual eclipses <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> can provide information about the satellite's radius. Spectroscopic investigations of a moon's RossiterMcLaughlin effect can yield information about its orbital geometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, although relevant effects require accuracies in stellar radial velocity of the order of a few cm/s.</p><p>Moons in the stellar habitable zone of low-mass stars must orbit their host planet very closely to remain gravitationally bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. This will trigger enhanced tidal heating on those hypothetical moons and could make them uninhabitable. While a threat to life, enormous tidal heating in terrestrial moons about giant planets could be strong enough to make them detectable by direct imaging <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Tidal heating in moons has been observed in the solar system, with Jupiter's moon Io serving as the most prominent example (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). As tidal heating in a satellite is proportional to the host planet's mass cubed, massive planets provide the most promising targets for direct imaging detections of tidally heated exomoons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Characterizing exomoons in the stellar habitable zone</head><p>A massive moon in the stellar habitable zone can be subject to strong tidal heating and hence be uninhabitable. To estimate its habitability, we have set up a model that includes stellar and planetary illumination as well as tidal heating <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. If their sum is greater than the critical flux for the moon to be subject to a runaway greenhouse effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, the moon will lose all its water and become uninhabitable. In the left panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> we show contours of the orbit-averaged illumination plus tidal heat flux of a hypothetical Mars-sized moon orbiting a Neptune-sized planet in the habitable zone of a 0.25 M ⊙ star. Abscissa indicates the planet-satellite semi-major axis in planetary radii, ordinate shows orbital eccentricity. In the reddish regions this prototype satellite will be desiccated and uninhabitable.</p><p>Given sufficiently long observational coverage and high-accuracy data, the techniques described in Sect. 2 make it possible to detect and considerably characterize a sub-Earth-sized moon orbiting a giant planet. In the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> we show the TTV amplitudes of a Mars-sized moon orbiting a range of host planets. It is assumed that the moon's orbit is circular and that both the circumstellar and the circum-planetary orbit are seen edge-on from Earth <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>To determine a satellite's mass and orbit via TTV and TDV, many transits of the host planet need to be observed. Thus, to find moons about planets in the stellar habitable zone within the Kepler duty cycle of 7 years, one might be tempted to conclude that they can preferably be detected in cool star systems (i.e. around M dwarfs), because their habitable zones are close-by where a planet performs potentially many transits in a given time span. However, the amplitude of a planet's TTV is smaller in cool star systems, given a fixed semi-major axis <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, and the lack of M dwarfs in the Kepler sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> further decreases the chance of finding habitable moons in cool star systems.</p><p>Beyond that, moons of planets in the habitable zones of cool stars might not be habitable in the first place <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. The planet's sphere of gravitational dominance, i.e. its Hill sphere, is relatively small due to the close star. Hence, any moon would have to follow a very tight orbit about the planet. Moreover, the close star will force the satellite's orbit to be non-circular. Both aspects, small orbital distance and an eccentric orbit, will cause any Earth-sized moon of a massive gaseous planet to experience enormous tidal heating. Ultimately, stellar irradiation and tidal heating will sum up to a top-of-theatmosphere energy flux that exceeds the critical flux for the initiation of the runaway greenhouse effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Moons of planets in the habitable zones of cool stars will thus be hot rather than habitable.</p><p>To characterize potentially habitable moons, that is to say, moons in the habitable zones of K and G type stars, using the TTV and TDV techniques will take about a decade of observations, at least. With the Kepler mission being scheduled for a total mission cycle of 7 years, such a detection might just be at the edge of what is possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. The tectonically most active body in the solar system is Jupiter's moon Io. Its enhanced volcanism is driven by tidal dissipation inside the satellite. The two inlets in the left image, taken by the Galileo Orbiter, show a sulfuric plume over a volcanic depression named Pillan Patera (upper photograph) and another eruption called the Prometheus plume (lower photograph). The right image shows the strong orange infrared emission of flowing lava in Tvashtar Catena, a chain of calderas on Io. In extrasolar moons, tidal heating may be much stronger and even make them detectable via direct imaging. (Image credits: NASA/JPL)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Hot Planets and Cool Stars r u n a w a y g r e e n h o u s e E a r t h s ' s a b s o r b e d f lFigure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Left: Total top-of-the-atmosphere flux (in logarithmic units of W/m 2 ) of a Mars-sized moon about a Neptune-sized planet in the habitable zone of a 0.25 M ⊙ star. Tidal heating increases with decreasing semi-major axis a ps (abscissa) and increasing eccentricity e ps (ordinate). Some examples for orbital elements of solar system moons are indicated. Right: Amplitude of the transit timing variation (dashed lines) for a Mass-sized moon about a range of host planets. Planetary masses are shown in Earth masses on the ordinate. The habitable edge [21] is indicated for three different orbital eccentricities e ps of the satellite: 0.1, 0.01, and 0.001.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Muirhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Apps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pineda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bottom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rojas-Ayala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schlawin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1201.2189</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">747</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whitmire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Levrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Paillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0710.5294</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">476</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sartoretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">553</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Szatmáry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0705.1046</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">470</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0810.2243</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">392</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0904.2565</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1797</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Á</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nesvorný</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1201.0752</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">750</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fossey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Campanella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0907.3909</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">400</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Szatmáry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Divéki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">450</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">601186</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R M</forename><surname>Tusnski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Valio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1111.5599</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">743</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Physical Journal Web of Conferences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1009</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1105.3499</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">416</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">703609</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1111.1741</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">420</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1630</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Szatmáry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2038</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1207.6966</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">758</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1209.0050</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">545</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1210.5172</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1209.4418</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1209.5323</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pierrehumbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of Planetary Climate</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caldwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Christiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mullally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1202.5852</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
