<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:13+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Equations of Magnetoquasigeostrophy</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013-01-02">2 Jan 2013 August 13, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Umurhan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Queen Mary University of London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E1 4NS</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">U.K</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Natural Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California Merced</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>95343</postCode>
									<settlement>Merced</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Equations of Magnetoquasigeostrophy</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2013-01-02">2 Jan 2013 August 13, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. mQG˙eqns˙AA˙v5 c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Hydrodynamics</term>
					<term>Magnetohydrodynamics</term>
					<term>Exoplanets</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. The dynamics contained in magnetized layers of exoplanet atmospheres are important to understand in order to characterize what observational signatures they may provide for future observations. It is important to develop a framework to begin studying and learning the physical processes possible under those conditions and what, if any, features contained in them may be observed in future observation missions. Aims. The aims of this study is to formally derive, from scaling arguments, a manageable reduced set of equations for analysis, i.e. a magnetic formulation of the equations of quasigeostrophy appropriate for a multi-layer atmosphere. We check these derived equations for consistency with respect to similar equations currently used in the literature like the magnetized shallow water equations and their precursors. The main goal is to provide a simpler theoretical platform to explore the dynamics possible within confined magnetized layers of exoplanet atmospheres. Methods. We primarily use scaling arguments to derive the reduced equations of &quot;magnetoquasigeostrophy&quot; which assumes dynamics to take place in an atmospheric layer which is vertically thin compared to its horizontal scales. Furthermore, the derivation exploits the fact that the Rossby Numbers of the emergent flows are small and that the Cowling Number is also near 1, the latter of which measures the relative content the energy per unit volume contained in the magnetic field to the corresponding kinetic energy of the flow. Results. The magnetized incarnation of the quasigeostrophic equations for a two-layer system are fully rederived from scaling arguments. The resulting equation set retains features existing in standard shallow-water magnetohydrodynamic equations but are absent in more classical derivations of the quasi-geostrophic limit, namely, the non-divergence of the in-plane components of the magnetic field. We liken this non-divergence of the in-plane magnetic fields as indicative of a quantity whose behaviour mimics a two-dimensional &quot;pseudo&quot;-magnetic monopole source. We also find, using the same scaling argument procedures, appropriate limits of the fundamental parameters of the system which yield reduced equations describing the flow dynamics primarily characterized by magnetostrophic balance. Conclusions. The standard scaling arguments employed here show how traditional magnetized quasigeostrophic equations connect to their magnetized shallow water forms. The equations derived are amenable to analysis using well-known techniques.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>It is now generally accepted that hot extrasolar giant planets ("hot-Jupiters") are commonplace in the Galaxy. Many orbit their parent stars in so close that recent calculations by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Koskinen et al. (2010)</ref> indicate that the upper atmospheric layers of these hot-Jupiters are sufficiently irradiated by the parent star's UV radiation field (and therefore sufficiently ionized) to treat the gas as a plasma. It is important therefore to understand what sorts of observational indications these upper layers may show to future telescope missions. Model atmosphere calculations show that these upper layers are likely to be stably stratified (like the Earth's stratosphere) and, therefore, it is justifiable to use global circulation models to describe and explore their flow dynamics <ref type="bibr">(Cooper &amp; Showman 2002</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, Cho et al. 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">, Menou &amp; Rauscher 2009</ref>, to name only a few). Preliminary examinations of the response of magnetized shallow-water models of exoplanets reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cho (2008)</ref> indicate that under not-too unreasonable conditions, the atmospheres of irradiated exoplanets could settle into a collection of stationary, planetary scale, magnetized vortices with zero total circulation. If this turns out to be a robust feature for hot irradiated Jupiters (for instance) then there will be obsevational consequences which may be detectable by the next generation of space missions.</p><p>The aim of this work is to begin to formulate a systematic approach toward understanding the dynamics of stably stratified flows on exoplanets under the influence of magnetohydrodynamic effects which are usually absent in standard meteorological modeling. The simplest place to begin exploring these kind of dynamics is in a quasi-geostrophic ("QG" for short) framework which is a setting representing dynamics (i) occurring on synoptic scales (horizontal scale dynamics which are much smaller than the planetary radius), (ii) described by order 1 Burger numbers and (iii) characterized by small Rossby number flows. The last of these is a measure of the ratio of the typical rotation time of the planet to the circulation time of a synoptic scale vortical structure. The Burger number is also a ratio between the planet's rotation time to the gravity wave propagation time across the synoptic scale. If such an atmosphere is also magnetic, then another important number governing the quality of the dynamics will be the Cowling number which measures the the relative importance of the Lorentz force. The Cowling Number here will be understood as the ratio of the energy contained in the magnetic field to the kinetic energy in vortical motions.</p><p>When the Cowling number becomes an order 1 quantity QG dynamics will be substantially modified. Examination of magnetohydrodynamic modified quasigeostrophic flow goes back to the original series of studies in the thesis work of Gilman (Gilman 1967a-c) motivated by the problem of solar differential rotation. The model equations derived in Gilman's original studies are the magnetohydrodynamic analog of the classical quasigeostrophic equations on a β-plane. In these equations the magnetic field is strictly two-dimensional and horizontal, where it is assumed that the magnetic energy content contained in this layer is outweighed by the energy contained in the hydrostatic configuration. As a result, the in-plane magnetic field does not figure into the lowest order geostrophic balance. Furthermore, the field lines, although they behave two-dimensionally, can generate vertical field lines through the action of vertical layer undulations. The variation scales of these vertical field fluctuations are, however, small compared to the horizontal divergences (at next order) and, thus, though vertical field lines may be generated they play no dynamical role in the equations of motion at lowest order.</p><p>These equations also support Rossby waves and Alfven waves, often referred to by their hybridized forms as 'hydromagnetic-planetary' waves <ref type="bibr">(Acheson &amp; Hide 1973)</ref>. Unlike the situation in classical QG, however, the magnetoquasigeostrophic equation (MGQ) set cannot be characterized by a conserved quantity like the potential vorticity in QG. However, the magnetic potential function (sometimes called a "flux"-function) is a materially conserved quantity of these equations. Also, motivated by meteorological modeling, Gilman (1967b) extended the basic MGQ formalism onto a multi-layer "stacked" model where the density in each layer are constant possibly differing from each other. As it is one of our goals to formulate something similar, Gilman's study shall serve as a guiding procedure in this respect.</p><p>The magnetohydrodynamic version of classical shallow water equations (hereafter SWMHD) was developed in Gilman (2000) in order to address the problem of the solar tachocline <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Spiegel &amp; Zahn, 1992)</ref>. The SWMHD are model equations confined to a thin-shell of magnetized gas which is stably (or marginally) stratified. In the familiar non-magnetized setting, the shallow water equations retain the action of gravity waves while the more simplified QG models do not. Gravity waves are absent in the latter because the Burger numbers are order 1 in QG, and since the timescales for dynamics in QG are much longer than the local planetary rotation time (because the Rossby number is small), it means that gravity waves are filtered out. In this sense, one may regard the shallow water equations as containing "more" physics over the QG set. The same is true of the SWMHD model in that it retains the hydromagnetic planetary waves found in the MGQ set and it further supports magnetically modified gravity waves whose properties and structure has received recent scrutiny ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Schecter et al. 2001</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">, Zaqarashvili et al. 2007</ref><ref type="bibr">, Heng &amp; Spitkovsky 2009</ref>.</p><p>Besides the absence of magnetically modified gravity waves, the SWMHD equations and the original MGQ models also diverge from one another in content because the horizontal divergence of the magnetic fields are not zero in SWMHD as they are in the original classical MGQ equations. This means that, for example, the dynamical evolution of the horizontal fields cannot be formulated in terms of the evolution of a scalar 'flux-function' as is usually done for horizontal-divergence free fields. It is shown in this study that one can view this non-divergence of the horizontal fields as corresponding to the presence of a globally conserved, two-dimensionally distributed "pseudo"-magnetic monopole charge, q (m) (x, y, t). 1 Therefore, in this sense, one may characterize the solutions contained within the various model approximations according to whether or not q (m) is zero. For example, the MGQ developed in the original papers of Gilman from 1967-8 have q (m) = 0 while the SWMHD models have q (m) = 0 in general.</p><p>What is achieved in this work: Since classical QG offers a sound conceptual platform to focus on and understand the dynamics of (mainly) small Rossby number vortical flows, it would be logical to start studying magnetized exoplanet atmospheres from a similar vantage point. It makes sense to begin this exploration from a MGQ framework and, once having uncovered some of the dynamics that this set of equations contain, verifying that some facet of these dynamics are contained in the SWMHD equations. However, some ambiguity persists as to the fate of the so-called "pseudo"-magnetic monopole distribution in the reduced MGQ system as it is identically zero in Gilman's original studies but clearly present in SWMHD. Does the MGQ framework contain some features of this "pseudo"-magnetic monopole field q (m) ? The answer is yes and it is one of our goals here to develop an intermediate framework to study magneto-vortical dynamics free of gravity waves but not necessarily free of the q (m) field. In this work the MGQ equations for arbitrary number of vertical layers of constant density is re-derived using familiar scale analysis techniques as, for instance, found in Vallis (2006) (see also <ref type="bibr">Pedlosky 1987)</ref>. We display the derived equations for a two-layer model. We show how the various aforementioned features between equation sets relate to one another.</p><p>The procedure implemented to derive the MGQ equations are sufficiently general also to establish the scalings which lead to magnetostrophic balance <ref type="bibr">(Acheson &amp; Hide, 1973)</ref>. Magnetostrophy is a limiting form for small Rossby numbers in which dominant dynamical balance exists between Coriolis, pressure and Lorentz forces. The magnetostrophic approximation has been extensively explored to study the Earth's geodynamo and associated turbulence (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fearn 1997</ref><ref type="bibr">, Moffat 2008</ref>). In our analysis and overall setting we find that the magnetostrophic balance at low Rossby numbers is achieved when (i) the Cowling number is sufficiently large in proportion to the inverse Rossby number and (ii) the Burger number is small in proportion to the Rossby number. After establishing this fundamental magnetostrophic balance we proceed to derive a set of self-contained equations describing dynamics which are analogous to the MGQ set. We only derive the resulting equations here and shall return to a more thorough discussion of them in a follow-up study.</p><p>In Section 2 the equations and assumptions are presented. In Section 3 the equations of motion are expanded around a given latitude, scaled and analyzed. In this section we formally define the non-dimensional parameters of the system and scale the equations of motion. Most importantly, we highlight the fundamental relationships that must be met between the various parameters in order to attain the aforementioned MGQ and magnetostrophic balancing. The actual expansion procedure completing the derivation of the MGQ equations is detailed in Section 4 while the same is done for the magnetostrophic set in Section 5. Because the main focus of this study is about the MGQ equations, in Section 6 they are summarized followed by a brief discussion demonstrating how a MGQ model reduction does exist which retains the q (m) field and how, most importantly, the classical MGQ system is recovered when q (m) is set to zero.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Equations and assumptions: an overview</head><p>The general equations of motion of an ideal, incompressible MHD fluid in a frame rotating with rotation vector Ω are</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">dU dT + 2ΩcurlU = 1 ρ gradP − gˆrgˆr + 1 ρ JcurlB,<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">div · U = 0, (2) ∂B ∂T + curl(U curlB) = 0,<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">div · B = 0,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where "div", "grad" and "curl" are the corresponding three dimensional operations of divergence, gradient and curl respectively. These equations will be considered in the next section in a Cartesionized representation around a point at some latitude located suitably away from the planet's equator. In the Cartesionized frame, X represents the zonal (longitudinal/east-west) direction while Y represents the meridional (latitudinal/north-south) direction while Z represents the vertical (i.e. planetary radius) direction. The corresponding velocities are (respectively) U, V, W while the magnetic fields are B X , B Y , B Z . P represents the pressure. We consider the dynamics of these equations subject to the following setting and restrictions:</p><p>1. The planetary β-plane, nominally centreed on a latitudinal zone which is significantly away from the planet's equatorial zone. 2. The dynamics of small Rossby number disturbances (i.e. Ro ≪ 1) are of interest so that we may develop the equations as a power series in this quantity . 3. As is standard practice in atmosphere modeling, we break the atmosphere up into several layers. We assume that the background density fields in each vertical layer is constant so that each layer is effectively incompressible as implied by (2). The layers, however, may have differing densities each given by ρ i where i denotes the layer under consideration. 4. We shall allow for either none, some or all of the layers to be electrically conducting so that MHD will be a good description of the dynamics in those layers that are magnetically active. This is why the induction equations for ideal MHD are included.</p><p>In the majority of the analysis performed in this study the dynamics are treated in two-layers. However, for the sake of generality of the procedures we implement, let us consider the possibility of an arbitrary number of constantdensity layers with, as yet, unassigned conductivity. Let us suppose that the heights delineating the transition from one constant density layer to another is given by H 1 &lt; H 2 respectively where Z = 0 represents the nominal "bottom" of the atmosphere (see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>). Then the prescription for the current J will be represented in this way by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">J = ϕcurlB; ϕ =              ϕ N , H N −1 &lt; Z ≤ H N . . . . . . ϕ i , H i−1 &lt; Z ≤ H i . . .</formula><p>. . .</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ϕ 1 , 0 ≤ Z ≤ H 1 (5)</formula><p>The functions ϕ i will take on either the values 0 or 1 depending upon the layer i. Sections 3-4 detail the derivation of the MGQ equations with explicit presentation of a two-layer model. The derivation follows the standard procedure outlined in Vallis (2006, § 5.3, pgs. 207-215) while exploiting some of the scaling arguments invoked by Gilman (1967a). We introduce here some of the relevant scalings and corresponding non-dimensional parameters appearing in the system analyzed. The planetary rotation as viewed from the latitude in question is scaled by Ω 0 2 . If the typical meridional/zonal velocity scales are given by U then we may define the Rossby number</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Ro ≡ U f 0 L , 2</formula><p>If the planetary rotation is given by ¯ Ω and if one is at latitude λ then the rotation normal to that latitude is Ω0 = ¯ Ω sin λ where f 0 = 2Ω 0 and R is the planetary radius and L represents the horizontal "synoptic" scale of the dynamics. Dynamic flow timescales are assumed to be 1/Ro times longer than the Coriolis timescale 1/f 0 -this is the basis of the quasigeostrophic analysis. The magnetic field strength is scaled by B. This then leads to a natural non-dimensional quantity</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">C ≡ B 2 4π˜ρ4π˜ 4π˜ρ 1 U 2 ,</formula><p>also known as the Cowling number. The scale density˜ρdensity˜ density˜ρ is equated to the density of the lower atmosphere layer. C is related to the inverse square of the usual β parameter frequently referred to in plasma physics studies. The Cowling number can be understood as a measure of the energy contained in the magnetic field versus that contained in kinetic motions. It can also be understood as the square of the magnetic Mach number, i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">C = U A 2 /U 2 , since U 2 A ≡ B 2 /4π˜ρ4π˜ 4π˜ρ is the Alfvén speed squared.</formula><p>The atmosphere also has the following vertical length scales that are important: the overall vertical extent of the atmosphere H, and the vertical length scale of atmospheric f luctuations˜hluctuations˜ luctuations˜h. Therefore, the zonal and meridional dynamical lengths (X, Y ) are scaled by L while the vertical scales (Z) are characterized by H. Given that the flow speeds are O (U) it follows that their typical characteristic timescales (T ) are Ro −1 times longer than 1/f 0 , consistent with the assertion made above. These are all formally reintroduced in the discussion appearing in the next section. Finally, the Burger number, Bu, measuring the relative importance of gravity, is given by the relationship</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Bu 2 = gH 4Ω 2 0 L 2 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Scalings and analysis</head><p>The local Cartesionization of the equations of motion around a latitude λ 0 is given by,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">dU dT + 2Ωˆz×U2Ωˆz×U = 1 ρ ∇Π − gˆzgˆz + 1 4πρ (B · ∇)B,<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">∇ · U = 0, (7) dB dT = (B · ∇)U,<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">∇ · B = 0,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where the total pressure Π is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">Π = P + 1 8π B 2 .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>The coordinate Z coincides with the effective gravity direction. The component of gravity g will be taken to be constant. In this construction X, Y denote the zonal and meridional coordinates respectively. Before analyzing these equations on the Cartesion plane, we explicitly nondimensionalize all quantities appearing in the equations of motion according to the dimensional quantities stated above. Henceforth, all lower case Latin symbols (some with hats over them) denote the corresponding non-dimensional quantity. The primary parameter that will be used for the following expansions will be the Rossby number, Ro. In terrestrial and planetary studies the Rossby number is typically substantially less than one, i.e. Ro ≪ 1. U is the typical velocity scale of the horizontal planetary scale atmospheric motions, that is to say,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">U → Uu, V → Uv,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where u, v are the non-dimensionalized order one representations of the longitudinal and latitudinal velocities. Since U measures an effective overturning speed of the synoptic scale vortex structures in the atmosphere, the corresponding time scale associated with it scales as Ro/Ω 0 . Thus we scale the horizontal lengths and time according to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">X → Lx; Y → Ly, T → t/(RoΩ 0 )</formula><p>where x, y, t are now understood to be non-dimensionalized quantities. The vertical scale is measured by H and this will be considered small compared to L. In problems in which the atmosphere is broken up into subplayers H represents the full vertical extent of the whole atmosphere under consideration. In order to recover the quasi-geostrophic ordering the smallness of the ratio H/L needs only be ≪ 1. Correspondingly, the vertical velocity will also be assumed to be small in proportion to the ratio H/L. Thus we scale these two quantities accordingly as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">Z → Hz, W → H L Uw</formula><p>where z and w are order 1 non-dimensional quantities. The variation of the Coriolis parameter (which is the usual function of latitude on a planet) is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">Ω = Ω 0 1 + L R βy + · · · ,</formula><p>where Ω 0 is the evaluation of the projected planetary rotation at latitude λ 0 in which yL/R ≡ λ − λ 0 . Ω 0 = ¯ Ω sin λ 0 and β = cos λ 0 , where ¯ Ω is the planetary rotation rate. The ratio L/R will be formally shown to be O (Ro) in Section 4 in order to retain the planetary-β effect. The magnetic field strength will be measured by B. Thus, in keeping with the formalism developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gilman (2000)</ref>, the horizontal fields are scaled by this,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">B x → Bb x , B y → Bb y ,</formula><p>while, because of the small aspect ratios under consideration, we shall only consider vertical fields which are smaller than the horizontal components in proportion to the ratio H/L,</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">B z → H L b z .</formula><p>The vertical extent of the atmosphere is subdivided into sublevels with vertical scale H i where i labels the level number. For our considerations we assume that all ∆H i = H i − H i−1 , representing the thicknesses of each layer, are an order 1 fraction of the overall vertical scale H. We let˜hlet˜let˜h i represent perturbations about the mean level height H i0 , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">H i = H i0 + ˜ h i ,</formula><p>If we assume that the deviations scale by a characteristic length˜hlength˜ length˜h, then we may introduce another parameter δ which measures the the deviations against the vertical scale of the atmosphere</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">δ ≡ ˜ h H .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>In typical quasigeostrophic scalings this factor δ is assumed small, usually O (Ro) for Ro small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Analysis of the vertical momentum equation</head><p>We seek to develop reductions of the equations of motion which are dynamically in hydrostatic equilibrium. This means assuming the pressure scaling to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">Π → gH˜ρgH˜ρ ˘ Π,</formula><p>where˜ρwhere˜ where˜ρ is the density scale, typically of the lowest atmosphere layer. Examining the vertical component of the momentum equation with the scalings thus far presented reveals</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">Ro 2 H L 2 (∂ t + u · ∇ + w∂ z ) w = Bu 2 ˜ ρ ρ ∂ z ˘ Π + ρ ˜ ρ + Ro 2 C ˜ ρ ρ H L 2 (b · ∇ + b z ∂ z )b z .<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Where the Burger number, Bu, and the Cowling number, C, are as defined at the end of Section 2. To insure that hydrostatic balance is always dominant we shall assume Bu always dominates the other terms appearing in <ref type="bibr">(13)</ref>. This means to say specifically that unless</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Bu 2 ≫ Ro 2 H L 2 , and Bu 2 ≫ Ro 2 H L 2 C,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>the assumption of hydrostatic balance will fail. For planetary atmospheres this criterion is generally met since H/L ≪ 1.</p><p>The new piece here is the second disparity involving the Cowling number. We return to this shortly below. As of this point we have said nothing about the specific orderings required of the both the Burger and Cowling numbers. In general for this study we shall assume that Ro and the ratio H/L are sufficiently smaller than 1. It follows that the lowest order balance of the vertical momentum equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(13)</ref> is hydrostatic,</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">∂ z ˘ Π + ρ ˜ ρ = 0.<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Henceforth we shall treat ρ as being non-dimensionalized by˜ρby˜ by˜ρ which means, in practice, that ρ/ ˜ ρ will be replaced everywhere by ρ. When multiple layers are handled we shall characterize the density as being constant in each layer with value ρ i . Furthermore, to be consistent with what was stated earlier, the density of the lowest layer will always be unity, thus ρ 1 = 1. The procedure performed here essentially mimics the strategy employed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Vallis (2006)</ref>. We allow the top layer to move about freely and assume the pressure is zero on the top surface. The solution for the pressure for an N-layered atmosphere (with a flat bottom located at z = 0) expressed in terms of the non-dimensionalized lid coordinates H i is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">˘ Π = z HN ρ ˜ ρ dz =                    ρ N (H N − z), H N &gt; z ≥ H N −1 N k=N ρ k (H k − H k−1 ) + ρ N −1 (H N −1 − z), H N −1 &gt; z ≥ H N −2 . . . . . . N k=i+1 ρ k (H k − H k−1 ) + ρ i (H i − z), H i &gt; z ≥ H i−1 . . . . . . N k=2 ρ k (H k − H k−1 ) + ρ 1 (H 1 − z), H 1 ≥ z ≥ 0.<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Note that in the above formulation the summation procedure begins with layer i = N − 1 and that it is explicitly absent in the top, i = N , layer. As was motivated earlier, the levels H i are further written in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">H i = H i0 + δh i ,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where the set {H i0 } are constants. Henceforth the procedure outlined in the remainder of this study will focus only on a two-layer system with the understanding that it straightforwardly generalizes to a multi-layer configuration. 3 Given the functional form postulated above we find that horizontal gradients (∇ ≡ ˆ x∂ x + ˆ y∂ y ) of the pressure are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">∇ ˘ Π = δ∇ˆΠδ∇ˆ δ∇ˆΠ = δ∇ˆΠ δ∇ˆ δ∇ˆΠ 2 = ρ 2 h 2 , H 2 &gt; z ≥ H 1 ˆ Π 1 = ρ 2 h 2 + (ρ 1 − ρ 2 )h 1 , H 1 ≥ z ≥ 0.<label>(18)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Analysis of the horizontal momentum equations</head><p>Now we are prepared to move onto the horizontal momentum equations. With the scalings proposed above the equations become</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">Ro 2 (∂ t + u · ∇ + w∂ z ) u + 2Ro 1 + L R βyˆz βyˆβyˆz × u = −δBu 2 1 ρ ∇ ˆ Π + Ro 2 C ρ (b · ∇ + b z ∂ z )b + O Ro 2 L R ,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>in which u = uˆxuˆx + vˆyvˆy and b = b x ˆ x + b y ˆ y. We note that the curvature terms neglected at this stage come in at an ordering of O Ro 2 · O (L/R), and since L/R will be assumed to be ≪ 1, the curvature terms will be neglected throughout. It is at this stage that we explore various balances:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1.">Quasigeostrophic/magnetoquasigeostrophic scalings</head><p>We assume that the deviations from the mean height scale to the Rossby number, i.e. δ = O (Ro) . Although it would be enough to require that L/R ≪ 1, in order to include the planetary β we require that L/R ∼ O (Ro) . In Section 4 we detail the full procedure leading to the quasigeostrophic reduction, however, we show here the leading order balances to illustrate the main flavour of the results. Expanding the pressure and velocities within each layer i in powers of Ro according to,</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">ˆ Π i = ˆ Π (0) i + Rô Π (1) i + · · ·, u i = u (0) i + Rou (1) i + · · · and b i = b (0) i + Rob<label>(1)</label></formula><p>i + · · ·, then it follows that the leading order terms of (19), which are O (Ro), reduce to the fundamental statement of geostrophic balance, that is to say,</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">2ˆz2ˆz × u (0) i = −Bu 2 1 ρ i ∇ ˆ Π (0) i .<label>(20)</label></formula><p>Because we consider the density in each layer to be constant, taking the curl of the above equation immediately reveals that the horizontal divergence of the lowest order velocity field is identically zero</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">∂ x u (0) i + ∂ x v (0) i = 0.</formula><p>Therefore it follows from this that the lowest order vertical velocity w (0) i must zero. Requiring δ to be less than order 1 actually follows from the horizontal divergence free condition of the lowest order horizontal velocity field. This consistency is formally shown in Section 4.</p><p>In order to understand how magnetic effects enter the resulting equations we carry out the expansion to order Ro 2 to find,</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">(∂ t + u (0) i · ∇)u (0) i + 2ˆz2ˆz × u (1) i + βyˆzβyˆz × u (0) i = −Bu 2 1 ρ i ∇ ˆ Π (1) i + C ρ i (b (0) i · ∇)b<label>(0)</label></formula><p>i .</p><p>3 To avoid any ambiguity: the general form of the disturbance pressure would be given by the general formulaê Π The above is a restatement of Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(37)</ref> where in arriving at this equation it is argued that the horizontal components of the magnetic field are independent of z at lowest order. All but the last term on the RHS of the above expression constitute the next order corrections which ultimately lead to the classical equations of quasigeostrophy. In particular if C ≪ 1 then this limiting form identically leads to classical QG. We see that the first non-trivial inclusion of magnetic effects comes in when C is an order 1 quantity. In this event, the resulting equations will be called magnetoquasigeostrophy (MGQ). The completed derivation of the latter is found in Section 4.</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">i = ρihi + N k=i+1 ρ k (h k − h k−1 ) withˆΠwithˆ withˆΠ (0) N = ρnhn.<label>(0)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Magnetostrophic balance</head><p>When magnetic effects are relatively strong there exists another more general lowest order balance between Coriolis, horizontal pressure gradients and the horizontal components of the Lorentz force. This magnetostrophic balance has been explored in the context of the Earth's geodynamo <ref type="bibr">(Acheson &amp; Hide 1973</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Fearn 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">, Moffatt 2008</ref>, to name just a few). Inspection of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(19)</ref> shows that in order to bring the Lorentz term in on the same order as the Coriolis term requires C = O Ro −1 . Thus, we define a new number</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">A ≡ B 2 8π˜ρUΩ8π˜ 8π˜ρUΩ 0 L ,</formula><p>which we shall, henceforth, call the Acheson Number . For this three-way balance to occur the Acheson Number must be an order 1 quantity. Similar inspection of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(19)</ref> shows that in order for the horizontal pressure gradient to enter the mix we must have the combination δ·Bu 2 = O (Ro). Inspection also shows that if the resulting scaling arguments are consistent with the resulting equations δ must be O (1) (see below). Thus we define a modified Burger number˜Bunumber˜ number˜Bu such that Bu = Ro 1/2 ˜ Bu, where˜Bu</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">where˜ where˜Bu 2 ≡ gH 2Ω 0 LU .</formula><p>With the assumption that (i) all quantities may be expanded in powers of Ro (as we did in the previous section) and (ii) the lowest order horizontal velocity and magnetic field components are z-independent in a layer, then we find that the magnetostrophic balances in the horizontal directions are</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">2ˆz2ˆz × u (0) i = − ˜ Bu 2 1 ρ i ∇ ˆ Π (0) i + A ρ i (b (0) i · ∇)b (0) i .<label>(21)</label></formula><p>The horizontal divergence of the lowest order velocity is not zero in general. In fact,</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">∂ x u (0) i + ∂ x v (0) i = A 2ρ i ∂ x b (0) xi + ∂ x b (0) yi + b (0) i · ∇ J (0) i = 0,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>in which J (0) i is the lowest order vertical current in the layer,</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">J (0) i ≡ ∂ x b (0) yi −∂ y b (0)</formula><p>xi . Unlike what we encounter in the MGQ scalings, it follows that the lowest order vertical velocity cannot be zero at lowest order. Since δ measures the vertical variations of each layer height and since the latter is related to the vertical velocity, in order for the magnetostrophic scalings to be consistent and to have the lowest order horizontal divergences to be non-zero it must be that δ = O (1), which is to say vertical motions are driven by vertical currents due to the Lorentz force at lowest order. The continued analysis of the magnetostrophic equations and development of a self-contained equation set is presented in Section 5.</p><p>In <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> we summarize the relative scalings of the relevant quantities that produce the reduced equations discussed to now (i.e., QG, MQG and magnetostrophy).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Analysis of the incompressibility and induction equations</head><p>The scalings assumed at the beginning of this section result in the incompressiblity equation in each layer rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">∂ x u i + ∂ y v i + ∂ z w i = 0.<label>(23)</label></formula><p>The induction equations are also similarly written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">(∂ t + u i · ∇ + w i ∂ z )b i = (b i · ∇ + b zi ∂ z )u i<label>(24)</label></formula><p>with the vertical field component b zi relating to the other field components through the divergence free condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">∂ x b xi + ∂ y b yi + ∂ z b zi = 0.<label>(25)</label></formula><p>4. Detailed derivation of the equations of magnetoquasigeostrophy</p><p>We formally develop the scaling analysis and equation reduction that we began in Section 3.2.1. Quantities in each layer i are expanded in the following way,</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">u i = u (0) i + Ro u (1) i + · · · b i = b (0) i + Ro b (1) i + · · · ˆ Π i = Π (0) i + Ro Π (1) i + · · · ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where the superscript denotes which order of the Ro expansion the term represents. As we stated before, insertion of these expansions into (19) results in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">(20)</ref> to lowest order. Since we are considering a two-layer problem we have by layer that</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">u (0) 1 = −∂ y Bu 2 2ρ 1 ˆ Π (0) 1 , v (0) 1 = ∂ x Bu 2 2ρ 1 ˆ Π (0) 1 ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">u (0) 2 = −∂ y Bu 2 2ρ 2 ˆ Π (0) 2 v (0) 2 = ∂ x Bu 2 2ρ 2 ˆ Π (0) 2 ,<label>(28)</label></formula><p>It will prove to be more convenient to write the pressure fieldsˆΠfieldsˆ fieldsˆΠ i in terms of a streamfunction ψ i such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">ψ (0) 1 ≡ Bu 2 2ρ 1 ˆ Π (0) 1 = Bu 2 2 ρ 2 ρ 1 h (0) 2 + 1 − ρ 2 ρ 1 h (0) 1 ,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">ψ (0) 2 ≡ Bu 2 2ρ 2 ˆ Π (0) 2 = Bu 2 2 h (0) 2 ,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where the height deviations have been similarly expanded in powers of Ro, i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">h i = h (0) i + Roh (0)</formula><p>i + · · · This rewriting expresses the relationships more transparently</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">u (0) 1 = −∂ y ψ (0) 1 , v (0) 1 = ∂ x ψ (0) 1 , u (0) 2 = −∂ y ψ (0) 2 , v (0) 2 = ∂ x ψ (0) 2 .<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Evidently the fields u (0) i are 2-dimensional incompressible flow independent of the vertical coordinate z. This means from the incompressibility equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(23)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_49">∂ x u (0) i + ∂ y v (0) i + ∂ z w (0) i = 0, we get ∂ z w (0) i = 0.<label>(32)</label></formula><p>Thus the leading order vertical velocity term is zero 4 motivating its expansion to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">w i = Ro w (1) i + · · ·<label>(33)</label></formula><p>Note that this is necessarily consistent with the assumption made at the outset that δ = O (Ro). In other words this says that if the vertical velocities are small then so must be the vertical variations of height. We turn to the leading order equation for the horizontal compoenents of the magnetic field and we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ b (0) i = b (0) i · ∇ + b (0) zi ∂ z u<label>(0)</label></formula><p>i .</p><p>However, since the horizontal velocity components are independent of z the above equation reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ b (0) i = b (0) i · ∇u (0) i ,<label>(34)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">which implies that b (0) i</formula><p>is independent of z as well. The leading order expansion of the source free condition (25)</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">∂ x b (0) xi + ∂ y b (0) yi = −∂ z b (0) zi<label>(35)</label></formula><p>relates the leading order vertical field b</p><p>zi to b</p><p>i . We note that it means b</p><p>zi is at most a linear function of the coordinate z within each layer. Furthermore, and quite unlike the geostrophic balance situation we encountered before for the leading order horizontal velocities, the horizontal magnetic fields are not strictly two-dimensional, i.e. b <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">(0)</ref> z is not identically zero <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Gilman, 2000)</ref>. It follows from this that there are modes of dynamical activity which will allow the divergence of the leading order horizontal magnetic field resulting in a certain amount of "breathing" into the vertical field component.</p><p>At order Ro of the incompressibility condition we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">∂ x u (1) i + ∂ y v (1) i = −∂ z w (1) i .<label>(36)</label></formula><p>The remaining order Ro terms of the horizontal momentum balance equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(19)</ref> are</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">(∂ t + u (0) i · ∇)u (0) i + 2ˆz2ˆz × u (1) i + βyˆzβyˆz × u (0) i = −Bu 2 1 ρ i ∇ ˆ Π (1) i + C(b (0) i · ∇)b (0) i ,<label>(37)</label></formula><p>where we have explicitly used the fact that b</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">(0) i</formula><p>is independent of z in writing (37). Because an examination of the next order expansion of the vertical momentum balance equation reveals that ˘ Π</p><p>(1) i is independent of the vertical coordinate, it follows that the next order horizontal velocity corrections u</p><p>(1) i are also independent of z. We may therefore take the curl of the above equation by operating the y-momentum component by ∂ x and subtracting from it the ∂ y operation upon the x-momentum equation to get</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">(∂ t + u (0) i · ∇) ∂ x v (0) i − ∂ y u (0) i + 2Ω (1) i = C i (b (0) i · ∇)(∂ x b (0) yi − ∂ y b (0) xi ) + C i (∂ x b (0) xi + ∂ y b (0) yi )(∂ x b (0) yi − ∂ y b (0) xi ).<label>(38)</label></formula><p>with C i ≡ C/ρ i and where, for notational convenience, we have defined</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">Ω (1) i = −(∂ x u (1) i + ∂ y v (1) i )<label>(39)</label></formula><p>In order to proceed we must determine how Ω</p><p>(1) i relate to h</p><p>i . To do this we begin by determining the equation for each of the level heights h i . The previous scaling analysis leads to the non-dimensionalized version for them which, at leading order, reveals that</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">(∂ t + u (0) i · ∇)h (0) j = w (1) i (z = H j )<label>(40)</label></formula><p>where care must be taken since one may evaluate the motion of the j th surface using the velocity fields from layer i. Specifically we explicitly write out the solution to the vertical velocities for each layer. In the bottom layer we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">w (1) 1 = Ω (1) 1 z,<label>(41)</label></formula><p>in which we have implicitly forced the vertical velocity to be zero at the bottom z = 0. To leading order it follows that</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">w (1) 1 (z = H 1 ) = H 10 Ω<label>(1)</label></formula><p>1 .</p><p>When viewed from the lower layer then we have the motion of the lower layer's interface to be given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">∂ t + u (0) 1 · ∇ h (0) 1 = H 10 Ω<label>(1)</label></formula><p>1 .</p><p>For the upper layer we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">w (1) 2 = w (1) 20 + Ω (1) 2 z,<label>(44)</label></formula><p>where w</p><p>20 is a constant velocity to be determined below. Now it is evident that the motion of the bottom boundary when viewed from the upper layer is</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">∂ t + u (0) 2 · ∇ h (0) 1 = w (1) 20 + H 10 Ω (1) 2 ,<label>(45)</label></formula><p>while the motion of the upper boundary when viewed from the upper layer is</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">∂ t + u (0) 2 · ∇ h (0) 2 = w (1) 20 + H 20 Ω (1) 2 . (46)</formula><p>Subtracting these two expresses the evolution of the width of the upper layer in terms of Ω <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> 2 , that is to say,</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">∂ t + u (0) 2 · ∇ h (0) 2 − h (0) 1 = (H 20 − H 10 )Ω (1) 2 ,<label>(47)</label></formula><p>which, we note, is purely in terms of the velocity fields u given by (43) and <ref type="bibr">(47)</ref>. To this end, we begin with the bottom layer</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">∂ t + u (0) 1 · ∇ ∂ x v (0) 1 − ∂ y u (0) 1 − 2h (0) 1 H 10 = C b (0) 1 · ∇ + ∂ x b (0) x1 + ∂ y b (0) y1 ∂ x b (0) y1 − ∂ y b (0) x1 ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>while for the top layer we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">∂ t + u (0) 2 · ∇ ∂ x v (0) 2 − ∂ y u (0) 2 − 2 h (0) 2 − h (0) 1 H 20 − H 10 = C ρ 1 ρ 2 b (0) 2 · ∇ + ∂ x b (0) x2 + ∂ y b (0) y2 ∂ x b (0) y2 − ∂ y b (0) x2 . (49)</formula><p>In order to simplify the expressions appearing above we rewrite the heights h</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">(0) i</formula><p>in terms of the streamfunctions</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">h (0) 1 = 2 Bu 2 ψ (0) 1 − ρ2 ρ1 ψ (0) 2 1 − ρ2 ρ1 , h (0) 2 = 2 Bu 2 ψ (0) 2 . (50)</formula><p>We may now rewrite the equations in more transparent form</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">∂ t + u (0) 1 · ∇ Q (0) 1 + βv (0) 1 = C b (0) 1 · ∇ + q (0) m1 J (0) 1 , (51) ∂ t + u (0) 2 · ∇ Q (0) 2 + βv (0) 2 = C ρ 1 ρ 2 b (0) 2 · ∇ + q (0) m2 J (0) 2 (52)</formula><p>where the potential vorticity in each layer is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">Q (0) 1 = ∇ 2 ψ (0) 1 − 1 L 2 10 ψ (0) 1 − ρ 2 ρ 1 ψ (0) 2 ,<label>(53)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">Q (0) 2 = ∇ 2 ψ (0) 2 − 1 L 2 21 ψ (0) 2 − ψ (0) 1 , (54)</formula><p>in which the L 10 and L 21 denote the Rossby radius of deformation for layers 1 and 2 respectively,</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">1 L 2 10 ≡ 4 Bu 2 H 10 1 − ρ2 ρ1 , 1 L 2 21 ≡ 4 Bu 2 (H 20 − H 10 ) 1 − ρ2 ρ1 . (55)</formula><p>The form presented above diverges slightly from the form presented in Vallis wherein the upper layer is constrained by an upper boundary while here we allow for the upper layer to undulate freely. The difference then is that the ratio ρ 2 /ρ 1 appearing on the RHS of (53), defining Q <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">(0)</ref> 1 , would be replaced by 1. We have also defined the currents J</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">(0) i appropriate to layer i J (0) 1 ≡ ∂ x b (0) y1 − ∂ y b (0) x1 , J (0) 2 ≡ ∂ x b (0) y2 − ∂ y b (0) x2 ,<label>(56)</label></formula><p>and the corresponding layer densities q</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">(0) mi , q (0) m1 ≡ ∂ x b (0) x1 + ∂ y b (0) y1 , q (0) m2 ≡ ∂ x b (0) x2 + ∂ y b (0) y2 .<label>(57)</label></formula><p>All the terms in these equations, as appearing in the summary Section 6, will be expressed with their individual superscripts "(0)" removed. Additionally, the expression for Bu is rewritten in terms the definition of the Rossby Deformation Radii.</p><p>5. Further development of the magnetostrophic limit and the derivation of a closed set of equations</p><p>The leading order magnetostrophic balance (21) leads to a diagnostic specification of the horizontal velocities which we explitly write here</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">2v (0) i = − ˜ Bu 2 ρ i ∂ x ˆ Π (0) i + A ρ i b (0) i · ∇b (0) xi , (58) 2u (0) i = ˜ Bu 2 ρ i ∂ y ˆ Π (0) i + A ρ i b (0) i · ∇b (0) yi .<label>(59)</label></formula><p>We shall assume henceforth that the horizontal components of the velocity and magnetic fields are z-independent within a given layer. Thus, the leading order induction equation is the same as (34) which we rewrite here for convenience,</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ b (0) i = b (0) i · ∇u (0) i .</formula><p>The horizontal velocity components are expressed in terms of b i . Because the horizontal divergence of the lowest order velocity field was shown to be non-zero and subsequently assumed to be independent of the vertical coordinate z, we can write the leading order vertical velocity to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">w (0) i = w (0) i0 + zΩ (0) i ,</formula><p>where, as before,</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">w (0)</formula><p>i0 is a z-independent undetermined vertical velocity. Because of the relationships set up between the velocities according to the leading order continuity equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">∂ x u (0) i + ∂ x v (0) i + ∂ x w (0) i = 0,</formula><p>together with the help of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">(22)</ref>, we can express the quantity Ω (0) i in terms of the horizontal magnetic field quantities as</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">Ω (0) i = − A 2ρ i ∂ x b (0) xi + ∂ x b (0) yi + b (0) i · ∇ J (0) i .<label>(60)</label></formula><p>We develop an equation for the height fluctuations in the same manner as was done in the development of the MGQ equations. Because we have argued the fluctuations are on the same scale as the mean height of any given layer (i.e. because δ = O (1)), instead of expressing the height H i as the sum H i0 + δh i we shall simply stick with the expression H i since it now makes no difference as both quantities are the same order of magnitude. Thus the vertical motion of layer height with position z = H i as viewed from the layer with index i is to leading order</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ H i = w z=Hi = w (0) i0 + H i Ω (0) i .</formula><p>Similarly the motion of the layer height with position z = H i−1 as viewed from the same layer with index i is to leading order</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ H i−1 = w z=Hi = w (0) i0 + H i−1 Ω (0) i .</formula><p>Subtracting these two equations and reordering the results reveals</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">∂ t + u (0) i · ∇ ln (H i − H i−1 ) = Ω (0) i = − A 2ρ i ∂ x b (0) xi + ∂ x b (0) yi + b (0) i · ∇ J (0) i .<label>(61)</label></formula><p>As presented, this magnetostrophic limit involves evolving equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">(22)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(61)</ref> with the horizontal flow quantities determined by the magnetstrophic balances explicitly given in (58) and (59), where the perturbation pressure fields Π</p><p>i , given in (18), are re-expressed in terms of H i . We remind the reader that (18) explicitly shows the pressure field quantities for a two-layer system. In general, for layers i &lt; N with h i expressed in terms of H i , we would have,</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">ˆ Π (0) i = ρ i H i + N k=i+1 ρ k (H k − H k−1 ),<label>(62)</label></formula><p>and for layer N we havê Π (0)</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">N = ρ N H N .</formula><p>To illustrate how these equations appear we write them out for a single layer atmosphere where we drop the superscripts,</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">(∂ t + u 1 · ∇) b 1 = b 1 · ∇u 1 , (63) (∂ t + u 1 · ∇) ln H 1 = −(A/2) (∂ x b x1 + ∂ x b y1 + b 1 · ∇) J 1 ,<label>(64)</label></formula><p>in which the velocities and currents are diagnostically given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">2v 1 = − ˜ Bu 2 ∂ x H 1 − Ab 1 · ∇b x ,<label>(65)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_99">2u 1 = ˜ Bu 2 ∂ y H 1 + Ab 1 · ∇b y ,<label>(66)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_100">J 1 = ∂ x b y − ∂ y b x .<label>(67)</label></formula><p>Note that these equations are governed by the two parameters, the modified Burger number˜Bunumber˜ number˜Bu and the Acheson number A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Summary and brief discussion of the equations of magnetoquasigeostrophy</head><p>The result of the lengthly procedure detailed in Section 4 are summarized for two layers. The equations for the potential vorticity in each layer are given explicitly,</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">(∂ t + u 1 · ∇) Q 1 + βv 1 = ϕ 1 C q (m) 1 + b 1 · ∇ J 1 ,<label>(68)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_102">(∂ t + u 2 · ∇) Q 2 + βv 2 = ϕ 2 C ρ 1 ρ 2 q (m) 2 + b 2 · ∇ J 2 ,<label>(69)</label></formula><p>in which the horizontal velocities in vector form are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">u i = u i ˆ x + v i ˆ y.</formula><p>The gradient operator ∇ is now understood to be two-dimensional so that, for instance,</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">u i · ∇ = u i ∂ x + v i ∂ y .</formula><p>The potential vorticities for each layer, Q i , are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">Q 1 = ∇ 2 ψ 1 − 1 L 2 10 ψ 1 − ρ 2 ρ 1 ψ 2 ,<label>(70)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_106">Q 2 = ∇ 2 ψ 2 − 1 L 2 21 (ψ 2 − ψ 1 ) ,<label>(71)</label></formula><p>where the streamfunctions ψ i relate to the velocity in each layer according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">u i = −∂ y ψ i , v i = ∂ x ψ i ,<label>(72)</label></formula><p>and where the 2 dimensional Laplacian operator is given by ∇ 2 → ∂ 2 x + ∂ 2 y . Note that because the leading order horizontal velocities are geostrophic it follows that their horizontal divergences are zero, i.e.</p><p>∇ · u i = 0.</p><p>The (non-dimensionalized) Rossby radii of deformation for each layer are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">L 2 10 ≡ gHH 10 4Ω 2 0 L 2 1 − ρ 2 ρ 1 , L 2 21 ≡ gH(H 20 − H 10 ) 4Ω 2 0 L 2 1 − ρ 2 ρ 1 ,<label>(73)</label></formula><p>where ρ 1 and ρ 2 are the densities of each corresponding layer. The dimensional value of each level height H i are given respectively according to their non-dimensional fractional measures H i0 . In other words if H i0 represents the vertical coordinate where the transition from density ρ i to ρ i+1 occurs in steady state then the following may be defined H 10 ≡ H 10 /H, H 20 ≡ H 20 /H. Since only two layers are considered here the value of H 20 = 1 as H 20 = H by construction. It follows that H 10 is some number less than 1. The horizontal magnetic field in each layer is denoted in vector form with b i = b xî x + b yî y and the equations for their evolution are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">(∂ t + u 1 · ∇)b 1 = (b 1 · ∇)u 1 ,<label>(74)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_110">(∂ t + u 2 · ∇)b 2 = (b 2 · ∇)u 2 .<label>(75)</label></formula><p>As in the study considered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gilman (2000)</ref>, and unlike what is encountered for the horizontal velocity components, the horizontal magnetic field components are not automatically divergence-free. Of course, the source free condition is met in three dimensions so that a non-zero divergence of the horizontal magnetic field components will result in the generation of a linearly varying (with respect to the vertical coordinate) vertical magnetic field b zi , as expressed in relationship (35). It so happens that for these orderings the vertical field (if there is one dynamically, see below) effects the dynamics diagnostically through the pseudo-source term q </p><p>and its influence can be seen in the Lorentz terms in the equations for the potential vorticity (68-69). The source term q (m) is the pseudo-magnetic monopole distribution referred to in the Introduction. Finally the z-directed currents for each layer are J i and defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">J i ≡ ∂ x b yi − ∂ y b xi .<label>(77)</label></formula><p>= 0,</p><p>it automatically follows that ∇ · b i = 0. Consequently, the flux functions relating to the magnetic field components are.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">b x1 = −∂ y φ 1 , b y1 = ∂ x φ 1 , b x2 = −∂ y φ 2 , b y2 = ∂ x φ 2 .<label>(80)</label></formula><p>Instead of solving the vector equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(74)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_110">(75)</ref>, the following simpler scalar equations must solved,</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">(∂ t + u 1 · ∇)φ 1 = 0, (81) (∂ t + u 2 · ∇)φ 2 = 0.<label>(82)</label></formula><p>In terms of flux functions, then, the currents in each layer are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">J 1 = ∇ 2 φ 1 , J 2 = ∇ 2 φ 2 .<label>(83)</label></formula><p>Thus the evolution equations given by <ref type="bibr">(68,</ref><ref type="bibr">69)</ref>, with q (m) i set to zero, and <ref type="bibr">(81,</ref><ref type="bibr">82)</ref>, together with all of the supporting ancillary definitions form the basis of the equations appropriate for this subclass. These are the same equations analyzed by <ref type="bibr">Gilman in 1967-8.</ref> In an upcoming series of publications, we study the linear and nonlinear response of these equations which are amenable to relatively unencumbered theoretical analyses using well-known techniques used in both the meterological and fluid dynamics literature for studies of the QG equations. To this end, we shall use as a guide and expand upon the work laid out by Gilman and collaborators. Our initial investigations will focus upon analyzing the physical stability of the compact magnetic vortices observed to emerge in the simulations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Cho (2008)</ref> and to hopefully, as a result, understand the nature of those structures and answer why they may be manifesting in those simulations with the observed robustness reported.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We are now in a position to rewrite (38) layer by layer by replacing all instances of Ω (1) i with its appropriate expressions in terms of h (0) i</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and the perturbation height fluctuations h i are contained in the perturbation pressure fieldsˆΠfieldsˆ fieldsˆΠ (0)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>≡ ∇ · b i = ∂ x b xi + ∂ y b yi ,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Summary of scalings and lowest order balances for hydrostatic disturbances. All balances shown assume Ro ≪ 1. The quoted extreme values in describing magnetostrophic balance is the same as saying the Acheson and modified Burger numbers (denoted in the text by A and˜Buand˜ and˜Bu respectively) are O (1) .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Balance Name 
O (Bu) O (δ) O 

˜ 
C 

O 
L 

R 


Lowest Order Balance 
QG 
1 
Ro 
≪ 1 
Ro 
Coriolis, Pressure Gradient 
MQG 
1 
Ro 
1 
Ro 
Coriolis, Pressure Gradient 
Magnetostrophy 
Ro 1/2 
1 
Ro −1 
≪ 1 
Coriolis, Pressure Gradient,Lorentz Force 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> This unfortunate tongue-in-cheek description is used for the lack of a better expression to describe how the non-zeroness of the horizontal divergence of the magnetic field would &quot;appear&quot; as a monopole charge source, albeit, in two-dimensions. Of course no such thing exists as the non-vanishing feature of the horizontal divergences of the magnetic fields means only that there correspondigly exists a vertical field with non-zero vertical gradient.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> if the totality of all the layers are not moving.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of Mathematical Functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abramowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stegun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
			<publisher>Dover</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric dynamics of tidally synchronized extrasolar planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.-K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4477" to="4488" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The changing face of the extrasolar giant planet HD 209458b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y.-K</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M S</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">587</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic meteorology at the photosphere of HD 209458b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Showman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<editor>Earths Deep Interior. Crossley, D.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">629</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Gordon and Breach</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The geodynamo</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of baroclinic flows in a zonal magnetic field: part I</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Atmos. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of baroclinic flows in a zonal magnetic field: part II</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Atmos. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of baroclinic flows in a zonal magnetic field: part III</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Atmos. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetohydrodynamic &quot;shallow water&quot; equations for the solar tachocline</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">544</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ionization of Extrasolar Giant Planet Atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Koskinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y.-K</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Achilleos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Aylward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">722</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetostrophic turbulence and the geodynamo</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moffatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IUTAM Symposium on computational physics and new perspectives in turbulence Y. Kaneda</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="346" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric circulationo f hot jupiters: a shallow three-dimensional model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rauscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pedlosky, J. 1987 Geophysical Fluid Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">700</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="887" to="897" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shallow-water&quot; magnetohydrodynamic waves in the solar tachocline</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schecter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">551</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The solar tachocline</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Spiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Zahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">265</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Atmospheric and Oceanic Fluid Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vallis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rossby waves in &quot;shallow water&quot; magnetohydrodynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Zaqarashvili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ballester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shergelashvili</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">470</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
