<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:15+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Beginning of activity in 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko and predictions for 2014/5</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-08-13">August 13, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
							<email>snodgrass@mps.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Max-Planck-Str. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>37191</postCode>
									<settlement>Katlenburg-Lindau</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tubiana</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Max-Planck-Str. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>37191</postCode>
									<settlement>Katlenburg-Lindau</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bramich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">European Southern Observatory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Karl-Schwarzschild-Strasse 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-85748</postCode>
									<settlement>Garching bei München</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Meech</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2680 Woodlawn Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>96822</postCode>
									<settlement>Honolulu</settlement>
									<region>HI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hawaii NASA Astrobiology Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>96822</postCode>
									<settlement>Honolulu</settlement>
									<region>HI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boehnhardt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Max-Planck-Str. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>37191</postCode>
									<settlement>Katlenburg-Lindau</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Barrera</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Metropolitana de Ciencias de la Educacion (UMCE)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Avda. Jose Pedro Alessandri 774</addrLine>
									<settlement>Santiago</settlement>
									<country key="CL">Chile</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Beginning of activity in 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko and predictions for 2014/5</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-08-13">August 13, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received ; accepted</note>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. snodgrass_67Pactivity</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>comets: individual: 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. Comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko was selected in 2003 as the new target of the Rosetta mission. It has since been the subject of a detailed campaign of observations to characterise its nucleus and activity. Aims. Here we present previously unpublished data taken around the start of activity of the comet in 2007/8, before its last perihelion passage. We constrain the time of the start of activity, and combine this with other data taken throughout the comet&apos;s orbit to make predictions for its likely behaviour during 2014/5 while Rosetta is operating. Methods. A considerable difficulty in observing 67P during the past years has been its position against crowded fields towards the Galactic centre for much of the time. The 2007/8 data presented here were particularly difficult, and the comet will once again be badly placed for Earth-based observations in 2014/5. We make use of the difference image analysis (DIA) technique, which is commonly used in variable star and exoplanet research, to remove background sources and extract images of the comet. In addition, we reprocess a large quantity of archival images of 67P covering its full orbit, to produce a heliocentric lightcurve. By using consistent reduction, measurement and calibration techniques we generate a remarkably clean lightcurve, which can be used to measure a brightness-distance relationship and to predict the future brightness of the comet. Results. We determine that the comet was active around November 2007, at a pre-perihelion distance from the Sun of 4.3 AU. The comet will reach this distance, and probably become active again, in March 2014. We find that the dust brightness can be well described by A f ρ ∝ r −3.2 pre-perihelion and ∝ r −3.4 post-perihelion, and that the comet has a higher dust-togas ratio than average, with log(A f ρ/Q(H 2 O)) = −24.94 ± 0.22 cm s molecule −1 at r &lt; 2 AU. A model fit to the photometric data suggests that only a small fraction (1.4%) of the surface is active.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Comets are known for their unpredictable nature, and the process which drives their activity is still poorly understood. While the rise in ice sublimation due to increased heating from the Sun explains, in general terms, the increase in activity of a comet on the inbound leg of its orbit, the precise mechanism causing this activity is not known. The question of when and how a comet will become active is therefore difficult to answer, and there is a wide variation in activity levels at the same heliocentric distance for different comets. Understanding how activity starts and evolves as a comet approaches the Sun is one of the key goals of ESA's Rosetta mission, which will rendezvous with comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko (hereafter 67P) in early 2014 and will follow it all the way to its next perihelion passage in 2015, and beyond. As part of the planning for this mission, and for a campaign of ground based observations in support of it, it is necessary to build up the best understanding possible of the behaviour of 67P before Rosetta's arrival.</p><p>Based on observations collected at the European Southern Observatory, Paranal, Chile -079.C-0687 &amp; 080.C-0259, and from archives.</p><p>Since 67P was selected as the Rosetta target in 2003 there have been a number of studies of this comet. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Schulz et al. (2004)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lamy et al. (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lara et al. (2005)</ref> obtained the first dedicated characterisation observations after it was selected, when the comet was on the outbound leg of its orbit, and still highly active, following its perihelion passage in 2002. As the comet passed through aphelion its inactive nucleus was studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Tubiana et al. (2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. ( , 2011</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lowry et al. (2012)</ref>, before it was observed in an active state again as it returned to perihelion in 2008 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Tozzi et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lara et al. 2011</ref>). Further authors have studied the longer lived dust trail associated with the comet <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Ishiguro 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kelley et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Agarwal et al. 2010</ref>), the dust's polarisation <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Hadamcik et al. 2010</ref>), the nucleus thermal properties ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kelley et al. 2006</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lamy et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kelley et al. 2009)</ref>, and the morphology ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Vincent et al. 2013</ref>) and composition <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Schleicher 2006</ref>) of its coma over multiple apparitions.</p><p>What has been missing so far from the published literature is a reliable estimate of the point in the orbit that activity begins. In this paper we present data taken in <ref type="bibr">2007 and 2008</ref> around the time of the expected onset, between the inactive nucleus observations taken in 2007 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lowry et al. 2012</ref>) and the active comet observations in 2008 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Tozzi et al. 2011</ref>). We use these to make estimates of the time of onset of activity in 2007/8, and from that make predictions for 2014.</p><p>To provide a broader context to the onset of activity observed in 2007/8, we also wish to study the activity of the comet throughout its orbit. The various studies of 67P in its active state that have been published in recent years have so far concentrated on a short segment of the orbit. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ferrín (2005)</ref> published a heliocentric lightcurve based on mostly amateur observations, up to the 2002 apparition. To provide a consistent overview of the activity history of 67P, we downloaded and reduced data available in various professional observatory archives (primarily from ESO) and measured the comet brightness in various apertures. We use this to produce a heliocentric lightcurve based on consistent measurements, which is described in section 4.1, before looking at the implications for dust and gas production rates around the orbit in sections 4.2 and 4.3 respectively. We introduce a model that describes the activity in section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Observations and data reduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">VLT observations</head><p>Observations were obtained in service mode at the VLT using the FORS instrument in imaging mode. Images were mostly obtained in the R-band; details are given in table 1. Standard reduction (bias level subtraction, flat fielding) was applied using IDL routines from the DanDIA / DanIDL packages <ref type="bibr">1</ref> . These packages provide an implementation of difference image analysis (DIA), which allows accurate subtraction of constant background sources in crowded fields, and includes corrections for changing seeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bramich 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Bramich et al. 2013</ref>). This technique has become a standard tool for variable star photometry in crowded fields, and especially microlensing, and we have recently demonstrated that it is also a powerful method for extracting moving (solar system) targets from dense background fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Snodgrass &amp; Bramich 2013)</ref>. Details on the method are given in these papers, but briefly the technique takes one 'reference' frame (normally the one with the best seeing in a sequence) and applies a fitted kernel model to match this reference with each other frame. Subtracting these model frames from the data give images with all constant sources removed, revealing any variable stars or moving objects. An example of the subtraction is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig. 1</ref>. Use of these techniques was necessary for all The comet is impossible to identify, much less perform photometry on, in such a crowded field, but is clearly revealed as a positive and negative pair in the subtracted frames. Saturated stars are masked in the difference image. North is up, East to the left. data taken during 2007 due to the exceptionally crowded stellar fields, as the comet appeared near to the Galactic centre (b ≤ 4</p><p>• throughout the period of observation).</p><p>Once the background stars have been subtracted, standard aperture photometry can be used to measure the flux of the moving object. We follow the techniques that we have previously applied for comet nucleus photometry (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Snodgrass et al. 2005)</ref>, using an aperture with radius equal to the FWHM of the image point-spread-function (PSF) to maximise the signal-to-noise and an aperture correction to ensure that the full flux from the nucleus is included. When using DIA the PSF shape is modelled for each frame as part of the subtraction process, so this can be used to measure a high accuracy correction from a narrow aperture to the full PSF. This PSF shape was also compared with the radial profile of the comet in all frames to search for faint activity. Absolute flux calibration of the resulting photometry was performed based on observations of Landolt/Stetson standard star fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Landolt 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Stetson 2000</ref>) observed on the same nights, all of which were photometric. As these observations were not taken with DIA in mind, this data set presented some challenges. Firstly, there were a relatively large number of saturated stars in each frame, as even 60 seconds is a long exposure time for an 8m telescope when observing at low galactic latitude. Saturated stars cannot be subtracted and have to be masked. We were fortunate that the comet itself was not too close to saturated stars in most of the data, but the saturation still meant that care had to be taken in the convolution kernel calculation. Secondly, each image set covered only a short period of time (∼40 minutes), with no separate background image (the star field without the comet) taken. This meant that the reference image needed to be taken from the comet frames, resulting in a negative image of the comet at the reference position in all frames, and the loss of 2-4 frames around the reference time where the comet flux could not be reliably measured due to this negative imprint. Enough well-subtracted frames remained to perform photometry on the comet for all nights except the 15th of November, when a combination of bad and highly variable seeing, high airmass, slow apparent motion of the comet, and nearby saturated stars meant that no useful comet images could be recovered. The total number of images used from each night is given in table 1.  Position of 67P in its orbit at the time of the observations used in this paper. Open symbols indicate visible activity, closed symbols indicate an apparently inactive nucleus. The VLT data presented in detail are marked by red diamonds, while the archival data are marked by triangles. The comet moves in an counter-clockwise fashion in this plot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Archival data</head><p>There is a large set of archival data on 67P, with professional observations on approximately 200 individual nights to date (mostly snap-shots, but some full nights of lightcurve observations). <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> summarises all of these observations, and indicates the ones used in this study. We selected only R-band images, to give an overall description of the brightness of the comet due to reflected sunlight, as this wavelength range is relatively free of gas emission lines. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows the position of the comet in its orbit at the date of each selected observation.</p><p>The vast majority of the data (especially since the selection of the comet as the new Rosetta target in 2003) has been taken at ESO, and is therefore available through the ESO archival service 2 . These data were largely taken by a few groups (led by Schulz, Böhnhardt, Barrera, Tubiana, Lowry and Tozzi) and have mostly been published elsewhere already. However, each group reported measurements in different ways, so we reprocessed all the data and performed the measurements in a consistent manner to give a uniform data set. Standard reduction was performed using DanDIA tools, although no image subtraction was necessary for the frames used. To allow automated processing of such a large data set, master bias and flat field frames covering long periods (∼ 1 year) were used for each instrument. While these introduce some systematic errors, this is not a problem at the level of photometric accuracy (∼ 0.1 mag) necessary for studying the total brightness evolution of the comet around its orbit. It is a testament to the stability of the ESO instruments that the reductions performed in this way are actually very good.</p><p>Calibration of each frame was performed, where possible, using field stars of known brightness and colour from photometric surveys. Throughout most of 2003 and some of 2010 the comet was in an area of sky covered by the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS), so calibration was performed using field stars in this catalogue. The 1995 data were calibrated using field stars available in the AAVSO Photometric All-Sky Survey (APASS) catalogue, which covers the full sky but unfortunately could not be used for most of the data due to either the small field of view or the long exposure time used, and consequently a lack of non-saturated catalogue stars. Where catalogue stars were not available in the comet field we determined nightly zeropoints using Landolt/Stetson star fields observed on the same night (assuming default extinction and colour term values to allow quick automated fitting). In a few cases where this was not possible we used the tabulated nightly zeropoints available for VLT instruments on the ESO web page, or default instrumental values. Where possible APASS and VLT nightly zeropoint calibrations were also checked against the SDSS; we find that the APASS and SDSS photometry give consistent results, while there is an offset of up to 0.5 mag between the VLT tabulated / default zeropoints and SDSS in 2003 -the points calibrated this way are treated with caution. The calibration source for each night is listed in table 4.</p><p>In addition to the ESO data, we also took some frames from the Japanese SMOKA archive (observations with the Kiso 1.05m Schmidt) and the SDSS (which serendipitously observed the comet in December 2002). Kiso observations were reduced in the same way as the ESO data, and calibrated using the APASS &amp; SDSS catalogues, while the SDSS data is already reduced and photometrically calibrated into the SDSS system. For the SDSS image, new aperture photometry was measured on the comet, and the SDSS r-band magnitudes then converted to Cousins (Landolt) R-band using 3</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">R = r − 0.1837(g − r) − 0.0971 (1)</formula><p>and solar (g − r) = 0.45 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Holmberg et al. 2006</ref>). Observations are also available in the HST and CFHT (Megacam) archives, although we chose not to include these for simplicity, as the dates of these observations are near to dates covered by ESO observations. Finally, images from the University of Hawaii 2.2m telescope were identified in Karen Meech's archive of comet observations, although these were unfortunately of limited use as the comet was either not detected or merged with background stars in many of the frames (these snap-shot images are not suitable for DIA processing, as no image of the field without the comet is available). The solar system object search tool of the Canadian Astronomy Data Centre 4 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gwyn et al. 2012</ref>) proved exceptionally useful in identifying archival observations in addition to those we already knew of.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">2007/8 results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Beginning of activity</head><p>We plot the measured R-band magnitude of the comet during 2007/8 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">fig. 3</ref>, which also shows the predicted nuclear magnitude based on the observations of the inactive nucleus in July 2007 and measurement of the nucleus phase function by <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Tubiana et al. (2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. ( , 2011</ref>. Our VLT observations were short sequences (covering only a small fraction on the comet's ∼ 12.7 hour rotation period), and we are looking for small changes in brightness (less than the ∆m ≈ 0.4 mag. variation due to the nucleus lightcurve). We therefore applied a correction to the photometry, by using the nucleus shape and pole model published by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lowry et al. (2012)</ref> to calculate the predicted rotational lightcurve phase at the time of the observations, and the corresponding offset from the mean effective magnitude, as would be observed for a nonvarying (spherical) nucleus. As Lowry et al. (2012) also use July 2007 data in their model, the uncertainty in the extrapolation of rotational phase is small (∼ 0.1% by November 2007). The corrections to the photometry due to rotation phase are at most 0.13 magnitudes (for the August 2007 data), and smaller than the uncertainties for all other months (Sep: -0.01 mag.; Oct:+0.01; Nov: +0.03; Mar: n/a). For each month we plot the average magnitude from the individual measurements, with the error bar given by the standard deviation on this mean. The individual photometric measurements, without correction for rotational phase, are given in table 3.</p><p>The offset from the predicted nucleus magnitude is clear for the March 2008 data, where faint activity is also apparent in the images ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">fig. 4</ref>). We can therefore be certain that the comet was active in March 2008, at 3.4 AU from the Sun on its inbound leg. The photometry also shows a significant amount of extra flux in November 2007 (MJD 54417), suggesting some weak activity at that time, when the comet was at 4.3 AU from the Sun. The October data also suggest a possible excess flux, although the uncertainty on this data point makes it consistent with the inactive nucleus at a 2σ level, while the September data set (where the comet was detected at high signal-to-noise, well away from residuals due to saturated stars) indicates that activity had not yet reached a detectable level at 4.4 AU.</p><p>In addition to measuring the brightness of the comet, we also test for activity by comparing its surface brightness profile with the shape of the PSF. Profiles were measured in each individual frame and also for a median stack of all frames in each night that showed the comet well separated from the negative imprint from the reference frame, and from any residuals due to saturated stars. The resulting profiles are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">fig. 5</ref>. This analysis also confirms that there was no detectable activity at 4.4 AU  presented the greatest challenges in data reduction, and that the night of the 15th produced no usable data to confirm the brightness increase seen on the night of the 12th. The presence of nearby stellar residuals in the profile indicates that we should be careful with the photometric identification of activity in the November data, but the seeing was good that night (FWHM &lt; 0.8 ) and the narrow aperture selected is well clear of any stars. 67P does not appear to have a sudden start in activity (a rapid rise in brightness) as seen in comet 10P/Tempel 2 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Knight et al. 2012</ref>), rather a more continuous increase in dust production that slowly crosses our detection threshold.</p><p>We therefore expect, assuming that the comet repeats its activity from one orbit to another, that detectable activity will begin in the current orbit at approximately 4.3 AU inbound, in March 2014. This is very early in the Rosetta mission, during the phase when the spacecraft and instruments will be recommissioned following deep-space hibernation, and Rosetta is still ∼ 5 × 10 6 km from the comet. This implies that an extra effort will be required by the Rosetta team to get images of the comet as early as possible, in order to observe the start of activity. At this time the comet will be just returning to visibility from the Earth, and will again be seen against a crowded background, making observations from ground-based telescopes challenging. We believe that these extra efforts (by both ESA and ground-based observers) are justified as we expect activity to begin at large distance. It will also be important to test the sensitivity of ground-based observations against in situ measurements from Rosetta's instruments -this mission will give us an interesting opportunity to test just how active a comet must be before careful processing of data from the largest telescopes can reveal the dust from Earth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">The colour of the coma at large heliocentric distance</head><p>Images were taken in 3 filters (Bessell V, R and I) during March 2008, which we use to measure the colour of the comet. As 67P was weakly active there was significant flux from the coma. Using the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Jewitt &amp; Danielson (1984)</ref>, which assumes a steady state coma, we find that the coma made up ∼ 20% of the flux within an aperture of radius 10,000 km at the comet (equivalent to 3.7 at the time of observation). The colours of the comet within this aperture are found to be (V − R) = 0.45 ± 0.05 and (R − I) = 0.39 ± 0.04, which are redder than solar colours ((V − R) = 0.35; (R − I) = 0.33) and similar to the average for cometary nuclei ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Snodgrass et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lamy &amp; Toth 2009</ref>). The coma is slightly bluer than the nucleus, which has an aver- Heliocentric lightcurve, showing the R-band magnitude measured within an aperture of radius 10,000 km at the distance of the comet, corrected to unit geocentric distance and zero phase angle, against heliocentric distance in AU. Negative heliocentric distance shows pre-perihelion measurements. Different symbols show data taken during different apparitions, and highlight 'our data' presented in section 3 (which were taken at the start of the 2009 apparition). The solid black line shows the expected magnitude of the bare nucleus, based on the absolute magnitude reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. (2011)</ref>. The dashed line shows a prediction for the total magnitude based on a water production rate model (see section 4.3), while the dotted lines show a power law fit to the data. age (V − R) = 0.53 ± 0.02 and (R − I) = 0.48 ± 0.02 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lamy et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Tubiana et al. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lowry et al. 2012</ref>). This implies that the grains in the coma are smaller than the dominant surface grains, preferentially scattering bluer wavelengths. An alternative explanation is the presence of significant gas emission lines, which can increase the flux in the V-band, but the (R − I) colour is not strongly affected by gas emissions and is also seen to be bluer than the nucleus, implying that this is a grain size effect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Archival data results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Heliocentric lightcurve</head><p>Heliocentric lightcurves give a good overview of the activity level of a comet around its orbit. The series of papers by Ferrín (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ferrín 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ferrín , 2010</ref>) have presented heliocentric (or 'secular') lightcurves for a number of comets based on photometry reported to the Minor Planets Center or available in the literature, and give a general description of the behaviour of each comet, even if the photometric scatter in these plots is large due to the varied data sources.</p><p>Here we present a heliocentric lightcurve for 67P based on a consistent re-reduction of professional data taken from archival sources. All data shown in figs. 6 and 7, and given in table 4, come from our own reprocessing of archival images, with the exception of some points around perihelion during the 2009 apparition taken from <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lara et al. (2011)</ref>, where the reported A f ρ within ρ = 10, 000 km was converted back into a flux within this aperture.</p><p>We choose to display the lightcurve measured within a ρ = 10, 000 km aperture for all measurements, to maintain a consistent physical volume of coma, independent of viewing geometry. We measured the photometry within a selection of different apertures, including fixed physical sizes and fixed apparent radii (we give results from both ρ = 10, 000 km and ρ = 5 in table 4). The table also gives the A f ρ quantity and slope of the radial profile of the comet (see section 4.2). Using a fixed aperture means that no attempt is made to measure the 'total' flux from the comet; near to perihelion the coma is clearly larger than 10,000 km in radius. This is quite deliberate, as a total flux measurement either requires a very large aperture to be sure to contain all possible coma (which would possibly mean an aperture larger than the field of view of the camera in some cases), and removal of all stars within that aperture, or to somehow define the edge of the coma, which clearly depends on the sensitivity of the camera used.</p><p>The measured photometry was reduced to geocentric distance ∆ = 1 AU and phase angle α = 0 • using</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">m R (r, 1, 0) = m R − 5log∆ − βα<label>(2)</label></formula><p>with the phase coefficient β = 0.02 mag deg −1 , as found for cometary dust over a range of phase angles up to α ≈ 30 • ). An alternative phase function, which is non-linear at larger angles, combines measurement of comet 1P/Halley ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Schleicher et al. 1998</ref>) with calculations by Marcus (2007) 5 . For α &lt; 55 • this is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">m R (r, 1, 0) = m R − 5log∆ − 2.5(0.01807α − 0.000177α 2 ),<label>(3)</label></formula><p>which can approximated with a linear β = 0.04 mag deg −1 relationship over most phase angles observable from Earth. Using this instead of β = 0.02 mag deg −1 makes only a small difference to the resulting photometry (increasing the perihelion brightness slightly, but not noticeably changing the shape of the lightcurve). We choose to use the simple linear phase function, and return to this topic in the discussion (see section 4.4).</p><p>The phase function behaviour of cometary dust is quite different from that of nuclei. The nucleus phase darkening has been measured for only a handful of comets, but these can be described by linear functions with an average coefficient of β = 0.053 ± 0.016 mag deg −1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Snodgrass et al. 2011</ref>). Slopes of β = 0.059 − 0.076 mag deg −1 have been found for 67P <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Lowry et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Tubiana et al. 2011</ref>). These are considerably steeper than the dust function, so the choice of 'dust-like' or 'nucleuslike' phase correction can have a significant effect on the photometric results. As the heliocentric lightcurve primarily contains data from the active phases, where the flux from the coma dominates, we use the dust law for all data. The difference for the handful of observations of the inactive nucleus is small, as these were generally taken near to opposition. A f ρ values are also corrected to zero phase.</p><p>The lightcurve demonstrates a number of noteworthy features. Firstly, the lightcurve is remarkably 'clean', showing the advantage of using only data taken with large professional telescopes and consistent methods. We conservatively estimate the uncertainty on any given point to be ∼ 0.1 mag. (the formal uncertainties including photon noise and calibration are typically ∼ 0.01 mag., but do not include any systematic uncertainty due to either the relatively 'quick and dirty' flat-fielding or occasional faint stars within the photometric aperture). This gives us some confidence in making further predictions based on the lightcurve. Power law fits to the data describe the flux as ∝ r −5.2 pre-perihelion and ∝ r −5.4 post-perihelion. The second point to note is that data taken around different perihelion passages <ref type="bibr">(1996, 2002 and 2009</ref>) all fit on the same smooth curve, implying that the activity level of the comet does not vary significantly between apparitions, and that any predictions for 2014/5 may be of some use (of course, with the usual caveats that even 'well behaved' comets can have unpredictable moments). It is unfortunate that the section of the lightcurve between -4 and -3.5 AU is one of the few badly covered parts, so we cannot add further to the question of the turn-on time discussed in the previous section, beyond noting that the pre-perihelion slope is consistent with departure from a bare nucleus at 4.3 AU. There was only one additional observation in this period in the archive, from the University of Hawaii 2.2m in August 2001 (r = −3.5 AU), where the comet was seen but was merged with brighter background stars. As this data set was a BVRI snap-shot, with only one frame per filter, it is not possible to apply DIA techniques to recover the R-band photometry. Finally, we note that the overall shape of the lightcurve is reasonably symmetrical around perihelion, although the comet is consistently brighter (by around 1 magnitude) at the same distance post-perihelion when compared to pre-perihelion. This is more clearly seen when the heliocentric lightcurve is plotted against time from perihelion ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">fig. 7)</ref>, which shows that the brightness peaks in the weeks immediately after perihelion.</p><p>The idea that 67P reaches its peak in activity shortly after perihelion is in agreement with past results based on water production rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Schleicher 2006</ref>) and coma morphology <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Vincent et al. 2013</ref>). Lightcurves based on amateur photometry around perihelion also show this asymmetry <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Kidger 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ferrín 2005)</ref>, with the peak occurring approximately one month after perihelion. The asymmetry can be explained by different hypotheses. Firstly, it can be due to the time taken for the thermal wave to travel from the comet's surface to the buried ice, meaning that the maximum sublimation rate lags behind the maximum solar insolation. Alternatively, the production of dust and gas could be a two stage process: Material is mostly lifted in large grains which subsequently fragment, delaying the majority of the production rate. This scenario is unlikely to explain a lag of weeks though, as the timescale for material to pass out of the 10,000 km radius aperture is only 2 or 3 days at typical grain speeds. Finally, the activity peak could be due to a seasonal effect. Based on the pole orientation measured by <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Vincent et al. (2013)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lowry et al. (2012)</ref>, it is expected that the comet reaches equinox around 50 days before perihelion, so it is possible that there are areas near the previously unlit pole (e.g. in crater-like depressions) that only see sunlight near to perihelion (and hence produce a boost in activity at this time). <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Vincent et al. (2013)</ref> use such a seasonal model to explain the relative strengths of jets seen in the coma. Observations by Rosetta will allow us to differentiate between these various effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Dust production</head><p>The R-band observations used in measuring the heliocentric lightcurve are sensitive to reflected sunlight from dust in the coma, and are not significantly affected by emission lines from gas. It is therefore natural to use these measurements to constrain the amount of dust in the coma, and the rate at which the comet produces dust. The dust brightness for active comets is often quantified by the A f ρ parameter (A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. 1989</ref>). The conversion from surface brightness to mass loss rate requires assumptions on the albedo, density, velocity and size distribution of dust grains, all of which are only poorly constrained. Various authors have built complex dust models which fit these parameters to the observed coma brightness and morphology (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agarwal et al. 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Agarwal et al. , 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fulle et al. 2010</ref>). The recent paper by <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Fink &amp; Rubin (2012)</ref> calculates expected A f ρ values considering variable dust albedo and phase behaviour dependent on grain size, based on the dust flux simulations for 67P by <ref type="bibr">Teni- shev et al. (2011)</ref>. This sort of modelling is beyond the scope of this paper; instead we report the observed A f ρ and briefly consider some caveats on its use.</p><p>A f ρ is useful as it is easily calculated and widely employed, providing a first order comparison of activity levels between different comets and at varying heliocentric distances. The values we derive for 67P are typical for Jupiter family comets, of order 10 2 − 10 3 cm around perihelion. The use of A f ρ to compare between comets (or even other observations of 67P) does have to be treated with care though. Firstly, the values we give in table 4 use a β = 0.02 mag deg −1 phase function to correct them to the values that would have been observed at a constant phase angle. We correct to α = 0 • , while others normalise to other angles or do no not apply any phase function correction. Secondly, it is important to note that A f ρ is independent of wavelength and of the choice of aperture radius ρ only for an idealised coma with grey dust and a 1/ρ brightness profile. In real comets this is not always the case, as the particle size distribution can influence the coma colour, and the assumption of a 1/ρ profile requires a steady state (dust being produced from the nucleus at the same rate it flows out of the aperture). We minimise these uncertainties by using a fixed physical aperture size and observations at a fixed wavelength, and a consistent correction for phase, so the A f ρ values we find can be compared with each other to assess dust production around the orbit. To judge how well our A f ρ values can be used in comparison with other work, we test how well 67P meets the steady state assumption.</p><p>It is clear from images of the comet (representative examples are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">fig. 8</ref>) that the morphology of its coma and tails changes throughout its orbit. Pre-perihelion the coma is quite symmetric, with a broad fan developing into a dust trail, while post-perihelion larger particles form a 'neckline'. Further image processing reveals jets within the coma, which are seen to change in strength around the orbit. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agarwal et al. (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Vincent et al. (2013)</ref> discuss the large scale and fine structure morphology of the comet in detail.  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2011)</ref> found that A f ρ varied with ρ for observations of 67P at r = 2.3 AU pre-perihelion, and so the coma did not behave as 1/ρ. We find that 67P does not match the steady state assumption over a wider range in heliocentric distance, by measuring the slope of the radial profile in all the archival data sets. When plotted as magnitudes (or fluxes on a logarithmic scale) against log(ρ), the surface brightness profile of an active comet should have a linear profile with a slope of -1, or -1.5 if the effects of radiation pressure are taken into account . We find that the slopes vary between shallower than -1 to -2 or steeper, with a correlation between slope and heliocentric distance. The steepest slopes are meaningless, as they correspond to images when the comet is inactive ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">fig. 8)</ref>, and the profile shape is actually the image PSF (and therefore a linear fit to a gaussian profile, with the result dependent on the seeing), but there is still a correlation when only the active profiles are considered. A possible explanation for this effect is the longer time that larger dust grains remain near to the nucleus, acting to slow the overall rate at which dust leaves an aperture when there are more large grains (presumably when activity is highest near to perihelion). A more complex dust model needs to be employed to look at this effect in detail, so it is not considered further here. The comet's changing morphology and variable surface brightness profile show that A f ρ measurements must be treated with caution. Despite this caveat, we find that inspection of the values determined from the archival data can give some useful constraints. We measure A f ρ values with a peak at ∼ 1000 cm in the weeks after perihelion, with values ∼ 100 cm at r = 2 AU, ∼ 50 cm at 3 AU, and dropping to single figures (where the flux is entirely from the inactive nucleus, and A f ρ is consequently meaningless) beyond 4.5 AU. A f ρ is larger at a given distance post-perihelion than it is pre-perihelion, consistent with the slight offset in the brightness peak and also with the observed tendency of comets to remain active to larger distances outbound (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kelley et al. 2013</ref>). All measurements are consistent with single power-law fits pre-and post-perihelion, given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">A f ρ = 958 × r −3.18 (cm)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">A f ρ = 1552 × r −3.35 (cm)<label>(5)</label></formula><p>respectively. These are steeper than the canonical 1/r 2 often assumed for comets (and the average A f ρ ∝ r −2.3 found by A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. (1995)</ref>), but are shallower than the r −5.8 fit for 67P found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kidger (2003)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref> found exponents of −9.5±5.6 and −8.0±3.6 pre-perihelion, and −0.6±1.3 and −0.4± 1.2 post-perihelion, for A f ρ in UV and green continuum filters, but over a much reduced range in r (especially pre-perihelion). A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. (1995)</ref> found a slope of −1.34 ± 0.81, for the same range of distances (1.3 &lt; r &lt; 1.9 AU) post-perihelion. Our result is significantly shallower than the best fit found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Agarwal et al. (2007)</ref>, who obtained A f ρ = 2393 × r −5.08 cm by fitting phase corrected values from a variety of sources (including both the <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kidger (2003)</ref> and Schleicher (2006) data sets) in the range −2 &lt; r &lt; 3 AU (over three apparitions), although these authors note that the data have a large scatter and the obtained exponent is unexpectedly steep. A f ρ is, under the simplest assumptions, directly proportional to the dust production rate, with an empirical calibration suggesting that A f ρ in cm ≈ Q d in kg s −1 (A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. 1995</ref>). We can therefore compare the r dependence we find to that assumed (Q d ∝ r δ ) in various dust models: 4. The model by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">de Sanctis et al. (2005)</ref> can be approximated pre-perihelion by δ = −3.5 for r &lt; 2 AU, with a much steeper δ = −10.2 beyond this (based on their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">fig. 9</ref>, model A). Postperihelion we find that δ = −3.2 for r &lt; 2 AU and δ = −10.5 for r &gt; 2 AU fit their model. 5. The complex GIADA dust model ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fulle et al. 2010</ref>) does not provide a simple scaling with r for comparison, as it is based on a higher order fit to A f ρ data. It is not clear that such a function is required, given the error bars on <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fulle et al. (2010)</ref>'s <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig. 1</ref>; we find that power laws with −3 &lt; δ &lt; −2 given reasonable fits to the displayed data, although these do not necessarily trace the complex behaviour of the model.</p><p>Most of these models agree on a perihelion dust production rate Q d ≈ 1000 kg s −1 (with the exception of Ishiguro <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2008)</ref>, who obtain an order of magnitude lower rate), comparable to the number from a simple calibration of A f ρ. It is clear that the generally steeper dependence on r in the models means that they predict relatively little dust at larger distances than our photometry suggests. While it would certainly be worth applying more complex models to the data we present here, it appears that current models underestimate the dust production that can be expected at large heliocentric distance, and Rosetta should be prepared to encounter significant dust early in its mission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Gas production</head><p>For Rosetta, it is important to constrain the gas production rate of 67P around the orbit. This is actually of greater importance than the dust production rate, in terms of mission planning, as the effects of gas drag on the large solar panels present more problems (and transfer more momentum) than dust impacts on the spacecraft. The gas production rate is, however, more difficult to measure, requiring spectra or images in narrow-band filters, and is typically only possible when the comet is near to the Earth and Sun, and therefore already highly active. The Rband images we present are not sensitive to gas emissions, but can be used to compare predictions on total brightness from gas production models. The most substantial set of gas production rate observations come from <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref>, who presents narrow-band photometry taken around the 1982 and 1996 perihelion passages, reaching a maximum distance of r = 1.86 AU outbound, and also reviews measurements from other authors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Ootsubo et al. (2012)</ref> measured water and CO 2 production rates using the Akari satellite when 67P was at r = 1.8 AU inbound in 2008. There is considerable scatter in these measurements, attributed to rotational variability by <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref>, but in general water production rate is found to peak at Q ≈ 10 28 molecules s −1 around a month after perihelion.</p><p>For Rosetta planning there are agreed minimum and maximum activity levels expected, in terms of production rates for H 2 O, CO and CO 2 , at perihelion, 2, 3 and 3.5 AU <ref type="bibr">(Biele &amp; Her- fort 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Biele &amp; Ulamec 2013)</ref>. These define boundary conditions for planning trajectories (and science operations) possible in the so called 'Low' and 'High' activity cases, and are based on simple extrapolations from the observations rather than any complex model. The ALICE and OSIRIS instruments on Rosetta are using a power law fit to the observed water production rates for their planning, based on time from perihelion ∆T rather than r to include the asymmetric peak in activity (A'Hearn, private communication). It is given by log(Q) = 27.66 + 0.006836∆T, ∆T &lt; 35 (6) log(Q) = 28.10 − 0.009858∆T, <ref type="bibr">∆T &gt; 35</ref> This fit falls neatly between the minimum and maximum activity levels considered by ESA, and so, while obviously only an approximate model, provides a reference production rate for the medium activity case, which we believe to be the most likely actual scenario at the comet.</p><p>The fit is displayed for comparison with our photometry in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">fig. 6 and fig. 7</ref>, where we have converted water production to total magnitude using the empirical relationship log(Q) = 30.675 -0.2453m h ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Jorda et al. 1992</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jorda et al. , 2008</ref>. The total magnitude m h is for visual observations (assumed to approximately match the V-band), and is reduced to unit geocentric distance but does not include any phase function correction. As it is based on estimates of 'total' brightness, it is not based on observations through any fixed aperture, with individual measurements showing great variation. The relationship is essentially uncalibrated for distances beyond 2 -3 AU, at the limit of the measurements on Q(H 2 O) for normal comets. Together, these limitations mean that the magnitudes estimated from this method are indications only, and not more accurate than ±0.5 magnitudes, but they do still allow a useful comparison. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref> shows that the total brightness estimated from the water production rate is significantly lower than the measured R-band magnitude (including a correction of (V − R) = 0.5), despite the fact that our measurements are taken within ρ = 10, 000 km, and therefore underestimate the total brightness near to perihelion. The difference is more than a magnitude at all distances pre-perihelion, only giving similar results around the peak in water production. As both the magnitude and the plotted water model are based on observations, including data from the same perihelion passage, this is a real effect, not due to a difference in models.</p><p>This implies that 67P must be a relatively dusty comet, either due to water lifting more dust from the surface than other comets with the same production rate, or due to a significant component of the activity being driven by a different gas species (e.g. CO or CO 2 ). The measurement by <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Ootsubo et al. (2012)</ref> shows the ratio of CO 2 /H 2 O for 67P to be relatively low (7%) compared with other comets (median 17%) measured within 2.5 AU from the Sun. According to the taxonomy of A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. (1995)</ref> 67P is a carbon-chain depleted comet (although only 'mildly depleted' based on the reanalysis of the same data by <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref>), meaning that it has a lower C 2 /CN ratio than other comets. As the parent species of C 2 and CN are still debated, this does not tell us much about what is driving the dust. The production rates of other gasses (C 3 , NH) relative to OH are close to the average values for the depleted group of comets (A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. 1995</ref>). Surprisingly, A' <ref type="bibr">Hearn et al. (1995)</ref> also find a typical 'dust production' for 67P, with log(A f ρ/Q(OH)) = −25.23 ± 0.50 cm s molecule −1 , compared with the mean for depleted comets of −25.30 ± 0.29. <ref type="bibr">Schle- icher (2006)</ref> slightly update the value to -25.27, and note that this value is dustier than 'typical' comets, and almost identical to that found for 81P/Wild 2. We find a mean value of log(A f ρ/Q(OH)) = −24.89 ± 0.21 cm s molecule −1 , based on the OH production rates from <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref> and using the r dependency given above to generate the expected values of A f ρ at the time of each observation. The difference is largely due to the fact that we have corrected our A f ρ values to zero phase angle. Following the same approach we find an average dust/water relationship with log(A f ρ/Q(H 2 O)) = −24.94 ± 0.22 cm s molecule −1 , where we have included all available measurements of the H 2 O production rate. These measurements cover a range −1.8 &lt; r &lt; 1.9 AU, and there is a trend of increasing dust-to-gas ratio over this range (which was also noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref>), so the average value must be treated with caution. The trend can be ap-</p><note type="other">Article number, page 10 of 15 C. Snodgrass et al.: Beginning of activity in 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko and predictions for 2014/5 proximated by A f ρ/Q ∝ r 2.8</note><p>, implying that the dust-to-gas ratio increases with increasing distance from the Sun. Taken together with equation 4, this suggests that the pre-perihelion water production rate can be estimated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Q(H 2 O) ≈ 2.3 × 10 28 r −5.9 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>implying that Rosetta will encounter production rates of Q ∼ 6 × 10 24 molecules s −1 at r = 4 AU, ∼ 3 × 10 25 at 3 AU, and ∼ 4 × 10 26 at 2 AU. These must be treated as approximate, as it is unlikely that the A f ρ ↔ Q(H 2 O) relationship is valid at these larger distances. The exponent is similar to that found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref> at smaller r, who obtained Q(OH) ∝ r −6.4 and ∝ r −5.4 for pre-and post-perihelion, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Dust phase function</head><p>Finally, we attempt to put independent constraints on the phase function of the dust in 67P's coma. To do this we assume that the lightcurve follows simple power laws, based on the good fit to the heliocentric lightcurve based on β = 0.02 mag deg −1 , and repeat the fitting process allowing β to vary. We continue to fit the pre-and post-perihelion power laws separately, with one power law for each, using a single value of β for each pair of fits (i.e. we allow the heliocentric brightness dependence to be different on inbound and outbound legs as before, and assume that the dust phase function does not change around the orbit). By minimising the root-mean-squared variation around the best fit straight lines m R vs log(r), we find an optimal β = 0.03 ± 0.02 mag deg −1 . The r-dependence does not change much from that found assuming either β = 0.02 mag deg −1 or the <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Schleicher et al. (1998)</ref> phase function, which is not surprising as they bracket the best fit value, and both are covered by the formal uncertainty. Using β = 0.03 mag deg −1 we find the R-band flux is ∝ r −5.4 pre-perihelion and ∝ r −5.6 post-perihelion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Activity model</head><p>The simple power-law relationships given in previous sections are useful as they present a straightforward way to present observed trends, and make predictions based on those. However, there is no physical reason to expect that the real outgassing rate actually follows such rules. Ultimately, full 3D thermal evolution models (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Prialnik et al. 2004</ref>) will be key to understanding and interpreting the composition and activity of comets, but this is beyond the scope of this work. As a first step we employ a simple ice sublimation model to explore activity over a range of distances. We use the model developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Meech et al. (1986)</ref> and applied to 103P/Hartley 2, based on the long campaign of photometry on that comet before and after the EPOXI mission encounter ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Meech et al. 2011</ref>). The physics behind the model are described in more detail by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Meech &amp; Svoreň (2004)</ref>, but are briefly introduced here. As ices sublimate, from either the surface or subsurface layers, the escaping gas drags dust from the nucleus to escape into the coma and tail. In the absence of gas fluorescence, the total comet brightness has a contribution from the nucleus and the scattered light from the dust. It can be shown that the total coma brightness can be expressed as a function of mass loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Meech et al. 1986</ref>) via: where the time, t, is a function of the projected aperture size and grain velocity (for simplicity we assume the Bobrovnikoff approximation v ≈ r −0.5 m s −1 , for r in AU), and a, p λ and D g are the grain radius, albedo, and density, respectively. The mass loss is computed using the energy balance at the nucleus:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">m coma = 30.7 − 2.5log 10 p λ (dM/dt)t D g ar 2 ∆ 2 (8)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">F (1 − A)/r 2 = χ[σT 4 + L(T )(dm s /dt) + κ(dT/dz)].<label>(9)</label></formula><p>The left hand side of the equation is the incident solar flux and the terms on the right hand side represent the blackbody energy, the energy going into sublimation and conduction into the interior (which we assume is negligibly small). χ is a rotation parameter expressing whether the heat is deposited only on one face of the nucleus (slow rotator) or evenly over the whole surface (fast rotator). The mass loss per unit area, (dm s /dt) is related to the sublimation vapor pressure and the average speed of the gas molecules leaving the surface. The sources for the latent heats L(T ) and sublimation vapor pressures for some common ices are summarized in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Meech et al. (1986)</ref>. The free parameters in the model include: ice type, nucleus radius, albedo, emissivity, density, properties of the dust (sizes, density, phase function), and fractional active area. For 67P we have the advantage that many of the required properties are known (or are at least reasonably well constrained), leaving us to adjust fractional active area and ice composition to match the light curve. The assumed values for the model parameters are given in table 5.</p><p>We iterate changing the fractional active surface area until the calculated gas production rates match those observed at specific heliocentric distances. For CO 2 we find a fit consistent with flux estimates from Bauer et al. (2012) using WISE observations at 3.32 AU inbound, which gave Q(CO 2 )= 5 × 10 25 molecules s −1 , and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Ootsubo et al. (2012)</ref>, who obtained Q(CO 2 )= 4.3×10 25 at 1.84 AU from observations with the Akari satellite. The models suggested that 0.04% of the surface area was producing CO 2 (inbound) and required an enhancement to 0.09% postperihelion. Matching the photometric light curve brightness required a dominant grain size in the 5-micron range. The models require that 1.4% of the surface area is active for watersublimation, but that the dominant grain size is around 1.5 microns to match the light curve brightness. Without external constraint on gas production, the light curve brightness can be matched either by increasing the gas production and sublimating area, or by increasing the effective cross section of the scatterers, which can be done by making the average grain size smaller. The curves shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">fig. 9</ref> are the best fit from the combined CO 2 +H 2 O models that are consistent with all of the reported gas production rates, and fix the parameters as shown in table 5. Model fit to the archival photometry, plotted against true anomaly in degrees. Here the photometry is plotted as apparent magnitudes within ρ = 5 (without correction for observing geometry), as the model includes the geometry (producing 'waves' near aphelion due to changing geocentric distance). The three perihelion passages <ref type="bibr">(1996, 2002 and 2009</ref>) are plotted separately. The scale across the top of each figure gives the corresponding heliocentric distance (AU) and ∆T (days). The model reproduces all data well except for that within ∼ 30 • (≈ ± 1 month) of perihelion, where there is enhanced activity.</p><p>The same parameters are used for all three apparitions, showing there is no discernable secular variation in the production. The three data points close to perihelion are too bright for the model parameters above; the fractional active area has to increase to near 4% around perihelion, also consistent with the reported water production rates from <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Schleicher (2006)</ref>. In fact, the reported water production tapers back down to the values consistent with the model within about 1 month of perihelion. At large r the production rates predicted by these parameters provide a close match to those given by the fit to ∆T (equation 6), although they underestimate the perihelion activity. The model gives an enhanced production rates relative to equation 7 between r ∼ 2 and 3.5 AU, and lower rates at distances smaller or larger than this, although the results are of the same order of magnitude. At 4.3 AU, the distance we found for the start of 'detectable' activity in section 3, the model gives production rates of Q(H 2 O) = 1.4 × 10 24 and Q(CO 2 ) = 7.7 × 10 24 molecules s −1 . <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref> gives results from the model for various dates and distances, including the dates of relevance to Rosetta marked in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig.  10</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Predictions for 2014/5</head><p>Our observations indicate that activity in 67P starts at large heliocentric distance, at least 4.3 AU inbound. Modelling the full heliocentric lightcurve suggests that there is likely to be a very low level of activity present at even larger distances, which implies that Rosetta will find an already active comet when the spacecraft wakes up in January 2014 (at 4.5 AU). We expect the activity to reach a level detectable from Earth (with a large telescope) by March 2014. It will be an interesting test of sensitivities to see whether the remote sensing instruments onboard Rosetta are capable of detecting activity before this, although it may not be possible to try, given the expected schedule of recommissioning following deep space hibernation. Once again the comet will appear against a crowded stellar background (low galactic latitude), as seen from Earth, in 2014, necessitating the use of DIA methods to perform photometry from the ground. We expect that the comet will begin to show a noticeable coma in Earth-based images around the same time as the comet's nucleus is resolved by the OSIRIS cameras onboard Rosetta, in July 2014.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig. 10</ref> we show the expected brightness of the comet, as seen from Earth, based on the fit to our heliocentric lightcurve and the observing geometry around the next perihelion. The repeatability of the comet's activity in the last three perihelion passages suggests that we can be reasonably confident about this prediction. We include 2016, to cover the period when the comet is most easily observed from Earth, and the potential extended mission for Rosetta beyond its current 2015-12-31 end date. This plot shows that 67P will reach perihelion while at low (∼ 45 • ) solar elongation, and consequently be difficult to observe with large professional telescopes. The expected magnitude (peaking at m R ≈ 13) is, however, sufficient that total brightness estimates will be possible using smaller telescopes. Production rate measurements, requiring spectra or narrow-band photometry, will be more challenging, but are of great interest. Rosetta will provide in situ measurements of gas abundance in localised areas of the inner coma, but not the wider view needed to link these measurements to ground-based observations of other comets; measurements of the overall production of the comet can be used to make this link. Furthermore, a very complete heliocentric lightcurve through 2015 will allow comparison between the dust production rate of the comet, as measured for the whole body, with the dust flux in the inner coma and the changes in the nucleus measured by Rosetta's instruments. As we have shown, careful consistent analysis and good calibration can result in a very clean lightcurve; if combined with a large campaign to give almost constant coverage then such an approach will reveal any subtle changes (e.g. small outbursts) that can be correlated with events seen by the spacecraft.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions</head><p>We make use of an advanced difference image analysis package to remove the stellar background in exceptionally crowded fields, to reveal the comet in previously unusable data. This data covers the critical period around R h ≈ 4 AU when activity is expected to start. In addition, we have located archival images of the comet throughout its orbit, and processed them in a consistent manner to produce a reliable heliocentric lightcurve. We find:</p><p>1. Detectable activity (using the world's best current telescopes) starts as far from the Sun as 4.3 AU, based on excess flux in photometric measurements, while the comet morphology shows visible activity by 3.4 AU. 2. The comet's morphology and surface brightness profile exhibit significant variations around the orbit, but the heliocentric light curve is very smooth, with a peak shortly after perihelion. 3. The dust flux can be described by single power law fits, with only slight differences in slope around perihelion. We find A f ρ ∝ r −3.2 pre-perihelion and ∝ r −3.4 post-perihelion. 4. These slopes are used to predict the dust flux around the next perihelion, with a peak R-band magnitude of ∼ 13 expected in August 2015, as seen from Earth and measured within a ρ = 10,000 km aperture, although the comet will be at relatively low solar elongation (∼ 45 • ) at the time. 5. By comparing our A f ρ fits with previously published measurements of the gas production rate, we find that the average dust-to-gas ratio for the comet can be expressed as log(A f ρ/Q(H 2 O)) = −24.94±0.22 cm s molecule −1 , for measurements within 1.9 AU of the Sun. A trend of increasing dust-to-gas with increasing distance allows us to find a very approximate r dependence for water production, Q(H 2 O) ∝ r −5.9 , although we caution that this is unlikely to match reality at larger distances. 6. A physical model based on sublimation from the nucleus is used to fit the observed brightness of the comet, and suggests that 1.4% of the surface is active (sublimating water), while 0.04-0.09% of the surface is sublimating CO 2 . There is a peak around perihelion requiring an increase of the active area to ∼ 4% of the surface. Using ρ = 10,000 km at the comet, and corrected to zero phase angle. (f) Calibration source for each night: APASS / SDSS -field stars from these catalogues; ESO -nightly (n) or default (d) zeropoints from ESO web page; Landolt -zeropoint calculated using observations of Landolt/Stetson standard stars on the same night; Tubiana -zeropoint solutions taken from Tubiana (2008) (from Landolt stars); Lara -photometry calculated from A f ρ values reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Lara et al. (2011)</ref>. The A f ρ value quoted here has been corrected to zero phase (Lara measurements were all taken at ∼ 36 • ).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example of the DIA method applied to 67P. This frame is taken from the October 2007 data set, and shows the original (left) and subtracted (right) versions of the same area, centred on the comet position. The comet is impossible to identify, much less perform photometry on, in such a crowded field, but is clearly revealed as a positive and negative pair in the subtracted frames. Saturated stars are masked in the difference image. North is up, East to the left.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Position of 67P in its orbit at the time of the observations used in this paper. Open symbols indicate visible activity, closed symbols indicate an apparently inactive nucleus. The VLT data presented in detail are marked by red diamonds, while the archival data are marked by triangles. The comet moves in an counter-clockwise fashion in this plot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Photometry covering the period July 2007 to March 2008, showing the apparent R-band magnitude of the comet (corrected for rotational phase). The solid line shows the predicted magnitude of the bare nucleus (based on the July 2007 data; Tubiana et al. (2011)), with the dashed lines showing the 1σ uncertainty on this. The comet appears to be significantly brighter than expected by November 2007, indicating some unresolved activity within the aperture at this point (at a heliocentric distance of 4.3 AU). By March 2008, when the comet is visibly active in images, the difference is more than 1 magnitude.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Median R-band image from 12×60 second images over 3 nights in March 2008. By this point (at r = 3.4 AU) the comet is visibly active, with a faint tail to the West (right in this image; North is up).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Surface brightness profiles for the comet in (a) August, (b) September, (c) October, (d) November 2007, and (e) March 2008. The points show the comet profile, while the line shows the image PSF. (a) -(c) show star-like profiles, while (e) shows clear activity. (d) is difficult to interpret due to residuals in the image from saturated stars (the bumps beyond ρ = 1 ). The gaps in the comet profiles in (a) -(c) around ρ ∼ 2 are due to the negative imprint from the reference image.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Heliocentric lightcurve, showing the R-band magnitude measured within an aperture of radius 10,000 km at the distance of the comet, corrected to unit geocentric distance and zero phase angle, against heliocentric distance in AU. Negative heliocentric distance shows pre-perihelion measurements. Different symbols show data taken during different apparitions, and highlight 'our data' presented in section 3 (which were taken at the start of the 2009 apparition). The solid black line shows the expected magnitude of the bare nucleus, based on the absolute magnitude reported by Tubiana et al. (2011). The dashed line shows a prediction for the total magnitude based on a water production rate model (see section 4.3), while the dotted lines show a power law fit to the data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Same as fig. 6, but with heliocentric lightcurve against time from perihelion in days. In this plot we show only data within ± 1 year of perihelion, to highlight the peak region.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Representative images and corresponding surface brightness profiles for 67P at four different points in its orbit. From left to right: May 2003, at 2.9 AU post-perihelion, showing high activity and a trail or neck-line of larger particles; June 2004, 4.9 AU post-perihelion, with the nucleus inactive but a clear neck-line; March 2008, 3.4 AU, at the start of visible activity; October 2008, 1.9 AU pre-perihelion, displaying a broad tail.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Predicted apparent R-band magnitude of the comet, as measured within an aperture with ρ =10,000 km, for 2014-2016. This covers the active phase of the Rosetta mission, including any extended mission beyond the end of 2015. Mission milestones in 2014 are marked: (a) Switch on of the spacecraft (January 20th, 2014); (b) Expected beginning of detectable activity, at 4.3 AU (March 2014); (c) The nucleus begins to be resolved by the OSIRIS Narrow Angle Camera on Rosetta (July 2014); (d) Orbit insertion (August 2014, at 3.5 AU); (e) Lander released (November 2014, at 3 AU). The observability of the comet from Earth is shown by hatched, cross-hatched and solid grey areas marking when the solar elongation is less than 50 • , 30 • and 15 • , respectively. Perihelion (in August 2015) is marked by a vertical dashed line. At that time the comet will be 43 • from the Sun, as seen from Earth. The lower 3 panels show various geometric parameters that describe the observability of the comet. Upper panel: Solar elongation (solid line) and phase angle (dashed line); Middle panel: Declination; Lower panel: Heliocentric (solid line) and geocentric (dashed line) distances.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Observational circumstances -67P monitoring 2007/8.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Date 
r a 
∆ b 
α c 
Exp d 
Filt. 
7/8/07 4.55 3.86 10.1 
10 × 60 (4) 
R 
10/9/07 4.41 4.21 13.1 
10 × 60 (5) 
R 
10/10/07 4.28 4.55 12.5 
20 × 60 (10) 
R 
12/11/07 4.13 4.82 9.2 
10 × 60 (7) 
R 
15/11/07 4.11 4.83 8.8 
20 × 30 (0) 
R 
27/3/08 3.39 3.80 14.6 3×15 + 4×60 (6) VRI 
29/3/08 3.38 3.76 14.9 3×15 + 4×60 (6) VRI 
30/3/08 3.38 3.74 15.0 3×15 + 4×60 (6) VRI 

(a) 

Heliocentric distance (AU). (b) Geocentric distance (AU). 
(c) Phase angle (degrees). (d) Number of exposures × exposure 
time (seconds) taken. The number in parenthesis gives the num-
ber of frames used in the analysis. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . Professional imaging of 67P, 1983-2010. Archival data from dates in bold face were used in this study.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>UT Date Instrument 
PI 
ESO Prog. ID. 
r (AU) 
∆ (AU) 
α (deg) 
Reference 
12 Oct 1982 -10 Mar 1983 Lowell photometer 
Schleicher 
-
1.3 -1.8 0.4 -1.1 
13 -37 
Schleicher (2006) 
10-16 Apr 1991 KPNO 2.1m+CCD 
Mueller 
-
4.9 
3.9 
4 
Mueller (1992) 
25 Jun 1995 2.2m+EFOSC 
Boehnhardt 055.F-0337 
2.5 
1.9 
22 
-
18 Nov 1995 -14 Apr 1996 Lowell photometer 
Schleicher 
-
1.3 -1.6 1.0 -1.8 
34 -48 
Schleicher (2006) 
12 Dec 1995 NTT+EMMI 
Boehnhardt 056.F-0133 
1.4 
1.0 
46 
-
09-11 Feb 1996 OHP 1.93m + CARELEC Weiler 
-
1.3 
1.2 
46 
Weiler et al. (2004) 
14 Jun 1999 JKT+CCD 
Lowry 
-
5.7 
4.8 
4 
Lowry et al. (2003) 
15 Jul 1999 NTT+SUSI 
Tancredi 
063.S-0504 
5.7 
5.1 
8 
-
25 May 2000 UH 2.2m 
Meech 
-
5.3 
4.3 
4 
-
30 Sep 2000 UH 2.2m 
Meech 
-
5.0 
5.1 
8 
-
17 Aug + 30 Sep 2001 UH 2.2m 
Meech 
-
3.3 -3.5 2.8 -3.0 
11 -17 
-
09 Sep 2002 Kiso 1.05m Schmidt 
Ishiguro 
-
1.3 
1.7 
36 
Ishiguro (2008) 
02 Dec 2002 + 01 Feb 2003 Kiso 1.05m Schmidt 
Ishiguro 
-
1.8 -2.2 1.4 -1.6 
18 -33 
Ishiguro (2008) 
11 Dec 2002 SDSS 
-
-
1.8 
1.6 
32 
-
10 Feb 2003 3.6m+EFOSC 
Boehnhardt 070.C-0505 
2.3 
1.4 
13 
Schulz et al. (2004) 
20 Feb + 27 Mar 2003 TNG+DOLORES 
Lara 
-
2.4 -2.6 1.4 -1.7 
9 -10 
Lara et al. (2005) 
Feb -Apr 2003 IAC-80+CCD 
Lara 
-
2.4 -2.8 1.4 -2.0 
8 -16 
Lara et al. (2005) 
07 Mar -30 May 2003 TLS 2m+CCD 
Weiler 
-
2.5 -3.1 1.5 -2.8 
4 -19 
Weiler et al. (2004) 
08 Mar 2003 3.6m+EFOSC 
Boehnhardt 070.C-0505 
2.5 
1.5 
4 
Schulz et al. (2004) 
12 -13 Mar 2003 HST+WFPC2 
Lamy 
-
2.5 
1.5 
5 
Lamy et al. (2006) 
25 Mar 2003 NTT+EMMI 
LSO tech 
-
2.6 
1.7 
9 
-
30 Apr -24 Jun 2003 VLT+FORS 
Schulz 
270.C-5035 
2.9 -3.2 2.3 -3.2 
18 -19 
Schulz et al. (2004) 
29+30 May 2003 UH 2.2m 
Meech 
-
3.0 
2.8 
19 
-
25-27 Jun 2003 Hale 200" + LFC 
Kelley 
-
3.2 
3.4 
18 
Kelley et al. (2008) 
22-26 Feb 2004 NTT+EMMI/SUSI 
LSO tech 
-
4.5 
4.0 
12 
Lowry et al. (2012) 
14 Apr 2004 VLT+FORS 
Boehnhardt 
073.C-0346 
4.7 
3.7 
2 
Tubiana et al. (2011) 
18-21 Apr 2004 2.2m+WFI 
Agarwal 
072.A-9011 
4.7 
3.7 
1 
Agarwal et al. (2010) 
23+27 Apr 2004 NTT+EMMI 
Lowry 
073.C-0061 
4.7 
3.7 
1 
-
30 Apr + 01 May 2004 3.6m+EFOSC 
Stuewe 
073.C-0846 
4.7 
3.7 
2 
-
13 Jun 2004 3.6m+EFOSC 
Rauer 
073.C-0571 
4.9 
4.2 
10 
-
16 Jun 2004 VLT+FORS 
Boehnhardt 073.C-0346 
4.9 
4.3 
10 
Tubiana et al. (2008) 
21+22 Jun 2004 UH 2.2m 
Meech 
-
4.9 
4.4 
11 
-
10-14 May 2005 NTT+EMMI 
Lowry 
075.C-0247 
5.6 
4.6 
0.1 -0.8 Lowry et al. (2012) 
11 May -01 Jun 2005 CFHT+Megacam 
Ishiguro 
-
5.6 
4.6 
0.1 -3 
-
04-05 Aug 2005 VLT+VIMOS 
Gruen 
275.B-5034 
5.7 
5.5 
10 
-
25 May -01 Jun 2006 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
077.C-0609 
5.6 
4.6 
1 
Tubiana et al. (2008) 
17-22 Aug 2006 VLT+FORS 
Boehnhardt 277.C-5038 
5.5 
5.3 
10 
Tubiana et al. (2008) 
16 Apr -16 Jul 2007 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
079.C-0687 
4.6 -5.0 3.7 -4.5 
4 -11 
Tubiana et al. (2011) 
16-22 Jul 2007 NTT+EMMI 
Lowry 
079.C-0384 
4.6 
3.7 
6 
Lowry et al. (2012) 
07 Aug 2007 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
079.C-0687 
4.6 
3.8 
10 
this work 
10 Sep 2007 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
079.C-0687 
4.4 
4.2 
13 
this work 
14 Sep 2007 NTT+EMMI 
Lowry 
079.C-0384 
4.4 
4.2 
13 
Lowry et al. (2012) 
10 Oct 2007 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
080.C-0259 
4.3 
4.5 
13 
this work 
12-15 Nov 2007 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
080.C-0259 
4.3 
4.6 
12 
this work 
27-30 Mar 2008 VLT+FORS 
Barrera 
080.C-0259 
3.4 
3.8 
15 
this work 
30-31 May 2008 VLT+FORS 
Schulz 
281.C-5004 
3.0 
2.5 
19 
-
01-05 Jun 2008 VLT+FORS/ISAAC 
Tozzi 
381.C-0123 
3.0 
2.5 
19 
Tozzi et al. (2011) 
02-04 Jul 2008 VLT+FORS 
Schulz 
281.C-5004 
2.8 
1.9 
14 
-
06-10 Jul 2008 2.2m+WFI 
Gruen 
081.A-9019 
2.7 
1.9 
14 
Agarwal et al. (2009) 
01-16 Aug 2008 2.2m+WFI 
LSO tech 
-
2.4 -2.6 1.5 -1.6 
6 
-
10 Aug 2008 VLT+FORS 
Schulz 
281.C-5004 
2.5 
1.5 
5 
-
03-07 Sep 2008 VLT+FORS/ISAAC 
Tozzi 
381.C-0123 
2.3 
1.4 
15 
Tozzi et al. (2011) 
13 Sep 2008 VLT+FORS 
Schulz 
281.C-5004 
2.2 
1.4 
19 
-
21-29 Oct 2008 VLT+FORS/ISAAC 
Tozzi 
082.C-0740 
1.9 
1.5 
31 
Tozzi et al. (2011) 
11 Dec 2008 IAA 1.52m + CCD 
-
-
1.6 
1.7 
35 
Fulle et al. (2010) 
25-27 Dec 2008 IGO 2m 
-
-
1.5 
1.7 
36 
Hadamcik et al. (2010) 
13 Jan 2009 TNG+DOLORES 
Tozzi 
-
1.4 
1.7 
36 
Tozzi et al. (2011) 
25 Jan -12 Mar 2009 Lulin 1m + CCD 
Lara 
-
1.2 -1.3 
1.7 
36 
Lara et al. (2011) 
28 Jan 2009 NTT+EFOSC 
Lowry 
082.C-0517 
1.3 
1.7 
36 
-
19 Mar 2009 CA 2.2m+CAFOS 
Lara 
-
1.3 
1.7 
35 
Lara et al. (2011) 
17-19 Mar 2009 OHP 0.8m 
-
-
1.3 
1.7 
35 
Hadamcik et al. (2010) 
30 Apr -01 May 2009 IGO 2m 
-
-
1.4 
2.0 
29 
Hadamcik et al. (2010) 
01 Feb -29 Mar 2010 VLT+FORS 
Boehnhardt 
384.C-0115 
3.4 -3.7 2.7 -3.0 
3 -16 
-
14-16 Feb 2010 NTT+EFOSC 
Snodgrass 
084.C-0594 
3.5 
2.9 
14 
-
16 Mar 2010 SOAR+SOI 
Barrera 
-
3.6 
2.7 
8 
-
09 Apr 2010 SOAR+SOI 
Barrera 
-
3.8 
2.8 
1 
-
14 Jul + 30 Aug 2010 NTT+EFOSC 
Lowry 
185.C-1033 
4.3 -4.5 4.3 -5.1 
9 -14 
-

Article number, page 3 of 15 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 3 . Photometry from the 2007/8 VLT data (without rotational phase correction).</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Date 
MJD 
m R 
σ R 
7/8/2007 
54320.05823 22.32 0.04 
54320.05951 22.27 0.03 
54320.06068 22.31 0.03 
54320.06194 22.31 0.04 
10/9/2007 54354.03934 22.76 0.06 
54354.04065 22.74 0.05 
54354.04185 22.75 0.06 
54354.04317 22.80 0.06 
54354.04437 22.67 0.05 
10/10/2007 54384.01135 22.40 0.06 
54384.01252 22.29 0.06 
54384.01358 22.32 0.06 
54384.01476 22.54 0.07 
54384.01583 22.60 0.08 
54384.01971 22.50 0.07 
54384.02079 22.70 0.08 
54384.02303 22.50 0.07 
54384.02420 22.38 0.06 
54384.02527 22.51 0.07 
12/11/2007 54417.00344 21.80 0.14 
54417.00449 21.87 0.12 
54417.00560 22.01 0.13 
54417.00664 21.86 0.12 
54417.00787 21.83 0.10 
54417.00901 21.95 0.12 
54417.01177 22.15 0.13 
27/3/2008 54553.37439 20.67 0.04 
54553.37554 20.82 0.04 
54553.37674 20.68 0.02 
54553.37785 20.77 0.02 
54553.37918 20.72 0.02 
54553.38026 20.77 0.02 
29/3/2008 54555.38642 20.80 0.04 
54555.38699 20.71 0.03 
54555.38801 20.69 0.02 
54555.38920 20.68 0.02 
54555.39027 20.67 0.02 
54555.39145 20.66 0.02 
30/3/2008 54556.38324 20.90 0.04 
54556.38381 20.78 0.04 
54556.38534 20.66 0.02 
54556.38642 20.67 0.02 
54556.38750 20.68 0.02 
54556.38858 20.72 0.02 

in September 2007. The October profile also appears star-like, 
while the November profile matches the image PSF in the inner 
parts. The presence of residuals from saturated stars near to the 
comet's position in November makes the profile difficult to mea-
sure at larger distances, so it is difficult to draw firm conclusions 
from it. By March 2008 the activity is obvious in the profile, as 
expected. 
Taken together, the photometry and profiles suggest that 
67P's activity reached a detectable level from the ground at 
around 4.3 AU in November 2007, just as it was lost from view 
from Earth due to decreasing solar elongation. It is unfortu-
nate that the two nights in November that were therefore critical 

Article number, page 5 of 15 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 5 . Parameters used in the activity model</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Parameter 
Value 
Reference 
Nucleus: 
Phase coefficient 0.076 mag deg −1 Tubiana et al. (2011) 
Albedo 
0.054 
Kelley et al. (2009) 
Radius 
2.04 km 
Kelley et al. (2009) 
Emissivity 
0.9 
assumed 
Rotation period 
12.68 hr (slow) 
Tubiana et al. (2011) 
Density 
400 kg m −3 
assumed 
Dust: 
Phase coefficient 0.02 mag deg −1 
assumed 
Grain density 
1000 kg m −3 
assumed 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 6 . Production rates in 2014/5 from the ice sublimation model.</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Date 
r 
Q(CO 2 ) 
Q(H 2 O) 
(AU) kg s −1 molec. s −1 kg s −1 molec. s −1 
20/01/14 
4.5 
0.50 
6.8E+24 
0.01 
5.2E+23 
20/03/14 
4.3 
0.57 
7.7E+24 
0.04 
1.4E+24 
23/05/14 
4.0 
0.69 
9.3E+24 
0.13 
4.7E+24 
20/07/14 
3.7 
0.80 
1.1E+25 
0.36 
1.4E+25 
20/08/14 
3.5 
0.89 
1.2E+25 
0.62 
2.3E+25 
11/11/14 
3.0 
1.30 
1.7E+25 
2.2 
8.1E+25 
21/01/15 
2.5 
1.90 
2.5E+25 
5.3 
2.0E+26 
28/03/15 
2.0 
2.90 
3.9E+25 
12 
4.4E+26 
04/06/15 
1.5 
5.20 
7.1E+25 
27 
1.0E+27 
13/08/15 
1.2 
7.70 
1.0E+26 
42 
1.6E+27 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Photometry from archival data 

Date 
Inst. 
N a 
r b 
∆T c 
m R 
m R (r,1,0) d 
m R 
m R (r,1,0) A f ρ e 
slope calib. f 
(AU) (days) 
(ρ = 10,000 km) 
(ρ = 5 ) 
(cm) 
1996 apparition: 
25/06/1995 EFOSC 
3 
-2.50 
-205 
17.46 
15.61 
17.60 
15.75 
46 
-1.93 APASS 
12/12/1995 EMMI 
1 
-1.37 
-36 
13.15 
12.22 
13.87 
12.94 
317 
-1.28 APASS 
2002 apparition: 
09/09/2002 KISO 
13 
1.32 
22 
13.34 
11.45 
13.94 
12.05 
598 
-1.90 SDSS 
11/12/2002 SDSS 
1 
1.84 
115 
15.35 
13.70 
15.97 
14.31 
146 
-1.29 SDSS 
10/02/2003 EFOSC 
1 
2.30 
177 
15.57 
14.57 
16.39 
15.39 
103 
-1.21 SDSS 
08/03/2003 EFOSC 
10 
2.49 
203 
15.91 
14.94 
16.68 
15.70 
86 
-1.21 SDSS 
25/03/2003 EMMI 
2 
2.61 
220 
16.61 
15.30 
17.26 
15.95 
67 
-1.21 SDSS 
30/04/2003 FORS 
5 
2.86 
256 
18.08 
15.97 
18.38 
16.27 
44 
-
SDSS 
01/05/2003 FORS 
5 
2.87 
257 
18.06 
15.93 
18.35 
16.22 
45 
-1.00 SDSS 
02/05/2003 FORS 
8 
2.87 
258 
18.10 
15.95 
18.38 
16.23 
45 
-0.70 SDSS 
03/05/2003 FORS 
9 
2.88 
259 
18.13 
15.96 
18.40 
16.24 
45 
-1.15 SDSS 
04/05/2003 FORS 
7 
2.89 
260 
18.18 
16.00 
18.44 
16.26 
43 
-
SDSS 
03/06/2003 FORS 
2 
3.08 
290 
18.93 
16.23 
18.83 
16.13 
40 
-0.82 SDSS 
04/06/2003 FORS 
1 
3.09 
291 
19.20 
16.49 
19.11 
16.40 
32 
-1.24 SDSS 
19/06/2003 FORS 
2 
3.19 
306 
19.42 
16.51 
19.18 
16.27 
33 
-0.94 SDSS 
20/06/2003 FORS 
1 
3.19 
307 
19.42 
16.50 
19.18 
16.26 
33 
-1.07 SDSS 
23/06/2003 FORS 
1 
3.21 
310 
19.50 
16.55 
19.23 
16.27 
32 
-1.59 SDSS 
24/06/2003 FORS 
1 
3.22 
311 
19.47 
16.50 
19.19 
16.23 
34 
-1.41 SDSS 
23/02/2004 SUSI 
4 
4.47 
555 
21.50 
18.27 
21.10 
17.87 
13 
-2.21 ESO (n) 
29/04/2004 EFOSC 
5 
4.73 
621 
21.65 
18.76 
21.56 
18.67 
9 
-2.38 SDSS 
16/06/2004 FORS 
10 
4.89 
669 
22.42 
19.05 
22.04 
18.67 
7 
-2.60 Tubiana 
2009 apparition: 
30/05/2006 FORS 
61 -5.61 -1005 22.68 
19.36 
22.65 
19.32 
7 
-2.64 ESO (n) 
17/08/2006 FORS 
3 
-5.51 
-926 
23.13 
19.32 
-
-
7 
-
Tubiana 
27/03/2008 FORS 
7 
-3.39 
-338 
20.38 
17.19 
20.29 
17.10 
20 
-
Landolt 
29/03/2008 FORS 
7 
-3.38 
-336 
20.47 
17.30 
20.57 
17.40 
18 
-2.55 Landolt 
30/03/2008 FORS 
7 
-3.38 
-335 
20.30 
17.13 
20.28 
17.11 
21 
-2.50 Landolt 
31/05/2008 FORS 
8 
-2.98 
-273 
18.90 
16.54 
18.93 
16.57 
28 
-1.97 Landolt 
03/06/2008 FORS 
8 
-2.96 
-270 
18.76 
16.45 
18.80 
16.50 
30 
-1.91 Landolt 
04/06/2008 FORS 
8 
-2.95 
-269 
18.78 
16.49 
18.83 
16.54 
29 
-1.89 Landolt 
04/07/2008 FORS 
6 
-2.75 
-239 
17.77 
16.10 
17.90 
16.23 
36 
-1.92 Landolt 
10/08/2008 FORS 
5 
-2.48 
-202 
16.16 
15.22 
16.51 
15.56 
66 
-1.72 Landolt 
03/09/2008 FORS 
16 -2.30 
-178 
16.23 
15.22 
16.58 
15.57 
56 
-1.70 ESO (n) 
05/09/2008 FORS 
16 -2.28 
-176 
15.90 
14.87 
16.27 
15.24 
77 
-1.79 Landolt 
06/09/2008 FORS 
16 -2.28 
-175 
15.96 
14.93 
16.32 
15.28 
73 
-1.62 Landolt 
07/09/2008 FORS 
16 -2.27 
-174 
16.21 
15.17 
16.56 
15.51 
58 
-1.63 ESO (n) 
13/09/2008 FORS 
1 
-2.22 
-168 
15.94 
14.84 
16.27 
15.17 
75 
-1.77 Landolt 
21/10/2008 FORS 
5 
-1.93 
-130 
15.99 
14.47 
16.31 
14.80 
79 
-1.71 ESO (n) 
25/10/2008 FORS 
5 
-1.90 
-126 
15.81 
14.26 
16.16 
14.60 
93 
-1.85 ESO (n) 
26/10/2008 FORS 
5 
-1.89 
-125 
16.01 
14.45 
16.33 
14.76 
78 
-1.86 ESO (n) 
25/01/2009 LOT 
-
-1.31 
-34 
13.52 
11.69 
-
-
476 
-
Lara 
28/01/2009 EFOSC 
3 
-1.30 
-31 
13.62 
11.79 
13.97 
12.13 
426 
-1.65 ESO (d) 
30/01/2009 LOT 
-
-1.29 
-29 
13.46 
11.62 
-
-
490 
-
Lara 
31/01/2009 LOT 
-
-1.29 
-28 
13.46 
11.63 
-
-
486 
-
Lara 
23/02/2009 LOT 
-
-1.25 
-5 
13.05 
11.21 
-
-
666 
-
Lara 
25/02/2009 LOT 
-
-1.25 
-3 
13.37 
11.53 
-
-
497 
-
Lara 
26/02/2009 LOT 
-
-1.25 
-2 
12.97 
11.12 
-
-
721 
-
Lara 
12/03/2009 LOT 
-
1.26 
12 
12.87 
11.01 
-
-
813 
-
Lara 
19/03/2009 CAFOS 
-
1.27 
19 
13.04 
11.16 
-
-
724 
-
Lara 
15/02/2010 EFOSC 
5 
3.49 
352 
19.93 
17.34 
19.86 
17.27 
19 
-1.88 SDSS 
16/02/2010 EFOSC 
3 
3.49 
353 
20.02 
17.44 
19.96 
17.38 
17 
-2.29 SDSS 
14/07/2010 EFOSC 
3 
4.26 
501 
21.74 
18.30 
21.15 
17.72 
11 
-
SDSS 

(a) 

Number of images used. (b) Heliocentric distance. Negative numbers indicate pre-perihelion, positive post-perihelion. (c) Time before or after 
perihelion date. (d) Magnitude reduced to unit geocentric distance and zero phase angle. (e) </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> http://archive.eso.org</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> http://www.sdss3.org/dr9/algorithms/sdssUBVRITransform.php 4 http://www1.cadc-ccda.hia-iha.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/ssos/ Article number, page 4 of 15 C. Snodgrass et al.: Beginning of activity in 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko and predictions for 2014/5</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> See http://asteroid.lowell.edu/comet/dustphase.html for details. Article number, page 7 of 15</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1">. Agarwal et al. (2010) assume an equivalent of δ = −5, based on the Agarwal et al. (2007) fit to A f ρ. 2. Kelley et al. (2008, 2009) use δ = −5.8, from the fit by Kidger (2003). 3. Ishiguro (2008) uses the neck-line appearance to find a weak constraint on δ = −3, although this model considers only activity near perihelion. Article number, page 9 of 15</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boehnhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gruen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">European Planetary Science Congress</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page">537</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Grün</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Space Sci. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">992</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>&amp;apos;hearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Campins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Millis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>&amp;apos;hearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Millis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Osip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Birch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">223</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mainzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">758</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Biele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Herfort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ESA TN RO-ESC-TN-5566</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Biele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ulamec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LPI Contributions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1719</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1392</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bramich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">386</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bramich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Horne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Albrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2275</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>De Sanctis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Capria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coradini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">605</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ferrín</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">493</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ferrín</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planet. Space Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">365</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Fink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">221</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">721</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fulle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Colangeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">522</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D J</forename><surname>Gwyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kavelaars</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">579</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hadamcik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Levasseur-Regourd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lasue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">517</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holmberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Flynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Portinari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">449</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ishiguro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">96</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Danielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">435</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meech</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">992</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jorda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crovisier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W E</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Asteroids, Comets, Meteors</title>
		<editor>A. W. Harris &amp; E. Bowell</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="288" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jorda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crovisier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W E</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">LPI Contributions</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1405" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8046</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Licandro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">225</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">475</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">572</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wooden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tubiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4633</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Harker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">651</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1256</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kidger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">767</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Farnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schwieterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Toth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">674</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Toth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Groussin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">777</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Toth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">458</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">669</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Landolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">340</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De León</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Licandro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gutiérrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Moon and Planets</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z.-Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rodrigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-H</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Duddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rozitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">548</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Collander-Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">397</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Comet Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>A&amp;apos;hearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">734</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">561</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">585</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Svoreň</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Comets II</title>
		<editor>M. C. Festou, H. U. Keller, &amp; H. A. Weaver</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Arizona Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="335" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E A</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Asteroids, Comets, Meteors</title>
		<editor>A. W. Harris &amp; E. Bowell</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="428" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ootsubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kawakita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">752</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Prialnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Benkhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Podolak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Comets II</title>
		<editor>M. C. Festou, H. U. Keller, &amp; H. A. Weaver</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Arizona Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="387" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Millis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Birch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">397</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stüwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boehnhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bramich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in prep</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">287</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Weissman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Snodgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">737</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stetson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">925</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tenishev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Combi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">732</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Patriarchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boehnhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">531</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">; C</forename><surname>Tubiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Barrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Drahus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boehnhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">377</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Technischen Universität Carolo-Wilhelmina zu Braunschweig Tubiana,</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tubiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Böhnhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">527</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-B</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z.-Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sierks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Helbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">749</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
