<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:28+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Physics Of Eclipsing Binaries. II. Towards the Increased Model Fidelity</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-12-15">15 Dec 2016 -2 -</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astrophysics and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Villanova University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>800 E Lancaster Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>19085</postCode>
									<settlement>Villanova</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Conroy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astrophysics and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Villanova University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>800 E Lancaster Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>19085</postCode>
									<settlement>Villanova</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6301 Stevenson Center Ln</addrLine>
									<postCode>37235</postCode>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Horvat</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astrophysics and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Villanova University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>800 E Lancaster Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>19085</postCode>
									<settlement>Villanova</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ljubljana</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jadranska 19</addrLine>
									<postCode>SI-1000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ljubljana</settlement>
									<country key="SI">Slovenia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pablo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Montréal</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Pavillon Roger-Gaudry</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2900, boul. ´ Edouard-Montpetit</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3T 1J4</postCode>
									<settlement>Montréal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kochoska</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astrophysics and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Villanova University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>800 E Lancaster Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>19085</postCode>
									<settlement>Villanova</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ljubljana</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jadranska 19</addrLine>
									<postCode>SI-1000</postCode>
									<settlement>Ljubljana</settlement>
									<country key="SI">Slovenia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bloemen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Radboud University Nijmegen</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">IMAPP</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 9010</postBox>
									<postCode>6500 GL</postCode>
									<settlement>Nijmegen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Giammarco</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astronomy and Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eastern University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1300 Eagle Rd</addrLine>
									<postCode>19087</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Davids</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hambleton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Astrophysics and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Villanova University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>800 E Lancaster Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>19085</postCode>
									<settlement>Villanova</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Jeremiah Horrocks Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Central Lancashire</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>PR1 2HE</postCode>
									<settlement>Preston</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Degroote</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Instituut voor Sterrenkunde</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Celestijnenlaan 200D</addrLine>
									<postCode>3001</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven, Heverlee</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Physics Of Eclipsing Binaries. II. Towards the Increased Model Fidelity</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-12-15">15 Dec 2016 -2 -</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received October 1, 2016; accepted mmm dd, yyyy Received ; accepted</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Subject headings: Methods: analytical, numerical</term>
					<term>Techniques: photometric, Techniques: spectroscopic</term>
					<term>Binaries: close, eclipsing</term>
					<term>Stars: fundamental parameters</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The precision of photometric and spectroscopic observations has been systematically improved in the last decade, mostly thanks to space-borne photometric missions and ground-based spectrographs dedicated to finding exoplanets. The field of eclipsing binary stars strongly benefited from this development. Eclipsing binaries serve as critical tools for determining fundamental stellar properties (masses, radii, temperatures and luminosities), yet the models are not capable of reproducing observed data well either because of the missing physics or because of insufficient precision. This led to a predicament where radiative and dynami-cal effects, insofar buried in noise, started showing up routinely in the data, but were not accounted for in the models. PHOEBE (PHysics Of Eclipsing BinariEs; http://phoebe-project.org) is an open source modeling code for computing theoretical light and radial velocity curves that addresses both problems by incorporating missing physics and by increasing the computational fidelity. In particular , we discuss triangulation as a superior surface discretization algorithm, meshing of rotating single stars, light time travel effect, advanced phase computation , volume conservation in eccentric orbits, and improved computation of local intensity across the stellar surfaces that includes photon-weighted mode, enhanced limb darkening treatment, better reflection treatment and Doppler boosting. Here we present the concepts on which PHOEBE is built on and proofs of concept that demonstrate the increased model fidelity.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Eclipsing binary stars (EBs) serve as cornerstones of stellar astrophysics. Their uniquely important role in determining fundamental stellar parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Popper 1980</ref>), distances <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Pietrzy´nskiPietrzy´nski et al. 2013</ref>) and providing rigorous tests for stellar evolution models <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Torres et al. 2010</ref>) have been widely appreciated. While the underlying principles that govern the modeling of EBs are simple (Newtonian mechanics and straight-forward geometry considerations), a plethora of complications arises from subtler effects: surface distortions, intensity variations due to gravity darkening, limb darkening, reflection and surface prominences. As the precision of the data increases, so does the number of subtleties that a reliable model needs to take into account.</p><p>This decade has provided us with a range of ground-breaking surveys and missions:</p><p>MOST ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Walker et al. 2003</ref>), CoRoT (Baglin 2003), <ref type="bibr">Kepler (Borucki et al. 2010</ref>), Pan-Starrs ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kaiser et al. 2002)</ref>, Gaia (de Bruijne 2012) and LSST <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Tyson &amp; LSST 2002)</ref>, to name just a few. These yielded a vast number of EBs ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Prša et al. 2011</ref> estimated ∼7 million from LSST alone), thousands to unprecedented quality (down to ∼20 ppm for Kepler light curves; cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> for several examples of attained precision). We are seeing phenomena that have been up until recently only theorized, but now they are appearing routinely: modern observations provide us with a glimpse into the micromagnitude scale. With such a tremendous boost in both quantity and quality, the tools we use to reduce, analyze and interpret data need to be able to cope with this literal firehose of observations. Yet from all the data currently available, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Torres et al. (2010)</ref> find only ∼100 EBs with the uncertainties in the masses and radii smaller than 3%. For such benchmark objects, this number is several orders of magnitude too low.</p><p>Having superb quality data in abundance has clear repercussions on our modeling capability. For the first time we observe astrophysical objects in a near-uninterrupted regime, with uncertainties that dip below 20 ppm. State-of-the-art models such as the renowned Wilson-Devinney code <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Wilson &amp; Devinney 1971;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Wilson 1979</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilson , 2008</ref> This is partly because of embedded approximations, partly because of the inconsistent use of physical units and constants (cf. the IAU 2015 resolution B3; <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Prša et al. 2016</ref>) and partly because of the missing and/or inadequate physics built into these models. The residuals of the best-fit models and observed data are no longer Gaussian, and we cannot assume that these effects are buried in noise; rather, we need to account for their signatures in light and radial velocity curves explicitly. Furthermore, the codes provide minimization algorithms that fit model curves to the data. EB data fitting is a highly non-linear problem that suffers from degenerate solutions: the right combination of the wrong parameters can often fit the observed data as well as the actual solution. The algorithms currently in use, namely Differential Corrections (DC), <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Powell (1964)</ref>'s direction set method, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Nelder &amp; Mead (1965)</ref>'s Simplex method (NMS), and genetic algorithms ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Attia et al. 2009</ref>), have all met with success, but cannot be run robustly without experienced human intervention, making the tools fully manual.</p><p>In this paper we discuss several deficiencies of our models and present advancements in improving the reliability of binary star solutions. The improvements result from including missing instrumental and astrophysical phenomena in the model explicitly, thus reducing systematical errors in correlated parameters that no longer need to compensate for the missing aspects in the code. The paper is accompanied by the release of the new version of the open source modeling code PHOEBE 2.0, available from http://phoebe-project.org, along with extensive documentation and tutorials.</p><p>The layout of the paper is as follows. In Section 2 we provide background on the PHOEBE project; Section 3 introduces the new triangulation scheme for surface discretization; Section 4 focuses on dynamical and temporal aspects of the model; Section 5 gives the rationale for computing all local quantities across the mesh; in Section 6 we discuss current limitations and provide concluding remarks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Revising the PHOEBE model</head><p>The original PHOEBE model ) was based on the Wilson-Devinney code <ref type="bibr">(Wilson &amp; Devinney 1971, hereafter WD)</ref>. The most important features of the model include: an analytic description of binary star orbits, including apsidal motion and light time travel effect; shape distortion due to tides and (asynchronous) rotation; radiative properties of binary star components, including model atmosphere intensities, gravity darkening, limb darkening and mutual irradiation; and spots, circumbinary attenuation clouds and third light. PHOEBE introduced several scientific and technical extensions: the use of observed spectra as input data, determining individual temperatures by means of color constraining, enhanced reddening treatment, improvements to differential corrections, introduction of the downhill simplex fitting method, the built-in scripting backend, and a graphical user interface.</p><p>Since PHOEBE inherited the underlying logic of WD, it also inherited its limitations.</p><p>These became apparent as ultra-precise photometric data became available: the model could no longer produce adequate fits to light curves at Kepler's level of precision. In addition, a wealth of triple and multiple stellar systems have been discovered that exhibit eclipse timing variations due to the light time travel effect and dynamical effects, circumbinary planets and multiply eclipsing systems, all of which render the old model unsuitable. To overcome these inherited limitations, the new version of PHOEBE presented here has been rewritten from scratch. We present all novel aspects of the model, benchmarks that prompted a redesign, and comparison between original and revised models. The rewrite of the code was initiated in 2011 but was limited by the lack of funding; the current release has been made possible by the NSF support #1517474, which we gratefully acknowledge. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Discretization of implicit surfaces</head><p>Computing the amount of flux received from an EB becomes a non-trivial task as soon as there is even a marginal surface distortion of the EB components. The employed generalized</p><p>Roche geometry provides us with that distortion, and a range of related phenomena is then taken into account: surface brightness variation due to gravity darkening, limb darkening and reflection, ellipsoidal variations due to the changing cross-section size that faces the observer, spots coming in and out of view, etc. The dynamical aspects then render the two components onto their respective orbits and a numerical integration is done over the visible surfaces, determined by eclipses and visible cross-sections, to compute the total flux. It is thus imperative that local conditions across the surfaces of both components be approximated as well as possible. To achieve this, the surfaces were traditionally discretized uniformly along co-latitude and longitude into planar, trapezoidal elements for which we assume uniform local conditions. The most significant problem with this strategy is that the surface is approximated by a disconnected, self-overlapping mesh that does not cover the surface completely. The left panel in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> displays a part of the star near a pole, a region where these problems are particularly exacerbated. To combat this</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 u [R N ] 0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 v [R N ]</formula><p>Trapezoidal meshing</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 u [R N ] 0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 v [R N ]</formula><p>Triangulated meshing <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-Mesh comparison between the trapezoidal discretization using trapezoidal elements (left) and triangulation (right). The crosses denote surface element centers. Both parts correspond to the same region on the star. The issues with trapezoidal discretization are disconnected, overlapping meshes with holes, and obvious "seams" across the surface. All these cause systematic effects in computed fluxes. deficiency, surface element areas are not computed from the trapezoids themselves but from the theoretical surface element differentials, dσ = 1 cos β ρ 2 sin θdθdφ, where ρ, θ and φ are spherical coordinates, and β is the angle between the surface normal and the radius vector.</p><p>The problems become more pronounced as the components become distorted, and especially when we deal with ultra-precise photometric data, since a uniform sampling in co-latitude and longitude implies that the sampling in terms of surface coverage is not uniform.</p><p>To overcome this problem, we replaced trapezoidal surface elements with triangles.</p><p>The triangulation of implicit surfaces is a long standing problem in computational physics.</p><p>Hartmann (1998) presents a marching method : an algorithm that can discretize any implicit surface into a set of near-equilateral triangles, so that every element on the surface has approximately the same area, irrespective of the position or the amount of surface distortion. The right panel in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> demonstrates this: the polar region of the star has no inherent symmetry that would impose "seams" across the surface, or surface elements of notably different sizes. In effect, any systematics that may arise from surface discretization will be minimized. A mesh generated this way is computationally tractable and it alleviates the problems with holes or overlaps between trapezoidal elements. An added benefit is that we can discretize any implicit geometric body (i.e. accretion disks, disintegrating planets, alien megastructures) and model any transient phenomena within the same formalism.</p><p>Triangulation by itself does not solve the problem of unequal surface areas of the mesh and of the isosurface that the mesh approximates. This leads to a similar problem that trapezoidal discretization suffers from: while a trapezoidal mesh overestimates the area because surface element centers are on the isosurface, triangulation underestimates the surface area because the vertices are on the isosurface. To correct for this, we offset all surface elements such that (1) the total surface area of the mesh exactly equals the analytical surface area of the isosurface, and (2) each surface element approximates the local isosurface optimally, i.e. it is positioned in a way that exactly balances isosurface deviations due to curvature below and above the surface element. The details of the mesh offsetting scheme are given in Appendix A.</p><p>PHOEBE currently supports two types of surface potentials: the Roche model and the rotating single star model. In general, though, any surface that can be described by an implicit equation can be readily incorporated into the code.</p><p>The generalized Roche lobe <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Wilson 1979</ref>) is defined by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Ω Roche (r; q, F, δ) = 1 r + q 1 (x − δ) 2 + y 2 + z 2 − x δ 2 + 1 2 (1 + q)F 2 (x 2 + y 2 ),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>expressed in Cartesian coordinates x, y and z, with the radius vector denoted by r = (x, y, z); q ≡ M 2 /M 1 is mass ratio, F ≡ P rot /P orb is synchronicity parameter and δ ≡ d/a is instantaneous separation between the stars relative to the semi-major axis a.</p><p>A significant difference between the marching and trapezoidal meshes arises in contact 1 binary systems computed with the Roche model. The trapezoidal method tends to diverge near the neck of contact envelopes, which requires the meshing of the surface to account for each star separately and "glue" them together at the neck <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Wilson 1979)</ref>. This can often lead to poor coverage of the neck region, particularly for systems with a small mass ratio and large fillout factor. The marching method, on the other hand, computes the entire contact binary mesh as one surface, with complete coverage of the neck region. Examples of a trapezoidal and triangulated mesh for a contact system are given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>.</p><p>The potential of an isolated star rotating around the z-axis is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Ω rot (r; ω) = 1 r + 1 2 ω 2 (x 2 + y 2 ),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where ω is the angular velocity of rotation. Support for other surface potentials will follow shortly, most notably for rotating and non-rotating spheres (designed for exoplanets), misaligned Roche potentials, general gravitational potentials (useful for multiple stellar systems) and accretion disk potentials (Horvat et al., in preparation). <ref type="bibr">1</ref> The original PHOEBE version, following the convention of the Wilson-Devinney nomenclature, used the term "overcontact"; here and throughout PHOEBE 2.0 we use the term "contact" as it avoids confusion with the outer lobe overflow and mass loss through L 2 and/or L 3 points, which is what "overcontact" might imply. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rucinski (1997)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Wilson (2001)</ref> for an in-depth discussion of this issue. The trapezoidal mesh is represented by its current implementation in PHOEBE , in which each trapezoid is split into two triangles for plotting, but retains its center, where all local quantities are computed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Dynamical aspects</head><p>Motions of two celestial bodies around the mutual center of mass are governed by</p><p>Kepler's equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Goldstein 1980</ref>). The orbits depend on the semi-major axis a, orbital period P 0 , mass ratio q, eccentricity e and systemic velocity v γ ; their orientation is given by inclination i, argument of periastron ω and longitude of the ascending node Ω. While this formalism describes dynamical positions of the bodies in their orbits, it does not describe the position where the observer sees the bodies due to the finite speed of light. This is all the more important when there are additional objects in the system because the systemic velocity of the binary is no longer constant.</p><p>To address this, PHOEBE defines the time reference t 0 with respect to the barycenter of the entire system, with a provision that the barycenter can move at a constant speed through space. The Light Travel Time Effect (LTTE) causes bodies closer to the observer w.r.t. barycenter to appear at an advanced point in orbit, while bodies farther from the observer w.r.t. barycenter appear retarded. In addition to the LTTE effect, perturbations of orbital elements (period change, apsidal motion, mass transfer, Kozai cycles, . . . ) also affect timing ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Borkovits et al. 2007</ref>). PHOEBE optionally accounts for these effects by computing all positions w.r.t. barycenter and then iteratively advancing or retarding the objects on their orbits by the amount consistent with their radial distance from the barycenter.</p><p>Support for hierarchically-nested Keplerian orbits as well as dynamics being driven by an N-body integrator, particularly applicable to triple and higher-order systems, is being developed (Conroy et al., in preparation).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Phase computation</head><p>Periodicity in eclipsing binary observables due to orbital dynamics is a backbone of modeling. All computations in PHOEBE are done in time-space, but it is often convenient to represent observables in phase-space as well. It is thus important to set a convention for phase. It is common practice to set the reference point t 0 at the time of superior conjunction (primary eclipse), but this is not a suitable convention because of apsidal motion (rotation of the line of apsides). Apsidal motion causes excursions of both conjunctions in the opposite directions with uniformly advancing time. Keeping a reference point at conjunction would cause us to measure an anomalous orbital period. In consequence, whatever reference point is chosen, it should not be linked to any particular point on the orbit (i.e. conjunction, periastron passage, etc). Instead, we define phase of conjunction w.r.t. the mean anomaly:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Φ C = M C + ω 2π − 1 4 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where mean anomaly M C is connected to the true anomaly via the familiar Kepler equations, and zero point in phase is set by convention to coincide with phase of conjunction when argument of periastron ω = π/2. This is chosen because the true anomaly (being measured from periastron) is υ C = π/2 − ω at superior conjunction. PHOEBE provides phases on the</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">[-0.5, 0.5] interval.</formula><p>To transform time to phase while allowing the period to vary linearly (i.e. ˙ P = 0), we solve the following differential equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">dΦ = mod dt P (t) ⇒ Φ(t) = mod dt P 0 + ˙ P (t − t 0 ) = mod 1 ˙ P log[P 0 + ˙ P (t − t 0 )] ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where P 0 is period at reference time t 0 , and mod is the modulo operation that maps its argument to the [−0.5, 0.5] interval. For ˙ P = 0, Φ(t) assumes a familiar expression:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Φ(t) = mod t − t 0 P 0 .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Note also that phase shift is a parameter that applies only to synthetic curves; it is used to reconcile the horizontal offset between data and the model when t 0 is kept at a geometric reference point, i.e. superior conjunction or argument of periastron. Phase shift does not affect phasing of observations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Volume conservation in eccentric orbits</head><p>A non-trivial assumption that partly follows from physical insight and partly from observations is stellar volume conservation in eccentric orbits. One of the fundamental assumptions of the Roche model is that a star adapts to the instantaneous force field on a timescale that is significantly shorter than the orbital period. In other words, a star will instantly change its shape to adapt to the equipotential that bounds it. In the case of eccentric orbits, however, equipotential lobes can change their volumes substantially. If a star adapted to this instantaneous equipotential at every point in its orbit, that would mean that it needs to rarefy or compress in order to fill the volume of the equipotential. In that case, some of the heat generated during compression would be irradiated away and thus not recovered during subsequent expansion. This energy would need to be replaced from the energy stored in orbit, leading to rapid circularization since even a tiny energy loss compounds quickly over many orbits. In effect, there would be essentially no eccentric short period binaries in the sky. This would also significantly impact the efficiency of Kozai cycles, which tighten the orbits on timescales orders of magnitude longer than the orbital period.</p><p>Observationally, if the volumes of stars changed on eccentric orbits, we would expect to see this effect in the measured radii of eclipsing binaries. However, eclipse durations are consistent with near-constant radii and, thus, near-constant volumes. Even the red giant and supergiant stars that would arguably be most susceptible to volume change don't exhibit any signs of an appreciable change in radius as a function of orbital phase. The star does not adapt to the equipotential but, instead, conserves its volume and fills a different equipotential to that at periastron. We thus conclude that volume conservation is a safe assumption with strong footing in both theoretical insight and observations.</p><p>That said, there is a particularly well suited test-bed for studying the validity of volume conservation in the limit of high eccentricities: highly eccentric ellipsoidal variables (also known as heartbeat stars; <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Thompson et al. 2012</ref>) that host red giants. Their components at periastron are separated by only a few stellar radii, giving rise to significant tidal forces that distort stellar surfaces. A total of 28 giants in heartbeat stars have been reported to date <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Nicholls &amp; Wood 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Gaulme et al. 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Gaulme et al. , 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Richardson et al. 2016</ref>); of these, there are 9 for which the authors developed a full model <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Nicholls &amp; Wood 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beck et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Richardson et al. 2016</ref>), all of them under the constant volume</p><p>assumption. Yet these are the prime candidates where small deviations from constant volume are plausible. Thus, even though the default mode of operation is to keep the volume constant, we allow the volume to change by a prescribed amount so that we can rigorously study the robustness of the volume conservation assumption. This will be the topic of Hambleton et al., in preparation.</p><p>To handle volume conservation within PHOEBE, the meshes are first built according to the equipotentials defined at periastron and their analytic volumes are computed (see Appendix B). When placed in orbit at any given time, the current instantaneous equipotential is then determined to be the equipotential that will result in this same volume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Sampling local quantities</head><p>In PHOEBE 1, the trapezoidal surface elements were placed so that the center of each element is on the equipotential surface. When using the marching method, the vertices of the triangles are placed on the equipotential. This allows us to sample all local physical quantities at the vertices rather than the centers of the surface elements. The physical quantity assigned to each fully visible triangle (partially visible triangles are discussed in Section 5.4) is the arithmetic mean of the values at each of the vertices. This is a linear approximation, i.e. we assume that the variation of each physical quantity across each discretized surface element is linear. It is therefore necessary to sample the surface with a sufficiently fine grid so that this approximation is accurate.</p><p>Building the mesh so that either the vertices or the centers of the elements are placed on the equipotential both suffer from the projected surface being either smaller or larger than the true surface, respectively (cf. discussion in Section 3). Although the local quantities are defined on the surface appropriately, the shadow created by the mesh is either smaller or larger than the equipotential surface, resulting in systematically offset times of ingress and egress. To correct this, we calculate two meshes: one in which the vertices are placed on the surface, and the other that is adjusted to the correct shadow size. The first mesh is used for all physical quantities, while the second mesh is used for all eclipse determination and geometric quantities, such as surface area of each element. As discussed in Section 3, the second mesh is computed by offsetting each vertex along its normal such that the surface area of the mesh matches the expected theoretical surface area of the Roche equipotential.</p><p>This operation depends on a local curvature of the mesh (see Appendix A for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Effective Temperatures</head><p>Local effective temperature distribution across the stellar disk depends on many factors, but predominantly on the tidal and rotational distortion of the stellar surface.</p><p>We model this distribution as a simple power law where local effective temperatures are computed for each vertex from the polar effective temperature:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">T eff = T pole G 1/4 , where</formula><p>the gravity darkening coefficient G = (g/g pole ) β is defined for each vertex, β is the gravity darkening parameter of the model and g is local surface gravity acceleration per vertex.</p><p>The polar temperature is computed from the mean effective temperature via:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">T pole = T eff,mean i A i i G i A i 1/4 ,</formula><p>where A is the area of each surface element and T eff,mean is the model parameter and a global property of the star. PHOEBE supports a simplistic spot model inherited from PHOEBE 1 (by way of WD).</p><p>Spots are defined by their colatitude, longitude, angular radius, and a temperature factor.</p><p>Any vertex that falls within the boundary of this circular spot region acquires a temperature that equals the product of the intrinsic effective temperature and the temperature factor.</p><p>Support for more complex spot treatment, including surface migration and size change, is being planned for the near future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Model atmospheres</head><p>Local normal emergent intensity is a complex function of local thermodynamical and hydrodynamical properties, most notably the local effective temperature, surface gravity, abundance of heavy elements, rotation and microturbulent velocity, but it also depends on extrinsic effects, such as Doppler boosting, interstellar extinction, extraneous light contamination, etc. The overly simplified case is to consider stars as blackbody radiators.</p><p>In that case the local normal emergent intensity depends solely on the local effective temperature, via Planck's law. A more realistic treatment necessitates the use of model atmospheres (i.e. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Hubeny &amp; Lanz 1995</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">, Hauschildt et al. 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">, Castelli &amp; Kurucz 2004</ref>).</p><p>Model atmospheres provide intensity as a function of the above mentioned quantities, and we need to assign an appropriate model atmosphere to each component in the modeled system, where the choice depends considerably on the type of star and on the intended use.</p><p>For example, plane-parallel model atmospheres might be perfectly adequate for Sun-like stars, whereas one would likely opt for spherical, non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (NLTE) models for hot O-and B-type stars. Similarly, a detailed, full-featured model atmosphere is required for comparing syntethic spectral energy distribution (SED) with observed spectral lines, while area-preserving parameters such as microturbulent velocity may be marginalized out if we are integrating SEDs to obtain local emergent passband intensities. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> depicts a comparison between the <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Castelli &amp; Kurucz (2004)</ref>, original <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Kurucz (1993)</ref> and blackbody atmospheres for a range of log g and abundance values by the <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Castelli &amp; Kurucz (2004)</ref> model atmospheres, the original Kurucz (1993) model atmospheres (red), and blackbody atmospheres (blue). Color tones correspond to the value of log g, where the darkest tone corresponds to the lowest log g and the lightest tone corresponds to highest log g value. Each line corresponds to a combination of log g and metal abundance. Model atmosphere flux differences are most notable on the low temperature end (below ∼8000 K), in excess of 200% for M stars. Blackbody fluxes deviate across the entire temperature range.</p><p>(denoted by different tones). The difference between the two model atmospheres at higher effective temperatures is ∼12%, and in excess of ∼200% at the lowest temperatures (not depicted in the figure to highlight the variation details rather than the overall amplitude).</p><p>The flatness beyond ∼8000 K implies that relative flux computations will vary to the extent of the deviation from the flat curve, but the absolute flux computations will differ by as much as ∼15%.</p><p>Model atmospheres in PHOEBE are used to (1) compute normal emergent passband intensity, i.e. local intensity perpendicular to the surface of the star integrated over a given passband response function; (2) compute center-to-limb variation in intensity, also known as limb darkening; (3) compute the increase in intensity due to reflection effect; and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(4)</ref> compute Doppler boosting due to kinematic properties of stellar surfaces. In the near future PHOEBE will also be able to synthesize theoretical SEDs and compare them with observed spectra. We provide some basic considerations for each use case next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">Passband intensity</head><p>Local normal emergent passband intensity I pb is obtained by multiplying the SED S(λ) ≡ dI(λ)/dλ in the direction perpendicular to the surface (µ ≡ cos θ = 1) with the passband transmission function P(λ) and integrating over wavelength:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">I pb (T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , . . . ) = λ S(λ; T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , . . . )P(λ)dλ.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>This is a time-consuming operation considering that for each local circumstance we need to synthesize the corresponding model atmosphere, multiply it with P(λ) and integrate it. To alleviate this computational burden, for each passband we store the integrated values of I pb for an extensive grid of T eff , log g and [M/H] values based on the <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Castelli &amp; Kurucz (2004)</ref> models. We then interpolate in these three quantities to get an accurate estimate of I pb .</p><p>Depending on the detector type used, Eq. (6) may not be appropriate. It implicitly assumes that our detector is bolometric in the sense that it measures intensity by accumulating energy, i.e. that intensity is energy-weighted. This is appropriate for observations that are flux-calibrated using standard stars. In contrast, photon-counting devices need to be photon count-weighted. Considering that the photon energy is E ν = hc/λ, Eq. (6) can be rewritten as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">I pb (T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , . . . ) = 1 hc λ λ S(λ; T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , . . . )P(λ)dλ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where I pb can still be considered intensity, but in units of photon counts. This version is more appropriate for observations where counts are not calibrated (including instrumental and differential photometry, including Kepler data) and passbands are wide <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bessell 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bessell &amp; Murphy 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Casagrande &amp; VandenBerg 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Brown et al. 2016</ref>).</p><p>PHOEBE supports both regimes and tabulates I pb values for energy-weighted and count-weighted intensities. The difference for solar-type stars amounts up to 1%. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> shows the difference between these as a function of the temperature of the stars. The effect is larger for cool stars (purple line) and is also dependent on the width of the passband.</p><p>Microturbulent velocity is generally an important parameter, but for passband intensities it does not play an appreciable role. This is crucial because it reduces the dimensionality of the interpolation table we need to prepare for calculating intensities. The lack of sensitivity can be understood by considering the effect of microturbulent velocity of spectral lines: the photons that originate at a certain convection cell are emitted from the line core region, but because the mean free path of a photon is larger than the typical size of the convection cell, the photon is absorbed closer to the line wing since the absorption cell is Doppler-shifted w.r.t. the originating cell. Thus, increasing values of v turb cause the lines to be shallower and broader, but the equivalent width remains roughly the same (cf. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>). This means that the integral does not change appreciably, and the only effect  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2.">Passband Luminosity</head><p>Passband intensities are computed (and interpolated) in absolute units, but actual data are rarely provided in absolute units. Passband luminosity of each star is used to scale the intensities into relative units. The observed luminosity of a star is determined by <ref type="bibr">856</ref>  Spectral lines with larger v turb are shallower and wider, but the integrated passband intensity is equal to within 0.1%. Thus, the effect of v turb on passband intensities is negligible.</p><p>integrating over all normal emergent passband intensities I multiplied by the integral of the limb darkening model D int to account for the intensity to flux conversion:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">L = ∂V I(µ = 1; T eff , log g, [M/H])D int (T eff , log g, [M/H])dA</formula><p>Rescaled intensities are then computed by scaling the observed luminosity L to match the prescribed passband luminosity a given passband.</p><p>Passband luminosities for each component in a binary can be either coupled or decoupled. When coupled, the luminosity is provided for one star, and the other star is scaled using the same determined factor. When decoupled, each star is scaled independently with separately provided passband luminosities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3.">Limb Darkening</head><p>Stellar photospheres are opaque to a certain optical depth, so the intensity received along the line of sight to the observer depends on the angle between the normal and the line of sight. If we look parallel to the normal, we see the deepest, hottest layer of the photosphere; this is the normal emergent passband intensity I pb given by Eq. (6).</p><p>As the angle increases, we see the progressively shallower, cooler layers, which results in intensity reduction; this is the limb darkened passband intensity I µ , where µ = cos θ is the measure of the emergent angle. This intensity variation with the distance from the center of the disk depends on geometry, but also on all other complex processes included in the atmosphere models that describe intensity as a function of emergent angle. This is another time-consuming operation, since each local circumstance requires an integration that depends on the angle, i.e.:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">I µ (T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , µ, . . . ) = λ S µ (λ; T eff , log g, [M/H], v turb , µ, . . . )P(λ)dλ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where S µ ≡ dI µ (λ)/dλ is the non-normal SED function. Traditionally, the functional form of I µ is approximated by 1-, 2-or 4-parameter models:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">I I 0 = 1 − x λ (1 − µ) linear model I I 0 = 1 − x λ (1 − µ) − y λ µ log 10 µ logarithmic model I I 0 = 1 − x λ (1 − µ) − y λ (1 − √ µ)</formula><p>square model Systematics that arises from using these low-parametric models can be significant.</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">I I 0 = 1 − x λ (1 − µ) − y λ (1 − µ) 2 quadratic model I I 0 = 1 − c 1,λ (1 − µ 1 2 ) − c 2,λ (1 − µ) − c 3,λ (1 − µ 3 2 ) − c 4,λ (1 − µ 2 ) power model</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4.">Reflection effect</head><p>A part of the emitted light of each component in a binary system that is directed towards its companion star is reflected off of the companion's surface. This effect needs to be taken into account when we determine radiosity F , defined as the radiant flux leaving (emitted, reflected and transmitted by) a surface per unit area. For this purpose, we treat the meshes of the bodies as diffusely reflecting and radiative surfaces. The heating of the stars caused by the absorbed part of the light is currently neglected and planned for future extension (Horvat et al., in preparation).</p><p>For reflection purposes, we define intensity as flux per unit solid angle per unit projected area, irradiance as radiant flux received per unit area, and exitance as radiant flux emitted per unit area at each surface point. The irradiance can be expressed as a function of the exitance using Lambert's cosine law or a limb-darkening law. Thus far, the reflection effect has been approximated by <ref type="bibr">Wilson (1990)</ref>'s model, which assumes that the total radiosity of a given surface is composed of the intrinsic emittance and the reflected irradiance as functions of diffusely radiated radiosity (given by the intrinsic intensities of the surface points) following a limb darkening law. There is no strong physical justification for this treatment of reflected light because the reflected and intrinsic light are not directly related and have to be dealt with separately. In order to overcome this issue, we have developed a new reflection model in which the irradiance is given as a function of two terms: the intrinsic emittance following the limb darkening law and the irradiance diffused by the Lambertian cosine law. In this approach, the bodies act as limb darkened radiators of Wilson's scheme is larger than by scattered Lambertian flux computed by our method. This is a consequence of the limb darkening model assumed by Wilson's scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.5.">Doppler boosting</head><p>The amount of light that reaches the observer is affected by the kinematic properties of the radiating body. There are three important velocity-induced changes to the received flux:</p><p>(1) Doppler shift of the spectrum causes the passband-weighted integral to change (Eqs. 6 and 7); (2) Doppler shift of the frequency causes arrival rate of the photons to change because of time dilation; and (3) relativistic beaming, where radiation is no longer isotropic but becomes direction-dependent because of light aberration <ref type="bibr">(Rybicki &amp; Lightman 1979, Chapter 4.8)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Loeb &amp; Gaudi (2003)</ref> showed that the boosting signal in exoplanet-hosting stars is larger than variability due to reflected light from the planet; <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Zucker et al. (2007)</ref> did a similar study for binary stars and showed that ellipsoidal variability, reflection and boosting are the same order-of-magnitude effects in binaries with a ∼10-d orbital period, while boosting dominates in binaries with a ∼100-d orbital period. Studies by van Kerkwijk The combined Doppler boosting signal can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">I λ = I 0,λ 1 − B(λ) v r c ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where I λ is the boosted passband intensity, I 0,λ is the initial passband intensity, v r is the radial velocity, c is the speed of light and B(λ) is the boosting index: </p><formula xml:id="formula_17">B(λ) = 5 + α ≡ 5 + d ln I d ln λ ,<label>(10)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">B pb = λ P(λ)S(λ)B(λ)dλ λ P(λ)S(λ)dλ<label>(11)</label></formula><p>(or its photon-weighted counterpart per Eq. 7). We do this by fitting a Legendre polynomial of the 5th order to the ln I µ (ln λ data; the order is determined by evaluating the rank of the coefficient matrix in the least squares fit and seeing where the values become susceptible to numerical noise. The series was fit iteratively as data points that lie below the −1σ</p><p>threshold were discarded by sigma-clipping the dataset. The iteration stopped when no further points are removed. Another benefit of Legendre polynomials is their analytical derivative; we use this analytic form do derive the average boosting index for every model atmosphere. <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> also shows that the dependence of the boosting index on µ is significant, so the traditional approach of using integrated flux SEDs to estimate B pb is less precise than the treatment presented here.</p><p>Boosting is a significant effect, and becomes a dominant effect over ellipsoidal variation and reflection for longer period systems.  The semi-major axis is constrained to conserve the masses of components. For this particular system, ellipsoidal variations dominate the short-period end, reflection takes over at ∼5.3 days and boosting takes over at ∼7.7 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Local radial velocities</head><p>does not affect the reported v z values), in which case the stored radial velocities are redshifted due to the mass of the originating surface gravity of the star:  </p><formula xml:id="formula_19">RV = v z + GM c/R pole<label>(12</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Eclipse and horizon computation</head><p>In order to determine the total flux received from the system, intensities must be integrated over the visible surface elements at any given time. PHOEBE determines the visibility of each mesh triangle though horizon and eclipse computation, which is performed once the meshes of all bodies are placed in orbit and their physical quantities computed for each vertex. Any given observable quantity of each triangle is then determined by arithmetic mean of that quantity at each vertex to determine the value at the centroid, under the assumption that these properties vary linearly across the local surface element (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 13</ref>).</p><p>Its observable area is then determined based on the provided ratio. This method allows for the accurate approximation of ingress/egress without the requirement of a fine mesh that is more computationally expensive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.1.">Flux computation</head><p>The actual observable in light curves is flux. A comparison between the resulting light curves of triangulated and trapezoidal meshes is depicted on the left panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 14</ref>. As a test case we use a contact system due to its highest level of distortion. The resulting light curves agree to ∼ 0.1%, with the exception of several discrepant points for which the trapezoidal mesh gives fluxes lower than excepted. This is due to the diverging centers which leave gaps in the mesh, as mentioned in Section 3.</p><p>To evaluate the precision of flux computation we consider the Sun-Earth system. This is a convenient test case because it is the best calibrated benchmark we have, and because it pushes model parameters to the extreme operation mode. We limit our test to the For fully visible (green) triangles, the centroids appear at geometric centers of the triangles whereas the partially visible (orange and yellow) triangles show the centroid moving away from the eclipsed region. These centroids and ratios are used to integrate over the visible surface of the star(s).</p><p>blackbody model because it is the only model that we can integrate analytically. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref> summarizes the results. The black line is the theoretical baseline computed by analytical integration. Other curves represent the results from meshed models and they depict fluxes as a function of the number of surface elements. Offset triangulation, explained in Appendix A, performs most robustly and it reproduces the analytical value effectively.   be sampled over mesh of each star; we refer to these as local RVs. Local RVs are assigned to each element by computing the projected velocity (already gravitationally redshifted;</p><p>cf. Section 5.3) at the visible centroid of each triangle, and then integrated over the visible area to the photometrically weighted, integrated RV curve.</p><p>The comparison of integrated RVs of a triangulated and trapezoidal mesh for an contact system is given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 14</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.">Finite integration time</head><p>When modeling short period systems, a finite exposure time starts to become relevant. This is especially true for Kepler data, where CCDs are read out every 6.54 seconds (6.02 s live time) and then summed into 29.4244-min Long Cadence bins. This implies that every exposure has an effective 30-min integration time during which any flux variation will be smeared into a single data point. This bears little significance for objects with periods longer than ∼10 days, but it becomes important for short period systems because it convolves the true signal with the exposure time boxcar, resulting in phase smearing. The effect is more pronounced for semi-detached and contact binaries, with orbital periods as short as a few hours. To account for the smoothing of observations due to finite exposure times, PHOEBE can oversample the light-curve and provide an averaged value for any given time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusions</head><p>This paper presented the first step towards the increased fidelity of computed eclipsing binary models. Triangulation replaces trapezoidal meshing, which provides a robust surface coverage by near-equilateral, near-isometric surface elements and the ability to discretize any 3-D body irrespective of its shape, whereas trapezoidal meshing relied on close-to-spherical shapes. To attain high mesh precision with small number of triangles, we offset mesh elements so that the discretized volume is identical to the analytical equipotential volume. We introduce a new type of body: rotating stars, which eliminates lengthy Roche computations when they are not necessary for the problem at hand. The treatment of dynamics has been updated by including light travel time delay for all bodies in a system, such that time is measured w.r.t. the barycenter of the system. Time-to-phase conversion accounts for all temporally changing quantities explicitly. In case of eccentric orbits, we provide an argument of why volume conservation is appropriate and we propose a test based on the eccentric ellipsoidal variable systems known as heartbeat stars. Passband Fourier-based approach with an algebraic scheme that is as accurate as the mesh itself.</p><p>Finite integration time acts as a smoothing filter on light curves, which is now supported on the synthetic end as well. Finally, flux computation in absolute units has been tested against the Earth-Sun system and the test demonstrates that the fidelity has indeed increased.</p><p>There are several limitations of PHOEBE 2.0 that we aim to address within the ongoing project: by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Limber (1963)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Kruszewski (1967)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Kopal (1978)</ref>. The properties of the critical equipotential lobe and Lagrangian points for circular orbits have been studied in detail</p><p>by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Avni &amp; Schiller (1982)</ref>. We are implementing a fully numerical determination of equipotential surfaces in misaligned binaries. These determine the shapes and radiative properties of components in binary stars and will be presented by Horvat et al., in preparation.</p><p>Graphical User Interface. It might come as a surprise that the current version of PHOEBE does not come with a standalone graphical user interface. We are working on a web-based user interface that is substantially more flexible than the original interface of PHOEBE 1. Its main characteristic is the combination of an interactive shell and a graphical interface that can be either run locally or remotely. The interface will be discussed by Conroy et al., in preparation. In conclusion, we respectfully invite the community to provide us with any feedback, criticism and suggested improvements to the model, and to help us critically evaluate model robustness in different operational regimes. We remind that PHOEBE is released as open source under the General Public License, is free and will always remain free, so anyone interested to join in our efforts to provide a robust, general modeling code to the community is welcome to join us.</p><p>The development and implementation of PHOEBE has been supported by the NSF approximate the isosurface as closely as possible, and the area of the entire mesh matches the isosurface area exactly: A(Mesh(V , C)) = A(S), where V = (v 1 , . . . , v n ) is a vector of shifted vertices.</p><p>Qualitatively we expect that shifts α i have the same sign as the isosurface curvature, and that their value should be larger for larger curvatures since larger curvatures imply larger distances to the neighboring triangles. Since the number of triangles is generally large, any local curvature across a single surface element can be considered constant. Thus, we can optimize α i on a perfectly spherical mesh and apply those corrections to local surface elements. Sphere triangulation using the marching method and recursive subdivision results in a uniform set of triangles; in the limit of large number of triangles we find that optimal shift for all vertices is equal to α ∼ A 2 t /4R, where 1/R is the curvature of the sphere and A t is the average area of a single triangle. This result can be generalized to the expected functional form α i = tH i S i , where t is the sole scalar parameter for all shifts, H i is the mean curvature of the underlying isosurface at the vertex approximated from the mesh <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Taubin 1995)</ref>, and S i is 1/3 of the area of triangles sharing the i-th vertex. As all shifted vertices V are parametrized with a single parameter t, we can easily solve the above equation for α i .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Volume and area of isosurfaces</head><p>The volume V , area A and derivative of the volume w.r.t. the potential V ,Ω 0 := ∂V /∂Ω 0 of a body within an isosurface S = {r : Ω(r) = Ω 0 } are essential ingredients of the robust working of PHOEBE. These quantities are computed to arbitrary precision directly from the definition of the Roche potential.</p><p>The volume and its derivative are essential for the process of volume conservation, in which the reference potential Ω * 0 of an isosurface is computed so that its volume matches the reference value V * . This is done by the Newton-Raphson iteration in the form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Ω 0,k+1 = Ω 0,k − V (Φ 0,k ) − V * V ,Ω 0 (Ω 0,k )</formula><p>where we assume convergence if lim k→∞ Ω 0,k = Ω * 0 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.1. Generalized Roche lobes</head><p>We discuss isosurfaces of the generalized potential potential Ω given by Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(1)</ref> around the reference value of the potential Ω 0 . We express the potential in rescaled cylindrical coordinates:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">Ω(ξ, σ, φ) = δΩ(δξ, δ √ σ cos φ, δ √ σ sin φ) (B1) = 1 ξ 2 + σ + q 1 σ + (ξ − 1) 2 − ξ + 1 2 B 2 (ξ 2 + σ cos(φ) 2 ) (B2)</formula><p>where ξ = x/δ is the dimensionless x coordinate, σ = (r/δ) 2 is the dimensionless square of the radius and B = F 2 (1 + q)δ 3 is an auxiliary constant. Additionally, we introduce the rescaled reference value Ω 0 = δΩ 0 corresponding to the Roche lobe of interest.</p><p>We can find the lower and upper bounds of the Roche lobe (denoted by ξ 0 and ξ 1 , respectively) along the ξ-axis, by solving the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">Ω(ξ i , 0, 0) = Ω 0 i = 0, 1 ,</formula><p>which we do using a combination of analytical estimates and general non-linear equation solvers.</p><p>The goal is to compute the following Roche lobe quantities at a reference Ω 0 :</p><p>• Volume:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">V = 2δ 3 ξ 1 ξ 0 dξ π/2 0 dφ σ(ξ, φ)</formula><p>• Derivative of volume w.r.t. rescaled reference value:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">V , Φ 0 = 2δ 3 ξ 1 ξ 0 dξ π/2 0 dφ [ Ω ,σ (ξ, σ(ξ, φ), φ)] −1 ,</formula><p>• Surface area:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">A = 4δ 2 ξ 1 ξ 0 dξ π/2 0 dφ σ(ξ, φ) + σ ,φ (ξ, σ(ξ, φ), φ) 2 /(4σ(ξ, φ)) + σ ,ξ (ξ, σ(ξ, φ), φ) 2 /4 ,</formula><p>where the derivatives of the squared radius w.r.t. to ξ and φ are given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">σ ,ξ (ξ, σ, φ) = − Ω ,ξ (ξ, σ, φ) Ω ,σ (ξ, σ, φ) σ ,φ (ξ, σ, φ) = − Ω ,φ (ξ, σ, φ) Ω ,σ (ξ, σ, φ)<label>(B3)</label></formula><p>Note that the derivative of the volume w.r.t. non-rescaled reference value, needed in volume conservation, is simply V ,Ω 0 = δV ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">Ω 0</formula><p>. All these quantities have a common functional form and can we written as an integral of some vector function F:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">I := (V, V , Ω 0 , A) , = ξ 1 ξ 0 dt π/4 0 dφ F(ξ, σ(ξ, φ), φ) .</formula><p>We can express I as an integral of its derivative along the t axis:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">I = ξ 1 ξ 0 dξ ˙ I(ξ) and ˙ I(ξ) = π/4 0 dφ F(ξ, σ(ξ, φ), φ)</formula><p>and with the use of a Legendre-Gauss quadrature of order n (see e.g. iň </p><formula xml:id="formula_30">˙ I(ξ) ≈ n i=1 w i F(ξ, σ(ξ, φ i ), φ i ) ,<label>(B4)</label></formula><p>where the weights w i and angles φ i ∈ [0, π/4] are calculated for the chosen quadrature rule and adapted to our case. With the introduction of a squared-radius at specific angles σ i (ξ) := σ(ξ, φ i ), Eqs. (B3) and (B4) yield a system of n + 3 ordinary differential equations -54 -for σ i and I:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">˙ σ i (ξ) = σ ,ξ (ξ, σ i (ξ), φ i ) i = 1, . . . , n ,<label>(B5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">˙ I(t) = n i=1 w i F(ξ, σ i (ξ), φ i ) (B6)</formula><p>We integrate the above system of equations in times ξ ∈ [ξ 0 , ξ 1 ] with initial conditions σ i (ξ 0 ) = 0 for i = 1, . . . , m and I(ξ 0 ) = 0. The Roche lobe quantities are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">I(ξ 1 ) = (V, V , Ω 0</formula><p>, A). In PHOEBE, we use Legendre-Gauss quadrature of order n = 10, 15 and integrate the system of equations using the RK4 method with adaptive step size ( ˇ Sirca &amp; Horvat 2012) to control the computation precision.</p><p>In the limit of high values of the potential Ω (i.e small Roche lobes), we use analytical approximations for the Roche lobe quantities. The analytical expressions are obtained by expressing the radius from the Roche potential in spherical coordinates as a power series of the reciprocal dimensionless potential Ω −1 . The standard formulae for the Roche lobe quantities can then be expressed purely as power series of Ω −1 . PHOEBE uses a 9-th degree power series approximation above a threshold value of the potential, which depends on the targeted precision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2. Rotating stars</head><p>The calculation of volume V , derivative of the volume w.r.t. value of reference potential V ,Ω 0 and surface area A of rotating stars is simpler than for the Roche lobes because of the rotational symmetry about the z axis.</p><p>We rewrite the isosurface condition Ω(x, y, z)/Ω 0 = 1 using substitutions for Cartesian <ref type="bibr">1]</ref> and σ(ξ = ±1) = 0. Rotating stellar surfaces are thus given by a single parameter b and analysis shows that closed surfaces only exist for b ≤ 8/27. The volume of the rotating star is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">coordinates (x, y, z) = Ω 0 ( √ σ cos φ, √ σ sin φ, ξ) into 1 ξ 2 + σ + 1 2 bσ = 1 , where b = ω 2 /Ω 3 0 , ξ ∈ [−1,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">V = 1 0 dξ ˙ V (ξ) where ˙ V (ξ) = 2π Ω 3 0 σ(ξ) ,</formula><p>while the derivative of the volume w.r.t. reference value of the potential V ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Ω 0 = − 3 Ω 0 (V +bV ,b )</formula><p>is expressed using:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">V ,b = 1 0 dξ ˙ V ,b (ξ) ˙ V ,b (ξ) = 2π Ω 3 0 σ ,b (ξ, σ(ξ)) ,</formula><p>and the area of the rotating star can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">A = 1 0 dt ˙ A(ξ) ˙ A(ξ) = 4π Ω 2 0 σ(ξ) + σ ,ξ (ξ, σ(ξ)) 2 /4 .</formula><p>The derivatives of σ w.r.t. t and b are:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">σ ,t (ξ, σ) = 2ξ b(ξ 2 + σ) 3/2 − 1 and σ ,b (ξ, σ) = − σ b − (ξ 2 + σ) −3/2 ,</formula><p>The above quantities (V, V ,b , A) and σ form a system of four ordinary differential equations: using adaptive step size for controlled precision. As before, in the limit of small b, we use analytic approximations in the form of the 9-th degree power series. For b &lt; 0.1, the precision of these analytic approximations is better than 10 −5 .</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">d dξ (σ, V, V ,b , A) = (σ ,ξ , ˙ V , ˙ V ,b , ˙ A) .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. The updated reflection model</head><p>Each component of a binary system has a closed boundary M i and the union of these boundaries is a surface M = i M i . We define a visibility function for points on this of each point on the surface is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">I(ˆ e, r) = ∂Φ ∂Ω∂A cos θ , cos θ = ˆ e · ˆ n , wherê e (e = 1) is the direction of emission.</formula><p>The irradiance F irr (i.e. radiant flux received by a surface per unit area due to this intensity) at point r ∈ M is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">F irr (r) = ˆ RI(r) ,<label>(C1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">= M dA(r )V (r, r ) ( (r − r) · ˆ n(r))( (r − r ) · ˆ n(r )) |r − r | 2 I( (r − r ), r ) ,<label>(C2)</label></formula><p>where theˆdesignation denotes unit vectors, ˆ n is the outward pointing normal vector on the surface, and operatorˆRoperatorˆ operatorˆR maps intensities to irradiances.</p><p>If we assume that the intensity I over the surface is described by the Lambert cosine law:</p><p>I(ˆ e; r) = I 0 (r) , then the radiant exitance (i.e. radiant flux emitted by a surface per unit area) at each point is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">F ext (r) = ˆ n·ê≥0</formula><p>dΩ(ˆ e)I(ˆ e; r) = πI 0 (r) .</p><p>Using the relation between exitance and intensities, we can express the irradiance with emission described by Lambert's cosine law as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">F irr = ˆ L L F extˆL extˆ extˆL L = 1 π ˆ R ,<label>(C3)</label></formula><p>where we introduce the Lambertian radiosity operatorˆLoperatorˆ operatorˆL L , which is commonly used in computer graphics (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Gershbein et al. 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Cohen et al. 1993</ref>). We are now in a position to introduce the limb-darkened intensity as:</p><p>I(ˆ e; r) = I 0 (r)D(ˆ e · ˆ n; r) , where I 0 (r) is the normal emergent intensity and D is the limb-darkening factor: D(1; r) = 1.</p><p>The corresponding radiant exitance then becomes: We can again express the irradiation as a function of the radiant exitance by introducing the limb-darkened radiosity operatorˆLoperatorˆ operatorˆL LD :</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">F irr = ˆ L LD F extˆL extˆ extˆL LD = ˆ R • D D 0 .<label>(C4)</label></formula><p>Both the irradiation and exitance are non-directional fluxes per unit area and with the two radiosity operators, L L and L LD , we are able to elegantly express the irradiation as a function of exitance.</p><p>Using the notation of radiosity operators we can introduce a simple implementation of reflection models in PHOEBE: the model of <ref type="bibr">Wilson (1990)</ref> and the approach presented here. The goal of all reflection models is to calculate the total radiosity F out of a surface,</p><p>given the intrinsic exitance F 0 or intensity I 0 of each surface point.</p><p>Wilson's model assumes that the total radiosity F out is composed of the intrinsic emittance and reflected irradiance given as radiosity diffusely radiated from the surface using the limb-darkening law:</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">F out (r) = F 0 (r) + ρ(r) ˆ L LD F out (r) .<label>(C5)</label></formula><p>Strictly speaking, the justification for this treatment of reflected light is not warranted.</p><p>Because heating by the absorbed light is neglected, the reflected and the intrinsic light are thus not constrained and have to be accounted for separately. As in Wilson's model, the radiosity F out is composed of intrinsic emittance F 0 and irradiance F in reflected from the surface. In our model, the irradiance is given as intrinsic emittance following the limb-darkening law and irradiance diffussed with the Lambertian cosine law. The equations determining the model are:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">F in (r) = ˆ L LD F 0 (r) + ˆ L L (ρF in )(r) ,<label>(C6)</label></formula><p>F out (r) = F 0 (r) + ρ(r)F in (r) .</p><p>In this approach, the bodies act as limb-darkened radiators of intrinsic light and ideal</p><p>Lambertian diffusive radiators of incoming light. In the case where both radiosity operators are the same, L LD = L L := L, expression (C7) reduces to Wilson's Eq. (C5).</p><p>In order to use these reflection models in practice, we need to discretize the operators and solve the corresponding equations. We start by partitioning M into disjoint parts: with coefficients f i and f j , respectively, can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">M = i S i S i ∩ S j = 0 i = j .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">f i = j L * i,j f j -59 - with A i = S i dA(r) L * i,j = 1 A i S i dA(r) S j dA(r )K * (r, r ) .</formula><p>The coefficients L * i,j are generalizations of the view-factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Modest 2003)</ref> and by collecting them in a matrix L * = [L * i,j ] i,j we get a discretized version of the operatorˆLoperatorˆ operatorˆL * .</p><p>The working surface M in PHOEBE is the mesh of triangles built over the smooth isosurface of an astrophysical object. We consider two approaches to discretizing operators:</p><p>per-triangle discretization and per-vertex discretization. In both cases we simplify the expressions for generalized view-factors:</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">L * i,j ≈ A j K * (r i , r j )</formula><p>where r i and r j are characteristic points chosen depending on the discretization scheme and </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Horizons on isosurfaces</head><p>The boundaries of our astrophysical bodies (binary stars, rotating stars, etc.) are defined as isosurfaces of the corresponding scalar potential function Φ. If we observe a smooth isosurface at a reference value Φ 0 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">Φ(r) = Φ 0 , r ∈ R 3 (D1)</formula><p>from directionˆvdirectionˆ directionˆv (ˆ v=1), the horizon is a 1-dimensional manifold that satisfies the equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">g(r) · ˆ v = 0 ,<label>(D2)</label></formula><p>where g = Φ is the gradient of the potential. The horizon of a smooth surface is a finite set of closed curves, which divides the isosurface into visible and invisible parts with respect to the external observer.</p><p>Let r(s) represent a naturally parametrized curve of the horizon. Its variation over the surface is given by the following differential equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">dr ds = (H(r) · ˆ v) × g(r) (H(r) · ˆ v) × g(r) ,<label>(D3)</label></formula><p>where H(r) = ( ⊗ ⊗)Φ(r) is the Hessian matrix of the potential Φ.</p><p>The curve of the horizon is obtained by integration of the differential equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(D3)</ref> from a starting point r * using the RK4 method. The starting point for the integration is obtained by solving the system of equations (D1) and (D2) via a Newton-Raphson iteration:</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">r k+1 = r k + δr(r k ) .</formula><p>The linear expansion of the equations, as requried by the Newton-Raphson scheme, reveals that the iteration step δr is uniquely determined. Its minimal length variant is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">δr(r) = α g(r) + β H(r) · ˆ v ,</formula><p>where the weights α and β are calculated via:</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">  α β   =   g(r) 2 g(r) · H(r) · ˆ v g(r) · H(r) · ˆ v H(r) · ˆ v 2   −1   Φ 0 − Φ(r) −g(r) · ˆ v   .</formula><p>The iteration is initiated from a point r 0 that lies sufficiently inside the isosurface, but sufficiently far so that the constraining of the inverse does not have a profound effect.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Kepler time series (left) and phased light curves (right) of KIC 5513861 (P=1.51012-d, detached EB), KIC 8074045 (P=0.53638-d, semi-detached EB), and KIC 3127873 (P=0.67146-d, contact EB), top-to-bottom.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>; Wilson &amp; Van Hamme 2014), ELC (Orosz &amp; Hauschildt 2000), and PHOEBE (Prša &amp; Zwitter 2005, paper I) are showing systematics in the derived values of fundamental stellar parameters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The version of PHOEBE presented here is 2.0. The code is not backwards- compatible to PHOEBE 1.0 because of the complete redesign of the backend, but original PHOEBE parameter files can be imported into the new version seamlessly. Versioning will follow the common semantic versioning syntax (major.minor.patch) with any critical bug fixes noted with an increment in the patch number (i.e. 2.0.1, 2.0.2), any new features noted with an increment in the minor number (i.e. 2.1.0, 2.2.0) and usually accompanied by a publication describing the new features, and any major new releases noted by an increment in the major number (i.e. 2.0.0, 3.0.0). If the patch number is 0, it can also be omitted (hence PHOEBE 2.0 instead of PHOEBE 2.0.0). Going forward with the 2.x versions of PHOEBE, all efforts will be made to maintain backwards compatibility, with any unavoidable changes listed clearly in the release notes and requiring a new release. PHOEBE is released as open source, under the General Public License. It is written in C (backend) and python (frontend). PHOEBE is available for download from http://phoebe-project.org.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-Comparison of the neck region coverage in a trapezoidal (left) and triangulated mesh (right) of a contact system with mass ratio q = 0.5 and fillout factor F F = 0.9.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The initial support for contact binaries in PHOEBE 2.0 retains the current approach to their treatment, with modifications to adapt it to marching meshes. In the trapezoidal approach, a boundary plane that separates the two components at the position of the minimum neck radius is computed (Wilson &amp; Biermann 1976). The centers of the trapezoids are then split with respect to the side of the plane they belong to and the fractional area of each trapezoid that intersects the boundary plane is retained as the area of its corresponding center. The fractional area of a trapezoid that partially belongs to one component, while its center belongs to the other, is added to the area of the center nearest in longitude. The fractional area assignment ensures that the mesh is well connected and deals with the overlaps between the trapezoids of the two components, but does not solve the issue of diverging centers, which may leave gaps in the mesh. Since all surface quantities of a marching mesh are computed in the triangle vertices, the split between components in a marching mesh of a contact binary is applied to vertices as opposed to centers. Whether a triangle and all its vertices belong to the primary or secondary component is determined based on the position of the triangle center, equivalent to the trapezoidal approach. All of the triangle vertices are then marked as belonging to one component, despite of the fact that some might cross the boundary plane. The components of the contact envelope have surface temperature distributions computed via their respective polar temperatures. For components with different temperatures this introduces unphysical discontinuities in the neck area, as neighboring triangles that belong to distinct components can have very different temperatures. This approach is thus mainly suitable for systems close to thermal equilibrium and we advise against its use for systems not in thermal equilibrium until a smooth temperature variation has been implemented (see Section 6; Kochoska et al., in preparation).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Relative difference between the normal emergent passband intensities computed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>v</head><label></label><figDesc>turb might have is at the edges of the passband transmission functions. Yet even there the effects are minimal since the transmission efficiency of a typical passband drops gradually.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Light curves for detached binaries with a temperature ratio of 0.9 in the Johnson V passband as a function of primary temperature (T eff,1 = 5000 K (purple), 7500 K (red), 10000 K (green), 12500 K (cyan) and 15000 K (blue). The lower panel shows the difference caused by weighting the intensities by photon count vs energy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-The effect of microturbulence on the SED. The spectrum is synthesized for the narrow infrared region, at T eff = 6000 K, log g = 4.5 and [M/H] = 0.0 using Castelli &amp; Kurucz (2004) model atmospheres and the spectrum synthesizer (Gray &amp; Corbally 1994). SEDs with v turb = 0.5 km s −1 , 1.0 km s −1 , 1.5 km s −1 , 2.0 km s −1 and 2.5 km s −1 are plotted.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 Fig. 7 .</head><label>77</label><figDesc>Fig. 7 depicts an example of limb darkening for a solar-like star, along with the fits</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-Relative flux difference between the Wilson (1990) treatment of reflection and Lambertian reflection for an A0-K0 system in a 1-day circular orbit. The differences are plotted for several values of inclination, where i = 0 • is face-on and i = 90 • is edge-on orientation. Eclipses are not included in the computation. The baseline difference at i = 0 is positive, implying that the contribution to the total flux by reprocessed flux computed by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>et al.</head><label></label><figDesc>(2010), Bloemen et al. (2011) and Bloemen et al. (2012) apply this correction to Kepler objects KOI-74, KOI-81 and KPD 1946+4340 and demonstrate that the contributions of boosting are indeed crucial to model the light curves correctly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>where</head><label></label><figDesc>α ≡ d(ln I)/d(ln λ) is the spectral index, and 5 comes from the Lorenz invariance of Iλ 5 (Loeb &amp; Gaudi 2003). Fig. 9 depicts the boosting index for the broad Johnson V passband, for a series of T eff = 6000 K, log g = 4.0, [M/H]= 0.0 spectra where µ ranges from 0.001 to 1.0. The dependence of the boosting index on wavelength is notable, but in the simplified approach we approximate the monochromatic boosting factor B(λ) with the passband-averaged value:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 10 shows a comparison in the amplitude of ellipsoidal variation (blue), reflection (green) and Doppler boosting (red) as a function of orbital period for an A0-K0 main sequence pair in the Johnson V passband. Ellipsoidal variation and reflection dominate the short period end, with boosting taking over at around 8 days. Fig. 11 depicts a light curve with no effects computed (black), with only ellipsoidal variations (blue), with ellipsoidal variations and reflection (green), and with ellipsoidal variations, reflection and boosting (red).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .</head><label>910</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.-Boosting index B(λ) for the Johnson V broadband filter. The spectra correspond to T eff = 6000 K, log g = 4.0, [M/H]= 0.0 and µ runs over 33 values ranging from 0.001 to 1.0. The dependence of the boosting index on wavelength is obvious, but at this time we approximate it with a weighted average across the passband (cf. Eq. (11)). The increased curviness at larger µ is due to the larger variations and larger fluxes as we look towards the center of the stellar disk.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11.-Light curve of an A0-K0 main sequence pair in a 7.5-day orbit. The top panel is the zoomed in version of the bottom panel. Four models are being plotted: the baseline model (black), which assumes spherical stars; the ellipsoidal variation model (blue), which includes surface deformation due to tides and rotation; the ellipsoidal variation model with reflection (green), which introduces reflection; and the complete model (red), which accounts for Doppler boosting on top of other effects. While the effects are small in amplitude as evident from the bottom panel, high precision (mmag or better) photometry will routinely demonstrate these effects.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12.-Horizon of a Roche star as determined by PHOEBE and WD in polar coordinates. The black curve represents the analytic horizon (described in Appendix D), the red curve represents the Fourier fit to the horizon used in WD, the blue points represent surface elements of the offset PHOEBE mesh that are on the horizon, and the blue line represents the polygonal shadow that these points span. The lower panel shows the residuals between the Fourier-based (red) and offset triangulation-based (blue) horizons with respect to the analytical horizon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Flux is computed by integrating scaled, limb-darkened, projected intensities along the line of sight over the visible surface of the star. Any extraneous light (passed as a parameter) is then added to this value to obtain the observable flux. The process is then repeated for each time-stamp, where local quantities are updated if the mesh has changed, and re-integrated to obtain a new flux.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13.-A segment of a partially-eclipsed mesh. The colors of each triangle represent the ratio of the triangle area that is currently visible, with green being fully visible and red being fully eclipsed. The blue crosses represent the centroid of the visible portion of the triangle.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14.-Light curves and radial velocities of the triangulated and trapezoidal meshes of an contact system with mass ratio q = 0.5, fillout factor F F = 0.9, equal surface temperatues T 1 = T 2 = 6000 K and inclination i = 90 0 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15.-Comparison of fluxes computed analytically (black line) and for different meshes: trapezoids with analytical areas (red line), triangulation (blue line) and offset triangulation (green line) as a function of mesh size. Corrected (offset) triangulated meshes are consistent with the benchmark and reach it for a smaller number of surface elements than any other method.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>intensities are based on the Castelli &amp; Kurucz (2004) model atmospheres and values for both energy-weighted and photon-weighted intensities are stored in lookup tables for fast operation. The old treatment of limb darkening caused severe artifacts near the limb of the star because of undersampling; this has been mitigated by providing the option to use actual intensity values as a function of µ instead of relying on 1-, 2-or 4-parameter models. Reflection effect has been restated to include Lambertian scattering, which paves the way for future inclusion of heat redistribution across the irradiated surface. Doppler boosting (comprised of Doppler shift of the spectrum, time dilation and relativistic beaming) is now fully taken into account. Local radial velocities are now corrected for the gravitational redshift. Eclipse and horizon computation is significantly improved by replacing the old</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Integrated flux dependence on the number of surface elements. Ideally, the computed flux should not depend on the computational aspects such as the fineness of the mesh, but this is an inherent limitation for all numerical schemes. Flux values converge to the analytical value linearly (∝ 1/N where N is the number of surface elements), which is quite slow and is further impacted by other second-order effects, most notably limb darkening. The exact convergence properties are difficult to assess because of the non-linearity of the parameter space, but tests show that for a moderate number of triangles (∼ 5000) the attained relative accuracy is of the order of 10 −3 . The impact on relative light curve shapes (i.e. flux ratios) is much smaller because all phase points are affected equivalently, but whenever flux values are sought, their dependence on the mesh size should be kept in mind. We are considering acceleration schemes that model the dependence of integrated flux on the number of surface elements by evaluating it for several mesh sizes and then extrapolating it to N → ∞, but no robust solutions have been worked out yet. Contact binaries. The trapezoidal model to modeling contact binaries is likely suitable only for systems in thermal equilibrium, since it introduces unphysical discontinuities in the neck area of systems with unequal temperatures (cf. Section 5). Even for systems in thermal equilibrium, the atmosphere tables used to derive the normal emergent intensities are computed assuming single, spherical stars, which introduces additional inconsistencies in the overall treatment of contact systems. We are currently working on the implementation of a more feasible model of contact binaries by studying the radiative transfer in the common envelope based on the structure of the whole star. The structure and radiative transfer computations are performed independently which allows for the exploitation of a wide range of hydro-thermodynamical models and the testing of the surface intensity distribution they give rise to. The full description of this novel model will be the topic of the paper by Kochoska et al., in preparation. Misaligned binaries. PHOEBE is currently based on the Roche geometry, which assumes perfect alignment between the orbital and the rotational axes and handles each component's tidal distortion as due to the companion's point mass. However, careful ground-based studies have been able to discern that the components of close binaries in a number of systems show misaligned rotational and orbital axes (Albrecht et al. 2011). Observationally this is most easily discerned via the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect. The misalignment has also been found for a number of "hot Jupiters" (Hébrard et al. 2008). Consequently, both EBs and transiting exoplanets bring into question the initial conditions for the formation of both binaries and planetary systems. The generalized Roche potential for binary systems where the stellar rotation is not aligned with the orbital revolution is fundamentally different to the currently implemented aligned potential. The modifications to the potential have been derived</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Fitting.</head><label></label><figDesc>The absence of the fitting interface is by no means an oversight. Deterministic minimizing programs used in the past, most notably Differential Corrections (DC; Wilson &amp; Devinney 1971), Nelder &amp; Mead's Simplex method (NMS; Prša &amp; Zwitter 2005) and Powell's direction set method (Prša &amp; Zwitter 2007), are not suited for the high fidelity demand of modern data, and do not lend themselves to automation that is necessary to address the firehose of data coming our way from surveys such as Gaia or LSST. We consider PHOEBE models as likelihood functions that, accompanied with an appropriate noise model, should feed probabilistic samplers, such as the Markov Chain Monte Carlo methods. The High Perfomance Computing (HPC) wrapper for PHOEBE is available on PHOEBE website and should be preferred to deterministic minimizers. The rationale for fitting will be discussed by Prša et al., in preparation. Computational time cost. The computational infrastructure of PHOEBE is implemented in the low-level C language for speed, and the interface part is written in the high-level python language that is inherently slow. A number of causal computations are still linked through python, which causes slowdown of the execution time. Yet the dominant source of slowdown is increased model fidelity. Shortcuts taken before are no longer in effect and, even though effects can be turned off by the user, the impact on the overall runtime is significant. That is why the preferred mode of deployment of PHOEBE is on HPC clusters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Sirca &amp; Horvat 2012), we can approximate the integral of ˙ I over φ ∈ [0, π/4] as a sum:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>These are integrated over the time interval ξ ∈ [0, 1] where the initial conditions are given at ξ = 1: (σ, V, V ,b , A)(ξ = 1) = 0 and the resulting surface values are computed at ξ = 0. The integration in PHOEBE is performed with the RK4 method ( ˇ Sirca &amp; Horvat 2012)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The intensity I(ˆ e, r) (i.e. flux per unit solid angle per projected unit area)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_29"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The introduced radiosity operators are linear and have the following functional form: ˆ L * f (r) = M dA(r )K * (r, r )f (r ) * = L, LD . where the kernel K * can refer to the Lambertian or limb-darkening model. Assuming that all functions are constant over each element S i of the partition: f (r) = i f i χ i (r) χ i (r) =    1 : r ∈ S i 0 : otherwise . The χ i is a characteristic function over S i and the set of all {χ i } i functions is our functional basis. The relation f = ˆ L * f where the functions f and f are expanded in the new basis</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_30"><head>A</head><label></label><figDesc>i are their attached areas. In per-triangle discretization, r i are the triangle barycenters, n i are the triangle normals and A i are the triangle areas, whereas in per-vertex discretization, r j are the vertices, n i are the vertex normals and A i is 1/3 of the sum of triangle areas sharing each vertex.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> http://www.angusj.com/delphi/clipper.php</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> http://paulbourke.net/geometry/polygonmesh/</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Curvature-dependent offsetting of mesh surface elements</head><p>The triangulation method computes n vertices of the mesh: V = (v 1 , . . . , v n ). These vertices span m triangles: T j (r c j,1 , r c j,2 , r c j,3 ), j = 1, . . . , m, where c j,i ∈ <ref type="bibr">[1, n]</ref> is an index of the i-th vertex spanning the j-th triangle. The triplets of indices (c j,1 , c j,2 , c j,3 ) are ordered in a way that the normal of the triangle, which is proportional to the vector product The mesh can only approximate a smooth isosurface of the potential Ω at some reference value Ω 0 . This implies that the area of the mesh is different from that of the isosurface and it needs to be corrected. This is achieved by linearly shifting each vertex of the mesh to v i = v i + α i n i , i = 1, . . . , n, where n i = Φ(r i )/Φ(r i ) is a normal to the isosurface in the i-th vertex and α i is the offset length at that vertex. Finding α i is an optimization problem done under two constraints: every local surface element needs to This manuscript was prepared with the AAS L A T E X macros v5.2.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">Seventh Framework Programme FP7-SPACE-2011-1, project number</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">312844</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SPACEINN</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conroy is supported under a NASA NESSF Fellowship #NNX15AR87H. The authors express sincere gratitude to R. E. Wilson, W. van Hamme and S. Rucinski for useful discussions. The anonymous reviewer provided us with further suggestions from the user&apos;s point of view</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>which were immensely helpful and highly appreciated. REFERENCES</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">738</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-F</forename><surname>Attia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mahmoud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Shahin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Osman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. New Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">285</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Avni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Schiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">257</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">703</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Space Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">345</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bessell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bessell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">293</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bloemen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">410</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1787</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2600</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Borkovits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Forgács-Dajka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Regály</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">191</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">977</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Breeveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W A</forename><surname>Roming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vandenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">392</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Castelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ArXiv Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Radiosity and Realistic Image Synthesis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press Professional, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H J</forename><surname>De Bruijne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap&amp;SS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gaulme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jackiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Appourchaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mosser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">785</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gaulme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mckeever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rawls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jackiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mosser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Guzik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gershbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 21st Annual Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, SIGGRAPH &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>the 21st Annual Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, SIGGRAPH &apos;94<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Classical mechanics, World student series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading (Mass.), Menlo Park (Calif.), Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Corbally</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">742</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hauschildt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Aufdenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schweitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series</title>
		<editor>U. Munari</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">179</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>GAIA Spectroscopy: Science and Technology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">488</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">763</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hubeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">439</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcguire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Akeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Computer graphics: principles and practice</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley Professional</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page">1264</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Survey and Other Telescope Technologies and Discoveries</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4836</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">154</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysics and Space Science Library</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kruszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">On the Evolution of Double Stars</title>
		<editor>J. Dommanget</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">146</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Peculiar versus Normal Phenomena in A-type and Related Stars</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dworetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Castelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Faraggiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Limber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1963" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Modest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Radiative Heat Transfer, Chemical, Petrochemical &amp; Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">308</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2616</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orosz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hauschildt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">265</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pietrzy´nskipietrzy´nski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">495</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Popper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zwitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">628</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">426</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zwitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series</title>
		<editor>O. Demircan, S. O. Selam, &amp; B. Albayrak</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">175</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Solar and Stellar Physics Through Eclipses</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prša</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zwitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Three-Dimensional Universe with Gaia</title>
		<editor>C. Turon, K. S. O&apos;Flaherty, &amp; M. A. C. Perryman</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">576</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">611</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ESA Special Publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">455</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">244</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rucinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Bulletin on Variable Stars</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">4460</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rybicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lightman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Radiative Processes in Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Taubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fifth International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>the Fifth International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV &apos;95<address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page">902</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">753</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tyson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lsst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van Kerkwijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Breton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Justham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Podsiadlowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">715</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Vatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sirca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Horvat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Computational Methods for Physicists: Compendium for Students</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Graduate Texts in Physics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">234</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1054</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">356</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">613</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series</title>
		<editor>Binary Star Research, ed. K.-C. Leung &amp; I.-S. Nha</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Bulletin on Variable Stars</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">5076</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">672</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">575</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Biermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">349</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Devinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">605</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Hamme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">780</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">670</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1326</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
