<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:28+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">con-tributed new reagents/analytic tools</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-06-25">June 25. 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Designed Research</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">; J.-W</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Performed Research</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">; J.-W</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">con-tributed new reagents/analytic tools</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27"/>
							<date type="published" when="2018-06-25">June 25. 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX</idno>
					<note type="submission">This manuscript was compiled on June 25, 2018</note>
					<note>wrote the paper. The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests 1 J.-W.X. and S.D. contributed equally to this work. 2 To whom correspondence may be addressed.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The nearly circular (mean eccentricity ¯ e ∼ 0.06) and coplanar (mean mutual inclination ¯ i ∼ 3 •) orbits of the Solar System planets motivated Kant and Laplace to put forth the hypothesis that planets are formed in disks, which has developed into the widely accepted theory of planet formation. Surprisingly, the first several hundred extrasolar planets (mostly Jovian) discovered using the Radial Velocity (RV) technique are commonly on eccentric orbits (¯ e ∼ 0.3). This raises a fundamental question: Are the Solar System and its formation special? The Kepler mission has found thousands of tran-siting planets dominated by sub-Neptunes, but most of their orbital eccentricities remain unknown. By using the precise spectroscopic host star parameters from the LAMOST observations, we measure the eccentricity distributions for a large (698) and homogeneous Ke-pler planet sample with transit duration statistics. Nearly half of the planets are in systems with single transiting planets (singles), while the other half are multiple-transiting planets (multiples). We find an eccentricity dichotomy: on average, Kepler singles are on eccentric orbits with ¯ e ≈ 0.3, while the multiples are on nearly circular (¯ e = 0.04 +0.03 −0.04) and coplanar (¯ i = 1.4 +0.8 −1.1 degree) orbits similar to the Solar System planets. Our results are consistent with previous studies of smaller samples and individual systems. We also show that Kepler multiples and Solar System objects follow a common relation (¯ e ∼(1-2)× ¯ i) between mean eccentricities and mutual inclinations. The prevalence of circular orbits and the common relation may imply that the Solar system is not so atypical in the Galaxy after all. Orbital Eccentricities | Exoplanets | Transit | Solar System | Planetary Dynamics O ur knowledge of orbital shapes (parameterized with eccentricities) of planetary systems has been drastically advanced in the last two decades largely thanks to the RV planet surveys, but there remain some major puzzles. For example, the majority of RV planets are found on eccentric orbits (¯ e ∼ 0.3)[1] in contrast to the Solar system planets, raising a fundamental question: Is the Solar System an atypical member of the planetary system population in the Galaxy?[2] Furthermore, the RV method has some key limitations. For example, several notable biases and degeneracies can introduce considerable systematical uncertainties into the eccentricity distributions derived from the RV technique [3-5]. In addition, the majority of eccentricities measured using the RV method are for giant planets (e.g., Jupiter size), while the eccentricity distributions of smaller planets (e.g., Earth to Neptune size) remain poorly understood. Complementary to the RV technique, the Kepler mission has discovered thousands of planet candidates down to about Earth radius using the transit technique [6]. About half of the Kepler planets are in systems with multiple transiting planets, and on average they are on nearly coplanar orbits similar to the Solar System (see review by [7]). For most transiting planets, eccentricities cannot be directly inferred from the light curves alone. Individual light-curve-based eccentricity measurements have been made for a small number of planets, most of which are systems meeting special conditions such as giant planets with high eccentricities[8], systems with precisely characterized host stars from asteroseismology [9] and highly compact and dynamically rich systems exhibiting transit timing variations (TTVs) (e.g. [10]). Analyzing TTVs for a sample of transit systems also allows to constrain eccentricity distributions[11], but this method only applies to a limited number (∼ 100) of Significance Statement The Kepler satellite has made revolutionary discoveries of thousands of planets down to Earth size. However, the orbital shapes (parameterized by eccentricities) of most Kepler planets remain unknown. We derive the eccentricity distributions of an unprecedented large and homogeneous sample of 698 Kepler planets. We discover a dichotomy in eccentricities: the systems with single transiting planets, comprised of half of the sample, have a large mean eccentricity (∼ 0.3) while the multiples are on nearly circular orbits. The average eccentricity and inclination of the Kepler multiples and the Solar System objects fit into an intriguing common pattern. Our results suggest that the circular and coplanar planetary orbits like our Solar System are likely typical in the Galaxy. systems with special (near-)resonant configurations. Method A robust general method to derive eccentricity distribution is based on the statistics of transit duration [12]-the time for transiting planets to cross the stellar disks. Based on Kepler&apos;s Third Law, for a planet on a circular orbit that transits across the stellar center, the transit duration T0 is uniquely determined by the orbital period P , the planet-to-star radius ratio r = Rp/R and stellar density ρ: T0 ∝ P 1/3 ρ −1/3 (1 + r). For an eccentric and inclined orbit, the transit duration T depends on the eccentricity e as well as the orientation of the orbit, which is described by the argument of periastron ω and the impact parameter b: T = T0 × (1 − b 2)(1 − e 2)/(1 + esinω) [1] P , T and r are observables that can be directly measured from the transit light curve with high precision. Using an ensemble of transiting planet systems, the distributions of ω and b can be modeled and used to infer the eccentricity distribution from the statistics of T /T0. Moreover, for systems with multiple transiting planets, the b distribution also depends on the mutual orbital inclinations (Throughout this paper, inclination and the symbol ¯ i always refer to the mutual orbital inclination unless otherwise stated.) among the planets, and thus both the eccentricity and inclination distributions can be inferred. See SI Appendix, section 3, for a full description of our methodology. This method hinges on the well-characterized host properties to derive reliable and precise stellar density ρ. Due to the difficulty of precisely characterizing large samples of stars, the method has hitherto not been applied to a large and homogeneous sample of Kepler planetary systems. Previous studies such as [13] have used stellar parameters from the Kepler input catalog (KIC), which are plagued by large systematic uncertainties (see SI Appendix, section 1). A recent study [9] uses a sample of 28 multi-transiting systems with precisely measured stellar densities from asteroseismology, and found that the planetary orbits in these systems have low eccentricities. The sample was nevertheless biased towards systems with asteroseismic detections, and did not include single transiting planets. Results Here, we derive the eccentricity distributions of 698 Kepler planet candidates using transit duration statistics. The analysis of this large and homogeneous sample [14] is made possible through spectroscopic observations by the Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST)[15, 16] with reliably derived stellar properties [17] from the LAM-OST Stellar Parameter (LASP) pipeline (see Sec 4.4 of [16] and also [18]). See SI Appendix Section 1 for further discussions on stellar parameters. Eccentricity Dichotomy. Our sample consists of 368 systems with single transiting planet candidates (Np = 1) and 330 planet candidates in multiples (Np &gt; 1). For the two subsam-ples, we simulate T /T0 distributions with various ¯ e and/or ¯ i assuming Rayleigh distributions, and fit them to the observed T /T0 distributions (see SI Appendix Section 4). The results are shown in Fig. 1 and 2 for the singles and multiples, respectively. The eccentricity distribution of singles is clearly non-circular with a mean eccentricity of ¯ e = 0.32 ± 0.02. In contrast, the orbits of multiples are consistent with being circular and nearly coplanar, with a mean eccentricity ¯ e &lt; 0.07 and a mean orbital inclinations 0.006 rad (0.3 •)&lt; ¯ i &lt;0.038 rad (2.2 •). We further divide the multiples into subsamples with Np = 2, Np = 3 and Np &gt; 3 transiting planets. We find that the mean eccentricities of these three subsamples are all close to zero and comparable to each other within statistical uncertainties, in contrast to the large mean eccentricity of singles (Fig. 3). Our results indicate an abrupt transition of ¯ e from singles (Np = 1) to multiples (Np &gt; 1) rather than a smooth correlation with Np as suggested from the study on the RV sample[19]. The low eccentricities of multiples found here are consistent with previous studies of smaller samples[9, 11, 20] and individual systems, e.g., Kepler-11[10], Kepler-36[21] etc. Singles: Two Populations. When viewed from different orien-tations, a multiple-planet system can result in multi-transiting and single-transiting systems. Our results provide a direct evidence that not all Kepler single-transiting system come from the same underlying planet population as the systems with multiple transiting planets. Instead, the Kepler planet population is likely dichotomic in eccentricities: at least some of the single-transits come from a dynamically hotter population than the underlying population of multi-transiting systems. We are therefore motivated to investigate the transit duration ratio of singles with a two-population model (Fig. 4). In the model, we fix the dynamically cold population with an eccentricity distribution corresponding to the best fit of multi-transiting systems, and fit the fraction (F hot) and mean eccentricity (¯ e hot) of the hot population. The best-fit two-population model provides a statistically significant improvement over the one-population model in matching the observations. We find that the hot population makes up a small fraction of the sample (F hot ∼ 16% − 36%) with an even higher mean eccentricity (¯ e hot &gt; 0.47), indicating that the singles are probably dominated by a cold population (F cold = 1 − F hot ∼ 64% − 84%). Prevalence of Circular Orbits. As the singles contribute to about half of all the Kepler planets, the fraction of planets in the cold population out of the whole sample is even higher (∼ 80% − 90%), leading to a conclusion that most Kepler planets are on near-circular orbits. The dominance of near-circular orbits may imply that planets mostly form and evolve in a relatively gentle manner dynamically. Violent dynamical scenarios which excite high eccentricities, for example through planet-planet scattering[22] and close stellar encounters[23], therefore must be relatively rare, unless there are subsequent processes that efficiently circularize the orbits. A common relation between eccentricity and inclination. The low eccentricities and inclinations of the Kepler multiples are naturally expected from simple considerations of terrestrial planet formation [24], and they are consistent with the expectation from the well-established coplanarity of the Kepler multiple systems (¯ i ∼ a few degrees)[25, 26], resembling the Solar System planets. Further comparing the orbital properties of Kepler multiples to those of the Solar System objects, 2 | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al. we find an intriguing pattern: orbital eccentricities and inclinations are distributed around ¯ e ∼(1-2)× ¯ i (see Fig. 5). All the regular moon systems are located in the dynamically cold end (bottom left), while the Asteroid Belt objects and Trans-Neptune objects (TNOs) are located in the dynamically hot end (up-right). Interestingly, the Kepler planets and the Solar System planets (¯ e ∼ 0.06, ¯ i ∼ 3 •) are located in the intermediate region and close to each other. Note that the Kepler single-transiting systems are not shown in Fig. 5 because we cannot measure their inclination distributions. If they were following the same pattern, they would be located in the dy-namical hot region (up right corner of Fig. 5) given their large mean eccentricity. If true, we would expect that the obliquity of Kepler single transiting systems should be systematically larger than those of the Kepler multiples[27]. Discussions In contrast to the low eccentricity of multiple-transit systems, the mean eccentricity of single-transit systems is much higher and similar to that of planets found by RV surveys, but unlike the RV planets, most of the Kepler single-transiting systems are sub-Neptune-sized planets (&lt; 4 Earth radii). We further compare the singles to the multiples in terms of planetary properties (radius and orbital period) and host properties (stellar mass, radius, metallicity and surface density). We found that these parameters are unlikely to play a decisive role in forming the eccentricity dichotomy (SI Appendix section 2.1). The dichotomy may have important implications for planet formation and evolution. From the perspective of evolution, current studies have found that the architecture of a planetary system may depend on various conditions during planet formation, e.g., the total mass and distribution of solid[28] and the degree of depletion of gas[29] in the planet-forming disk. From the perspective of evolution, long-term planet-planet interactions can sculpt the planet architectures [30-32] after planet formation. The eccentricity dichotomy found in this work may help to pin down the initial conditions for planet formation and shed light on planet dynamical evolution. One important concern about the eccentricity dichotomy is the likely larger false positive (FP) rate of the singles as compared to that of the multiples. To investigate this issue, we perform two sets of analyses (see SI Appendix section 5.4). In the first set of analysis, we remove singles with large FP probability to reduce the total FP rate of single sample to a degree (a few percents) that is comparable to that of the multiple sample. In the other analysis, we model the effects of the FP on transit duration ratio distribution by injecting FPs into our simulations and fit the data. Both analyses lead to results (SI Appendix Fig.S13, Fig.S14, Fig.S16 and Fig.S17) that are consistent with those shown in Fig. 4. Based on these analyses, we conclude that FP should not qualitatively change our main conclusion, namely the Kepler singles are composed of dynamically cold and dynamically hot populations. The correlation between eccentricities and inclinations shown in Fig. 5 is generally expected from popular planet formation models, which predict that orbital eccentricities are less than twice of orbital inclinations on average[33] (the grey region in Fig. 5). In fact, ¯ e ∼ 2 ¯ i is consistent with the prediction of energy equipartition among the various degrees of freedom of planetary orbit[34]. The prevalence of circular orbits among Kepler planets and the common pattern between Kepler multiples and Solar System planets may imply that our planetary system is not so atypical in the Galaxy after all. ACKNOWLEDGMENTS. We thankA. Gould, S. Tremaine, Y.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Significance Statement</head><p>The Kepler satellite has made revolutionary discoveries of thousands of planets down to Earth size. However, the orbital shapes (parameterized by eccentricities) of most Kepler planets remain unknown. We derive the eccentricity distributions of an unprecedented large and homogeneous sample of 698 Kepler planets. We discover a dichotomy in eccentricities: the systems with single transiting planets, comprised of half of the sample, have a large mean eccentricity (∼ 0.3) while the multiples are on nearly circular orbits. The average eccentricity and inclination of the Kepler multiples and the Solar System objects fit into an intriguing common pattern. Our results suggest that the circular and coplanar planetary orbits like our Solar System are likely typical in the Galaxy.</p><p>systems with special (near-)resonant configurations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>A robust general method to derive eccentricity distribution is based on the statistics of transit duration <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> -the time for transiting planets to cross the stellar disks. Based on Kepler's Third Law, for a planet on a circular orbit that transits across the stellar center, the transit duration T0 is uniquely determined by the orbital period P , the planet-tostar radius ratio r = Rp/R and stellar density ρ: T0 ∝ P 1/3 ρ −1/3</p><p>(1 + r). For an eccentric and inclined orbit, the transit duration T depends on the eccentricity e as well as the orientation of the orbit, which is described by the argument of periastron ω and the impact parameter b:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T = T0 × (1 − b 2 )(1 − e 2 )/(1 + esinω) [1]</formula><p>P , T and r are observables that can be directly measured from the transit light curve with high precision. Using an ensemble of transiting planet systems, the distributions of ω and b can be modeled and used to infer the eccentricity distribution from the statistics of T /T0. Moreover, for systems with multiple transiting planets, the b distribution also depends on the mutual orbital inclinations (Throughout this paper, inclination and the symbol ¯ i always refer to the mutual orbital inclination unless otherwise stated.) among the planets, and thus both the eccentricity and inclination distributions can be inferred. See SI Appendix, section 3, for a full description of our methodology. This method hinges on the well-characterized host properties to derive reliable and precise stellar density ρ. Due to the difficulty of precisely characterizing large samples of stars, the method has hitherto not been applied to a large and homogeneous sample of Kepler planetary systems. Previous studies such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> have used stellar parameters from the Kepler input catalog (KIC), which are plagued by large systematic uncertainties (see SI Appendix, section 1). A recent study <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> uses a sample of 28 multi-transiting systems with precisely measured stellar densities from asteroseismology, and found that the planetary orbits in these systems have low eccentricities. The sample was nevertheless biased towards systems with asteroseismic detections, and did not include single transiting planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Here, we derive the eccentricity distributions of 698 Kepler planet candidates using transit duration statistics. The analysis of this large and homogeneous sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> is made possible through spectroscopic observations by the Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> with reliably derived stellar properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> from the LAM-OST Stellar Parameter (LASP) pipeline (see Sec 4.4 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and also <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>). See SI Appendix Section 1 for further discussions on stellar parameters.</p><p>Eccentricity Dichotomy. Our sample consists of 368 systems with single transiting planet candidates (Np = 1) and 330 planet candidates in multiples (Np &gt; 1). For the two subsamples, we simulate T /T0 distributions with various ¯ e and/or ¯ i assuming Rayleigh distributions, and fit them to the observed T /T0 distributions (see SI Appendix Section 4). The results are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 and 2</ref> for the singles and multiples, respectively.</p><p>The eccentricity distribution of singles is clearly non-circular with a mean eccentricity of ¯ e = 0.32 ± 0.02. In contrast, the orbits of multiples are consistent with being circular and nearly coplanar, with a mean eccentricity ¯ e &lt; 0.07 and a mean orbital inclinations 0.006 rad (0.3 • )&lt; ¯ i &lt;0.038 rad (2.2 • ). We further divide the multiples into subsamples with Np = 2, Np = 3 and Np &gt; 3 transiting planets. We find that the mean eccentricities of these three subsamples are all close to zero and comparable to each other within statistical uncertainties, in contrast to the large mean eccentricity of singles <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref>. Our results indicate an abrupt transition of ¯ e from singles (Np = 1) to multiples (Np &gt; 1) rather than a smooth correlation with Np as suggested from the study on the RV sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. The low eccentricities of multiples found here are consistent with previous studies of smaller samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref> and individual systems, e.g., <ref type="bibr">Kepler-11[10]</ref>, Kepler-36 <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> etc.</p><p>Singles: Two Populations. When viewed from different orientations, a multiple-planet system can result in multi-transiting and single-transiting systems. Our results provide a direct evidence that not all Kepler single-transiting system come from the same underlying planet population as the systems with multiple transiting planets. Instead, the Kepler planet population is likely dichotomic in eccentricities: at least some of the single-transits come from a dynamically hotter population than the underlying population of multi-transiting systems.</p><p>We are therefore motivated to investigate the transit duration ratio of singles with a two-population model <ref type="figure">(Fig. 4)</ref>. In the model, we fix the dynamically cold population with an eccentricity distribution corresponding to the best fit of multi-transiting systems, and fit the fraction (F hot ) and mean eccentricity (¯ e hot ) of the hot population. The best-fit two-population model provides a statistically significant improvement over the one-population model in matching the observations. We find that the hot population makes up a small fraction of the sample (F hot ∼ 16% − 36%) with an even higher mean eccentricity (¯ e hot &gt; 0.47), indicating that the singles are probably dominated by a cold population</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(F cold = 1 − F hot ∼ 64% − 84%).</formula><p>Prevalence of Circular Orbits. As the singles contribute to about half of all the Kepler planets, the fraction of planets in the cold population out of the whole sample is even higher (∼ 80% − 90%), leading to a conclusion that most Kepler planets are on near-circular orbits. The dominance of nearcircular orbits may imply that planets mostly form and evolve in a relatively gentle manner dynamically. Violent dynamical scenarios which excite high eccentricities, for example through planet-planet scattering <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and close stellar encounters <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, therefore must be relatively rare, unless there are subsequent processes that efficiently circularize the orbits.</p><p>A common relation between eccentricity and inclination. The low eccentricities and inclinations of the Kepler multiples are naturally expected from simple considerations of terrestrial planet formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, and they are consistent with the expectation from the well-established coplanarity of the Kepler multiple systems ( ¯ i ∼ a few degrees) <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>, resembling the Solar System planets. Further comparing the orbital properties of Kepler multiples to those of the Solar System objects, we find an intriguing pattern: orbital eccentricities and inclinations are distributed around ¯ e ∼(1-2)× ¯ i (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>). All the regular moon systems are located in the dynamically cold end (bottom left), while the Asteroid Belt objects and TransNeptune objects (TNOs) are located in the dynamically hot end (up-right). Interestingly, the Kepler planets and the Solar System planets (¯ e ∼ 0.06, ¯ i ∼ 3 • ) are located in the intermediate region and close to each other. Note that the Kepler single-transiting systems are not shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref> because we cannot measure their inclination distributions. If they were following the same pattern, they would be located in the dynamical hot region (up right corner of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5)</ref> given their large mean eccentricity. If true, we would expect that the obliquity of Kepler single transiting systems should be systematically larger than those of the Kepler multiples <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussions</head><p>In contrast to the low eccentricity of multiple-transit systems, the mean eccentricity of single-transit systems is much higher and similar to that of planets found by RV surveys, but unlike the RV planets, most of the Kepler single-transiting systems are sub-Neptune-sized planets (&lt; 4 Earth radii). We further compare the singles to the multiples in terms of planetary properties (radius and orbital period) and host properties (stellar mass, radius, metallicity and surface density). We found that these parameters are unlikely to play a decisive role in forming the eccentricity dichotomy (SI Appendix section 2.1). The dichotomy may have important implications for planet formation and evolution. From the perspective of evolution, current studies have found that the architecture of a planetary system may depend on various conditions during planet formation, e.g., the total mass and distribution of solid <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and the degree of depletion of gas <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> in the planet-forming disk. From the perspective of evolution, long-term planet-planet interactions can sculpt the planet architectures <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> after planet formation. The eccentricity dichotomy found in this work may help to pin down the initial conditions for planet formation and shed light on planet dynamical evolution.</p><p>One important concern about the eccentricity dichotomy is the likely larger false positive (FP) rate of the singles as compared to that of the multiples. To investigate this issue, we perform two sets of analyses (see SI Appendix section 5.4). In the first set of analysis, we remove singles with large FP probability to reduce the total FP rate of single sample to a degree (a few percents) that is comparable to that of the multiple sample. In the other analysis, we model the effects of the FP on transit duration ratio distribution by injecting FPs into our simulations and fit the data. Both analyses lead to results (SI <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Appendix Fig.S13, Fig.S14</ref>, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S16</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S17</ref>) that are consistent with those shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Based on these analyses, we conclude that FP should not qualitatively change our main conclusion, namely the Kepler singles are composed of dynamically cold and dynamically hot populations.</p><p>The correlation between eccentricities and inclinations shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref> is generally expected from popular planet formation models, which predict that orbital eccentricities are less than twice of orbital inclinations on average <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> (the grey region in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>). In fact, ¯ e ∼ 2 ¯ i is consistent with the prediction of energy equipartition among the various degrees of freedom of planetary orbit <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. The prevalence of circular orbits among Kepler planets and the common pattern between</p><p>Kepler multiples and Solar System planets may imply that our planetary system is not so atypical in the Galaxy after all. The circular-orbit model (dotted-dashed) is clearly ruled out. The models shown (grey scale) assume Rayleigh eccentricity distributions with mean eccentricities ¯ e varying between 0 and 0.6 (dashed). The best-fit model with ¯ e = 0.32 is shown in blue. The observed distribution has relatively large deviations from the best-fit model in the range of T /T0 ∼ 1.0 − 2.0, which may indicate either the breakdown of the assumed model Rayleigh distribution or the need for more than one underlying populations (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>   Best-fit model:    </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">¯ e = 0.04 ¯ i = 0.024 = 1.4 • ¯ e = 0, ¯ i = 0 − 10 • ¯ e = 0 − 0.5, ¯ i = 10 • (A) ¯ e = 0.5, ¯ i = 10 • ¯ e = 0, ¯ i = 10 • ¯ e = 0, ¯ i = 0 •</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">¯ e =2 ¯ i ¯ e = ¯ i</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting Information (SI) Appendix</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Stellar Parameters</head><p>LAMOST has been performing large-scale Galactic surveys with the spectral resolution R ∼ 1800 <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>, and the LAMOST observations of the Kepler field started in 2011 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. We use the stellar parameters extracted from the LAMOST Stellar Parameter Pipeline (LASP) (see Sec 4.4 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and also <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>) in the "AFGK high quality stellar parameter catalog" of LAMOST DR1, DR2 and DR3-alpha data releases. There are 29553 unique Kepler targets that have LAMOST/LASP stellar parameters. We perform several internal and external examinations on the accuracy of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameters for the dwarfs.</p><p>There are 5924 Kepler targets that have LAMOST/LASP stellar parameters from more than one epochs of LAMOST observations. We assess the internal errors by making comparisons of the multiepoch observations for the same objects. We use the unbiased estimator <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">∆Q i = n/(n − 1)(Q i − ¯ Q)</formula><p>, with i = 1, 2, ..., n, where i denotes each of the individual measurement of n repeated measurements for the stellar parameter Q for each star. Because there are a small number of common stars with low SNRs, it is difficult to calibrate the errors directly from external calibrators for low-SNR measurements. In order to estimate the error bars for both high-and low-SNR measurements, the standard deviations derived from high-SNR measurements are added in quadrature with the internal error bars in the form of the second-order polynomials shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S1</ref>. Since the standard deviations for high-SNR measurements from the external calibrations are much larger than the internal errors at similar SNRs, this approach keeps external error calibrations at high SNRs while takes the internal calibrations into account for low-SNR measurements.</p><p>We have also made comparisons in log(g) with the Kepler asteroseismology sample for solar-type stars <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[39]</ref>. There are 260 common stars between the LAMOST/LASP and the seismology samples. We find that the log(g) determinations from LAM-OST/LASP are in excellent agreement with asteroseismic values, with ∆log(g) = 0.03 ± 0.09 for SNRg &gt; 50 (see the red points in the bottom panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). The dispersion (0.09 dex) is smaller than that from the comparison with the spectroscopic sample (0.15 dex). The larger dispersion for the latter likely reflects the systematic uncertainties in the SPC method, as demonstrated by comparison with the Kepler seismology sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref>. We apply the same quadrature corrections taking into account for the internal errors and the resulting values as a function of SNR are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref> (dashed line in the bottom panel). Note that similar comparisons have been made before for LAMOST log(g) but mostly for giant stars <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref> or a mixture of giant and dwarf stars <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. For giant stars, LAMOST log(g) appears to have larger uncertainties compared to that for the results for the dwarfs studied here. <ref type="figure">Fig. S3</ref> shows the T eff and log(g) distributions of the LAMOST (black), high-resolution spectroscopy (blue) and asteroseismology (red) samples discussed above. For the planet hosts studied in our main work, we only include dwarfs with log(g) &gt; 4 (log(g) = 4 is shown as dashed line). Even though asteroseismology provides higher precision in log(g) than high-resolution spectroscopy, the available seismology stars cover poorly for log(g) &gt; 4.4 thus possibly limiting the parameter space for its applicability. Given the limitation for both calibrators, we adopt two sets of log(g) with uncertainties determined from high-resolution spectroscopy and seismology respectively, and we derive the eccentricity distributions using both sets of log(g) uncertainties separately. We have also make similar comparisons with the SPC sample published in 2014 <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[42]</ref>, and there are twice as many common stars available as compared to the 2012 sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref> used above. The mean differences and standard deviations of ∆T eff , ∆log(g), ∆[Fe/H] are 15K ± 111K, −0.04 ± 0.15, −0.05 ± 0.14 for the 2014 sample. The standard deviations in ∆T eff and ∆log(g) are similar to the 2012 sample while twice larger in <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>. This likely due to the new prior in log(g) introduced to the 2014 study <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[42]</ref> and the covariance between log(g) and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>. In this work, we adopt the uncertainties derived from earlier SPC sample <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>. <ref type="figure">Fig. S4</ref> shows the comparison in log(g) between the Kepler input catalog (KIC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref> and LAMOST/LASP. KIC stellar parameters are widely used for studies of Kepler planets, including previous studies of Kepler planet distributions using transit duration statistics <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. From the comparison, for stars with log(g) LAMOST &gt; 3.5, the standard deviation of ∆log(g) = log(g) KIC − log(g) LAMOST is 0.3 dex, translating to 0.45 dex in uncertainties for ρ * . In addition, there are serious trends of ∆log(g) as a function of stellar parameters, in particular log(g). The average ∆log(g) is close to zero for stars with close to solar gravity log(g) ∼ 4.4, but for the stars bigger than the Sun, the KIC log(g) values tend to be under-estimated while for the stars smaller than the Sun, the KIC log(g) tend to be over-estimated. The dynamical range of KIC log(g) is smaller than the spectroscopic log(g). The large dispersion and severe systematic render any statistical studies based on KIC log(g) likely untrustworthy.</p><p>We determine the stellar mass, radius and density with the LAMOST/LASP T eff , log(g), <ref type="bibr">[</ref>Fe/H] using isochrone fitting on a dense grid of isochrones. We use the 2012 version of the interpolated isochrones from "The Dartmouth Stellar Evolution Database" <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref> with a range of [Fe/H] from -1.5 dex to 0.5 dex (grid size of 0.02 dex) and stellar age from 1 to 13 Gyrs (grid size of 0.5 dex). We have also applied a separate method <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref> with the Dartmouth isochrones and found good consistency between the two.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The Sample</head><p>We adopt the transit parameters from the cumulative Kepler planet candidate catalog reported at the NASA Exoplanet Archive (exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu; retrieved on June 29th, 2015). We crossmatch the Kepler planet candidates with LAMOST data releases discussed above, and there are 941 planet candidates with host stars characterized by the LAMOST spectroscopy. We further rule out those unusual large candidates (radius Rp &gt; 15 Earth radii) and those with too low transit signal noise ratio (SNR&lt; 7.1) (more discussion on the cuts on planet parameters in Section 5.4 and 5.5) and sub-giant/giant hosts (surface gravity log(g) &lt;4), which have relatively large false positive rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref>. We also rule out a handful of candidates with less than 3 transit, as the number of transit is too few to obtain accurate orbital period. After the cuts, we have a final sample of 698 planet candidates orbiting 501 stars. The stellar and planetary properties can be accessed from the Supplementary dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Singles vs. Multiples. Our sample consists of 368 and 330 planet</head><p>candidates in single and multiple transiting systems, respectively. The multiplicity rate is about 47%, which is comparable to that of the total Kepler sample (42% if applying the same cuts above), showing that LAMOST observations were unbiased with respect to singles or multiples as compared to the full Kepler sample. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. S5</ref>, we compare various properties (stellar and planetary) for the two subsets. All stellar parameters are from the LAMOST spectral characterizations. The planet orbital periods are adopted from the Kepler catalog. The planet radii are calculated via Rp = R * r with R adopted derived from LAMOST and the ratio of planet and star radius, r, from the Kepler catalog. There appears to be no significant difference (i.e., KS p value &lt;5%) between the singles and multiple in terms of stellar mass, radius, metallicity, surface gravity, except for planetary radius and orbital period. If we further cut the sample to eliminate those candidates in the regime with relatively high false positive rate (i.e., Rp &gt; 6R ⊕ and orbital period P &lt; 3 day), we find that the differences in various parameters between singles and multiples are even smaller. As we show below (Section 4 and 5), these two populations however differ substantially in their transit duration ratio distributions and thus their orbital eccentricities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Comparison with the RV Sample. From the Exoplanet Orbit</head><p>Database (exoplanets.org) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, we find 439 RV planets. <ref type="figure">Fig. S6</ref> shows the distributions of planetary mass in the RV sample and the estimated mass assuming a simple mass-radius relation from our sample. We see that the two samples occupy different part of parameter space. The RV sample is primarily composed of giant planets, while our sample contains mainly small planets (Earth to super-Earths and/or sub-Neptunes). <ref type="bibr">(2014)</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> have extracted the eccentricity distribution of 139 nearresonance Kepler planets/candidates from transit timing variation (TTV sample). They find the orbits of these near-resonance planets are nearly circular with mean eccentricity ¯ e ∼ 0.02. Van Eylen &amp; Albrecht (2015) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> have derived the orbital eccentricities of 66 Kepler planets (candidates) in 28 multiple transiting systems whose host stars are characterized by asteroseismology (seismology sample). They also find these multiple systems are generally with small eccentricities. <ref type="bibr">Shabram et al. 2015[47]</ref> have calculated the eccentricities of 50 short period Kepler planets (candidates) by occultation (i.e., secondary eclipse) (occultation sample). They find that the mean eccentricity is about 0.08 and a two-component model provides a better fit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Comparison to Previous Studies. Recently, Hadden &amp; Lithwick</head><p>In <ref type="figure">Fig. S7</ref>, we compare our sample (LAMOST sample) to the samples of these previous studies, in terms of stellar and planetary properties. The stars in the seismology sample are biased toward sub-giants. Due to the requirements for having occultation, the occultation sample contains mostly giant planets on short orbital period, in contrast with the predominantly sub-Neptune planets of the whole Kepler planet sample and our sample. We note that <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref> also studied the eccentricity distribution of Kepler giant planets and found that it was consistent with that derived from RV giant planets. Due to the TTV detection limit, the TTV sample are restricted to planets with relatively large radius (larger radius corresponds to higher SNR) and intermediate period (shorter period corresponds to shorter transit duration, longer period corresponds to fewer transit). Furthermore, TTV studies are restricted to special orbital configurations of near-resonance. In contrast, the host stars and planets in the LAMOST sample are broadly distributed and represent an unbiased and homogeneous sample from Kepler.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Simulations of Transit Duration Ratio Distribution</head><p>In this Section, we describe the method and procedure that are used to model the transit duration ratio distribution. Compared to previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, there are two major improvements in our modeling. Moorhead et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> stressed the importance of uncertainties of stellar and transit parameters in modeling transit duration ratio but they did not take these uncertainties into account when comparing with observation. We include the uncertainties in our modeling. Second, we treat singles and multiples separately. In particular, when modeling the transit duration distribution for multi-transiting systems, it is important to take the mutual inclination distribution into account. We stress that these two corrections are crucial for transit duration statistics to infer eccentricity from Kepler, and without taking them into account, it can lead to serious errors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Single Transiting Systems.</head><p>For each planet candidate in singletransiting systems, we perform the following steps to generate a simulated transit duration ratio.</p><p>Step 1: We first draw an eccentricity (e) between 0 and 1 from a Rayleigh distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50]</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">dN = e σ 2 e exp − e 2 2σ 2 e de, [S1]</formula><p>where σe is the Rayleigh parameter and the mean eccentricity ¯ e = σe π/2. We repeat this step if (1 − e)a R &lt; 1 because it is unphysical (the planet is inside the star). Here a R is the ratio of orbital semi-major axis (a) and the radius of the host star (R). Considering the Kepler's third law, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">a R = 4.2 P d 2/3 ρ ρ 1/3 , [S2]</formula><p>where P and ρ are the transit orbital period and the density of the host star, and they are adopted from the observed values for a given system. Note that for large σe, due to the eccentricity cutoffs (e &lt; 1 and (1 − e)a R &gt; 1), the mean eccentricity of those drawn from our simulation is smaller than ¯ e = σe π/2, and we report the mean eccentricity calculated from the simulation.</p><p>Step 2: We draw a prior argument of pericenter (ω) and a prior cos i 0 from a uniform distributions and calculate the impact parameter,</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">b = a R ccosi 0 , [S3]</formula><p>where i 0 is the orbital inclination with respect to the plane of the sky, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">c = (1 − e 2 )/(1 + esinω).</formula><p>[S4]</p><p>If b &gt; 1 + r, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">r = Rp/R [S5]</formula><p>is the radius ratio of planet/star, it indicates that no transit occurs, then we go back to Step 1. In practice, we set the maximum of cos i 0 as min(1, (1 + r)/(a R c)) to avoid drawing a lot of non-transiting cases. After the above transit selection (by cutting off b &gt; 1 + r), the distribution of the simulated ω (especially in the case of large eccentricity) will deviate from the prior uniform distribution because of the well-known geometric effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[51]</ref>, namely, transit probability is enhanced near the periastron and reduced near the apstron.</p><p>Step 3: We calculate the transit duration (total duration, first to fourth contact) following <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Kipping (2010)</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[52]</ref>, namely</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">T = P π 2 c √ 1 − e 2 arcsin (1 + r) 2 − a 2 R 2 c cos 2 i 0 a R csini 0 .</formula><p>[S6]</p><p>For illustrating purpose only (we always use Equation S6 in our computation), the above equation can be approximately reduced to,</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">T ∼ T 0 * F (e, ω, b), [S7]</formula><p>where the function</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">F (e, ω, b) = (1 − b 2 )(1 − e 2 ) 1 + esinω , [S8]</formula><p>and T 0 is a characteristic time scale, denoting the transit duration if the planet moves on a circular orbit and transits the center of the host star. T 0 is calculated from Equation S6 by setting e = 0 and b = 0, and it can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">T 0 = 13 hr(P/yr) 1/3 (ρ/ρ ) −1/3 (1 + r). [S9]</formula><p>The transit duration ratio (TDR) is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">TDR mod = T /T 0 . [S10]</formula><p>Note that here TDR mod is the duration ratio predicted from pure theoretical model without any observational uncertainty.</p><p>Step 4: To simulate a transit duration ratio observation, one needs to consider the observational uncertainties of T and T 0 . The simulated duration T sim is obtained by taking the observed duration into account (assuming a Gaussian distribution),</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">T sim = T * [1 + R N * (σ T obs /T obs )], [S11]</formula><p>where σ T obs is the observed uncertainty of T obs and R N is a random variable drawn from a normal distribution centered at 0 and with standard deviation of 1. Here we assume the simulated transit duration has the same relative uncertainty as the observation. Similarly,</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">T 0sim = T 0 * [1 + R N * (σ T 0 /T 0 )].</formula><p>[S12]</p><p>By propagating errors, the relative error of T 0 can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">σ T 0 /T 0 = σρ 3ρ 2 + σr 1 + r 2 [S13]</formula><p>where σρ and σr are the observed uncertainties of ρ and r, and R N is a random number drawn from a normal distribution centered at 0 and with standard deviation of 1. Note the two R N in equations (S11) and (S12) are indepedent. For each simulated T sim , following Fabrycky et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, we assign a signal noise ratio SNR sim = SNR obs T sim /T obs , where SNR obs and T obs are the observed transit signal noise ratio and duration. We uses a SNR cut to take into account the detection efficiency of the Kepler pipeline. We go back to Step 1 if SNR sim &lt; 7.1. About 5% of simulated transits are eliminated by the SNR cut. Otherwise, the ratio T sim /T 0sim contributes to the simulated transit duration ratio distribution, namely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">TDR sim = T sim /T 0sim .</formula><p>[S14]</p><p>The uncertainty of TDR sim or TDR obs is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">σTDR = σ T obs T obs 2 + σρ 3ρ 2 + σr 1 + r 2 .</formula><p>[S15]</p><p>Here, the covariances among the parameters (T obs , ρ and r) are ignored. Their contributions are minor, and the total uncertainty is dominated by that from the stellar properties, σρ 3ρ</p><p>as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. S8</ref>.</p><p>In the single-transiting case, the only free model parameter is the mean eccentricity ¯ e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Multiple Transiting Systems.</head><p>For multiple transiting systems, the method is the same as above except for drawing inclination cos i 0 distribution in the Step 2 of Section 3.1. For single transiting systems, the cos i 0 from different systems are independent of each other. However, this is not the case for multiple transiting systems, where cos i 0 of different planets in the same system are correlated. In order to take into account the above effect, for a multiple transiting system, we first draw a reference cos i 0 uniformly, then for each transiting planet in the system, similarly to Fabrycky et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, we set its cos i 0 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">cos i 0 = cos i 0 + R N * σ i , [S16]</formula><p>where R N is a random number drawn from a normal distribution centered at 0 and with standard deviation of 1, resulting in a Rayleigh distribution of width σ i in mutual inclination i, namely</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">dN = i σ 2 i exp − i 2 2σ 2 i di, [S17]</formula><p>where σ i is Rayleigh parameter and the mean inclination ¯ i = σ i π/2. In the multiple transiting case, there are two free parameters for modeling the transit duration ratio, which are the mean eccentricity ¯ e and the mean inclination ¯ i. Note that we simulate transit duration ratios system by system. A simulated system is selected if all the simulated planets in the system have enough S/N to be detected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Transit Duration Ratio: Observations vs Simulations</head><p>In this section, we describe using Maximum Likelihood (hereafter ML) method to estimate the planet eccentricity and/or inclination distributions by modeling the observed transit duration ratio distributions.</p><p>We calculate the likelihood L as a function of ¯ e and/or ¯ i, and the best-fit model has the maximum L. The likelihood function L is computed similarly to Hadden &amp; Lithwick <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The likelihood that a given planet in our sample has observed transit duration ratio TDR obs is</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">L(TDR obs |¯ e, ¯ i) = P (TDR|¯ e, ¯ i)exp[−(TDR − TDR obs ) 2 /2σ 2 TDR ]dTDR. [S18]</formula><p>where the first term on the right hand side, P (TDR|¯ e, ¯ i), is the probability that the transit duration ratio as determined by the theoretical model (equation S10), assuming the model parameters ¯ e and ¯ i are randomly drawn from the Rayleigh distribution (equations S1 and S17). The second term, exp[−(TDR − TDR obs ) 2 /2σ 2 TDR ], is the probability that the model TDR generates the observed one TDR obs given the noise distribution. Here σ TDR is the 1-sigma uncertainty of TDR obs (equation S15). We compute the total likelihood L by multiplying together the likelihoods for all planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Single Transiting Systems.</head><p>In this case, the only fitting parameter is the mean orbital eccentricity ¯ e. We consider a series of ¯ e from 0.0001 (essentially 0) to 0.6 with an interval of 0.002. For each ¯ e, following section 3.1, we generate 300 simulated transit duration ratio TDR mod for each planet to calculate the probability P (TDR|¯ e) in equation S18. The total likelihood, L is plotted as a function of ¯ e in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> in the main text. The likelihood values are then smoothed as a function of ¯ e using a spline function to estimate the confidence intervals (1-σ: 68.3%, 2-σ:95.4% and 3-σ: 99.7%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Multiple Transiting Systems.</head><p>In this case, the fitting parameter is the mean orbital eccentricity ¯ e (equation S1) and mean mutual orbital inclination ¯ i. We consider a grid of ¯ i − ¯ e, where ¯ i from 0.00001 (essentially 0) to 0.2 (∼ 11.5 • ) with an interval of 0.002 and ¯ e is from 0.0001 (essentially 0) to 0.4 with an interval of 0.01. For each pair of ¯ e and ¯ i, following section 3.2, we generate 100 modeled transit duration ratios TDR mod for each planet to calculate the probability predicted by the model, i.e., P (TDR|¯ e, ¯ i) in equation S18. L is shown as a contour map in the plane of ¯ i − ¯ e in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> in the main text, which gives the confidence intervals (1-σ: 68.3%, 2-σ:95.4% and 3-σ: 99.7%) of ¯ i and ¯ e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Further Discussions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">An Abrupt Transition or A Smooth Correlation?.</head><p>Recently, Limbach &amp; Turner <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> analyzed the RV planet sample and they reported that the planetary eccentricity is anti-correlated to planetary multiplicity -the mean eccentricity progressively decreases with the number of planets in the system. In our work, as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>, all ¯ e in the three multiple subsamples are comparable within uncertainties and close to zero, which is in contrast to the relatively large ¯ e in the single subsample (Np = 1). This suggests an abrupt transition rather than a smooth correlation as a function of number of transiting planets in the system. However, we caution that it is challenging to make a direct comparison between these two works: First, the majority of RV planets are Jovian planets, while most Kepler planets are super-Earths/Sub-Neptunes. Second, the detection efficiency and selection bias are different between RV and Kepler transit surveys, thus the number of planets in the system Np have different meanings between the two works. For example, some single transiting systems can come from intrinsically multiple-planet systems with only one planet transiting (see more discussions in the next section).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Impact Parameter Distribution.</head><p>Transit light curves contain information of impact parameter (e.g., Seager &amp; Mallen-Ornelas <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[53]</ref>) and in principle, such information can be incorporated into modeling the transit duration ratio distributions. In practice, inferences of individual impact parameters are most reliable for the Kepler planets with short-cadence (1 min) data, good knowledge of limb darkening and/or deep transits (i.e., high SNRs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[54]</ref>. Previous works (e.g., see <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> of <ref type="bibr">Swift et al. [55]</ref>) have shown that impact parameter is difficult to determine from the long cadence data. As our sample is mainly composed of small planets (thus relatively shallow depth) with long cadence (30 minutes) data, we choose not to use the derived impact parameters for individual objects. Instead, we model the impact parameter distribution from simulation as given in supplementary Section 3.</p><p>In the following, we discuss the impact parameter distributions of the singles, which are plotted in <ref type="figure">Fig. S9</ref>. The blue and green lines depict the distributions in our nominal simulation with signal noise ratio cut SNRc = 7.1 and simulation with SNRc = 15 (see section 5.5), respectively. The impact parameters are smaller compared to the uniform distribution (black dashed line) <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[55]</ref>, and this is because smaller impact parameters lead to larger transit duration and thus higher SNR (i.e., more detectable).</p><p>There is another additional possible bias for having relatively larger contribution from larger impact parameters for singles. If a significant fraction of single-transiting systems come from coplanar multiple planet systems, their impact parameters should be biased towards large value to avoid seeing outer planets. In the following, we show that this bias is minor.</p><p>We generate a synthetic single transiting population by following the method described by <ref type="bibr">Fang &amp; Margot[56]</ref>. Specifically, we first generate 10 6 planetary systems assuming that each systems have N planets with mutual orbital inclination of i. Here N is drawn from a bounded uniform distribution represented by a single parameter λ, and i is drawn from Rayleigh distribution with a scaling parameter of σ i . We adopt λ = 2.5 (best fit of <ref type="bibr">Fang &amp; Margot[56]</ref>), and σ i = 2 • (motivated by our results shown in the <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> of the main text). We then arbitrarily select a viewing angle and choose the single transiting systems. The red line in <ref type="figure">Fig. S9</ref> shows the impact parameter distribution of the synthetic single transiting population. As compared to the uniform distribution, it biases towards large impact parameter as expected. Adopting the synthetic impact parameter distribution to fit the transit duration ratio, we obtain ¯ e = 0.275 +0.029 −0.026 , which is consistent with our nominal result shown in the <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> of the main text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Outermost of Multiples.</head><p>For multiple transiting systems, if we only consider the outermost ones, then there is no need to fit the mutual inclination. In this case, we can do eccentricity-only fit as is done for the singles to perform a direct comparison. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S10</ref> shows the eccentricity fitting results for the outermost of multiples, which are consistent with nearly circular orbits in contrast to the relatively large eccentricities of singles ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 in the main text)</ref>. The results reinforce our conclusion: on average, multiples are dynamically cold while singles are hot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">False Positive. The majority of</head><p>Kepler planet candidates lack direct confirmation with RV, and it is important to assess how much the false positives (FPs) may affect the eccentricity distributions derived in our work. The overwhelming majority of Kepler multiples (∼ 98%) are believed to be bona fide planets <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[57]</ref>, thus the issue of FPs is most concerning for the single-transiting systems. We perform the following two sets of analyses to study the effects of FPs on our results.</p><p>(1) We attempt to eliminate KOIs with large estimated false positive probabilities (FPPs) by making various cuts on our sample.</p><p>First, we remove subsets of our samples with large estimated FPPs. Indirect statistical estimates generally find a low ( 10%) averaged FPP for the entire sample of Kepler planet candidates <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[58]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[59]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[60]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref> but the FPPs can be much higher for certain subsets of candidates. Approximately half of the Kepler giant planet candidates measured by Santern et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">63]</ref> with radial velocities are found to be FPs, and statistical studies also find that FPPs are substantially higher for large planet candidates (radius &gt;6R ⊕ ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">61]</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[64]</ref> found that FPPs can also depend on orbital periods, and the close-in planet candidates with orbital period &lt;3 d may have higher FPPs. We remove the large (&gt;6R ⊕ ) and close-in (&lt; 3 d) planet candidates, yielding smaller samples with 280 and 291 planet candidates in the single and multiple transiting systems, respectively. The transit duration ratio distribution fits to these two samples give ¯ e = 0.285 +0.024 −0.023 for singles and ¯ e ≤ 0.076, 0.017 &lt; ¯ i ≤ 0.065 for multipls, and they are consistent with the results shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> and 2 in the main text.</p><p>Second, we reduce the averaged FPP of our sample by eliminating the candidates with large estimated FPPs by Morton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>. Recently Morton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref> published their FPP estimates for all KOIs individually, and their estimates are consistent with existing direct RV measurements such as Santern et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>.</p><p>At first thought, one might proceed the analysis by selecting the KOIs with low FPP (e.g., FPP&lt; 4.6% and FPP&lt; 0.3%, corresponding to 2-σ and 3-σ confidence for true planets). However, we find that only analyzing those with low FFPs can be problematic. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S11</ref> shows the transit duration distributions of single-transiting planet candidates with various FPP cuts. The distributions for FPP&lt; 4.6% (2-σ; red) and FPP&lt; 0.3% (3-σ; cyan) differ significantly. Both distributions are truncated at T /T 0 0.3 − 0.4, while T /T 0 should get down to ∼ 0 (corresponding to impact parameter b = 1) in any physically valid models. Similar patterns show up for multiple-transiting systems by performing the same FPP cuts (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. S12</ref>) and the resulting distributions are not consistent with any models (e.g., ¯ e = 0 − 0.5, gray and black lines), signifying the failure with this approach. A main problem with this approach is that, cutting at a low FPP threshold (e.g., FPP&lt;4.6%) excludes a significant fraction of KOIs with relatively high probabilities being true planets (e.g., FPP∼10% thus ∼ 90% probability being true planets). While in Morton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>, transit duration is used as part of input information to infer FPP, so FPP may have some dependence on transit duration. For example, some true planets at high impact parameters and thus small transit duration ratios can have relatively large FPPs. Cutting the sample at low FPP thresholds can therefore remove true planets in a way that depend on their transit duration ratios, which in turn introduces a bias in the resulting transit duration ratio distribution. In our single-planet sample, according to <ref type="bibr">Morton et al.[61]</ref>, the mean FPP is ∼ 12%, but performing cuts of FPP&lt; 4.6% and FPP&lt; 0.3% remove ∼ 27% and ∼ 49% of the sample, respectively. So the difference between the transit duration ratio distributions of the &lt; 4.6% and &lt; 0.3% FPP cuts are not mainly caused by eliminating FPs but rather by removing a large fraction of true planets in a biased fashion from the sample.</p><p>Instead of keeping planet candidates with low FPPs, we choose to remove planet candidates with high FPPs. We find that in Morton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>, the FPPs of the sample are dominated by those with high FPPs. If we remove planet candidates with high FPPs (those with FPP&gt;68.3% and FPP&gt;95.4%), the mean FPP of the sample reduce to ∼2.2% and ∼5.9% respectively, which are comparable to the mean FPP (∼2.4% and ∼3.9%) of multiple transiting systems by making the same FPP cuts. With such low mean FPPs, the effects of FPs should be nearly negligible. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S13</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S14</ref>, we plot the results of two-population fit for singles using the two high FPP cuts (by keeping candidates with FPP&lt;68.3% and FPP&lt;95.4%) respectively. Qualitatively, the results are comparable to those in the main text without FPP cut <ref type="figure">(Fig.4)</ref>, namely, they all reveal a hot and a cold populations in the singles. Quantitatively, the results are consistent with each other within their 1-σ uncertainties. As compared to <ref type="figure">Fig.4</ref>, the best-fit mean eccentricities for the hot population are lower (∼ 0.3 − 0.4 as compared to ∼ 0.6), while the fraction of the hot population are somewhat higher (∼ 0.3 as compared to ∼ 0.2).</p><p>(2) Alternatively, we try to model the impact of FPs by injecting FPs into our simulations. It is beyond the scope of our work to directly simulate the expected transit duration ratio distribution of FPs from first principles. We instead take an empirical approach by using the KOIs with large FPP according to <ref type="bibr">Morton et al.[61]</ref>. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref>, we plot the transit duration ratio distributions of KOIs with FFP greater than 68.3%, 95.4% and 99.7%, corresponding to 1-σ, 2-σ and 3-σ confidence levels of FPs. Their distributions (blue, green and red lines) are shallower than expected from the planet models (gray and black lines for ¯ e = 0 − 0.5). This is consistent with our qualitative expectation that the duration distribution should be wider for the transits/eclipses from the FPs. Furthermore, we see that the duration distribution of FP is not very sensitive to the FPP criteria. All three FP criteria lead to similar duration distributions while the 3-σ one (red line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref>) has a somewhat larger deviation from the others between T /T 0 = 1 and T /T 0 = 3. Following this approach, we are not able to completely eliminate the true planets to obtain the "pristine" FP transit duration ratio distribution, and also there are systematic uncertainties due to the dependency of FPP estimates on transit duration. Despite these limitations, since the three distributions are similar to each other and consistent qualitatively with expectations from FPs, they may be useful in informing us the effects of FPs on the transit duration ratio distribution. In order to account for the systematic uncertainties as much as possible, below we use all three distributions presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref> to model the FP distributions.</p><p>Using the FPP estimates given by Morton et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>, we find that the mean FPP of singles in our original single-planet sample is ∼12%. Thus, we inject 12% simulated candidates with transit duration ratio T /T 0 drawn from the distributions of FPs by adopting various FP criteria as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref> and discussed in the previous paragraph. We then repeat the two-population fit as done in <ref type="figure">Fig.4</ref>. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S16</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S17</ref>, we plot the results of using the 2-σ (green line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref>) and the 3-σ (red line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S15</ref>) FP criteria, respectively. The result of the 1-σ criterion is nearly identical to the one using the 2-σ criterion and is not shown. As can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S16</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S17</ref>, the results are consistent with those shown in <ref type="figure">Fig.4</ref> of the main article -the singles are composed of a major dynamically cold population and a minor dynamically hot population. However, we note that, the goodness of fit with modeling FP injection <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig.S16</ref> or <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.S17</ref>) is considerably worse than that of fit with performing FP cut from the sample <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">( Fig.S13 and Fig.S14</ref>). This is not surprising -in the FP injection approach, we implicitly assume that those "hidden" FPs with relatively low FPPs in the sample also follow the injected FP duration distributions selected from high FPPs, but this assumption is almost certainly not warranted.</p><p>Based on the above two kinds of analyses, we therefore conclude that the main conclusions shown in the main text <ref type="figure">(Fig.4)</ref> is qualitatively sound despite the uncertainties introduced by FPs.</p><p>5.5 Signal-to-Noise Ratio. In this work, the Signal-to-Noise Ratio for detection is cut at SN Rc = 7.1 (Step 4 of Section 2.1) for both simulation and observation. To see how the SNR cut affects our results, we vary the threshold of SNR, i.e., SNRc = 10 and 15, and repeat the same analyses. We find the results are all consistent with those shown in the <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 and 2</ref> in the main text, suggesting that the adopted SNR cut is unlikely to affect our results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">Stellar Property Calibrator.</head><p>As mentioned in Section 1, we derived two sets of uncertainties of stellar properties (e.g. log(g)) based on the calibrators of high-resolution spectroscopy and seismology respectively. All the above results are based on the seismology calibrator. For comparison, we have performed the same analyses as those resulting in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 and 2</ref> but using the stellar properties derived from the calibrator of high-resolution spectroscopy. We find that both calibrators generally give consistent results, i.e., the singles are dynamically hot with mean eccentricities about 0.2-0.3, while the multiples are dynamically cold with eccentricities close to zero. Nevertheless, we note that the mean eccentricity of the singles derived from the spectroscopy calibrator is 0.21 ± 0.04, which is somewhat smaller (by about 2 σ) than that derived from the seismology calibrator. with external errors added in quadrature to produce the final error bars (see <ref type="figure">Fig. S2</ref>). </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Transit duration ratio statistics of Kepler single transiting planets. (A) The cumulative distribution of the observed transit duration T normalized by the expected values for circular and edge-on orbit T0 for the Kepler singles (red). The circular-orbit model (dotted-dashed) is clearly ruled out. The models shown (grey scale) assume Rayleigh eccentricity distributions with mean eccentricities ¯ e varying between 0 and 0.6 (dashed). The best-fit model with ¯ e = 0.32 is shown in blue. The observed distribution has relatively large deviations from the best-fit model in the range of T /T0 ∼ 1.0 − 2.0, which may indicate either the breakdown of the assumed model Rayleigh distribution or the need for more than one underlying populations (see Fig. 4 and related discussion in the main text). (B) Relative likelihood in logarithm as a function of ¯ e. The blue, green and red hatched regions indicate the 68.3% (1σ) 95.4% (2σ) and 99.7% (3σ) confidence levels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Transit duration ratio statistics of Kepler single transiting planets. (A) The cumulative distribution of the observed transit duration T normalized by the expected values for circular and edge-on orbit T0 for the Kepler singles (red). The circular-orbit model (dotted-dashed) is clearly ruled out. The models shown (grey scale) assume Rayleigh eccentricity distributions with mean eccentricities ¯ e varying between 0 and 0.6 (dashed). The best-fit model with ¯ e = 0.32 is shown in blue. The observed distribution has relatively large deviations from the best-fit model in the range of T /T0 ∼ 1.0 − 2.0, which may indicate either the breakdown of the assumed model Rayleigh distribution or the need for more than one underlying populations (see Fig. 4 and related discussion in the main text). (B) Relative likelihood in logarithm as a function of ¯ e. The blue, green and red hatched regions indicate the 68.3% (1σ) 95.4% (2σ) and 99.7% (3σ) confidence levels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 . Transit duration ratio statistics of Kepler multiple transiting planets. (A)Fig. 3 .Fig. 4 .</head><label>234</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Transit duration ratio statistics of Kepler multiple transiting planets. (A) Cumulative distribution of observed transit duration ratios T /T0 for Kepler multiples is shown in red. It is fitted with models assuming Rayleigh distributions in eccentricities and mutual inclinations. A range of circular-orbit models with ¯ e = 0 and ¯ i between 0 and 10 • are shown in green. The orbits of Kepler multiples are consistent with being circular and nearly coplanar. The best-fit model (blue) has ¯ e = 0.04 and ¯ i = 0.024(1.4 • ). For comparison, a range of models with mean eccentricities between 0 and 0.5 and inclinations between 0 and 10 degrees are shown in grey scale. (B) Contours of relative likelihood in logarithm in the ¯ i − ¯ e plane. The blue, green and red contours indicate the 68.3% (1σ) 95.4% (2σ) and 99.7% (3σ) confidence levels of ¯ e and ¯ i. The blue star marks the best-fit values.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .mean eccentricity and inclination of Kepler multiples fit into the pattern of the Solar System objects.</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The mean eccentricity and inclination of Kepler multiples fit into the pattern of the Solar System objects. The thin filled circle and error bars show the mean values and 68% confidence intervals of orbital eccentricity and inclination distributions for Solar System objects, including 8 planets (blue), regular moons of Jupiter, Saturn and Uranus (light green, yellow and black), main belt asteroids (green) and Trans-Neptune objects (TNOs -both the classical Kuiper Belt objects with orbital semi-major axes 30-55 AU shown in red and the scattered disk objects with semi-major axes &gt;55 AU shown in cyan). They follow an approximately linear relation with ¯ e ∼(1-2)× ¯ i (dashed and dotted lines). The thick purple filled circle, error bar (and arrow) show the eccentricity and inclination constraints of Kepler multiples: 0.006 rad (0.3 • )&lt; ¯ i &lt;0.038 rad (2.2 • ) and ¯ e &lt; 0.07 derived in this work. The Kepler multiples fall on the linear relation of the Solar System objects, and they are on similarly circular and coplanar orbits as the Solar System planets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. S1 shows ∆T eff , ∆log(g) and ∆[Fe/H] using the unbiased estimator (black dots). We calculate the 68.3% confidence interval in vari- ous bins of g-band Signal-to-Noise-Ratio per pixel (SNRg) from LAMOST/LASP and find that they are well described by the second- order polynomials as a function of SNRg shown in Fig. S1. For measurements with high SNR (SNRg &gt; 50), the internal errors in T eff , log(g) and [Fe/H] are less than 35K, 0.05 dex and 0.03 dex, respectively. Following a previous approach of external examination of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameters [17], we compare the LAM- OST/LASP parameters with those obtained from the high-resolution spectroscopy with the SPC method [38]. There are 87 stars in com- mon between the SPC and LAMOST/LASP samples. The results of the comparison are shown in the top three panels of Fig. S2. The mean differences are small: ∆T eff = 27K, ∆log(g) = −0.04 dex, ∆[Fe/H] = 0.015 dex, respectively. For those with SNRg &gt; 50, the standard deviations in ∆T eff , ∆log(g), ∆[Fe/H] are 101K, 0.15 dex, 0.074 dex, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. S1. Internal calibration of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameter uncertainties.</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. S1. Internal calibration of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameter uncertainties. The unbiased estimators defined in Supplementary Sec. 1 in T eff , log(g), [Fe/H] from the repeated observations as a function of SNRg . The 68.3% confidence levels in the log(SNRg) bins are well described by second-order polynomials as a function of log(SNRg) plotted in red solid lines. Note the points are for internal errors and curves describing the internal errors as a function of SNR are later combined</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. S2. External calibration of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameter uncertainties for dwarfs.Fig. S5. Normalized cumulative distributions of stellar (mass, radius, metallicity and surface gravity) and planetary (radius and orbital period) properties.Fig. S6. Normalized cumulative distributions of planetary masses of RV planets and the Kepler sample (blue).Fig. S7. Comparisons in host star (Left Panel) and planet (Right Panel) properties with previous studies.Fig. S9. Transit impact parameter distributions of single transiting systems.Fig. S10.Fig. S11.Fig. S12.Fig. S13.Fig. S14.Fig. S15.Fig. S16.Fig. S17.</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. S2. External calibration of LAMOST/LASP stellar parameter uncertainties for dwarfs. The top 3 panels show comparisons in T eff , log(g) and [Fe/H] between LAMOST/LASP and SPC method for high-resolution spectra [38] and the bottom panel shows the comparison in log(g) with asteroseismology [39]. The dotted line shows the mean and the dashed line shows the dispersion taking both internal and external uncertainties into account. Xie et al. PNAS | June 25, 2018 | vol. XXX | no. XX | 15</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table of Contents</head><label>of</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>(1) Stellar Parameters. (Fig.S1-S4) 

(2) The Sample. 
2.1 Singles vs. Multiples. (Fig. S5) 
2.2 Comparison with the RV Sample. (Fig. S6) 
2.3 Comparison with Previous Studies. (Fig. S7) 

(3) Simulations of Transit Duration Ratio Distribu-
tion. (Fig. S8) 
3.1 Single Transiting Systems. 
3.2 Multiple Transiting Systems. 

(4) Transit Duration Ratio: Observations vs. 
Simu-
lations. 
4.1 Single Transiting Systems. 
4.2 Multiple Transiting Systems. 
(5) Further Discussions. 
5.1 An Abrupt Transition or A Smooth Correlation? 
5.2 Impact Parameter Distribution. (</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot">levels. The magenta line (left panel) and magenta star symbol (right panel) indicate the best fit of the two-population model, while the blue ones are for the one-population model. The differences in BIC (Bayesian Information Criterion) between the best fits of the one-population and two-population models is ∆BIC = −2∆ln(L) − ln(N obs ) = 40.2, which indicates a significant improvement in fitting. Xie et al. PNAS | June 25, 2018 | vol. XXX | no. XX | 7</note>

			<note place="foot" n="8"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="10"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot">Xie et al. PNAS | June 25, 2018 | vol. XXX | no. XX | 11</note>

			<note place="foot" n="12"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="14"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="16"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="18"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="20"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="22"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="24"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="26"> | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Xie et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Exoplanet Orbit Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publ. Astron. Soc. Pacif</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="412" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical Properties of Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Eccentricity Distribution of Exoplanets from Radial Velocity Surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">685</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Eccentric Orbital Solutions Can Hide Planetary Systems in 2:1 Resonant Orbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Anglada-Escudé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>López-Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">709</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observational biases in determining extrasolar planet eccentricities in single-planet systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zakamska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">410</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1895" to="1910" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planetary Candidates Observed by Kepler. VI. Planet Sample from Q1-Q16 (47 Months)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mullally</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in exoplanet science from Kepler</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">513</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Photoeccentric Effect and Proto-hot Jupiters. I. Measuring Photometric Eccentricities of Individual Transiting Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">756</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eccentricity from Transit Photometry: Small Planets in Kepler Multi-planet Systems Have Low Eccentricities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Van Eylen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Albrecht</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">808</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A closely packed system of low-mass, low-density planets transiting Kepler-11</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">470</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Densities and Eccentricities of 139 Kepler Planets from Transit Time Variations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lithwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">787</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the Orbital Eccentricities of Transiting Extrasolar Planets with Photometric Observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Veras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">678</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1407" to="1418" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Distribution of Transit Durations for Kepler Planet Candidates and Implications for Their Orbital Eccentricities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lamost Observations in the Kepler Field. I. Database of Low-resolution Spectra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>De Cat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAM-OST)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1197" to="1242" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The first data release (DR1) of the LAMOST regular survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1095</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Metallicities of Kepler Stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">789</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic stellar spectral parameterization pipeline for LAMOST survey in Statistical Challenges in 21st Century Cosmology, IAU Symposium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Heavens A, Starck JL, Krone-Martins A.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">306</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="342" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanet orbital eccentricity: Multiplicity relation and the Solar System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Limbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Density and Eccentricity of Kepler Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lithwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">772</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kepler-36: A Pair of Planets with Neighboring Orbits and Dissimilar Densities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">337</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">556</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origins of Eccentric Extrasolar Planets: Testing the Planet-Planet Scattering Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rasio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="636" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Close encounters in young stellar clusters: implications for planetary systems in the solar neighbourhood</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Malmberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1216" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Statistical Mechanics of Planet Orbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">807</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Statistics of Multi-planet Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Architecture of Kepler&apos;s Multi-transiting Systems. II. New Investigations with Twice as Many Candidates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">790</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">146</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obliquities of Kepler Stars: Comparison of Single-and Multipletransit Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">796</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Kepler Dichotomy in Planetary Disks: Linking Kepler Observables to Simulations of Late-Stage Planet Formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moriarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ballard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlations between Compositions and Orbits Established by the Giant Impact Era of Planet Formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">822</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can Planetary Instability Explain the Kepler Dichotomy?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Church</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Holmelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">758</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spacing of Kepler Planets: Sculpting by Dynamical Instability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">807</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Destruction of Inner Planetary Systems during High-eccentricity Migration of Gas Giants</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mustill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">808</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stirring and dynamical friction rates of planetesimals in the solar gravitational field</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamics of planetesimals: the role of two-body relaxation in IAU Colloq. 197: Dynamics of Populations of Planetary Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kokubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Kneževi´cKneževi´c Z, Milani A</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LAMOST spectral survey: An overview. Res</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="734" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Preface: The LAMOST Galactic surveys and early results</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Res</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1089</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redshift-space clustering of SDSS galaxies -luminosity dependence, halo occupation distribution, and velocity bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4368" to="4383" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An abundance of small exoplanets around stars with a wide range of metallicities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">486</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asteroseismic Fundamental Properties of Solar-type Stars Observed by the NASA Kepler Mission</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fundamental Properties of Kepler Planet-candidate Host Stars using Asteroseismology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the LSP3 estimates of surface gravity for LAMOST-Kepler stars with asteroseismic measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three regimes of extrasolar planet radius inferred from host star metallicities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="593" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kepler Input Catalog: Photometric Calibration and Stellar Classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Esquerdo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Dartmouth Stellar Evolution Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian analysis of ages, masses and distances to cool stars with non-LTE spectroscopic parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Serenelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bergemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ruchti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">429</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3645" to="3657" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A High False Positive Rate for Kepler Planetary Candidates of Giant Stars using Asterodensity Profiling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sliski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">788</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">148</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Eccentricity Distribution of Short-Period Planet Candidates Detected by Kepler in Occultation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shabram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cisewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The exoplanet eccentricity distribution from Kepler planet candidates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gelino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Von Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">425</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="757" to="762" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-oligarchic Evolution of Protoplanetary Embryos and the Stability of Planetary Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dnc</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">666</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="435" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamical Origin of Extrasolar Planet Eccentricity Distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Juri´cjuri´c</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="620" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Transits and Occultations. ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Investigations of approximate expressions for the transit duration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">407</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="313" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Unique Solution of Planet and Star Parameters from an Extrasolar Planet Transit Light Curve</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mallén-Ornelas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1038" to="1055" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Low Can You Go? The Photoeccentric Effect for Planets of Various Sizes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">799</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the Cool KOIs. VIII. Parameters of the Planets Orbiting Kepler Coolest Dwarfs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Swift</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Architecture of Planetary Systems Based on Kepler Data: Number of Planets and Coplanarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Margot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">761</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Almost All of Kepler&apos;s Multiple-planet Candidates Are Planets. Astrophys</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">750</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Low False Positive Probabilities of Kepler Planet Candidates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">738</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The False Positive Rate of Kepler and the Occurrence of Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">766</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low False Positive Rate of Kepler Candidates Estimated From A Combination Of Spitzer And Follow-Up Observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">804</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">False Positive Probabilities for all Kepler Objects of Interest: 1284 Newly Validated Planets and 428 Likely False Positives</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">822</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SOPHIE velocimetry of Kepler transit candidates. VII. A false-positive rate of 35% for Kepler close-in giant candidates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">545</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SOPHIE velocimetry of Kepler transit candidates XVII. The physical properties of giant exoplanets within 400 days of period</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constraining the false positive rate for Kepler planet candidates with multicolour photometry from the GTC</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Colón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Morehead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Architecture and Dynamics of Kepler&apos;s Candidate Multiple Transiting Planet Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<editor>8. LAMOST Chaplin et al. (seismology) Buchhave et al.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>high-res spec</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">T eff and log(g) distribution for the LAMOST/LASP and two external stellar parameter calibration samples. LAMOST stars in the Kepler field are shown in black dots, the asteroseismology sample [39] in red solid circles and the high-resolution spectroscopic sample [38] in blue open circles. The sample used in this work has log(g) larger than 4</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Fig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>S3</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>which is shown in black dashed line</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
