<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:14+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Coronagraphic phase diversity: performance study and laboratory demonstration</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013-03-01">1 Mar 2013 August 13, 2018 Preprint online version: March 1, 2013</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Sauvage</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Onera -The French Aerospace Lab</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-92322</postCode>
									<settlement>Chatillon</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">Groupement d&apos;intérêt scientifique PHASE (Partenariat Haute résolution Angulaire Sol et Espace) between Onera</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille and Institut de Planétologie et d&apos;Astrophysique de Grenoble</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Observatoire de Paris</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Université Diderot</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Coronagraphic phase diversity: performance study and laboratory demonstration</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2013-03-01">1 Mar 2013 August 13, 2018 Preprint online version: March 1, 2013</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. article_fin c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>instrumentation: adaptive optics</term>
					<term>instrumentation: high angular resolution</term>
					<term>techniques: image processing</term>
					<term>meth- ods: numerical</term>
					<term>methods: laboratory</term>
					<term>telescopes</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. The final performance of current and future instruments dedicated to exoplanet detection and characterization (such as SPHERE on the European Very Large Telescope, GPI on Gemini North, or future instruments on Extremely Large Telescopes) is limited by uncorrected quasi-static aberrations. These aberrations create long-lived speckles in the scientific image plane, which can easily be mistaken for planets. Aims. Common adaptive optics systems require dedicated components to perform wave-front analysis. The ultimate wave-front measurement performance is thus limited by the unavoidable differential aberrations between the wavefront sensor and the scientific camera. To reach the level of detectivity required by high-contrast imaging, these differential aberrations must be estimated and compensated for. In this paper, we characterize and experimentally validate a wave-front sensing method that relies on focal-plane data. Methods. Our method, called COFFEE (for COronagraphic Focal-plane wave-Front Estimation for Exoplanet detection), is based on a Bayesian approach, and it consists in an extension of phase diversity to high-contrast imaging. It estimates the differential aberrations using only two focal-plane coronagraphic images recorded from the scientific camera itself. Results. We first present a thorough characterization of COFFEE&apos;s performance by means of numerical simulations. This characterization is then compared with an experimental validation of COFFEE using an in-house adaptive optics bench and an apodized Roddier &amp; Roddier phase mask coronagraph. An excellent match between experimental results and the theoretical study is found. Lastly, we present a preliminary validation of COFFEE&apos;s ability to compensate for the aberrations upstream of a coronagraph.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Exoplanet imaging is one of the main challenges in today's astronomy. A direct observation of these planets can provide information on both the chemical composition of their atmospheres and their temperatures. Such observations have recently been made possible ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kalas et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Marois et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Lagrange et al. 2009</ref>), but only thanks to their high mass or their wide apparent distance from their host star. Being able to image an object as faint as an extra-solar planet very close to its parent star requires the use of extreme AO (XAO) systems coupled to a high-contrast imaging technique, such as coronagraphy. Instruments dedicated to exoplanet imaging using these two techniques (SPHERE on the VLT, ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Beuzit et al. 2007</ref>), GPI on Gemini North, ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Macintosh et al. 2008)</ref>) are currently being integrated. The performance of such systems is limited by residual speckles on the detector. These speckles, which originate in quasi-static non common path aberrations (NCPA), strongly decrease the extinction provided by the coronagraph and can be difficult to distinguish from an exoplanet. To achieve the ultimate system performance, these aberrations must be measured and compensated for. The current-generation instruments, SPHERE and GPI, respectively rely on phase diversity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Gonsalvez 1982)</ref> and an interferometry approach ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Wallace et al. 2010</ref>) to compensate for these NCPA. Several techniques dedicated to high-contrast imaging system optimization have been proposed for future systems. Some of them rely on a dedicated wave-front sensing hardware ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Guyon et al. 2009</ref>), others use scientific focal plane data assuming small aberrations. Speckle nulling iterative techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bordé &amp; Traub 2006</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Give'on et al. 2007</ref>) estimate the electric field in the detector plane using at least three images. The technique proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baudoz et al. (2006)</ref> relies on a modification of the imaging system, but requires only one image. These techniques aim at minimizing the energy in a chosen area ("Dark Hole"), leading to a contrast optimization on the detector ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Trauger et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baudoz et al. 2012</ref>) in a closed loop process. We have recently proposed a focal-plane wave-front sensor, COFFEE ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Sauvage et al. 2012)</ref>, which is an extension of conventional phase diversity ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Mugnier et al. 2006</ref>) to a coronagraphic system. Since COFFEE uses focal-plane images, it is possible to characterize the whole bench without any differential aberration. This method requires only two focal-plane images to estimate the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph without any modification of the coronagraphic imaging system or assuming small aberrations. COFFEE's principle and its application to the apodized Roddier &amp; Roddier phase mask (ARPM) are described in Section 2. In Section 3, we evaluate the quality of NCPA estimation by realistic simulations. In Section 4, we present the experimental results from the laboratory demonstration of COFFEE on an in-house adaptive optics bench (BOA) with an ARPM. Section 5 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">COFFEE: principle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Extension of phase diversity to coronagraphic images</head><p>Figure 1 describes the coronagraphic imaging scheme considered in this paper. We consider four successive planes denoted A (circular entrance pupil of diameter D u ), B (coronagraphic focal plane), C (Lyot Stop), and D (detector plane). The optical aberrations are considered as static and introduced in the pupil planes A and C. The coronagraphic device is composed of a focal plane mask located in plane B and a Lyot Stop situated in plane C. No particular assumption is made on the pupil shape or intensity. Thus, the description of COFFEE is compatible with several coronagraphic devices. COFFEE uses two images, i f c and i d c , recorded on the detector (plane D in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>) that, as in phase diversity, differ from a known aberration, φ div , to estimate aberrations both upstream (φ u ) and downstream (φ d ) of the coronagraph.</p><p>Considering the calibration of the instrument with an unresolved object, we use the following imaging model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i foc c = α.h det ⋆ h c (φ u , φ d ) + n foc + β i div c = α.h det ⋆ h c (φ u + φ div , φ d ) + n div + β (1)</formula><p>where α is the incoming flux, h c the coronagraphic "point spread function" (PSF) of the instrument (i.e. the response of a coronagraphic imaging system to a point source), h det the known detector PSF, n foc and n div are the measurement noises, β is a uniform background (offset), and ⋆ denotes the discrete convolution operation. Such an imaging model can be used for any coronagraphic PSF expression h c . The measurement noises n foc and n div comprise both photon and detector noises. Because calibration is assumed to be performed with high flux levels, we adopt a nonstationary white Gaussian model, which is a good approximation of a mix of photon and detector noises. Its variance is the sum of the photon and detector noise variances: <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Mugnier et al. 2004</ref>), with t the pixel position in the detector plane. The former can be estimated as the image itself thresholded to positive values, and the latter can be calibrated prior to the observations. We adopt a maximum a posteriori (MAP) approach and estimate the aberrations φ u and φ d , the flux α, and the background β that minimize the neg-log-likelihood of the data, potentially penalized by regularization terms on φ u and φ d designed to enforce smoothness of the sought phases:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">σ 2 n [t] = σ 2 ph [t] + σ 2 det (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">(ˆ α, ˆ β, ˆ φ u , ˆ φ d ) = arg min α,β,φ u ,φ d J(α, β, φ u , φ d )<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">J(α, β, φ u , φ d ) = 1 2 i foc c − (α.h d ⋆ h c (φ u , φ d ) + β) σ foc n 2 + 1 2 i div c − (α.h d ⋆ h c (φ u + φ div , φ d ) + β) σ div n 2 + R(φ u ) + R(φ d )<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where x 2 denotes the sum of squared pixel values of map x, σ foc n , and σ div n are the noise standard deviation maps of each image, and R is a regularization metric for the phase. Any aberration φ is expanded on a basis {Z k } that is typically either Zernike polynomials or the pixel indicator functions in the corresponding pupil plane: φ = k a k Z k where the summation is, in practice, limited to the number of coefficients considered sufficient to correctly describe the aberrations. In this paper, the phase is expanded on a truncated Zernike basis. The impact of using a regularization metric with such a basis is studied later in this paper. In the MAP framework, the regularization metrics R(φ u ) and R(φ d ) are deduced from the assumed a priori statistics of φ u and φ d . Assuming these aberrations are zero-mean, Gaussian, and neglecting a priori correlations between Zernike modes, we obtain, for an estimation performed on N Zernike modes: = a div 5 = 80 nm RMS, introduced upstream of the coronagraph. We therefore use this diversity phase in the following.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">R(φ x ) = 1 2 a t x R −1 ax a x = 1 2 N k=1 a 2 x k σ 2 x k ,<label>(4)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Coronagraphic imaging model</head><p>The imaging model used by COFFEE in the criterion minimization (equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(3)</ref>) requires a coronagraphic PSF expression. In this paper, we use the analytical coronagraphic imaging model developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sauvage et al. (2010)</ref>, whose formalism is developed in this section, where r is the pupil plane position vector, r its modulus, and γ the focal plane position vector. The entrance pupil function P u (r) is such that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">P u (r) = Π 2r D u Φ(r)<label>(5)</label></formula><p>with Π 2r Du = 1 for r ≤ Du 2 , pupil entrance diameter, 0 otherwise, and Φ is an apodization function. In this paper, Article number, page 2 of 11 B. Paul et al.: Coronagraphic phase diversity: performance study and laboratory demonstration we consider that the impact of amplitude aberrations is negligible, which is a reasonable assumption for a ground-based, highcontrast imaging system such as SPHERE. Considering only static aberrations (no residual turbulent aberrations), the electric field Ψ A in the entrance pupil plane can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Ψ A (r) = P u (r)e jφ u (r) ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The field amplitude Ψ B (γ) in plane B can be calculated, following <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sauvage et al. (2010)</ref>, using the analytical coronagraphic imaging model (which is called "perfect coronagraph model" hereafter):</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Ψ B (γ) = FT −1 (Ψ A (r)) − η 0 FT −1 (P u (r)),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where η 0 is the scalar that minimizes the outcoming energy from focal plane B, whose analytical value is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">η 0 = 1 N S Ψ * A (r)P u (r)dr,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">N = S P * u (r)P u (r)dr.<label>(9)</label></formula><p>It is worthy mentioning that η 0 is the exact definition of the instantaneous Strehl ratio given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Born &amp; Wolf (1989)</ref>. One can notice that η 0 = 1 when there is no aberration upstream of the coronagraph (φ u (r) = 0), so that Ψ B = 0 in such a case. No aberration in the entrance pupil leads to no outcoming energy from plane B, and thus to a perfect extinction in the detector plane D. Propagating the wave from plane B (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>) to plane D, we can write the electric field Ψ D (γ) in the detector plane:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Ψ D (γ) =FT −1 P d (r)e j(φ u (r)+φ d (r)) − η 0 FT −1 P d (r)e jφ d (r) ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where P d (r) is the Lyot stop pupil function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">P d (r) = Π 2r D d P u (r), with D d the Lyot stop pupil diameter (D d ≤ D u ).</formula><p>For the sake of simplicity, we omit the spatial variables r and γ in the following. The coronagraphic PSF of the instrument, denoted by h c , is the square modulus of Ψ D :</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">h c (φ u , φ d ) = FT −1 (P d e j(φ u +φ d ) ) − η 0 FT −1 (P d e jφ d ) 2 .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>In this paper, this expression of the coronagraphic PSF is the one used by COFFEE for estimating φ u and φ d ; i.e., Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">(11)</ref> is inserted into the imaging model (Eq. (1)) used in the criterion minimization described in Eq. (3). As described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sauvage et al. (2010)</ref>, this model, which analytically describes the impact of a coronagraph in an imaging system, considers that the coronagraph removes the projection of the incoming electric field on an Airy pattern, represented by the parameter η 0 (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(8)</ref>). Since it does not assume small aberrations, it can be used for any wave-front error upstream of the coronagraph. The quality of the fit of this analytical imaging model with the ARPM coronagraph is discussed later in this paper (Section 3.5). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Performance assessment by numerical simulation</head><p>The aim of this section is to quantify the impact of each error source on COFFEE's aberration estimation. Such a study will show COFFEE's sensitivity to the classical error sources that limit the phase retrieval in a real system (and thus the final extinction of the coronagraph), which will be of high interest in defining COFFEE's upgrades. Likewise, it will allow us to estimate the accuracy level expected on our AO bench. In this section, we present the evolution of this reconstruction error with respect to the incoming flux (Section 3.1), to the size of the source (Section 3.2), to an error made on the assumed diversity phase used in the reconstruction (Section 3.3), and to the number of Zernike modes used in the reconstruction (Section 3.4).</p><p>For each error source, coronagraphic images will be computed using the imaging model presented in Eq. (1), using the perfect coronagraph model to calculate the coronagraphic PSF h c whose expression is given Eq. (11). COFFEE will then perform the phase estimation using these two images. The compatibility of COFFEE with realistic coronagraphic images will be studied as well (Section 3.5) by computing coronagraphic images using a realistic coronagraph model and then running COFFEE to estimate the aberrations both upstream and downstream of the coronagraph. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> gathers the parameters used for these simulations.</p><p>The chosen wave-front error (WFE) values upstream and downstream of the coronagraph for these simulations are typical of the aberrations that will be estimated on our AO bench in Section 4 (so that experimental results can be compared to the following simulations). Since these simulations are performed with a small number of Zernike modes (36), there is no need of regularization metrics in such simulations. To simulate realistic aberrations, we have considered that the variance per Zernike mode σ 2 k was decreasing with the radial order n(k) of the considered Zernike mode k (Noll 1976):</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">σ 2 k ∝ 1 n(k) 2 .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>This corresponds to a decrease in the static aberration spatial spectrum as 1 |ν| 2 , where ν is the spatial frequency, which is a common assumption for mirror fabrication errors. To evaluate COFFEE's performance, we define the reconstruction error ǫ x </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">ǫ = N −1 k=2 |a k − ˆ a k | 2<label>(13)</label></formula><p>with a k the Zernike coefficients (starting with k = 2 corresponding to tilt) used for the simulation, ˆ a k the reconstructed Zernike coefficients, and N the number of Zernike modes. In this section, every reconstruction error value is an average value, computed from ten independent simulated phases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Noise propagation</head><p>The ultimate limitation of an instrument lies in the amount of noise in the images. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>, we present the reconstruction error for the aberrations upstream (φ u ) and downstream (φ d ) of the coronagraph with respect to the total incoming flux. Photon noise and detector noise (σ det = 6 e − ) are added in the coronagraphic images for simulation.</p><p>The evolution of the reconstruction error presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig- ure 2</ref> is proportional to (1/α) for the detector noise limited regime (low flux) and to (1/ √ α) for the photon noise limited regime (high flux). In this figure, it can be seen that for an incoming flux α ≥ 10 6 photons, the reconstruction error ǫ u for the phase upstream of the coronagraph is smaller than 1 nm RMS. Thus, in a calibration process, where high values of flux (≥ 10 6 photons) can be easily reached, COFFEE's performance will not be significantly affected by noise. It is noteworthy that the results of many similar simulations with various levels of upstream aberrations show that COFFEE's reconstruction error does not depend on the amplitude of the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph, as long as the diversity phase amplitude is larger than the WFE of the aberrations to be estimated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Impact of the source size on the reconstruction error</head><p>Our imaging model, presented in Section 2.1 (Eq. 1), assumes an unresolved object. Thus, the presence of a real source with a given spatial extension will have an impact on the phase reconstruction, which is quantified here. We consider here a Gaussianshaped laser source, emitted from a single-mode fiber. Because of the incoming light coherence, it can be represented as a Gaussian amplitude in the entrance pupil plane (where COFFEE assumes a uniform amplitude). Knowing this, coronagraphic images are simulated by considering a small coherent Gaussianshaped beam (FWHM ≤ 0.5 λ D ) on the coronagraph, and then processed by COFFEE.</p><p>Since the imaging model assumes an unresolved object, both reconstruction errors for the phases upstream and downstream of the coronagraph increase with the FWHM of the coherent object, as showed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>, but remains low: for an FWHM smaller than λ 3D , the reconstruction error is indeed sub-nanometric. The size of the laser source will thus definitely not be a limitation for COFFEE: if this error is not negligible in the total error budget, it is possible to include it in the imaging model used by COFFEE (Eq. 1) as a non-uniform (Gaussian) entrance pupil function P u (r).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Sensitivity to a diversity phase error</head><p>The diversity phase φ div = a div 4 Z 4 + a div 5 Z 5 has been defined in Section 2.1. This phase φ div is one of the inputs that COFFEE needs in order to perform phase retrieval, so it must be calibrated as accurately as possible. To optimize the use of COFFEE, the impact of an error on such a calibration is studied. In this section, we consider that the diversity phase used to create the diversity image is not perfectly known. The coronagraphic simulated diversity image is computed with a diversity phase φ ′ div = φ div + φ err , with φ err a randomly generated phase of given RMS value, and COFFEE's phase reconstruction is done considering that the diversity phase is equal to φ div . In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, we see that the reconstruction error increases linearly with the calibration error on the diversity phase, with a slope of 0.5. Thus, the requirement on the calibration precision for the diversity phase is typically the precision wanted for the aberration measurement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Impact of aliasing</head><p>The phase estimation is performed here on a truncated Zernike basis. In real images (recorded from a bench), some speckles will originate in high-order aberrations. These aberrations, which cannot be fitted by the truncated Zernike basis, will have an impact on the phase estimation, called aliasing error hereafter. Thus, it is necessary to study this aliasing error as a function of the number of Zernike modes used in the phase reconstruction. Here, we generate a phase on a large number of Zernike modes, and compute the corresponding images using the perfect coronagraph model. Aberrations both upstream and downstream of the coronagraph are then estimated by COFFEE using an increasing number of Zernike modes. Since one of the aims of this simulation is to determine the size of the truncated Zernike basis to be used with experimental data recorded on an in-house bench, the noise level in the simulated images corresponds to the one we have on this bench. The total incoming flux is 5 10 6 photons, and the detector noise is σ det = 1 e − per pixel. Parameters used for this simulation are gathered in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. This simulation has been done with and without a regularization metric, so that we can demonstrate the relevance of this metric on phase estimation. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> presents the evolution of the reconstruction errors when the number of reconstructed Zernike modes increases. Here, every reconstruction error (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(13)</ref>) is calculated on a basis of 350 Zernike modes; thus, the error originates both in high-order aberrations, which are not considered by COFFEE because of the Zernike basis finite size (modelling error), and in the impact of these high-order aberrations on the estimated ones (aliasing). The WFE corresponding to the aberrations that are   <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>) is called "unmodelled WFE" hereafter.</p><note type="other">Zernike basis used for φ u and φ d simulation 350 Zernike polynomials Incoming flux 5 10 6 photons noise photon noise, detector noise (σ det = 1 e − ) COFFEE: phase estimation Zernike basis used for φ u and φ d reconstruction from 15 to 275 Zernike polynomials Regularization metric With and without</note><p>In the plot of the reconstruction error upstream of the coronagraph evolution ( <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, top), one can see that without a regularization metric, the reconstruction error increases for a large number of Zernike modes. An interpretation of this behaviour is the following: because high-order aberrations have a smaller variance, their associated speckle intensity is lower. Thus, owing to the photon and detector noise in the image, the SNR is smaller for these aberrations. Such behaviour leads to a trade-off between aliasing and noise amplification for the optimal number of Zernike modes ( <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>). The best number of Zernike modes is then a function of the aberrations level (WFE) and spectrum, as well as of the level of noise. The use of a regularization metric allows us to avoid this noise amplification ( <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>): the reconstruction error roughly reaches a saturation level (rather than growing to very high values). Additionally, the use of regularization reduces the aliasing error, and avoids the need for the difficult and somewhat ad hoc choice of number of Zernike modes for the reconstruction. According to the results presented in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, we have chosen to estimate the aberrations upstream and downstream of the coronagraph on 170 Zernike modes with the regularization metric of Eq. (4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Model mismatch</head><p>We have already demonstrated that ARPM images are compatible with the perfect coronagraph model and therefore with COFFEE estimation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Sauvage et al. (2012</ref>  is very close), there is a model mismatch in the estimation of aberrations upstream of the coronagraph φ u , which varies linearly with the WFE of φ u , as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. The model mismatch can thus be quantified as 7.5% of the WFE RMS value of φ u , except for very small WFE (≤ 1 nm RMS), where the variation is non-linear, but remains below 1 nm RMS.</p><p>Since the variation in this model mismatch varies linearly with the WFE of φ u , it should not limit the ability to compensate for the aberration upstream of an ARPM using COFFEE as focal plane wave-front sensor (WFS).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Laboratory demonstration</head><p>In this section we present experimental validations in the coronagraphic phase diversity. These validations are done on the bench BOA, described in Section 4.1. Section 4.2 describes a carefully designed method developed to introduce calibrated static aberrations on the AO bench to be measured with COFFEE. The error made on the measurements of aberrations upstream of the coronagraph (NCPA) is quantified in Section 4.3. Section 4.4 presents the static aberration measurement performance, and Section 4.5 details the procedure for compensating for the measured aberrations. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the design of our in-house bench. The input beam, emitted from a fibered laser source (λ = 635 nm) comes through the prolate apodizer Φ, which is in the entrance pupil plane (P u ). The beam is reflected by the tip-tilt mirror (TTM) and then by the deformable mirror (DM, entrance pupil, D u = 40 mm, 6 × 6 actuators). The beam-splitter sends a fraction of the beam to the AO wave-front sensor (Shack-Hartmann, 5 × 5 sub-apertures). On the other channel, the light is focused onto a RRPM, whose diameter is d c = 18.1 µm (angular diameter is 1.06 λ Du ). After going through the Lyot stop plane (P d , with D d = 0.99D u ), the beam is focused onto the camera (256 × 256 pixels images with an oversampling of 2.75, detector noise σ det = 1 e − ). For faster computations, recorded images are rebinned to 128 × 128 pixels images with an oversampling of 1.38.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Experimental setup</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Introduction of calibrated aberrations</head><p>To evaluate COFFEE's performance, we introduce calibrated aberrations on the bench using a process described in this section. We consider an aberration phase φ cal to be introduced on BOA. First, since the phase is represented by the DM with a finite number of actuators (6 × 6), the introduced aberration will not match the aberration φ cal perfectly, as illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> in the case of a pure spherical aberration.</p><p>Our aim is here to introduce, using the DM, the closest aberration to the aberration φ cal . We let F be the DM influence matrix (obtained by calibration); any DM introduced aberration φ DM can be described as a set of actuator voltages u (φ DM = F u). We are thus looking for the set u cal which solves the least-squares problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">u cal = arg min u F u − φ cal 2 .<label>(14)</label></formula><p>The solution of this problem can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">u cal = T φ cal ,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>with T the generalized inverse of matrix F . Using the interaction matrix D (resulting from calibration), we can compute the corresponding set of slopes s cal (s cal = Du cal ), which can then be used to modify the AO loop reference slopes s ref . Thus, closing the AO loop with the reference slopes s ref + s cal , we introduce an aberration φ DM cal = F u cal = F T φ cal on the bench, which is the best fit of φ cal in the least squares sense. We also have to consider that the bench BOA presents its own unknown static aberrations φ BOA u and φ BOA d upstream and downstream of the coronagraph (respectively). Thus, if a calibrated aberration φ cal is introduced in the entrance pupil, aberrations φ u upstream of the coronagraph will be</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">φ u = φ cal + φ BOA u .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>To get rid of the unknown aberration φ BOA u , we perform a differential phase estimation:</p><p>1. We introduce the aberration φ DM cal on the bench. A phasêphasê φ</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">+ u = ˆ φ DM cal + ˆ φ BOA u</formula><p>is estimated using focused and diverse images recorded on the camera. 2. The opposite aberration −φ DM cal is then introduced. A phasêphasê φ</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">− u = − ˆ φ DM cal + ˆ φ BOA u is estimated. 3. The half differencê φ DM cal = ˆ φ + u − ˆ φ − u 2</formula><p>is our estimate of φ cal .</p><p>The first use of this process is to calibrate the diversity phase itself. Since this phase will be introduced using the AO system, the actually introduced diversity phase will not exactly match the theoretical mix of defocus and astigmatism. We introduce the aberrations φ div and −φ div on the bench using the AO system. These two aberrations are then estimated using classical phase diversity (no coronagraph), with a pure defocus of diversity phase introduced using a flat glass plate of known thickness e in a focused beam. Such a process gives us an accurate estimation of the diversity phase really introduced on the bench, with an estimated accuracy of 4 nm RMS on the introduced aberration. This calibration is then used in COFFEE's estimations performed on experimental images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Performance assessment: error budget</head><p>From simulations presented in Section 3, we establish an error budget for estimating aberrations upstream of the coronagraph using experimental data:</p><p>⋄ Photon and detector noise error: on the BOA bench, the typical incoming flux is f BOA = 5 10 6 photons. Knowing that we have photon noise and a detector noise with σ det = 1 e − , we can evaluate the noise error: ǫ noise = 0.9 nm RMS. ⋄ The diversity phase φ div has been calibrated using classical phase diversity, using the process presented in Section 4.2. Such an estimation has been performed with an error of 4.0 nm RMS (value calculated from an error budget evaluated for a classical phase diversity estimation on the BOA bench. Such accuracy has already been obtained on this bench by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sauvage et al. (2007)</ref>). According to Section 3.3, this error on the diversity phase leads to an error ǫ model = 2.0 nm RMS. ⋄ The source is a coherent Gaussian-shaped beam whose FWHM is 0.27 λ D on the coronagraph. According to the simulations of Section 3.2, this leads to a reconstruction error: ǫ obj = 0.7 nm RMS. ⋄ Residual turbulent speckles, which originate in uncorrected turbulent aberrations, are not included in the imaging model. To measure the impact of these speckle on the reconstruction, several wave-fronts have been successively recorded using a commercial Shack-Hartmann wave-front sensor. From these acquisitions, we calculate the WFE of the residual turbulent phase: σ φturb = 1.2 nm RMS. This residual turbulence will create speckles on the detector, which will be considered by COFFEE as originating in NCPA. Thus, the residual turbulence error ǫ turb made by COFFEE is estimated to ǫ turb = σ φturb = 1.2 nm RMS. ⋄ Aliasing error, which originates in high-order aberrations, has been studied in Section 3.4. For a phase upstream of the coronagraph estimated on N = 170 Zernike modes, we have ǫ aliasing = 18.3 nm RMS. ⋄ From simulations, we know that the model mismatch is 7.5%</p><p>of WFE. For this study, we will not estimate aberrations with a WFE stronger than 80 nm RMS. For such a WFE, the model error is ǫ model = 6.0 nm RMS.</p><p>As one can see in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>, the error budget is mainly driven by the aliasing error. The second most important term is the model mismatch (even though it goes to zero with the WFE).  <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>. COFFEE: error budget for the estimation of an aberration upstream of the coronagraph on BOA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Measurement of aberrations upstream of the coronagraph</head><p>In this section, we introduce calibrated aberrations on the BOA bench upstream of the coronagraph, and then estimate them with COFFEE in order to evaluate its performance. In the course of this study, we realized that the position of the coronagraphic image on the detector (quantified by the tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph) is a critical issue. Indeed, it occurred that COFFEE was able to perform phase retrieval only for downstream tip-tilt</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">[a 2 , a 3 ] values within the range [−100 nm RMS; 100 nm RMS] ([− λ 6D ; λ 6D ])</formula><p>. To get rid of this constraint, we have developed a method to perform a preliminary estimation of the tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph. This method, which uses the diversity image, is fully described in Appendix B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1.">Measurement of tip-tilt upstream of the coronagraph</head><p>We present the estimation of a tilt aberration upstream of the coronagraph using COFFEE in this section. Using the AO system, we introduce a tilt aberration by adding a constant value δs TT to the AO wave-front sensor references slopes s ref , and then closing the AO loop on the slopes s ref + δs TT . To accurately calibrate the introduced tilt, for each position, we first estimate the aberrations using classical phase diversity (no coronagraph). Then, the RRPM is put in the focal plane, and the same operation is repeated: for each position, we record two images, and then estimate the aberrations using COFFEE.</p><p>From the upstream tilt reconstruction performed by COF-FEE <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Figure 9</ref>), we calculate an average reconstruction error: ǫ tilt = 2.1 nm. Part of this error is due to an error on the estimation of tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph. An improved estimation has been performed by setting boundaries on the downstream tip-tilt. Its value is evaluated before COFFEE's estimation using the method described in appendix B with the diversity coronagraphic image recorded for a tip-tilt upstream the coronagraph value close to 0 nm RMS (centered coronagraph). Such an estimation process gives us an estimation of tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph {a do 2 , a do 3 } with an accuracy of ±1.5 nm RMS. Using this estimation as the starting value for the minimization, and setting bounds of ±1.5 nm RMS on it, we processed the same experimental data. This, in turn, results in a better estimation of tilt upstream of the coronagraph <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Figure 9)</ref>, with an average error ǫ tilt = 1.5 nm, which is close to the expected error per Zernike mode given in Section 4.3 (ǫ ′ = 1.6 nm RMS). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2.">NCPA measurements</head><p>In this section, we introduce aberrations upstream of the coronagraph. The aberration φ cal is expanded on the first 15 Zernike modes (which is the largest number of modes we can properly describe with our 6×6 DM ), and then we estimate these aberrations using COFFEE, following the process described in Section 4.2. To take the DM action into account on the introduced phase (illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>), aberrations φ cal are first estimated with classical phase diversity (no phase mask in the coronagraphic focal plane ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sauvage et al. 2007)</ref>). This estimation gives us a calibration of the introduced aberration, which is then used to evaluate the accuracy of COFFEE's estimation.</p><p>At convergence of the reconstruction, a very good match can be observed between the experimental images and the ones computed for the estimated aberrations ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10, top and middle)</ref>. This, in turn, results in a very good match between the aberrations measured by COFFEE <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 10, right)</ref> and the introduced ones <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 10, left)</ref>. From the experimental phase estimation presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>, we compute a reconstruction error between the classical diversity phase calibrated aberration and COFFEE's estimation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">ǫ exp = 22.5 nm RMS.<label>(17)</label></formula><p>One can notice that this error is close to the expected error budget, i.e. that there is a good match between the performance assessment study carried out in Section 3 and the experimental results presented in this section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Low-order NCPA compensation</head><p>Lastly, the ability of COFFEE to compensate for the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph is experimented on BOA. In Section 4.4, the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph are expanded on 170 Zernike modes, in order to have the smallest reconstruction error (according to Section 3.4  Zernike modes: the aliasing error, which is the most important error source, will mainly degrade the estimation accuracy of the reconstructed high orders (close to Z 36 ). To demonstrate the ability of COFFEE to be used in a closed loop, we introduce a set of aberrations on the DM by modifying the reference slopes, as described in Section 4.2. Then, we use the pseudo-closed loop (PCL) method described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sauvage et al. (2007)</ref>. This iterative process has two stages: for the PCL iteration i: The computation time (step 2) varies from 1 minute to 2.5 minutes, allowing us to compensate for quasi-static aberrations upstream of the coronagraph. This compensation process is limited by the estimation accuracy of the first 15 Zernike modes performed by COFFEE, which corresponds to the error budget established in Section 4.3), and by the ability of the DM to reproduce a given wave-front. Indeed, the correction introduced on the bench (step 2 of the PCL process) is the best fit of the estimated phasê φ i u in the least-square sense (as presented in Section 4.2). The difference between the estimated aberration and the actual introduced correction will thus limit the compensation performance of the PCL process. Considering these two limitations, one can compute the variance σ 2 BOA (for the first 15 Zernike modes) that can be reached on the BOA bench:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">σ 2 BOA = 4.4 10 −2 rad RMS 2 .<label>(18)</label></formula><p>The correction and stabilization of the NCPA variance can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. One can see that the variance of the 15 corrected Zernike modes reaches the expected asymptotic value σ 2</p><p>BOA . This result is the very first demonstration of COFFEE's ability to compensate for aberrations upstream of the coronagraph. A compensation at levels compatible with SPHERE or GPI-like instruments will require th using a DM with many more actuators, and working on the reduction of the dominant term of the error budget, which is aliasing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, we have presented a thorough simulation study (Section 3) and a first experimental validation (Section 4) of the coronagraphic wave-front sensor called COFFEE, which consists mainly in the extension of the phase diversity concept to a coronagraphic imaging system. From the validation and careful performance assessment of COFFEE, we showed that COFFEE is currently limited by the aliasing error, due to high-order aberrations, which are difficult to model with a Zernike basis. In Section 4, we presented a first experimental validation of COFFEE using an ARPM. We introduced calibrated aberrations upstream of the coronagraph (NCPA), using the AO sub-system, and estimated them with COFFEE. The accuracy we obtained on these estimation shows a very good match with our error budget. Lastly, we used COFFEE in an iterative process to perform a preliminary validation of COFFEE's ability to compensate for the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph. Several perspectives are currently considered to optimize COF-FEE: firstly, in order to minimize the impact of the aliasing error on the phase reconstruction, we plan to perform the phase reconstruction on a pixel-wise map, which is more suitable than a truncated Zernike basis. Secondly, we would like to improve the imaging model, both to make COFFEE work with other coronagraph than the ARPM and to reduce the model error, which is currently the second most important one, even though it goes to zero with the WFE. Two solutions are considered. In the absence of residual turbulence, an accurate imaging model is obtained by propagating the electric field through each plane of the coronagraphic imaging system <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>) for an arbitrary focal plane coronagraphic mask. Such a method, where no model error needs to be considered, can be used for a laboratory calibration. Alternatively, a more accurate analytical imaging model, which could include a residual turbulent aberration, can be developed. Such a model, which could include a residual turbulent aberration, will ultimately allow us to perform NCPA estimation on images from the sky. These improvements should allow us to estimate and compensate for the aberrations upstream of the coronagraph using COFFEE with a nanometric precision in a closed loop process. A further perspective is to extend COFFEE to phase and amplitude aberration estimation, in order to create a dark hole region in the coronagraphic image.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Coronagraphic imaging instrument: principle</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Aberrations upstream (φ u (WFE = 80 nm), top) and downstream (φ d (WFE = 20 nm), bottom) of the coronagraph: reconstruction error (solid red line) as a function of the incoming flux α. For comparison, 1 α (cyan dashed line) and 1 √ α (magenta dashed line) theoretical behaviours are plotted for detector noise only and photon noise only (respectively).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Error reconstructions upstream (red line) and downstream (blue line) of the coronagraph as functions of the size of the source on the coronagraph.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Error reconstructions upstream (solid red line) and downstream (solid blue line) of the coronagraph as functions of the error on the diversity phase.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .FiberedFig. 7 .</head><label>567</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Error reconstructions upstream (top) and downstream (bottom) of the coronagraph as functions of the number of reconstructed Zernike modes, with a regularization metric (solid blue line) and without (solid red line)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Estimation of a tilt aberration on BOA: calibration (solid blue line) and COFFEE's estimation with bound on the tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph (dashed crossed red line) and without boundaries (dashed diamond green line)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. COFFEE: NCPA estimation of an introduced phase φ cal on BOA. Top: for an aberration +φ cal , recorded coronagraphic image from the bench (left) and computed image using the reconstructed aberrationˆφrationˆ rationˆφ + u (right) (log. scale, same range for both images). Middle: same images for an aberration −φ cal introduced and a reconstructed aberrationˆφaberrationˆ aberrationˆφ − u (log. scale, same range for both images). Bottom: calibrated introduced aberration (left) and COFFEE estimated aberration (right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>1</head><label></label><figDesc>. acquisition of the focused i f c and diverse i f d images; 2. estimation of the aberrationˆφaberrationˆ aberrationˆφ i u upstream of the coronagraph; 3. computation of the corresponding reference slopes correc- tion δs = gDTˆφgDTˆ gDTˆφ i u , where D and T are the interaction and influence matrices defined in Section 4.2 and g is the PCL gain; 4. the AO loop is closed on the modified reference slopes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. PCL on the bench BOA (gPCL = 0.5): variance of the residual static aberrations upstream of the coronagraph for the 36 COFFEE estimated Zernike modes (solid red line) and the 15 corrected modes (solid blue line). The magenta dashed line represents the ultimate performance one can reach according to the error budget detailed in 4.3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>COFFEE: simulation parameters for studying the aliasing er-
ror. 

not estimated by COFFEE (from N to 350, where N varies be-
tween 15 and 275 according to </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A: Implementation details</head><p>COFFEE performs a phase estimation by minimizing a criterion J whose expression is given by equation 3. To estimate φ u and φ d (expanded on a truncated Zernike basis), we need both gradients ∂J ∂au and ∂J ∂a d</p><p>, where a x = {a x1 , a x2 , ..., a xN } is a vector that contains the Zernike coefficients, for an aberration expanded on N Zernike modes (x is for u (upstream) or d (downstream)). Let us write the numerical expression of J foc , using the notations defined in Section 2.1:</p><p>With t the pixel position in the detector plane. σ foc n and σ div n are the noise variance maps. Considering the expression of J, we derive J foc , and then deduce the gradients expressions of J div using a trivial substitution. Expressions of the regularization terms gradients </p><p>Then, the calculation consists in derivating the gradient of the PSF h c with respect to phases φ u <ref type="bibr">[k]</ref> and φ d <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> at pixels k, l in pupils upstream and downstream of the coronagraph, respectively, and applying the chain rule, as already done in a noncoronagraphic case, e.g. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Thiébaut &amp; Conan (1995)</ref>. The calculation of both gradients ∂J foc ∂φ u <ref type="bibr">[k]</ref> and ∂J foc ∂φ d <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> gives</p><p>(A.5)</p><p>With ℑ and ℜ the imaginary and real part (respectively), and</p><p>Since the phases are expanded on a Zernike basis, we need the gradients of J foc with respect to the Zernike coefficients a xi of phase φ x . These gradients are given by the expression <ref type="bibr">(Mug- nier et al. 2001)</ref>:</p><p>Flux α and constant background β are also analytically estimated during the minimization, considering that</p><p>Where p is for "foc" (focused) or "div" (diverse). For the sake of simplicity, we shall omit the variable t. We have</p><p>Which gives us, in a matricial form:</p><p>(A.10)</p><p>A simple matrix inversion gives us the analytical estimation of the flux α and the background β for each iteration. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix B: Tip-tilt estimation downstream of the coronagraph</head><p>The tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph (which represents the image position on the detector) strongly limits COFFEE's performance. Indeed, we determine that the phase estimation was accurate when −100 nm RMS ≤ a i ≤ 100 nm RMS, with a i the Zernike coefficient for tip or tilt (i ∈ {2, 3}). Beyond this range, COFFEE is unable to properly estimate both phases φ u and φ d . Such a phenomenon strongly limits COFFEE's performance on a bench, since its utilization requires a restrictive location of the PSF on the detector. To get rid of this limitation, we have developed a simple and fast method of estimating the tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph before COFFEE's estimation, based on the diversity image. This image is created by adding a known aberration</p><p>= 80 nm RMS) to φ u . Since the amplitude of this aberration is important (σ φ div = 113 nm RMS), the speckles we have in the coronagraphic diversity image mainly originate in this diversity aberration. This is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure B</ref>.1, where we show two diversity images: one computed with randomly generated phases φ u (WFE 30 nm RMS), φ d (WFE 10 nm RMS), and another computed with no aberrations other than the diversity ones.</p><p>As one can see in <ref type="figure">Figure B</ref>.1, we can clearly identify the aberrations which originate in the diversity φ div . The principle of our method lies in the research of these well-known aberrations (since we know the phase φ div we introduce) in the diversity image i d c by comparing it with a theoretical diversity image i d c th , calculated with no other aberrations than the diversity ones:</p><p>The comparison of i d c th with i d c is performed using the method developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Gratadour et al. (2005)</ref>, which consists in minimizing the following criterion J TT</p><p>Where δ is the dirac function. Minimization of J TT gives us the shift [x M , y M ]between both images. It is then possible to calculate the corresponding tip (a 2 ) and tilt (a 3 ) downstream of the coronagraph knowing the image sampling s:</p><p>Finally, these estimated tip-tilt values are given to COFFEE as an input of the minimization, and are used as initial values to begin phase reconstruction. This method performs, on our experimental images, a fast preliminary estimation (∼ 1 second for a 256 × 256 image) of the tip-tilt downstream of the coronagraph with an accuracy of 1.5 nm RMS, which is far enough, compared to the level of accuracy (±100 nm RMS) required by COFFEE.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baudoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boccaletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baudrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rouan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. IAU Colloquium</title>
		<meeting>IAU Colloquium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baudoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mazoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Galicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rousset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Groundbased and Airborn Intrusmentation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8446</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Astronomy IV</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Beuzit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Feldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dohlen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the conference In the Spirit of Bernard Lyot: The Direct Detection of Planets and Circumstellar Disks in the 21st Century</title>
		<editor>P. Kalas</editor>
		<meeting>the conference In the Spirit of Bernard Lyot: The Direct Detection of Planets and Circumstellar Disks in the 21st Century<address><addrLine>Berkeley, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">638</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of California</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Born</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of Optics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pergamon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Give&amp;apos;on</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Belikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shaklan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kasdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Opt. Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gonsalvez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Opt. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gratadour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rouan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">443</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">357</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Angel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">693</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Guyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roddier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Graves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Pub. Astron. Soc. Pacific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">332</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gratadour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Adaptive Optics Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7015</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">322</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Idier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Advances in Imaging and Electron Physics</title>
		<editor>P. Hawkes</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="76" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fusco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Conan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1841</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Conan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Michau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">862</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Noll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Numerical Recipes : the art of scientific computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Roddier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roddier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Pub. Astron. Soc. Pacific</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Sauvage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fusco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rousset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Petit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2334</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Sauvage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Villecroze</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Opt. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4808</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Sauvage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rousset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fusco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Soummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aime</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Falloon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">397</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Soummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pueyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sivaramakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vanderbei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Express</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Thiébaut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Astronomical Data Analysis II</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4847</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="183" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Thiébaut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Conan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Am. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">485</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Trauger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Give&amp;apos;on</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Tecniques and Instrumentation for Detection of Exoplanets III</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6693</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burruss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bartos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Adaptive Optics Systems II</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7736</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
