<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:18+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PLANET FORMATION IN STELLAR BINARIES I: PLANETESIMAL DYNAMICS IN MASSIVE PROTOPLANETARY DISKS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-08-21">21 Aug 2014 July 9, 2018 July 9, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roman</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rafikov</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kedron</forename><surname>Silsbee</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PLANET FORMATION IN STELLAR BINARIES I: PLANETESIMAL DYNAMICS IN MASSIVE PROTOPLANETARY DISKS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-08-21">21 Aug 2014 July 9, 2018 July 9, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Draft version Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 5/2/11 Draft version</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: planets and satellites: formation -protoplanetary disks -planetary systems - binaries: close</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>About 20% of exoplanets discovered by radial velocity surveys reside in stellar binaries. To clarify their origin one has to understand the dynamics of planetesimals in protoplanetary disks within binaries. The standard description, accounting for only gas drag and gravity of the companion star has been challenged recently, as the gravity of the protoplanetary disk was shown to play a crucial role in planetesimal dynamics. An added complication is the tendency of protoplanetary disks in binaries to become eccentric, giving rise to additional excitation of planetesimal eccentricity. Here, for the first time, we analytically explore secular dynamics of planetesimals in binaries such as α Cen and γ Cep under the combined action of (1) gravity of the eccentric protoplanetary disk, (2) perturbations due to the (coplanar) eccentric companion, and (3) gas drag. We derive explicit solutions for the behavior of planetesimal eccentricity e p in non-precessing disks (and in precessing disks in certain limits). We obtain the analytical form of the distribution of relative velocities of planetesimals, which is a key input for understanding their collisional evolution. Disk gravity strongly influences relative velocities and tends to push sizes of planetesimals colliding with comparable objects at the highest speed to small values, ∼ 1 km. We also find that planetesimals in eccentric protoplanetary disks apsidally aligned with the binary orbit collide at lower relative velocities than in mis-aligned disks. Our results highlight a decisive role that disk gravity plays in planetesimal dynamics in binaries.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PROBLEM SETUP.</head><p>Our general setup is similar to that explored in SR13. We consider an elliptical disk around a primary star in a binary with semi-major axis a b , eccentricity e b , and component masses M p (primary) and M s (secondary). We define µ ≡ M s /(M p + M s ) and ν ≡ M s /M p . Binary, disk, and planetesimal orbits within it are assumed to be coplanar. This distinguishes our work from many other studies focused on the effects of Lidov-Kozai oscillations <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Lidov 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kozai 1962</ref>) on planetesimal dynamics in systems with inclined companions ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Batygin et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Zhao et al. 2012</ref>).</p><p>Non-axisymmetric disk structure is described via the non-zero disk eccentricity, which is a viable approximation given that simulations tend to show the prevalence of m = 1 azimuthal harmonic of the disk shape distortion ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Marzari et al. 2012</ref>). Fluid elements in a disk follow elliptical trajectories with eccentricity e g (a d ) which is a function of the semi-major axis a d of a particular ellipse. All of them have the primary star of the binary as a focus. For simplicity we assume all fluid elliptical trajectories to have aligned apsidal lines, uniquely determining disk orientation via a single parameter ̟ d -the angle between the disk and binary apsidal lines. The latter is assumed to be fixed in space as the precession of the binary under the gravity of the disk is slower than all other processes.</p><p>The assumption of apsidal alignment does not affect the qualitative features of planetesimal dynamics and can be easily relaxed using the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Statler (2001)</ref>.</p><p>Because gas moves on ellipses its surface density generally varies along the trajectory <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Statler 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ogilvie 2001)</ref>. To obtain gas surface density Σ(r d , φ d ) at a point in a disk with polar coordinates (r d , φ d ) we specify gas surface density at periastron of each elliptical trajectory Σ p (a d ) as a function of semi-major axis of the corre-sponding ellipse a d . SR13 show how this and the knowledge of e g (a d ) can be used to derive Σ(r d , φ d ) everywhere in the disk. In this work, following SR13, we assume simple power law dependence for both e g and Σ p :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Σ p (a d ) = Σ 0 a out a d p , e g (a d ) = e 0 a out a d q . (1)</formula><p>where a out is the semi-major axis of the outermost elliptical trajectory of the disk, and Σ 0 and e 0 are the values of Σ p and e g at a out . Gravity of the companion truncates the disk at this outer radius a out , which for eccentric binaries with e b = 0.4 is about (0.2−0.3)a b <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Artymowicz &amp; Lubow 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Regály et al. 2011</ref>). Unless stated otherwise we will be using a out = 5 AU in this work.</p><p>In all calculations of this paper we will be using a disk model with p = 1 and q = −1. Some motivation for singling out these particular values of p and q for circumstellar disks in binaries has been provided in R13 and SR13.</p><p>The total disk mass</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M d ≈ 2π aout ain Σ p (a d )a d da d en- closed within a out can be used to express Σ p as Σ p (a d ) = 2 − p 2π M d a 2 out a out a d p (2) ≈ 3 × 10 3 g cm −2 M d,−2 a −1 out,5 a −1 d,1 , (numerical estimate is for p = 1) where M d,−2 ≡ M d /(10 −2 M ⊙ ), a out,5 ≡ a out /(5 AU) and a d,1 ≡ a d /AU.</formula><p>In equation <ref type="formula">(2)</ref> we neglected disk ellipticity and assumed p &lt; 2, so that most of the disk mass is concentrated in its outer part.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">BASIC EQUATIONS.</head><p>We are interested in the dynamics of planetesimals orbiting the primary within the disk and coplanar with it. We characterize their orbits by semi-major axis a p , eccentricity e p and the apsidal angle (w.r.t. the binary apsidal line) ̟ p . Orbital evolution of planetesimals is treated in secular approximation, i.e. neglecting shortterm gravitational perturbations <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Murray &amp; Dermott 1999</ref>). We also assume e p ≪ 1 as well as e g ≪ 1 and introduce for convenience the planetesimal eccentricity vector</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">e p = (k p , h p ) = e p (cos ̟ p , sin ̟ p ).</formula><p>In this work we fully account for gravitational perturbations due to both the binary companion and the eccentric disk using the approach advanced in SR13. For the disk properties described by equation (1) SR13 calculated an analytic expression for the planetesimal disturbing function accounting for the gravity of both disk and secondary. They then derived a set of Lagrange equations [see their equations (16)-(17)] describing the evolution of e p under the influence of gravitational forces alone.</p><p>In addition, in this work we take into account the effects of gas drag on the secular evolution of planetesimal eccentricity. Drag-induced dissipation also results in non-conservation of energy and evolution of a p . However, to zeroth order we can neglect this as the radial inspiral of planetesimals usually occurs on much longer timescale than their eccentricity evolution ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adachi et al. 1976)</ref>. As a result, we can concentrate on the behavior of e p at fixed a p and determine the relative velocities of planetesimals and their collisional outcomes.</p><p>Gas drag introduces additional terms in the eccentricity evolution equations of SR13, which we re-write in the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">dh p dt = Ak p + B b + B d cos ̟ d (t) + ˙ h drag p ,<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">dk p dt = −Ah p − B d sin ̟ d (t) + ˙ k drag p .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Here A = A b + A d is the planetesimal precession rate. It is contributed both by the gravity of the secondary (A b ) and the disk (A d ), with</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">A b = ν 4 n p α 2 b b (1) 3/2 (α b ) ≈ 3 4 n p ν a p a b 3 (5) ≈ 5.9 × 10 −4 yr −1 ν M 1/2 p,1 a b,20 a 3/2 p,1 ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">n p = (GM p /a 3 p ) 1/2 is the planetesimal mean rate, M p,1 ≡ M p /M ⊙ , a p,1 ≡ a p /AU, a b,20 ≡ a b /(20 AU), b (j)</formula><p>s (α) is the standard Laplace coefficient <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Murray &amp; Dermott 1999)</ref>, α b ≡ a p /a b and the approximation in (5) works for α b ≪ 1. The disk contribution is</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">A d = 2π GΣ p (a p ) a p n p ψ 1 = (2 − p)ψ 1 n p M d M p a p a out 2−p (6) ≈ −6.3 × 10 −3 yr −1 a −1/2 p,1 M d,−2 M 1/2 p,1 a out,5</formula><p>where the numerical estimate is for p = 1 so that ψ 1 = −0.5 (SR13). Dimensionless coefficients of order unity ψ 1 and ψ 2 (see equation <ref type="formula">(8)</ref>) have been calculated in SR13 and are functions of the disk model and the distance of planetesimal orbit from the disk edges. One can see that for reasonable assumptions about the disk mass (M d ∼ 10 −2 M ⊙ ) the planetesimal precession rate at 1 AU is dominated by the disk gravity. Eccentricity excitation by the binary (B b ) and the disk (B d ) are described by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">B b = − ν 4 n p α 2 b b (2) 3/2 (α b )e b ≈ − 15 16 n p ν a p a b 4 e b , (7) B d = π GΣ p (a p ) a p n p e d (a p )ψ 2 (8) = 2 − p 2 ψ 2 e g (a p )n p M d M p a p a out 2−p ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>with the latter explicitly depending on the local value of the disk eccentricity e g (a p ).</p><p>Note that ̟ d in equations (3-4) is not necessarily constant -it can be an explicit function of time, allowing one to treat the case of a precessing disk.</p><p>Terms ˙ h drag p and ˙ k drag p absent in the original version of equations (3)-(4) in SR13 represent the effect of gas drag on the eccentricity evolution; they are derived in §4. The main goal of this work is to see how their introduction affects planetesimal dynamics.</p><p>Next we derive the expressions for the drag-induced eccentricity evolution terms ˙ h drag p and ˙ k drag p applicable to the case of an eccentric disk.</p><p>Because of our assumption of small eccentricities for both gas and planetesimals, it is reasonable to employ the local (or guiding center) approximation. This approach is often used in studies of planetesimal and galactic dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Binney &amp; Tremaine 2008)</ref> and forms a basis of the so-called Hill approximation <ref type="bibr">(Hénon &amp; Petit 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hasegawa &amp; Nakazawa 1990)</ref>. It considers planetesimal motion in a local Cartesian x−y reference system aligned with radial and azimuthal directions, respectively. Main features of this approximation are reviewed in Appendix A. In particular, equations (A8) describe how k p and h p evolve under the effect of external force F.</p><p>In our case F is the drag force arising because of the motion of planetesimals with respect to gas. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adachi et al. (1976)</ref> gives the following expression for quadratic drag force appropriate for rapidly moving objects with size larger than the mean free path of gas molecules:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">F = − C D 2 πd 2 p ρ g v r v r ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where C D is a constant drag coefficient taken to be 0.5 throughout this paper, d p is the particle size, and ρ g is the gas density. The relative particle-gas velocity v r is given by equations (A5), (A6), and (A7) with relative particle-gas eccentricity components</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">h r = h p − h g , k r = k p − k g ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>and e g = (k g , h g ) = e g (cos ̟ d , sin ̟ g ) being the local value of the gas eccentricity vector. Using these expressions we obtain the force components F x and F y :</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">F x = − 3C D 8 m p D v a r (k r sin n p t − h r cos n p t) ,<label>(12)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">F y = − 3C D 16 m p D v a r (k r cos n p t + h r sin n p t) ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where m p is the planetesimal mass, and the relative velocity v a r is given by equation (A7). The prefactor D is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">D = n p Σ g ρ p d p r h ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>with ρ p being the particle bulk density and h = c s /n p being the disk scale height (c s = (kT g /µ) 1/2 ). Now we plug the expressions for F x , F y into the first two equations (A8) and then average them in time t over planetesimal orbital period (this is the secular, i.e. timeaveraged approximation). One can easily see that to get the result to lowest-order in e r we do not need to keep terms O(e r , e d , e p ) in the expression for ρ g . As a result we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">˙ k drag p = − 3C D 4π E √ 3 2 D k r e r ,<label>(15)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">˙ h drag p = − 3C D 4π E √ 3 2 D h r e r ,<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where E √ 3/2 ≈ 1.211 is a complete elliptic integral, and e 2 r = k 2 r + h 2 r . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 1</ref>.-Time evolution of the components of the relative eccentricity vector er = (kr, hr) = ep − eg for planetesimals of two different sizes -dp = 0.3 km (red) and 8 km (green) starting with two different sets of initial conditions -er = (0.015, 0.01) (solid) and er = (−0.03, −0.02) (dashed). Calculations are carried out for the parameters of γ Cep system at 2 AU in a 0.001M ⊙ disk aligned with the binary; disk eccentricity at its outer edge aout = 5 AU is e 0 = 0.05, and p = 1, q = −1, see equations (1). After the short initial transient kr and hr converge to the forced values given by equations (22)-(23).</p><p>We can rewrite equations (15)-(16) in the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">˙ k drag p = − k p − k g τ d , ˙ h drag p = − h p − h g τ d ,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where the eccentricity damping time</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">τ d = 4π 3C D E √ 3/2 D −1 e −1 r (18) ≈ 600 yr C −1 D a out,5 a p,1 M 1/2 p,1 M d,−2 h/r 0.1 10 −2 e r d p,1 .</formula><p>Here d p,1 ≡ d p /(1 km) and numerical estimate is for p = 1 and ρ p = 3 g cm −3 ; in the case of quadratic drag law (10) τ d depends on k p and h p through e r , see equation (11).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">ECCENTRICITY EVOLUTION.</head><p>Results of §4 allow us to understand the behavior of e p . For simplicity, we start by considering the case of a non-precessing disk, i.e. ̟ d =const. Even in this case equations (3)-(4) with the quadratic drag terms (15)-(16) cannot be solved analytically in general because of the τ d dependence on e r .</p><p>However, it can be easily shown that solutions of these equations inevitably converge to a steady-state formthe free eccentricity, which depends on initial conditions (R13, SR13), damps out and e p converges to the forced eccentricity vector <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Beaugé et al 2010)</ref>. This is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref> where we solve evolution equations numerically. It is clear that starting with arbitrary initial conditions and after initial (sometimes oscillatory) evolution k p and h p do converge to the same steady state values (depending only on the disk parameters and planetesimal size), which are given by equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(23)</ref> derived below. This point is additionally illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2a</ref> where we plot the trajectory of e p as it evolves in h rk r coordinates. There one can clearly see e p converging to a fixed point solution, in oscillatory fashion for large planetesimals, and exponentially for small objects, which rapidly couple to the gas disk.</p><p>Damping of the memory of initial conditions can also be demonstrated by solving equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(3)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(4)</ref> analytically in a simplified but qualitatively similar case of a linear drag law, when τ d is independent of h p and k p . Such solution is presented in Appendix B for the general case of a precessing gaseous disk. Non-precessing disk solution is obtained by setting ˙ ̟ d = 0. It clearly demonstrates the convergence of e p to a time-independent, forced value.</p><p>SR13 have demonstrated that in the absence gas drag, under the action of only the gravity of the disk and the companion star, the steady state (forced) eccentricity is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">e n/drag p = k n/drag p h n/drag p = e b + e d ,<label>(19)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">e b = k b h b = − B b A 1 0 ,<label>(20)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">e d = k d h d = − B d A cos ̟ d sin ̟ d ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where e b and e d are forced eccentricity vectors due to the secondary and disk gravity, respectively. Note that the accuracy of analytical expression <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">(20)</ref> for the binary contribution is known to worsen (beyond the ∼ 10% level) when a p /a b 0.1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thébault et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barnes &amp; Green- berg 2006</ref>). More refined calculations of e b are possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Veras &amp; Armitage 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Giuppone et al. 2011</ref>) but for the purposes of this work it is sufficient to use equation <ref type="bibr">(20)</ref>. With the gas drag included the behavior of e p changes. To determine the steady-state values of k p and h p and analyze their properties we use the prescription (17), set to zero time derivatives in the left-hand-sides of equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(3)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(4)</ref> and solve the resulting algebraic system with respect to h p and k p . We find as a result</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">k p = k b + k d + (k g − k b − k d ) − (h g − h d ) (Aτ d ) 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 ,<label>(22)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">h p = h d + (h g − h d ) + (k g − k b − k d ) (Aτ d ) 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 ,<label>(23)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">k b , k d , h b , h d are defined in equations (20)-(21).</formula><p>These asymptotic results are valid even if τ d is a function of e r -in that case they simply represent two implicit relations for h p and k p .</p><p>Solutions <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(23)</ref> can be re-written in vectorial form as  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref>. One can see the convergence of trajectories starting at different ep to fixed point solutions (indicated by crosses), which depend on planetesimal radius dp. (b) Same for a disk precessing at the rate of ˙ ̟ d = A. Evolution trajectories converge to a limit cycle behavior in the precessing disk. See §6 for more details. Color and line type scheme is the same for both panels.</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">e p = k p h p = e f,b + e f,d ,<label>(24)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">e f,b = k b (Aτ d ) 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 (Aτ d ) −1 ,<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">e f,d = e 2 g + τ 2 d B 2 d 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 1/2 cos (̟ d + φ) sin (̟ d + φ) ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where the phase shift φ is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">cos φ = e g − AB d τ 2 d e 2 g + τ 2 d B 2 d 1/2 [1 + (Aτ d ) 2 ] 1/2 .<label>(27)</label></formula><p>In the limit of vanishing drag, Aτ d → ∞, one finds φ → π and solution <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(24)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">(26)</ref> reduces to the non-drag result with no free eccentricity <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(19)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">(21)</ref>, see SR13.</p><p>In the limit of strong drag (Aτ d → 0) in a circular disk (i.e. e g = 0) and no disk gravity (i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">A d = B d = 0) one finds h p /k p → −∞.</formula><p>This means that in this case planetesimal apsidal lines cluster around ̟ p = 3π/2, in agreement with <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Marzari &amp; Scholl (2000)</ref>. Also, |e p | → B b τ d directly depends on planetesimal size, which implies that in this limit planetesimals of different sizes collide with non-zero speeds even despite their apsidal alignment ).</p><p>Expressions <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(24)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">(26)</ref> clearly show that e p can be split into two distinct components: a contribution e f,b due to the gravity of the binary and a contribution e f,b related to both the gravitational and gas drag effects of the disk. It is also clear that after reaching steady state planetesimal orbits are in general aligned with neither the disk (̟ p = ̟ d ) nor the binary (̟ p = 0).</p><p>5.1. Relative particle-gas eccentricity.</p><p>In the case of quadratic drag (10) we can further analyze eccentricity behavior. Using equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(23)</ref> we express relative particle-gas eccentricity as</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">e r = |e p − e g | = e c (Aτ d ) 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 ,<label>(28)</label></formula><p>where we introduced a characteristic eccentricity e c = e</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">n/drag p − e g given by e c ≡ (h g − h d ) 2 + (k g − k b − k d ) 2 1/2 (29) = (Ae g + B d ) 2 + B 2 b + 2 cos ̟ d B b (Ae g + B d ) 1/2 |A| .</formula><p>Plugging this expression for e r into equation <ref type="formula">(18)</ref> one obtains the following bi-quadratic equation for (Aτ d ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">(Aτ d ) 4 = d p d c 2 (Aτ d ) 2 + 1 ,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where we have introduced a characteristic planetesimal size d c defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">d c ≡ 3C D E √ 3/2 4π n p |A| Σ g ρ p r h e c .<label>(31)</label></formula><p>All our subsequent results can be formulated completely in terms of e c and d p /d c , underscoring the significance of these variables. Detailed discussion of the characteristic values and general behavior of e c and d c is provided in §7.1 and 7.3. Solving equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(30)</ref> one finds</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">|Aτ d | = d p d c   1 2 + 1 4 + d c d p 2   1/2 ,<label>(32)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">i.e. that |Aτ d | is a function of d r /d c only.</formula><p>Plugging <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(32)</ref> into <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">(28)</ref> one also finds the general expression for the relative particle-gas eccentricity</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">e r = e c d p d c   1 4 + d c d p 2 − 1 2   1/2 (33) Fig.</formula><p>3.-Dependence of er/ec and |Aτ d | on planetesimal size dp/dc, given by equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">(28)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(32)</ref> respectively. Asymptotic scalings <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(34)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(38)</ref> are also indicated. For dp ∼ dc one finds |Aτ d | ∼ 1 and er ∼ ec.</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">valid for arbitrary d p /d c .</formula><p>We illustrate the behaviors of |Aτ d | and e r given by equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(32)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(33)</ref>  It is instructive to further explore general solutions (32), (33) valid for arbitrary d p /d c in the two limits covered next.</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">5.2. Small objects, d p d c -strong drag (|Aτ d | 1).</formula><p>In the limit of strong gas drag we expect damping time τ d to be very short and |Aτ d | ≪ 1, so that gas-particle velocity differential is rapidly reduced to zero. According to equation (32), this regime is valid for small objects with d p d c , when</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">|Aτ d | ≈ (d p /d c ) 1/2 1.<label>(34)</label></formula><p>From equation (28) the relative particle-gas eccentricity is</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">e r ≈ |Aτ d | e c ≈ e c (d p /d c ) 1/2<label>(35)</label></formula><p>to leading order in (Aτ d ).</p><p>Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(23)</ref> become</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">k p → k g + (h d − h g ) (Aτ d ) − (k g − k b − k d ) (Aτ d ) 2 ,<label>(36)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">h p → h g + (k g − k b − k d ) (Aτ d ) + (h d − h g ) (Aτ d ) 2 .<label>(37)</label></formula><p>Here brackets encompass the leading order subdominant terms, compared to the zeroth order terms outside brackets.</p><p>It is clear from these asymptotic expressions that in the case of strong drag, the eccentricity vector of planetesimals tends to the eccentricity vector of the gas, e p → e g . It is only weakly sensitive to gravitational perturbations due to either the companion or the disk. Thus, to leading order the value of eccentricity vector is independent of particle size (which enters only through τ d ).</p><p>5.3. Big objects, d p d c -weak drag (|Aτ d | 1). In the opposite limit of weak drag or long damping time |Aτ d | ≫ 1 valid for large objects with d p d c equation (32) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">(Aτ d ) ≈ d p /d c 1,<label>(38)</label></formula><p>while the relative particle-gas eccentricity is</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">e r ≈ e c<label>(39)</label></formula><p>see equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">(28)</ref>. Thus, in the weak drag regime e r saturates at the value independent of the size of the object.</p><p>Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>-(23) reduce in this limit to</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">k p → k b + k d + (h d − h g ) (Aτ d ) −1 + (k g − k b − k d ) (Aτ d ) −2 ,<label>(40)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_45">h p → h g + (k g − k b − k d ) (Aτ d ) −1 − (h d − h g ) (Aτ d ) −2 .<label>(41)</label></formula><p>Again, terms in brackets are subdominant compared to the leading terms (outside brackets). This solution shows that in the limit of weak drag e p → e n/drag p , i.e. the behavior of the particle eccentricity vector is determined predominantly by the gravitational effects of the secondary and the disk. Thus, e p is again almost independent of the particle size.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">PRECESSING DISKS.</head><p>So far we have assumed the orientation of the disk to be fixed in the binary frame. However, some simulations find disks in binaries to precess (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Müller &amp; Kley 2012)</ref>. We now study how planetesimal dynamics change in the case of a disk uniformly precessing at a constant rate ˙ ̟ d . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2b</ref> displays evolution of e p for the same parameters as in panel (a) of that Figure, but in a disk precessing at the rate ˙ ̟ d = A. One can see that the main difference compared to the nonprecessing case is that in the long run e p converged to the limit cycle behavior ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Beaugé et al. 2010</ref>) rather than to a fixed point, as in panel (a). The sizes and shapes of the asymptotic limit cycles depend on both the planetesimal size d p and the disk precession rate ˙ ̟ d , as discussed in detail in Appendix C and shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9</ref>. This certainly complicates planetesimal dynamics.</p><p>To gain additional insights, in Appendix B we derive a full time-dependent solution for e p in a precessing disk for the case of linear gas drag, when τ d is independent of the relative particle-gas eccentricity e r . This solution fully accounts for the gravitational and gas drag effects of the precessing disk as well as for the gravity of the binary companion.</p><p>We use this solution as a basis for understanding planetesimal dynamics in a precessing disk in the more complicated but realistic case of quadratic gas drag. This regime, which does not admit general analytical solution even for the long-term behavior is explored in Appendix C. There we show that planetesimal dynamics with drag law (10) depend on the relative role played by the binary companion, as described next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Strong binary perturbation case.</head><p>Results of Appendices B &amp; C show that whenever binary gravity dominates e p excitation and the condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">|(A − ˙ ̟ d ) e g + B d | |B b |<label>(42)</label></formula><p>is fulfilled, planetesimal dynamics proceed as if the disk were not precessing: neither the gas eccentricity e g nor the eccentricity driven by disk gravity e d , equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">(21)</ref>, are significant compared to the forced eccentricity due to binary e b = B b /A (note that both binary and disk gravity contribute to A).</p><p>In this case e p is close to the relative planetesimalgas eccentricity e r and is approximately constant. As a result, planetesimal orbit maintains roughly fixed orientation with respect to the binary orbit and</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">k p ≈ k b (Aτ d ) 2 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 , h p ≈ −k b (Aτ d ) 1 + (Aτ d ) 2 ,<label>(43)</label></formula><p>with k b defined by equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">(20</ref> Interestingly, even though gas eccentricity e g does not appear in these expressions (and neither does the precession rate ˙ ̟ d , at the lowest order) the effect of the gas drag is explicitly present via the non-trivial τ d dependence. Thus, our precessing disk results obtained in the limit (42) apply equally well to planetesimal dynamics in a purely axisymmetric (e g = 0) gaseous disk, extending the results of R13 to the case of non-zero gas dragnote that A in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(43)</ref> and in the definition of k b is the full precession rate due to both binary and the disk.</p><p>The value of e r in the regime (42) is given by equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">(28)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(33)</ref> with d c and</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">|Aτ d | computed using e c ≈ e b = |B b /A| (i.e. equation (29) in the limit B d → 0, e g → 0)</formula><p>, see equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(31)</ref> and (32).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Weak binary perturbation case.</head><p>In the opposite case of weak driving of e p by the binary companion we combine solutions (C5) and find the relative particle-gas eccentricity to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">e r = |e pr c | |A − ˙ ̟ d | τ d 1 + (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 2 τ 2 d ,<label>(44)</label></formula><p>replacing equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">(28)</ref> in the case of precessing disk.</p><p>Here we defined characteristic eccentricity</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">e pr c = − B d A − ˙ ̟ d − e g ,<label>(45)</label></formula><p>which, according to SR13, is the relative particle-gas forced eccentricity in the no drag (τ d → ∞) and no binary (B b → 0) case. As ˙ ̟ d → 0 one finds |e pr c | → e c given by equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(29)</ref> with k b = h b = 0; also, equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(44)</ref> reduces to the non-precessing disk result (28). Plugging this expression for e r into equation <ref type="formula">(18)</ref> one finds</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">|A − ˙ ̟ d | τ d = d p d pr c   1 2 + 1 4 + d pr c d p 2   1/2 ,<label>(46)</label></formula><p>with a new characteristic planetesimal size</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">d pr c ≡ 3C D E √ 3/2 4π n p |A − ˙ ̟ d | Σ g ρ p r h |e pr c | .<label>(47)</label></formula><p>These expressions are different from equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(31)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(32)</ref> </p><note type="other">in using A − ˙ ̟ d instead of A and |e pr c | instead of e c . It is then clear that whenever a precessing disk dominates planetesimal dynamics equation (33) also holds provided that we replace d c → d pr c and e c → |e pr c |. The same is true for our asymptotic results on e p behavior presented in §5.2-5.3 if we also take k b → 0.</note><p>In the limit ˙ ̟ d → 0 the value of e f reduces to e f,d given by equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">(26)</ref>. But when | ˙ ̟ d | ≫ |A| rapid disk precession suppresses excitation of planetesimal eccentricity by the disk gravity, i.e. the first term in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(45)</ref>.</p><p>It it worth noting that results of Appendix B for the case of linear drag suggest that neglecting binary gravity in the case of precessing disk might require a condition different from the direct opposite to the constraint (42). Indeed, asymptotic solution (B5) for the relative eccentricity of planetesimals in the case of weak drag</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">(τ d,1 , τ d,2 ≫ |A − ˙ ̟ d | −1 )</formula><p>shows that the term proportional to k b can be neglected only when</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">|(A − ˙ ̟ d ) e g + B d | |B b | A − ˙ ̟ d A 2 ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>which is a more stringent criterion whenever | ˙ ̟ d | ≫ |A|. The same constraint may be needed in the case of quadratic drag. However, in practice one often finds | ˙ ̟ d | |A|, see Paper II in which case equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(48)</ref> is just the opposite of the condition (42).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">DIVERSITY OF PLANETESIMAL DYNAMICS.</head><p>Results of §5 demonstrate that the steady state value of the eccentricity vector e p is fully determined by just two key parameters -characteristic eccentricity e c and critical planetesimal size d c , see equation (33). Eccentricity e c sets the overall scale of the e p , while d c is the planetesimal size at which planetesimal coupling to gas changes from weak to strong. We now explore the behavior of these variables as a function of system parameters to elucidate some important features of planetesimal dynamics.  giving rise to a secular resonance. According to equations (19)- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">(21)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(29)</ref> e c gets driven to high values as A → 0. This resonance has been previously discussed in R13 and SR13.</p><p>Equations <ref type="formula">(5)</ref>- <ref type="formula">(6)</ref> predict that at a given distance from the primary a p this resonance occurs for the disk mass</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">M d,A=0 = M s 3 4(2 − p)|ψ 1 | a p a b 1+p a out a b 2−p (49) ≈ 1.5 × 10 −3 M ⊙ M s 0.4 M ⊙ a out,5 a 3 b,20 a 2 p,2 ,</formula><p>where a out,5 ≡ a out /(5 AU), a p,2 ≡ a p /(2 AU), and a b,20 ≡ a b /(20 AU). This estimate agrees with <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  4a</ref>,b for the γ Cep parameters and a disk with p = 1 and ψ 1 (p = 1) = −0.5 (SR13). Existence of this resonance is independent of the relative disk-binary orientation because planetesimal precession rates A b and A d are determined by the axisymmetric components of the binary and disk gravitational potentials. For this reason M d,A=0 is the same for all disk orientations. To the right of the secular resonance disk gravity dominates planetesimal precession rate and suppresses e c if disk eccentricity is small (R13).</p><p>At high disk eccentricity, typically e 0 0.05, this suppression vanishes because for large M d 10 −3 M ⊙ disk gravity starts to dominate e p excitation. This statement is true above the blue line |B b | = |B d | in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>,b (the origin of the low-e c band at small M d and high e 0 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref> is discussed in §7.2). Further increase of the disk mass in this region does not affect e c because planetesimal dynamics switches to the so-called DD regime (SR13) in which e p (a p ) ≈ |ψ 2 /ψ 1 |e g (a p ), independent of M d . As a result, high e g leads to high e p .</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4c</ref>,d we explore the dependence of e c on the distance from the binary a p and M d for two different values of the disk eccentricity e 0 = 0.1 and 0.01. Here we look only at an aligned disk case. Again, an obvious feature of these maps is the secular resonance around the blue dashed curve for |A d | = |A b |, where e c is very large and collisional growth is impossible. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4d</ref> there is also a "valley" of low e c to the right from the blue line |B b | = |B d |, whose origin is discussed in §7.2.</p><p>These maps make it clear that e c becomes independent of M d (at a given separation a p ) when the disk mass becomes large enough. This is a direct consequence of the planetesimal dynamics switching into the DD regime (SR13), when both eccentricity excitation and apsidal precession of planetesimals are dominated by the disk gravity with negligible contribution from the binary companion. In the high-M d regime e c decreases as a p goes down. This is a consequence of our adopted disk model, in which e d ∝ a p and the fact that e c ∝ e d in the DD regime.</p><p>7.2. Valley of stability in aligned disks. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>,b shows that irrespective of the disk orientation e c is low for high M d 10 −2 M ⊙ and small disk eccentricity, e 0 10 −2 . Outside this corner of phase space e c is much higher, which makes planetesimal growth problematic there. At the same time, in the case of an aligned disk (̟ d = 0) low values of e c are also possible in a narrow "valley" stretching towards high e 0 and low M d . Since this feature may have interesting implications for planet formation in binaries (see Paper II for details) we discuss its origin in more detail.</p><p>Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(29)</ref> implies that in an aligned disk</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">h g = h d = 0 so that e c ≈ |k g − k d − k b | = B b + B d + Ae g A .<label>(50)</label></formula><p>For massive disks, to the right from the vertical |A b | = |A d | line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>, one can set A ≈ A d and relate it to B d via equations (6) and <ref type="bibr">(8)</ref>. As a result, equation (50) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">e c ≈ B b + B d 1 + 2ψ 1 ψ −1 2 A d .<label>(51)</label></formula><p>For the disk model considered here (p = 1, q = −1) one has ψ 1 = −0.5, ψ 2 = 1.5 and 1 + 2ψ 1 ψ −1 2 = 1/3 so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">e c ≈ |A d | −1 |B b + B d /3|. Also B d &gt; 0 while B b</formula><p>is always negative, see equations <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> From this discussion we see that e c ≈ 0 for values of e 0 and M d , which are close to the curve</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">M d,|B b |=|B d | = M s 15 8(2 − p)|ψ 2 | e b e 0 (52) × a p a b 2+p+q a out a b 2−p−q ≈ 1.2 × 10 −3 M ⊙ M s 0.4 M ⊙ e b 0.4 0.1 e 0 a 2 out,5 a 4 b,20 a 2 p,2 ,</formula><p>on which |B b | = |B d |, see equations <ref type="formula">(7)</ref>- <ref type="formula">(8)</ref> in which we took p = 1, q = −1. This relation is shown by the blue line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> and is quite close to the valley of low e c .</p><p>Note that according to equation (51) the value of e c can be lowered globally in a massive disk if its structure is such that 1 + 2ψ 1 ψ −1 2 = 0. However, this is not the case for the disk model used in this work.</p><p>The situation is different for the low mass, aligned disks to the left of the |A d | = |A b | (blue dashed) line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  4a</ref>. Here A ≈ A b and B b dominates over B d for low enough M d at a fixed e 0 , which in terminology of SR13 corresponds to the Case BB of planetesimal excitation. In this regime equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_56">(50)</ref> shows that</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">e c → e g + B b A b = e g − 5 4 a p a b e b<label>(53)</label></formula><p>Our adopted radial scaling of e g in the form (1) with q = −1 results in a particular value of</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">e 0 ec→0 = 5 4 a out a b e b = 0.125 a out /a b 0.25 e b 0.4 ,<label>(54)</label></formula><p>for which e c → 0. This critical value of e 0 in independent of M d explaining why the valley of low e c starts going almost horizontally for</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">M d M d A=0</formula><p>in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>. Moreover, e 0 | ec→0 is also independent of a p , which means that e c → 0 globally when e 0 → e 0 | ec→0 in parts of the disk where |A b | |A d | and |B b | |B d |. This is the reason why in the upper left corner of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4c</ref> e c is considerably lower than in the same region of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  4d</ref>, despite e 0 being an order of magnitude higher in the former case. Indeed, according to equation (54) e 0 = 0.1 used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4c</ref> is very close to e 0 | ec→0 for the adopted system parameters. As a result of this coincidence, e c is strongly suppressed in the BB regime in a rather eccentric (e 0 = 0.1) disk.</p><p>A narrow region of low e c stretching along the blue curve |B b | = |B d | in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4c</ref> If the disk is not aligned with the binary orbit and ̟ d is not small then both h d and h g are nonzero and contribute to e c , see equation <ref type="bibr">(29)</ref>. Moreover, for disks which are close to being anti-aligned with the binary, k b and k d have the same sign, eliminating the possibility of their mutual cancellation. As a result, the low-e c valley at high e 0 and low M d disappears as long as</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">|̟ d − ̟ b | 10 • .</formula><p>To summarize, the valley of stability creates favorable conditions for lowering planetesimal velocity in aligned disks locally, around some particular locations, even in low mass disks with M d 10 −2 M ⊙ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.">Behavior of d c .</head><p>Next we discuss the behavior of the characteristic size d c at which planetesimals of similar (but not equal) mass collide at highest relative velocity ∼ e c v K . Equation (31) makes it clear that for a given value of e c critical size is a </p><formula xml:id="formula_64">d c = C D E( √ 3/2) πν r h Σ g ρ p a b a p 3 e c<label>(55)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">≈ 30 km C D ν 0.1 h/r M d,−2 a 3 b,20</formula><p>a out,5</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">e c 0.1 a −4 p,1</formula><p>where the numerical estimate is for p = 1 disk and ρ p = 3 g cm −3 . In the opposite case, when precession is dominated by the disk gravity and A = A d one obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">d c = 3C D E( √ 3/2) 8π 2 ψ 1 r h M p ρ p a 2 p e c (56) ≈ 1 km C D ψ 1 0.1 h/r e c 0.1 M p,1 a −2 p,1 ,</formula><p>independent of the disk mass. It is obvious that in the disk-dominated case d c is much smaller than in the binary-dominated case for a p 1AU, a fact predicted in R13. This difference can be easily seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8</ref>, where the situation depicted in panel (a) corresponds to the DD regime, in which equation (56) applies. As a result, the planetesimal size for which the low-e r "waist" in this Figure is narrowest is around 1 km. On the contrary, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8b</ref> shows a situation in which disk gravity has been turned off, so the dynamics are in the BB regime and equation (55) applies. Not surprisingly, this pushes the characteristic d p at the narrowest point of the waist to be about 30 km.</p><p>Using this reasoning one might expect the critical "dangerous" size d p at which e r ∼ e c for objects of comparable size to be smaller for more massive disks in which |A d | ≫ |A b |. However, this logic directly applies only if e c were kept the same. In reality, changing A also directly affects the value of e c , see equation <ref type="bibr">(29)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> shows that in practice the behavior of d c largely reflects that of e c , with all the features of e c maps (e.g. valleys of low d c ) present in d c maps as well. In particular, the valley of stability shows up prominently in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5a</ref>,d.</p><p>The only noticeable difference with <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> is the increase of d c with decreasing a p in the high-M d (DD) regime, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5c</ref>,d, a behavior which is predicted by equation (56). Also, in agreement with equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">(55)</ref>, d c decreases with increasing a p in the outer disk for small M d (upper left in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5c,d)</ref> even though e c varies there weakly. In this region planetesimal dynamics is determined predominantly by the binary companion (BB regime of SR12) and equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">(55)</ref> applies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">DISTRIBUTION OF RELATIVE PLANETESIMAL</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VELOCITIES.</head><p>Our next step is to study the behavior of the relative approach velocity v 12 between planetesimals with sizes d 1 and d 2 . It is this velocity that determines the outcome of their collision.</p><p>We now provide a calculation of the distribution df 12 /dv 12 of v 12 between the two planetesimal populations, one with eccentricity vector e p (d 1 ) and another with e p (d 2 ). In previous sections we have shown that after the initial transient period when the free eccentricity damps out, the value of e p becomes time-independent and is uniquely determined by the planetesimal size. Then the only additional orbital parameter that can give rise to the variation of the relative velocity v 12 is the difference in semi-major axes b 12 between approaching particles, see equation (A7) of Appendix A. Using equations (A4), (A7) it can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">v 12 = Ωa p e 2 12 − 3 4 b 12 a p 2 1/2 ,<label>(57)</label></formula><p>where a is the mean semi-major axis of both planetesimals, and the condition of close approach x 12 = 0 was used. Note that in this expression we ignored the contribution of particle inclination to the velocity. This is a reasonable assumption since we expect eccentricity excitation in the binary plane to dominate over the out of plane excitation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ida et al. (1993)</ref> consider encounters between the two populations of objects with fixed eccentricity vectors e 1 = (k 1 , h 1 ) and e 2 = (k 2 , h 2 ). They derive the following expression for the flux of objects with eccentricity e 2 approaching a given object with eccentricity e 1 with random orbital phases, having separation of their semi-major axes b 12 in the range (b 12 , b 12 + db 12 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">dF 12 = 1 π 2 Σ 2 a p m 2 i 12 v 12 db 12 [e 2 12 − (b 12 /a p ) 2 ] 1/2 .<label>(58)</label></formula><p>Here</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">e 12 = (h 1 − h 2 ) 2 + (k 1 − k 2 ) 2 1/2</formula><p>is the relative eccentricity between the two particle populations, i 12 is their relative inclination, and Σ 2 is the surface density of objects with eccentricity e 2 .</p><p>Using equation (57) we can express db in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_69">(58)</ref>  . <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(59)</ref> We now express b 12 via v 12 using equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_68">(57)</ref> and in-  <ref type="formula">(62)</ref>. Relative velocity is normalized by its maximum value vmax = e 12 npr, where e 12 is the relative eccentricity of the two planetesimals, which is a function of their sizes, see §9.1-9.3. Minimum approach velocity is vmax/2.</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">troduce v min = 1 2 e 12 na p , v max = e 12 na p .<label>(60)</label></formula><p>Then it is clear that v min &lt; v 12 &lt; v max and we can re-write (59) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">dF 12 dv 12 = 1 π 2 Σ 2 m 2 i 12 v 2 12 [(v 2 max − v 2 12 ) (v 2 12 − v 2 min )] 1/2 .<label>(61)</label></formula><p>From this we find that the distribution of relative velocities df 12 /dv 12 of different planetesimals normalized to unity is given by the following expression:</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">df 12 dv 12 = v −1 max E √ 3/2 v 2 12 [(v 2 max − v 2 12 ) (v 2 12 − v 2 min )] 1/2</formula><p>. <ref type="formula">(62)</ref> Particle sizes enter into this expression only through e 12 via equations (60). This distribution of relative velocities is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig- ure 6</ref>. It diverges at both v = v min and v = v max , but the total particle flux is finite and given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">F 12 = vmax vmin dF 12 dv 12 dv 12 = E √ 3/2 π 2 Σ 2 e max m 2 i 12<label>(63)</label></formula><p>With distribution function (61) one finds the mean relative velocity v 12 ≈ 0.81v max = 0.81e 12 n p a p , while the rms velocity is given by v rms = v 2 12 1/2 = 0.828e 12 n p a p .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">RELATIVE VELOCITY BETWEEN PLANETESIMALS.</head><p>The results of the previous section clearly demonstrate that the relative velocity with which two planetesimals with sizes d 1 and d 2 approach each other prior to collision is determined by their relative eccentricity e 12 = |e p (d 1 ) − e p (d 2 )|. Using solutions <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(23)</ref> it is trivial to show that</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">e 12 = e c |Aτ d,1 − Aτ d,2 | 1 + A 2 τ 2 d,1 1 + A 2 τ 2 d,2 ,<label>(64)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">τ d,i ≡ τ d (d i ), i = 1, 2.</formula><p>According to the results of §5, Aτ d and, subsequently, e 12 , are functions of (1) sizes of the colliding planetesimals d 1,2 and (2) binary parameters and local disk properties, which set the values of both e c and d c , see equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(29)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(31)</ref>. We already explored the latter in §7 and now we turn our attention to understanding e 1,2 (d 1 , d 2 ). In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref> we map out e 12 (d 1 , d 2 ) (as well as the relative velocity v 12 = e 1,2 v K ) at the location of the planet a p = 2 AU in the γ Cephei system for different characteristics of the disk, for which a model (1) with p = 1, q = −1 is adopted. We vary disk mass M d , eccentricity at its outer edge e 0 , and its orientation with respect to the binary orbit ̟ d , one at a time keeping other disk parameters fixed. All panels clearly show several key invariant features.</p><p>First, there is a critical size of order d c , around d 1 = d 2 ∼ (0.1 − 1) km, at which maps exhibit a "waist", in which e 12 is small for collisions of equal size bodies. Second, e 12 becomes small for encounters between both the small bodies, with d 1 , d 2 d c , and for large objects with d 1 , d 2 d c . Third, e 12 saturates at a value roughly independent of d 1 or d 2 for collisions of particles with very different sizes, i.e. when d 1 d c d 2 , and vice versa.</p><p>These gross features, as well as the variations of the overall velocity scale seen in these maps, are addressed below using the results of §5. Given that particles can be in different drag regimes -strong or weak -we will consider several possibilities separately.</p><p>9.1. Strong-strong encounters.</p><p>When both planetesimals are in strong drag regime,</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">d 1 , d 2 ≪ d c , both |Aτ d,1 | ≪ 1 and |Aτ d,2 | ≪ 1. Then equation (64) predicts that e ss 12 ≈ e c ||Aτ d,1 | − |Aτ d,2 || (65) ≈ e c d 1 d c 1/2 − d 2 d c 1/2 .<label>(66)</label></formula><p>where we used equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(34)</ref> to express |Aτ d | in terms of planetesimal sizes. Since d 1,2 ≪ d c in the strong drag limit, one finds that e ss r e c , which explains low values of e r in the lower left corner in maps in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>.</p><p>Physically, in this regime relative velocity of two planetesimals is considerably lower than their individual velocities because of the apsidal alignment of their orbits by gas drag, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Marzari &amp; Scholl (2000)</ref>) and similar magnitudes of e p .</p><p>9.2. Weak-weak encounters. When both planetesimals are in the weak drag regime |Aτ d,1 | ≫ 1 and |Aτ d,2 | ≫ 1, one finds using equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(64)</ref> that</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">e ww 12 ≈ e c |Aτd,1| −1 − (Aτ d,2 | −1 (67) ≈ e c d c d 1 − d c d 2 .<label>(68)</label></formula><p>where equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(38)</ref> has been used. Since d 1,2 ≫ d c in the weak drag limit, one again finds that e ww r e c , explaining the low relative eccentricity in the upper right corner in maps in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>.</p><p>In this case apsidal alignment is again at work, lowering e r compared to e p (d 1 ), e p (d 2 ). However, now it is caused by the disk+binary gravity, which affects planetesimals in the same way when they are weakly coupled to gas. This is because the gas damps the free eccentricity, but is not strong enough to significantly change the forced eccentricity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3.">Weak-strong encounters.</head><p>When one of the planetesimals (e.g. of size d 1 ) is in the strong drag regime, |Aτ d,1 | ≪ 1, while the other is in the weak drag regime, |Aτ d,2 | ≫ 1, equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(64)</ref> shows that their relative eccentricity e 12 is just</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">e sw 12 ≈ e c .<label>(69)</label></formula><p>One can see that e 12 is roughly independent of the sizes of particles participating in an encounter.</p><p>9.4. Overall e 12 scale as a function of disk parameters. The overall scale of e 12 in each of the maps shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref> is characterized by e 12 in one of the highvelocity corners. According to §9.3 this scale is just e c , which allows us to use the results of §7 to understand how the typical e 12 varies as we change the disk parameters. Note that in</p><p>Comparison of panels (a) and (b) of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref> shows that disk mass M d plays an important role in setting e 1,2 : planetesimals in low mass disks (M d = 4×10 −4 M ⊙ ) collide with much higher speeds than in higher mass (M d = 2 × 10 −2 M ⊙ ) disk. This is because for the chosen value of e 0 = 0.05 the low mass disk is in the BB regime and the value of e c ≈ 0.05 is high, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>. Increasing M d as in panel (a) brings the disk in the DD regime and also close to the valley of stability. For that reason, in higher mass disk with M d = 0.02M ⊙ one gets much lower e c ≈ 0.008.</p><p>Lowering e 0 for a high mass disk as in panel (c) reduces relative velocity scale even more, simply because for e 0 = 0.007 the system gets even deeper into the valley of stability, where the corresponding e c ≈ 1.5 × 10 −3 , see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref>.</p><p>Comparison of panels (a) and (d) shows that changing disk orientation also strongly affects e r : there is no valley of stability in the misaligned disk and characteristic eccentricity scale becomes e c ≈ 0.014. As a result, particles in a mis-aligned disk collide at higher speeds than in the aligned disk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">DISCUSSION.</head><p>Our work extends and complements existing results on planetesimal dynamics in binaries in several important ways.</p><p>First, for the first time, our solutions for e p in §5 simultaneously account for a number of key physical ingredients needed for a complete description of secular dynamics of planetesimals in binaries: gravity of both eccentric disk and eccentric companion as well as the gas drag, which causes orbital phasing of planetesimals and reduces their relative eccentricity in certain regimes.</p><p>Second, we provide a rigorous derivation of the equations of eccentricity evolution due to gas drag (15)- <ref type="formula">(18)</ref> in an eccentric disk. Previously, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adachi et al. (1976)</ref> derived analogous equations for the case of a circular disk, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Beaugé et al. (2010)</ref> proposed a set of empirical equations similar to (15)-(16) but without proper calculation of the constant pre-factors.</p><p>Third, we derive an analytic expression (62) for the relative velocity distribution function df 12 /dv 12 for locally homogeneous populations of objects with fixed eccentricity vectors, which is appropriate in the limit |e p | ≪ 1 in the presence of gas drag. We also provide an in-depth analysis of e 12 behavior for objects of different sizes in systems with different parameters ( §9). Previously the distribution of planetesimal encounter velocities has been explored only numerically, by following a large number of trace particles in simulations of different kinds <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Thébault et al. 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Paardekooper et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fragner et al. 2011</ref>). Thus, our derivation of df 12 /dv r represents an important analytical step in understanding planetesimal dynamics.</p><p>We now provide a more detailed comparison of our results with previous studies and discuss the limitations of this work.  Our calculations account for both the precession of planetesimal orbits due to the axisymmetric part of the disk potential and the eccentricity excitation due to its non-axisymmetric component. Disk non-axisymmetry is modeled via its nonzero eccentricity, i.e. m = 1 distortion, which can be a function of radius. We expect this approximation to capture the key effect of the disk asymmetry, as higher-m distortions of the disk shape are relatively small <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Marzari et al. 2012</ref>).</p><p>In <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> we summarize some (this list is not exhaustive) existing (semi-)analytical treatments of planetesimal dynamics (including this work), classified according to the physical ingredients that are taken into account. We primarily focus on studies of secular effects to put our work in proper context. Our current results cover all dynamical regimes listed in this table in appropriate limits. The majority of previous studies considered planetesimal dynamics in the presence of gas drag, with only the direct binary gravitational perturbations taken into account <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Marzari &amp; Scholl 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Thébault et al. 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thébault et al. , 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Thébault et al. , 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Thébault et al. , 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Paardekooper et al. 2008</ref>). As shown in SR13 this approximation is unwarranted as long as the disk mass M d 10 −2 M ⊙ since then the disk potential dominates gravitational perturbation.</p><p>We also provide full analytical solutions for test particle dynamics in a general precessing or non-precessing disk without companion perturbation, see equations (44)-(47). Previously, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Beaugé et al. (2010)</ref> studied this regime for a precessing disk but did not account for the gravitational effect of the disk (i.e. only gas drag was taken into account). In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8</ref> we illustrate the differences in various descriptions of planetesimal dynamics. It shows relative eccentricity as a function of planetesimal sizes d 1 and d 2 at 1 AU in an aligned disk of M d = 10 −2 M p and e 0 = 0.1 around a primary of γ Cephei in four different limits. Panel (a) presents a full calculation with all physical ingredients (gas drag, gravity of both the eccentric disk and the binary companion) accounted for using the solutions obtained in §5.</p><p>In panel (b) we show how things change if disk gravity is completely switched off by setting A d = B d = 0 -an approximation common to a number of previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Marzari &amp; Scholl 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Thébault et al. 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thébault et al. , 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Thébault et al. , 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Thébault et al. , 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Paardekooper et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Beaugé et al. 2010</ref>). One can see that without disk gravity relative planetesimal velocities go up by a factor of several. Moreover, the "waist" between the two high-e 12 regions in panel (b) is narrowest at d 1 ∼ d 2 ∼ 10 2 km, which is considerably larger than in panel (a) where this happens for d ∼ 0.3 km objects. This difference is in complete agreement with equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">(55)</ref> and <ref type="formula">(56)</ref>.</p><p>In panel (c) we account for the gravitational effect of a non-axisymmetric disk but neglect gas drag (τ d → ∞), i.e. use equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(19)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">(21)</ref>, as was done in SR13. In the absence of gas drag there is no apsidal alignment of planetesimal orbits and they approach each other at random phases. Also, e r is independent of d 1 and d 2 (the size-dependent drag is absent) explaining uniform color in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8c</ref>. Absence of gas drag results in rather high relative velocities of planetesimals making their survival in collisions problematic. Thus, apsidal alignment of planetesimal orbits and eccentricity suppression due to gas drag are very important for the proper description of their dynamics.</p><p>Finally, in panel (d) we retain only the axisymmetric component of the disk potential neglecting the eccentricity excitation by the disk, i.e. B d = 0 but A d = 0. In this limit, also neglecting gas drag (accounted for here) R13 predicted dramatic lowering of e p . Comparison with panel (a) clearly shows this not to be the case when gas drag included, which can be understood by noticing that e c in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(29)</ref> can significantly deviate from e n/drag p because of e g contribution. This is why lowering e n/drag p by setting B d = 0 and increasing |A| does not necessarily result in smaller e c , as expected in R13.</p><p>To summarize, simultaneously accounting for all the physical processes affecting planetesimals -gas drag, disk and secondary gravity -is very important for understanding planetesimal growth. Omission of even a single physical ingredient can significantly affect the conclusions drawn from the dynamical calculations.</p><p>Previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kley &amp; Nelson (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fragner et al. (2011)</ref> numerically explored planetesimal dynamics in gaseous disks, which were evolved using direct hydrodynamical simulations. They accounted for the effect of disk gravity on planetesimal motion and at least some of their calculations assumed coplanarity of the disk and the binary. However, even though the setup of these studies is very similar to that of our present work, some subtle differences prevent direct comparison of their results. In particular, when estimating the relative velocities of planetesimals based on their orbit crossing <ref type="bibr">Kley &amp; Nel- son (2007)</ref> do not take into account the apsidal phasing of their orbits <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Marzari &amp; Scholl 2000)</ref>, clearly obvious in their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 10</ref>. As a result they find very high relative speeds even between equal-size planetesimals, which we believe is an artefact of their neglect of apsidal phasing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fragner et al. (2011)</ref> study the case of a circular binary, in which apsidal phasing is naturally absent, resulting in high relative speeds of planetesimals. As a result, the applicability of calculations using circular binaries to understanding planetesimal dynamics in eccentric systems like γ Cep is not obvious.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.2.">Limitations of this work.</head><p>Finally, we discuss limitations of our study. Some of them have to do with the adoption of secular, i.e. orbitaveraged, approximation. While averaging over the planetesimal orbit is justified because n −1 p is always much shorter than other periodicities (e.g. of planetesimal apsidal precession), when averaging over the longer binary period one may overlook important dynamical features of the systems possessing very massive disks. Indeed, equation <ref type="formula">(6)</ref> suggests that for M d ∼ 0.1M ⊙ planetesimal precession rate |A d | becomes comparable to the binary angular frequency -n p ≈ 0.1 yr −1 for γ Cephei. In these conditions averaging over the latter is not justified and new effects, such as the possibility of evection resonance <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Touma &amp; Wisdom 1998</ref>) inside the disk, may additionally affect planetesimal dynamics.</p><p>Other effects omitted in our study, such as the density waves or higher-m contributions to the azimuthal mass distribution in the disk, short-term fluctuations of the disk potential, may also affect planetesimal dynamics. They may account for some of the difference between the results of this work, which uses secular, time-averaged description of the disk and binary potential, and direct numerical studies of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kley &amp; Nelson (2007) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fragner et al. (2011)</ref>. Planetesimal eccentricity can be additionally excited by the stochastic gravitational perturbations due to the turbulence in the disk. This issue has been previously investigated for disks around single stars ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Ida et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Yang et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Yang et al. , 2012</ref>) and for circumbinary disks <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Meschiari 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Coplanarity of the disk and the binary orbit is another restriction, that can be easily eliminated in future studies. We believe that small but non-zero inclination (Xie &amp; Zhou 2009) would not affect our solutions for the behavior of planetesimal eccentricity. However, as shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Xie et al. (2010)</ref>, such non-zero inclination has strong effect on planetesimal collision rates.</p><p>There is also room for improvement within the framework of our model. Some approximations that we adopt such as the power law behavior of Σ(a) and e d (a), constant 3 ̟ d (a) are dictated by our desire to obtain ana-lytical solutions using the results of SR13 whenever possible. Also, we did not investigate the conditions under which our model (1) represents a steady-state solution for a fluid disk perturbed by a companion <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Statler 2001)</ref>. More refined semi-analytical or numerical calculations using improved disk models are certainly desirable but are unlikely to seriously affect our results and conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">SUMMARY.</head><p>We studied secular dynamics of planetesimals and explored prospects for planet formation around one of the components of an eccentric binary. We believe that our study includes most, if not all, of the important physical ingredients relevant for this problem -perturbations due to the binary, gas drag, and gravitational effects of an eccentric disk. This is the first time planetesimal dynamics in binaries have been studied analytically in such generality. The analytical nature of our solutions for planetesimal dynamical variables allowed us to explore their dependence on system parameters in great detail.</p><p>Our main results can be summarized as follows:</p><p>• We find that under the action of gas drag as well as the gravitational effects of the binary companion and the eccentric disk, planetesimal eccentricity vector e p converges to a constant value depending on the planetesimal size and the disk and binary properties. We obtained complete analytical solutions for e p in the case of non-precessing disk and analyzed them in detail, extending results of previous studies.</p><p>• We showed that relative particle-gas (equation (33)) and particle-particle velocities can be expressed as simple functions of only two key parameters -the characteristic eccentricity e c and planetesimal size d/d c in units of characteristic size d c , given by equations (29) and (31). Behavior of these variables has been explored in detail in §7.</p><p>• We show that in massive disks containing enough gas to form giant planets (M d 10 −2 M ⊙ ) planetesimal dynamics is always in the regime when apsidal precession of planetesimal orbits is dominated by disk gravity, i.e. in the DB or DD regimes in classification of SR13. Significantly eccentric (e 0 10 −3 ) disks also dominate eccentricity excitation of planetesimals by their gravity (DD regime). This emphasizes the key role of the disk gravity in relation to planet formation in binaries.</p><p>• We derive the explicit form of the relative velocity distribution between the populations of planetesimals with different sizes and show that it depends only on the relative eccentricity e 12 of the approaching objects.</p><p>• In disks aligned with the binary planetesimals collide with lower velocities than in mis-aligned disks. Thus, planetesimal growth favors disk-binary apsidal alignment.</p><p>• We also present analytical results for the dynamics of planetesimals in precessing disks in certain limits.</p><p>Our results will be used in Paper II to understand planet formation in small separation binaries, such as γ Cep and α Cen. They can also be used to understand the circumbinary planet formation.</p><p>We are grateful to Jihad Touma for useful discussions.</p><p>Assuming that fluid in a gaseous disk also moves on eccentric Keplerian orbits, motion of the gas can be represented by analogous equations</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">x g = b g − a 0 (k g cos n p t + h g sin n p t), y g = ψ g − 3 2 n p b g t + 2a 0 (k g sin n p t − h g cos n p t).<label>(A3)</label></formula><p>Relative motion of a particular fluid element and a particle is described using relative coordinates x r = x p − x g , y r = y p − y g . According to equations (A2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">x r = b r − a p (k r cos n p t + h r sin n p t), y r = ψ r − 3 2 n p b r t + 2a p (k r sin n p t − h r cos n p t),<label>(A4)</label></formula><p>where k r ≡ k p − k g , h r ≡ h p − h g are the components of the relative eccentricity vector, b r ≡ b p − b g is the semi-major axis separation between the particle and fluid element, and ψ r ≡ ψ p − ψ g . We have also used the fact that a g ≈ a 0 ≈ a p and switched from a 0 to a p . Velocity of Keplerian motion in the local approximation is obtained by differentiating equations (A4) with respect to time. In particular, relative particle-gas velocity is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">v x,r = n p a p (k r sin n p t − h r cos n p t), v y,r = − 3 2 n p b r + 2n p a p (k r cos n p t + h r sin n p t).<label>(A5)</label></formula><p>Analogous formulae apply to the relative motion of two planetesimals with sizes d 1 and d 2 , with the replacement e r → e 12 , b r → b 12 , (x r , y r ) → (x 12 , y 12 ), and so on. In particular, equation (A4) shows that two objects with |b 12 | &lt; a p e 12 can experience close approaches. When this happens x 12 = y 12 = 0 and b 12 can be eliminated from equation (A5) giving</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">v 12,y (x 12 = 0) = 1 2 n p a p (k 12 cos n p t + h 12 sin n p t),<label>(A6)</label></formula><p>(here e 12 = (k 12 , h 12 )) so that the relative approach velocity (i.e. the velocity unaffected by the mutual gravitational attraction of particles) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">v 12 = n p a p k 2 12 + h 2 12 − (3/4)(k 12 cos n p t + h 12 sin n p t) 2 1/2 . (A7)</formula><p>Whenever particle is affected by forces other than the stellar gravity, i.e. F = 0, solutions (A2) are no longer strictly valid. However, one can still represent particle motion via these solutions, assuming that orbital elements osculate, i.e. evolve in time. <ref type="bibr">Hasegawa &amp; Nakazawa (1991)</ref> derived equations for the orbital element evolution, in particular ˙ a p = ˙ b p = 2F y n p m p , ˙ k p = 1 n p a p m p (2F y cos n p t + F x sin n p t) , ˙ h p = 1 n p a p m p (2F y sin n p t − F x cos n p t) . (A8)</p><p>For a given force expression F these equations, after averaging over the orbital period, represent the extra terms entering the equations (3)-(4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLANETESIMAL ECCENTRICITY IN A PRECESSING DISK IN THE CASE OF LINEAR DRAG.</head><p>Here we derive the full time-dependent solution for planetesimal eccentricity starting with arbitrary initial conditions and assuming that the gas drag is linear, i.e. τ d in equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">(17)</ref> is a constant independent of e p . We also include a possibility of the uniform disk precession so that ̟ d (t) = ˙ ̟ d t + ̟ d0 . Then equations (3)-(4) represent a linear system of equations which can be trivially solved to give</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">k(t) h(t) = e free e −t/τ d cos (At + ̟ 0 ) sin (At + ̟ 0 ) + k f h f , (B1)</formula><p>where the first term represents the free eccentricity, with e free and ̟ 0 being constant, while the second is the forced eccentricity e f = (k f , h f ) = e f,b + e f,d , where e f,b is given by equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">(25)</ref> and</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">e f,d = e 2 g + τ 2 d B 2 d 1 + τ 2 d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 2 1/2 cos (̟ d (t) + φ) sin (̟ d (t) + φ) , cos φ = e g − τ 2 d B d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) e 2 g + τ 2 d B 2 d 1/2 1 + τ 2 d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 2 1/2 .<label>(B2)</label></formula><p>In the limit of slow precession | ˙ ̟ d | ≪ |A| one finds that e f is given by expressions (24)- <ref type="bibr">(27)</ref>. Generally, the relative planetesimal-gas eccentricity e r = e f − e g is .-Limit cycles to which relative gas-planetesimal eccentricity vector er converges in precessing disks. Panel (a) shows evolution of the limits cycles as a function of planetesimal size dp, while in panel (b) we vary disk precession rate ˙ ̟ d . Calculations have been performed at ap = 2.5 AU in a standard aligned disk with M d = 10 −3 Mp, e 0 = 0.04, aout = 5 AU in γ Cep system. These parameters place planetesimal dynamics in the strong binary perturbation regime, see §6.1. Crosses mark the centers of the limit cycles computed according to equation <ref type="bibr">(43)</ref>. Note the evolution of the positions and shapes of the limit cycles as dp and ˙ ̟ d are varied.</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">e r = e f,b − τ d B d + e g (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 1 + τ 2 d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 2 1/2 cos (̟ d (t) − φ r ) sin (̟ d (t) − φ r ) , cos φ r = τ d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 1 + τ 2 d (A − ˙ ̟ d ) 2 1/2 .<label>(B3</label></formula><p>Independent of the initial conditions (i.e. the values of e free and ̟ 0 ) the free eccentricity contribution damps out on a characteristic timescale τ d . As a result, in the long run e p inevitably converges to e f .</p><p>In the limit of strong gas drag, τ d → 0, one finds that e f → e g as expected, since drag is strong enough to align planetesimal orbits with fluid trajectories. In this limit the relative eccentricity between planetesimals of different sizes having different damping times τ d,1 and τ d,2 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">e 12 → |A − ˙ ̟ d | |τ d,1 − τ d,2 | (e pr c sin ̟ d ) 2 + e pr c cos ̟ d + k b A A − ˙ ̟ d 2 1/2 , τ d,1 , τ d,2 ≪ |A − ˙ ̟ d | −1 ,<label>(B4)</label></formula><p>where e pr c is given by equation (45). In the opposite extreme τ d → ∞ (weak drag) one finds φ → π and e f reduces to the forced eccentricity value (with disk precession) obtained in SR13. The relative velocity becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">e 12 → 1 |A − ˙ ̟ d | τ −1 d,1 − τ −1 d,2 (e pr c sin ̟ d ) 2 + e pr c cos ̟ d + k b A − ˙ ̟ d A 2 1/2 , τ d,1 , τ d,2 ≫ |A − ˙ ̟ d | −1 . (B5)</formula><p>Note that in this expression k b is multiplied by a factor different from that in equation (B4). However, it is clear that in both limiting cases e 12 ≪ e 1 , e 2 , i.e. the relative planetesimal eccentricity is much less than the individual eccentricities e 1 and e 2 , a result that remains valid in a precessing disk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLANETESIMAL ECCENTRICITY IN A PRECESSING DISK IN THE CASE OF QUADRATIC DRAG.</head><p>In the case of quadratic drag (10) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2b</ref> clearly shows the phenomenon of e p convergence to a quasi-stationary limit cycle behavior, similar to the results of §B. This behavior is further illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9</ref>, where we show the dependence of the limit cycles on planetesimal size d p and disk precession rate ˙ ̟ d . Because of the nonlinear drag law the shapes of the limit cycles in general deviate from ellipses.</p><p>Nevertheless, their gross features still can be understood our linear solution (B3). In particular, limit cycles are not centered on (k r , h r ) = 0 because of the binary companion perturbations, i.e. non-zero e f,b varying as d p (and τ d ) change. Amplitude of the limit cycles goes down for smaller d p because τ d is also smaller, which according to equation (B3) reduces the oscillating contribution to e r . As we vary ˙ ̟ d in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9b</ref> the binary contribution stays unchanged and all limits cycles stay centered on the same point in h r -k r space.</p><p>Their sizes ary with ˙ ̟ d as predicted by equation (B3). They shrink at high | ˙ ̟ d | ∼ |A|, in agreement with equation (B3). For slow precession | ˙ ̟ d | ≪ |A| limit cycles converge to the trajectory for the non-precessing disk solution (24) in which ̟ d is set to vary as ̟ d (t) = ˙ ̟ d t + ̟ d0 . Note that such convergence to solution (24) is obvious only in the case of | ˙ ̟ d τ d | ≪ 1, i.e. when gas drag allows e p to quickly readjust to a new "quasi-static" solution as ̟ d changes. This is the case shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9b</ref>. In the opposite case of | ˙ ̟ d τ d | ≫ 1 (and | ˙ ̟ d | ≪ |A|) this convergence is not obvious as the disk precession constantly drives free eccentricity, while the gas drag is not strong enough to quickly damp it. We leave detailed exploration of such details to a future study. Now, let us rewrite equations (3)-(4) in terms of the relative particle-gas eccentricity components k r and h r :</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">dh r dt = Ak r − h r τ d + B b + [(A − ˙ ̟ d ) e g + B d ] cos ̟ d (t),<label>(C1)</label></formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2.-(a) Planetesimal eccentricity evolution trajectories in kr − hr space in a non-precessing, aligned (̟ d = 0) disk for the four cases shown in Figure 1. One can see the convergence of trajectories starting at different ep to fixed point solutions (indicated by crosses), which depend on planetesimal radius dp. (b) Same for a disk precessing at the rate of ˙ ̟ d = A. Evolution trajectories converge to a limit cycle behavior in the precessing disk. See §6 for more details. Color and line type scheme is the same for both panels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>in Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>It reveals the mean- ing of the characteristic size d c : objects with d p ∼ d c have |Aτ d | ∼ 1, i.e. their stopping time due to gas drag is comparable to their orbital precession period, and their relative eccentricity with respect to gas is e r ∼ e c .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Planetesimal orbits are aligned with the binary (̟ p → 0) for |Aτ d | → ∞ (weak drag), but in the case of strong drag |Aτ d | → 0 planetes- imal apsidal line points at ̟ d = 270 • , which agrees with Marzari &amp; Scholl (2000) despite the disk precession.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>7. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Behavior of e c . In Figure 4a,b we show e c computed for γ Cep system at 2 AU -the semi-major axis of its planet -as a function of disk mass M d and eccentricity e 0 , for two disk orientations -aligned (̟ d = 0) and anti-aligned (̟ d = π) with the apsidal line of the binary. One can immediately see a feature common to both panels -a narrow valley of high e c (white because of saturation at high e c ) at almost constant M d . It appears because at this value of disk mass A d = −A b and A = 0,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Map of the characteristic eccentricity ec as a function of e 0 and M d (upper panels) for two different disk orientations -̟ d = 0 (a) and (b) -and as a function of ap and M d for two values of disk eccentricity e 0 at aout (lower panels). Calculation is done for γ Cep system at ap = 2 AU (the observed semi-major axis of the planet). The dashed red line corresponds to Mp sin i for the observed planet in the γ Cephei system. The purple line is where |A d | = |A b |, and the blue line is where |B d | = |B b |. See text for details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>-( 8 )</head><label>8</label><figDesc>. Given that B d ∝ e 0 M d it is then obvious that one can make e c ≈ 0 by choosing e 0 M d such that |B b | ≈ |B d |/3. Thus, in the case of an aligned disk a "valley" of low e c is described by the relation e 0 ∝ M −1 d as long as |A d | |A b | (i.e. for massive disks).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>,d is the same valley of stability, but now revealing itself in M d − a p coordinates 2 . It may lie inside (for low e 0 ) as well as outside (for high e 0 ) of the secular resonance. Note that in Figure 4c the |A d | = |A b | and |B d | = |B b | curves fall almost on top of each other, which is a coincidence caused by our choice of e 0 = 0.1 in this case. Because of that the valley of stability appears as a very narrow band of low e c just to the left of the |B d | = |B b | curve in this panel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Same as Fig. 4 but for the behavior of the characteristic size dc given by equation (31). sensitive function of the planetesimal precession rate A: d c is smaller for higher |A|. If planetesimal precession is dominated by the potential of the secondary then A = A b , and one finds</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-Distribution of the relative approach velocity v 12 of colliding planetesimals given by equation (62). Relative velocity is normalized by its maximum value vmax = e 12 npr, where e 12 is the relative eccentricity of the two planetesimals, which is a function of their sizes, see §9.1-9.3. Minimum approach velocity is vmax/2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-Relative approach velocity (right color bar) and relative eccentricity (left color bar) of planetesimals with sizes d 1 and d 2 experiencing close approach. Calculation is done for γ Cephei system at 2 AU assuming an eccentric disk with p = 1, q = −1 and other disk parameters -M d , e 0 , ̟ d -varying as indicated on the panels. Eccentricity and planetesimal size scales ec and dc in different panels can be inferred from Figures 4a,b and 5a,b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Note.</head><label></label><figDesc>-[1] This work, [2] Giuppone et al. (2011), [3] Heppenheimer (1978), [4] Marzari &amp; Scholl (2000), [5] Paardekooper et al. (2008), [6] Beaugé et al. (2010), [7] Rafikov (2013), [8] Silsbee &amp; Rafikov (2013), [9] Thebault et al. (2006), [10] Xie &amp; Zhou (2008)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-Comparison of different approximations for describing planetesimal dynamics (indicated on panels), as reflected in the map of the relative eccentricity of planetesimals er of different sizes; see text for details. Maps are drawn for an aligned disk in γ Cep at 1AU (note the different semi-major axis compared to other figures).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.-Limit cycles to which relative gas-planetesimal eccentricity vector er converges in precessing disks. Panel (a) shows evolution of the limits cycles as a function of planetesimal size dp, while in panel (b) we vary disk precession rate ˙ ̟ d . Calculations have been performed at ap = 2.5 AU in a standard aligned disk with M d = 10 −3 Mp, e 0 = 0.04, aout = 5 AU in γ Cep system. These parameters place planetesimal dynamics in the strong binary perturbation regime, see §6.1. Crosses mark the centers of the limit cycles computed according to equation (43). Note the evolution of the positions and shapes of the limit cycles as dp and ˙ ̟ d are varied.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>TABLE 1 Different</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>approximations for planetesimal 
dynamics in binaries 

Gravitational effects 
W/o gas drag With gas drag 
included 

Binary companion only 
2,3 
4,5,6,8,9,10 

Axisymmetric disk 
7 
1 
and binary companion 

Non-axisymmetric disk 
8 
1 
and binary companion 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> Department of Astrophysical Sciences, Princeton University, Ivy Lane, Princeton, NJ 08540; rrr@astro.princeton.edu</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4">. DRAG FORCE CALCULATION.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> Curves of |A d | = |A b | and |B d | = |B b | run parallel to each other in Figure 4c,d because e d ∝ ap in our disk model, see equations (5)-(8).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="10">.1. Comparison of different dynamical approximations. The main novelty of our study is the extension of the line of analytical investigation of disk gravity effects, started in R13 and SR13 for axisymmetric and non-axisymmetric disks, respectively, by including gas drag. Previous (semi-)analytical studies of planetesimal dynamics in binaries neglected the gravitational effect of the disk.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Variable ̟ d (a) can be used to describe disks with density waves.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LOCAL APPROXIMATION.</head><p>Here we review local (or guiding center) approximation, which is often used in studies of planetesimal and galactic dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Binney &amp; Tremaine 2008)</ref> and forms the basis of the so-called Hill approximation <ref type="bibr">(Hénon &amp; Petit 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hasegawa &amp; Nakazawa 1990)</ref>. In this approach eccentric motion of a planetesimal is considered in a locally Cartesian frame (x p , y p ), with e x , e y pointing in the radial and horizontal directions, correspondingly. The origin of this frame is in circular Keplerian motion at some characteristic semi-major axis a 0 , which is close to planetesimal semi-major axis a p , so that b p ≡ |a p − a 0 | ≪ a p . Equations of motion for a particle of mass m p subject to external force F = (F x , F y ) can be reduced to</p><p>Provided that e p ≪ 1 one can represent planetesimal motion unperturbed by external forces as</p><p>where ψ p is a constant and e p = (k p , h p ). This is an exact solution of equations (A1) with F = 0 and is a superposition of linear shear and epicyclic motion.</p><p>with τ d given by equation <ref type="formula">(18)</ref> and dependent upon e r . Explicit time dependence of the last terms in these nonlinear equations precludes us from finding their general analytical solutions even in the case of the limit-cycle behavior. However, we can still obtain analytical results for planetesimal eccentricity in the two limiting cases, reviewed next.</p><p>First, one can assume that binary companion dominates eccentricity forcing, which implies that the condition (42) is fulfilled. Then one can drop last ̟ d -dependent terms in equations (C1)-(C2) removing the explicit time dependence from them. This is essentially equivalent to neglecting both the gravitational effect of the disk, i.e. |e d | → 0, and the gas eccentricity e g compared to |e b |. As a result, we find a steady-state solution (43) for k r ≈ k p and h r ≈ h p , which is essentially the equations <ref type="formula">(22)</ref>- <ref type="formula">(23)</ref> with |e d |, |e g | → 0. Then planetesimal dynamics is described by the analytical results of §5 with e c ≈ |B b /A|.</p><p>In the opposite extreme of weak eccentricity excitation by the binary companion we introduce new coordinates <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Beaugé et al. 2010</ref> for a similar treatment). Then the evolution of H and K is given by</p><p>When the eccentricity excitation by the companion is small we can drop the B b terms in these equations, removing the explicit time-dependence, which appears because of circulating k g and h g . As a result, we find the steady state solutions for H and K in the implicit form</p><p>where τ d is a function of the relative particle-gas eccentricity e r = e −1</p><p>given by equation (44). This solution corresponds to eccentricity vector e p fixed in a disk frame, which uniformly precesses at the rate ˙ ̟ d . Using these solutions it is trivial to show that e p → e f,d given by equation (B2) with B b set to zero. That in the weak binary perturbation regime we find the same expression for e p as in the case of linear drag is not surprising: with B b = 0 one finds that |e r | is constant in time, so that τ d is also constant. Then equations (C3)-(C4) are the same as in the linear drag case and have the same steady state solutions (C5).</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Adachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Theor. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1756</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Artymowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lubow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">638</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">478</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Batygin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tsiganis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leiva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haghighipour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">503</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Binney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Galactic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Dynamics</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Beust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eggenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eggenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Beuzit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Perrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Sivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ségransan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">479</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">271</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Desidera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">345</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dumusque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">491</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dvorak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">OAWMN</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">423</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fragner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A40</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Giuppone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leiva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Correa-Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A103</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">530</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wilner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">751</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hasegawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">227</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">619</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hatzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. 133</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">770</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hatzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Paulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">599</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1383</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Henon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Petit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dynam. Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heppenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kokubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Makino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">263</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1292</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:0705.3421</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">486</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">617</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ogilvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">487</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">671</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kozai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">591</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leiva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Correa-Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">436</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3772</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lidov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P&amp;SS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">719</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">543</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">328</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thebault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A98</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">539</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">507</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">508</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1493</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meschiari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. L7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">761</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mizuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Progr. Theor. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W A</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A18</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">539</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solar System Dynamics Ogilvie</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">231</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Okazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ogilvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">337</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">967</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mellema</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">386</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">973</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Picogna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id.A148</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">556</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rafikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. L8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">765</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>Regály</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>Sándor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dullemond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. A93</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Silsbee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rafikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1309.3290</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Statler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">524</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Statler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2257</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Turrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">427</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1097</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">193</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1528</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thébault</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CeMDA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Touma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wisdom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1653</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Veras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">661</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1311</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1309.7097</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">164</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Windmark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Birnstiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ormel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dullemond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. L16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">570</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">698</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2066</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">708</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-M</forename><surname>Mac Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">707</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1233</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-M</forename><surname>Mac Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. 79</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">748</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">749</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">172</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">695</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
