<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:07+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An Algorithm for correcting CoRoT raw light curves</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010-07-29">29 Jul 2010 November 1, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mislis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Hamburger Sternwarte</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gojenbergsweg 112</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-21029</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H M M</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Hamburger Sternwarte</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gojenbergsweg 112</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-21029</postCode>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carone</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Rheinisches Institut für Umweltforschung</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Abteilung Planetenforschung</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Köln</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aachener Str. 209</addrLine>
									<postCode>50931</postCode>
									<settlement>Köln</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Thüringer Landessternwarte Tautenburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sternwarte 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-07778</postCode>
									<settlement>Tautenburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pätzold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Rheinisches Institut für Umweltforschung</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Abteilung Planetenforschung</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Köln</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Aachener Str. 209</addrLine>
									<postCode>50931</postCode>
									<settlement>Köln</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An Algorithm for correcting CoRoT raw light curves</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2010-07-29">29 Jul 2010 November 1, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Accepted ?? July 2010</note>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. aa c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>methods: data analysis</term>
					<term>surveys</term>
					<term>planetary systems</term>
					<term>stars: variables</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We introduce the CoRoT Detrend Algorithm (CDA) for detrending CoRoT stellar light curves. CDA has the capability to remove random jumps and systematic trends encountered in typical CoRoT data in a fully automatic fashion. Since huge jumps in flux can destroy the information content of a light curve, such an algorithm is essential. From a study of 1030 light curves in the CoRoT IRa01 field we developed three simple assumptions CDA is based upon. In this paper we describe analytically the algorithm and we provide some examples of how it works. We demonstrate its functionality of the algorithm in the cases of CoRoT0102702789, CoRoT0102874481, CoRoT0102741994 and CoRoT0102729260. Using CDA in the specific case of CoRoT0102729260 we detect a candidate exoplanet around the host star of spectral type G5, which remains undetected in the raw light curve; the estimated planetary parameters are R p = 6.27R E and P = 1.6986 days.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The CoRoT satellite was successfully launched in 2006. On board CoRoT there is a small 27cm telescope feeding two science channels to study astroseismology and transits respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Baglin et al. 2000)</ref>. The CoRoT has a field of view (FOV) of ∼ 2.7 o x 3.05 o . In its first field (IRa01 -α = 6 h 46 m 53 s &amp; δ = −00 o 12 ′ 00"), CoRoT had observed continuously for 60 days, producing uninterrupted light curves for the first time. The data from the IRa01 have been public since December 2008 and the astronomical community has access to these data. Unfortunately, the CoRoT light curves are affected by a variety of instrumental problems, which severely hamper the data interpretation. In order to overcome these difficulties we have developed the CoRot Detrend Algorithm (CDA). In this paper the algorithm is presented and demonstrate its function on some typical CoRoT data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">CoRoT light curves: The problems</head><p>The CoRoT data files contain multi-color light curves, produced by inserting a low-resolution dispersing prism into the telescope beam. With this set-up it is intended to provide simultaneous light curves in the red (R), green (G) and blue (B) bands, however, these bands do not correspond to true photometric filters and, in fact, the bands may differ from star to star. We study the multi-color data in this paper, but also consider the total (white) flux obtained by summing up the individual light curves through W = R + G + B. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> are typical CoRoT light curves from IRa01. The first panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> shows a typical exponential jump very similar to a flare star. A trend is also evident. In the second light curve there appears a box-shape jump, in the third and fourth light curves one finds features similar as in the first and second light curves, except that the jumps are downwards. We note that the downward jump in the third light curve is very similar to a transit event, thus making the detection of true transits difficult. Combinations of all the above features appear, in fact a rather typical CoRoT light curve. Essentially, two basic instrumental problems appear in all CoRoT light curves: First, there is a long-term trend, forcing a secular decrease of the light curve intensity over the full observing period of 60 days. The strengths of the trends in different sources may be different; the physical cause of these trends is not well understood. The second and even more serious problem is the instrumental jumps in the light curves. The term "jump" refers to a sudden variation of intensity without any obvious reason. Many of these jumps do in fact look like stellar flares, however, the vast majority of these features is clearly instrumental. The physical explanation for these jumps could be, cosmic radiation and the time evolution of bright pixels (Pinheiro da <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Silva et al. 2008</ref>). These jumps are a random phenomenon and affect each filter differently. An inspection of hundreds of CoRoT light curves similar to those presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> allows to classify the observed shapes of jumps into five groups:</p><p>-Sudden intensity increase and exponentially decrease ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> -panel a) -Sudden intensity increase and decreases (box shape, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> panel b) -Sudden intensity decrease and exponentially increase afterwards ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> -panel c) -Sudden intensity decrease and increase (negative box shape, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> -panel d) -All of the combinations above ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 -panel e)</ref> A statistical analysis of IRa01 field (visual inspection) shows that only a small minority <ref type="table">(Table 1</ref>) of all jumps is so powerful that they simultaneously appear in each colour. Most of the light  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Statistical analysis of 1030 CoRoT light curves from IRa01. Jumps appear in more than 50% of all light curves in all filters; in 0.82% of all light curves jumps in all filters occur at the same time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R f ilter G f ilter B f ilter T otal</head><p>38.14% 14.4% 15.1% 67.6% curves are affected not only by one single jump, but by many jumps occurring in the different filters at different times. In <ref type="table">Table  1</ref> we show the results of a statistical study of the appearance and the shapes of jumps using data form IRa01. The three first columns of <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> show the number of light curves which suffer from jumps in the respective filter filter and the fourth column shows the total amount.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The CDA Algorithm</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">General features</head><p>It is quite difficult to describe all the features perturbing CoRoT light curve with a given function, since there are many different shapes of jumps with many different functional forms. Furthermore, the problem is complex, because we do not know which of light curve features are real signals (real transits, real flares etc.) or instrumental effects. The algorithm is based on three assumptions: (a) trends appear in almost all light curves and both flux increases and decreases can occur. The trends are not periodic and we assume them to be a long-term phenomenon ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aigrain et al. 2009</ref>). (b) The second assumption also accrues from the statistical analysis of the data. The study of 1030 light curves from IRa01 field shows that only 0.82 % of them are affected by a jump in all three filters at the same time. In these cases the jump is very large and affects all bands with the same temporal pattern, however, in most cases the jumps affect only one band at any given time <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2)</ref>, and we therefore ignore those cases where jumps occur simultaneously in all three bands. (c) Real transits must appear in all three filters, while, of course, the intensity and transit depth can vary from filter to filter. In summary, for the CDA we assume that -Long term trends appear in all CoRoT light curves -Jumps are random phenomena appearing in different filters at different times. -The real signals from transits appear in all three bands We emphasize that CDA works only for events (like transits), which appear in two or more bands; CDA does not work for stellar flares, since most stellar flares do not show any flux enhancements in the red and green band, but in the blue band. Under these circumstances CDA will destroy real signals, unless the flare is so powerful to appear in all bands.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">The algorithm</head><p>CDA uses all the colour light curve simultaneously of each star to remove the instrumental features. The basic idea of CDA is to use the cleanest filter band as a proxy for the whole light curve. The raw data files of each CoRoT light curve have a quality flag (CoRoT files -column 4), indicating the quality of each data point ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Mazeh et al. 2009</ref>). We first remove all these "bad points" (points with high noise flagged by CoRoT); note that these "bad points" are same for all the filters per star. In this paper we will use light curves with all "bad points" already removed (as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.  1</ref>). As noted above in our first assumption, trends are a longterm phenomenon. A 3 rd degree polynomial is fit to the entire light curve in order to remove the trend in each filter per star. Because each CoRoT light curve typically has thousands of data points, the polynomial does not fit short-term variations and real short-term events like transits. We thus write</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Flux = a + b · JD + c · JD 2 + d · JD 3 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where JD is the Julian date (normalized to range −1 ≤ JD ≤ 1) and a, b, c and d are the fit parameters for the third degree polynomial. At the end of this procedure, we have a detrended light curve per filter for each star. After this step CDA proceeds to remove the jumps. In order to identify the cleanest light curve for a reliable jump removal we create "sub-light curves", which we typical take with a duration of a day. Thus, for the IRa01 field we create 60 "sublight" curves, called simply light curves in the following. These 60 blocks were selected after we checked various combinations. If the number of blocks are too large, then transit signals are reduced, and if the number of blocks are too small, the probability to include a jump in the "sublight" curve increases. Let us assume that there are three full light curves for a given star in each band with N points per light curve; denote by F R,i , F G,i and F B,i with i = 1, N the individual data values in the red, green and blue filters, respectively. Then we divide each color light curve in 60 sub-light curves (one sub-light curve per day for IRa01 -60 days). For each sub-light curve we calculate the mean value MR, MG and MB and normalize each sub-light curve by its mean value; we compute new, normalized sub-light curves NF through</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">NF R,G,B,i = F R,G,B,i M R,G,B<label>(2)</label></formula><p>for each filter band and it is clear that all of these light curves have a mean of unity. This normalization is necessary since otherwise the whole process would be dominated by the light curve with the highest signal, which is usually the red light curve. As a side effect, CDA normalizes the depth of a possible transit in all filters using equation 2, so when the algorithm continues with its next steps, all transit events in each filter will have the same depth and thus CDA does not destroy real signals from the transits.</p><p>The normalized light curves have now the same mean, their dispersions will, however, differ. Our next goal is to identify the instrumental scatter, caused, for example by jumps, in each light curve and disentangle this instrumental scatter from statistical noise. In order to achieve this, CDA extracts five random packages of twenty adjacent points each from all colour bands and calculates the standard deviation of each package per filter; the result should represent a good estimate of the correct light curve value at that time. If we use many packages the probability to include jumps increases. The correct combination packages-points is a function of the duration of the jumps which is a random value, thus there is no a fix combination. We define as the mean standard deviation (MS D), the mean value of these five packages of each filter</p><note type="other">4 D. Mislis et. al.: An Algorithm for correcting CoRoT raw light curves</note><formula xml:id="formula_2">MS D R,G,B = 1 5 5 j=1 1 20 k j +20 i=k j (NF R,G,B,i − Mean min ) 2 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where the induces k j denotes 5 different random data points of the light curve and Mean min is the mean value of the flux of each package. In general, each filter has a different MS D value, which is compared with the standard deviation of each filter T S D defined through</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">T S D R,G,B = 1 N N i=1 (NF R,G,B,i − Mean min ) 2<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Finally, the relative standard deviation of each filter RSD is computed and defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">RS D R,G,B = T S D R,G,B MS D R,G,B .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>At the end of this process we have three normalized light curves NF R,i NF G,i and NF B,i , and three values for the relative standard deviation RS D R , RS D G and RS D B for each filter light curve respectively. CDA compares these three numbers and calls the light curve with the minimum RSD the base and the light curve with the maximum RSD, target. To make the procedure more understandable we continue with an example: Suppose the base is the blue light curve (NF B,i ) and the target is the red (NF R,i ) light curve. Using base and target CDA calculates a new mean light curve (AF i ); in our example CDA computes</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">AF i = 1 2 (NF R,i + NF B,i ).<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and then it recalls the AF i as the light curve with the maximum RSD (in this example recall AF i as NF R,i ). According to assumptions 2 and 3, in the AF i light curve remains any possible real signal but all the fake (jumps) tend to be reduced, because jumps appear only at specific times in each filter. As a final result we will have a red light curve reduced and two others (green and blue) untouched. If we try to run the algorithm again we will notice that the new values of RSD have changed because one light curve has changed. This means that every time we run the previous step of the algorithm, CDA removes a part of a fake signal <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 3)</ref>.</p><p>When these loops end, we re-normalize the final light curve of the red channel to the raw mean value,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">NFR f inal = NR · NF R,i<label>(7)</label></formula><p>and the procedure has been completed. NFR f inal is the final sub-light curve. The final step is to put all the 60 sub-light curves together. This is the final light curve and we are ready to search for exoplanets <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Fig. 5)</ref>. Of course we use many loops for procedure, but if we use too many, CDA starts to destroy the light curve because it is obvious that after some loops there is a "saturation" in the procedure. To avoid this effect, we do not use the same loop number of each light curve. We calculate the standard deviation of each light curve after each loop and CDA stops when the standard deviation starts to increases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Simulations</head><p>In order to verify the functionality of CDA, we simulated CoRoT light curves as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>. We specifically simulated a light curve in three filters (R,G,B), where jumps and trends appear at different times in each filter; also a long-term trend is included. In these light curve a transit pattern with period P=520 time units and a relative depth ∆Flux = 0.01 is included. The transits are masked by the high noise. As can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>, all jumps are removed and the resulting output light curve shows some regions with higher noise and some others with lower noise, but this does not affect the real signal. Applying transit detection algorithms (e.g. Box Least Squares -BLS <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Kovács et al. (2002)</ref>), the included transit pattern is also detected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head><p>In order to illustrate the algorithm with real light curves, CDA is applied to four CoRoT light curves, i.e., CoRoT0102702789, CoRoT0102874481, CoRoT0102741994 and CoRoT0102729260.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">The case of CoRoT0102702789</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 5</ref> we show the raw red light curve which includes a trend and jumps and the final light curve after applying CDA with 5 loops. The light curve of CoRoT012702789 has one huge jump around JD ∼ 2614 and many other smaller jumps. The RS D R value of the raw light curve is 5.048 and the final light curve is 0.95. <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 2</ref> shows analytically the values of RSD from the total light curves, in these 10 loops of each filter. The green filter has the minimum value and thus CDA uses it as a base. The red filter on the other hand has the maximum value and we call it target, but in principal CDA defines different filters as base or target in each loop. For this reason in the first four loops the target is the red filter and base the green filter, then target changes to blue and green remains as base etc.; as already mentioned, the red light curve as the most common filter to search for transits.</p><p>The example of CoRoT012702789 shows us how CDA works and how it removes jumps from a distorted light curve. As far as we can tell from out reconstructed light curve, there are no clear flares or transits in the light curve of CoRoT012702789.</p><p>The critical question at this point is how CDA works if the raw light curve has real events like transits.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 2</ref> shows how RSD is changing in each loop. In the first four loops, red filter is the target and green the base. In loop five this situations has changed. Blue is the target now and green is the base. These values refers to the RSD values of the full light curve of each filter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Loop No RS D R RS D G RS D B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>♯1</head><p>5.0485 0.9497 1.0658 ♯2</p><p>1.8632 0.9497 1.0658 ♯3</p><p>1 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">The case of CoRoT0102874481</head><p>An even more extreme case is CoRoT0102874481. The light curve of which is affected by many jumps; the raw (red) light curve of CoRoT0102874481 is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref>. In the raw data it is very difficult to distinguish real from instrumental events.</p><p>As demonstrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref>,CDA corrects all the jumps except for a real transit around JD ∼ 2612. The standard deviation before and after CDA is 2203.13 and 336.44 ADUs, respectively. Only a small jump from green and blue filters remains at the end of light curve. Because this transit is the only transit in the light curve, we cannot determine the period and the nature of the transiting object. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 7</ref> shows that CDA does not reduce the depth of the transit, which is ∼ 0.036. According to the CoRoT team  (http://idoc-corot.ias.u-psud.fr), the host star's spectral type is A0IV. Assuming the typical radius and mass of such a star as R s = 4.4R o and M s = 2.8M o and assuming the transiting object to be a true exoplanet, we determine the planet's radius as R p = 4.28R J by using the relation between radius and transit depth <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Seager &amp; Mallén-Ornelas 2003</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">R p = R s · √ ∆Flux,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where R s is the radius of the star and R p is the radius of the planet. From Kepler's 3 rd law the semi-major axis of the orbit is α &gt; 0.78AU, because the period is P &gt; 60 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">The case of CoRoT0102741994</head><p>CoRoT0102741994 seems to be a binary system. Our main interest in this example is not to check if CDA can remove the jump but to check how the algorithm preserves the eclipses and the flux of the light curve. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 8</ref> shows how the algorithm converts the light curve. The light curve is affected only by a week jump (∆Flux ∼ 1.25%) around JD ∼ 2615. The flux depth of the primary and secondary eclipse is 9% and 7%, respectively. At the top figure is the light curve of the star before the application of CDA. The two eclipses are obvious, while the bottom figure shows the light curve after application of CDA. Clearly, the jump is removed completely. The depth of the primary and secondary eclipses now are 9.5% and 6.5% respectively. As a general result we can say that CDA does not remove the real signal but corrects the jumps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">The case of CoRoT0102729260</head><p>Finally, the case of CoRoT0102729260, is a combination of strong and weak jumps and trends. The raw light curve of CoRoT0102729260 does not show any transits. It is interesting to note that a transit detection algorithm like BLS does not detect any transit event in this light curve <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 10, top panel)</ref>. However, having applied CDA to remove all jumps, we implement again BLS on the final light curve and a possible transit appears <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">(Fig.  9, bottom panel)</ref>.</p><p>This transit is only detectable after applying CDA, but not in the raw data. Our analysis of the phased light curve suggests are period of P = 1.6986 days. The photometry by the CoRoT team (http://idoc-corot.ias.u-psud.fr) provides some information   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref> shows the phase folded light curves. Also <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 3</ref> gives some additional information of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>We have introduced and presented a method dubbed CDA that removes instrumental artefacts from CoRoT data and demonstrated its usefulness in some practical applications. We emphasize that the CDA algorithm prepares CoRoT data for any transit detection; it should not be used for transit analysis since it is contingent to remove some real signal. Of course this is not a problem for the detection inasmuch instrumental jumps destroy much more the light curve. From our study of 1030 light curves in the first CoRoT field (IRao01) we found that only very few Down: Final light curve after CDA. The algorithm succeed to remove all the jumps and trends and improve the light curve enough to detect the "concealed" transit.</p><p>light curves have no instrumentally caused features and remain as they are, while the vast majority of light curves are appreciably improved. We present some examples which show how the algorithm affects the light curves. Our main theme is that instrumental jumps substantially affect the CoRoT light curves, making a transit detection in fainter stars impossible. In order to present how the algorithm affect the full sample, we calculated the Median Absolute Deviation (MAD) before and after appling CDA. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref> shows the differences between the two procedures.</p><p>We prove our case with the example of CoRoT0102729260, a possible candidate exoplanet which is detected only after applying CDA on the raw data.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Jumps and trends in CoRoT light curves. CoRoT01027-21492</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. CoRoT0102729260. Three filter light curves (R (a), G (b), B (c)) from a data set. The jumps in red light curve does not appear in the other filters and vice versa.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Standard deviation vs number of blocks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig 3 shows the best block number vs standard deviation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Simulated data. R -(a), G -(b) and B -(c) color respectively. Plot (d) is the final light curve after CDA and the plot (e) is the phase diagram of the transit after CDA &amp; BLS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. CoRoT012874481 -red filter Top: Raw light curve. Bottom: The same light curve after CDA. Jumps are removed and a clear transit is appearing. The subframe is a zoom-in plot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. CoRoT012702789 red light curve and CDA results. Raw data -(a), after 1 -(b), 3 -(c), 5 -(d) loops respectively. All jumps are removed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. CoRoT012874481 residuals before minus after CDA. The signal from the real transit is not reduced by the algorithm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. CoRoT012741994 -red filter Up: Raw data. We just remove all the "bad points". The light curve suffers from one jump around JD ∼ 2615 and a trend. Down: The same light curve after CDA. The jumps is reduced. CDA does not effects the transit depth.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. CoRoT0102729260 -red filter. Up: Raw data before CDA. Down: Final light curve after CDA. The algorithm succeed to remove all the jumps and trends and improve the light curve enough to detect the "concealed" transit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. CoRoT0102729260 -red filter. Up: Periodogramm of the raw light curve before CDA without any obvious signal. Down: Same plot after CDA. A clear periodic signal (P ∼ 1.698) is detected.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. CoRoT0102729260. Top: A Phase folded light curve before CDA. Bottom: A phase folded light curve after CDA.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Median Absolute Deviation (MAD) before and after CDA using 1030 lightcurve sample.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 2 . CoRoT01270289.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Physical Parameters of CoRoT0102729260. 

Color Index 
0.752 
S tar Radius R s 0.91R o 
Period 
1.6986 days 
Planet Radius R p 6.27R E 
Depth (Flux) 
0.004 

for the parameter of the host star, which appears to be a main 
sequence star (G5V) of apparent brightness m V = 14.772 mags. 
Assuming the spectral type to be correct, we can estimate the 
radius of the star R s ∼ 0.91R o . With a transit depth of ∆Flux = 
0.004, we deduce a planetary radius of R p = 6.27R E applying 
Eq. 8. </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aigrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">åp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">425</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vauclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Corot</forename><surname>The</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Team</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Astrophysics and Astronomy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">319</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kovács</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">391</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">369</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Guterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aigrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">åp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">431</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pinheiro Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rolland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lapeyrere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Auvergne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1337</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mallén-Ornelas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1038</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
