<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Estimations of orbital parameters of exoplanets from transit photometry by using dynamical constraints</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-06-01">1 Jun 2006</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zsolt</forename><surname>Sándor</surname></persName>
							<email>zs.sandor@astro.elte.hu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Eötvös University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H-1117</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest, Pázmány Péter stny. 1/A</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Estimations of orbital parameters of exoplanets from transit photometry by using dynamical constraints</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-06-01">1 Jun 2006</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>exoplanets</term>
					<term>planetary transit</term>
					<term>three-body problem</term>
					<term>stability</term>
					<term>chaos de- tection</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The probability of the detection of Earth-like exoplanets may increase in the near future after the launch of the space missions using the transit photometry as observation method. By using this technique only the semi-major axis of the detected planet can be determined, and there will be no information on the upper limit of its orbital eccentricity. However, the orbital eccentricity is a very important parameter, not only from a dynamical point of view, since it gives also information on the climate and the habitability of the Earth-like planets. In this paper a possible procedure is suggested for confining the eccentricity of an exoplanet discovered by transit photometry if an already known giant planet orbits also in the system.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In the last decade, following the discovery of the first extrasolar planet around 51 Pegasi ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Mayor and Queloz 1995)</ref>, more than 168 exoplanets have been observed. The detection of exoplanets is of great importance, since they form planetary systems around their hosting stars, and by studying the main properties of these exoplanetary systems, the characteristics, formation and evolution of the Solar System can be treated and understood from a wider perspective. However, the above picture is rather ideal than complete yet, since the exoplanets observed until now are mainly Jupiter-like gas giants. This is a consequence of the fact that by using radial-velocity measurements, which is the most effective ground-based observing technique, it is not possible to detect Earthlike planets yet. (We note, however, that the detection of a ∼ 8M ⊕ planet by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Rivera et al. (2005)</ref> indicates that radial velocity searches might be able to detect Earth-like planets in the future.)</p><p>The most compelling question related to exoplanetary research is the detection of Earth-like planets. Beside their importance in testing and improving formation theories of planetary systems, a major question is their habitability. If an Earth-like planet orbits in the habitable zone of a star, there could be chances of appearing (water based) life on its surface. On the habitable zone we mean that region around a star, where liquid water can exist on the surface of a planet, for details see in ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Kasting et al. 1993)</ref>.</p><p>In order to find Earth-like planets, there are space missions in construction and planning phase. Such a mission is COROT (sponsored by CNES, ESA and other countries) to be launched in 2006, and the Kepler Mission (NASA) with a launch in 2008. These missions will use the transit photometry as detection technique, which is based on measuring the periodic dimming of a star's light intensity caused by an unseen transiting planet. Observations performed by these instruments will provide the semi-major axis a of the transiting planet calculated from Kepler's third law by measuring the period T of the transits, and assuming that the mass m * of the hosting star is known. Since m * is known only with limited accuracy, an uncertainty appears in a.</p><p>(We note that m * can be determined by spectroscopic observations and by stellar model calculations.) The error appearing in a and in the eccentricity e of the transiting planet due to the uncertainties in stellar mass will be estimated in 3.2.</p><p>In this paper we present a procedure which can be used to estimate the orbital eccentricity and inclination of a transiting planet, if (i) we can measure the duration of the transit, and (ii) there is another (giant) planet in the system. We shall see that an equation can be derived, which connects the mass and the radius R of the star, the semi-major axis a, the eccentricity e, the argument of the periastron ω, the inclination i of the transiting planet, and the duration τ of the transit. In this equation there are three unknowns, e, ω, and i. By fixing i, the corresponding (ω, e) pairs can be visualized as curves on the ω − e parameter plane. Thus the problem is underdetermined and there is no way to give an upper limit for e. We note that during one revolution of the transiting planet, in principle there are two minima in the light curve of the star. The first minimum occurs when the planet moves in front of the star, the second appears when the star is between the observer and the planet. The maximum of the light curve can be observed when both the star and the planet are visible. By using the second minimum observation, the eccentricity of the transiting planet can be estimated. However, the maximum and the second minimum of the light curve can not be seen in the case of an Earth-like planet, since its contribution to the whole light flux is not detectable. (The light curve is the variation of the light intensity of the star as a function of the orbital phase of the transiting planet.)</p><p>On the other hand, as suggested by planetary formation scenarios, we expect that beside Earth-like planets Jupiter-like giant planets can also be found in the majority of planetary systems. Having discovered an Earth-like planet around a star, by using complementary techniques (as observations by Space Interferometry Mission and ground-based Doppler spectroscopy) other more massive planets can be identified in the system, and their orbital parameters can be determined too. (Although the above scenario sounds very optimistic, it is one of the scientific goals of Kepler Mission, see http://kepler.nasa.gov/basis/goals.html.)</p><p>The presence of one or more additional giant planets (beside the transiting one) results in that, that both ordered and chaotic regions appear in the phase space of the system. If the phase trajectory of the Earth-like planet is in an ordered region of the phase space, the motion of the planet is stable for arbitrary long times. If the initial conditions of its orbit are in a chaotic region of the phase space, the motion of the planet can become unstable after some time. In this paper we try to exclude those orbital parameters of the transiting planet, which result in chaotic motion. We shall demonstrate that in some cases it is possible to determine an upper limit for the eccentricity and a lower limit for the inclination of the transiting planet. We stress that the eccentricity is a very important orbital parameter not only from a dynamical point of view, but also in studying the habitability and climatic variations of the Earth-like planet.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows: first we derive an equation between the duration of the transit and some important parameters of the star and the transiting body, then we solve this equation numerically. After examining the solutions of this equation, we map the stability structure of the system assuming the presence of a giant planet. Then we determine lower limits for the inclination and an upper bound for the eccentricity of the transiting planet depending on the eccentricity and the semi-major axis of the known giant planet.</p><p>2. An equation connecting the parameters of a star, a transiting planet and the transit</p><p>In this section we shall derive an equation between the orbital parameters of the transiting planet, the star's mass, and the duration of the transit from the geometry of the transit. Let us suppose that the star's disc is a circle with radius R, and a planet is moving in a front of this disc with an average velocity v tr . If the duration of the transit is denoted by τ and the lenght of the path of the transiting planet is d (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>), the following approximation holds: We note that according to Kepler's second law, the velocity of the planet is changing during the transit (except in the case of circular orbits), however this change is negligible for moderate eccentricities.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">v tr = d τ .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>From the triangle in Figure 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">R 2 = ρ 2 + d 2 2 .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>From Equation (2) the lenght of the transit's path d can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">d = 2 R 2 − r 2 cos 2 i,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where, according to <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ρ = r cos i,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>i being the inclination (e.g. the angle between the orbital plane and the tangent plane to the celestial sphere), and r the distance between the center of the star and the planet at the moment of the middle of the transit. By using the well known formula for r:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">r = a(1 − e 2 ) 1 + e cos v ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>(where a is the semi-major axis, e is the eccentricity, and v is the true anomaly of the transiting planet), and Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref>, the average transiting velocity of the planet (v tr ) can be written as where v is the true anomaly of the transiting planet at the middle of the transit.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">v tr = 2 τ R 2 − a(1 − e 2 ) 1 + e cos v 2 cos 2 i ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, v tr can also be approximated on the basis of the two-body problem. In the coordinate system (ξ, η), in which the axes of the orbital ellipse are on the axes ξ and η, the components of the orbital velocity vector are (Murray and Dermott 1999):</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">˙ ξ = − µ p sin v ,<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">˙ η = µ p (e + cos v) ,</formula><p>where p = a(1−e 2 ) is the parameter of the ellipse and µ = k 2 (m * +m p ), m * and m p being the stellar and planetary masses respectively, and k is the Gaussian constant of gravity. Let (x, y) denote the coordinate system in which the x-axis is the projection of the line of sight (e.g. the line connecting the center of the star to the observer) to the orbital plane of the transiting planet. From <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> it can be seen that the system (ξ, η) is just a rotation of the system (x, y) by an angle ω, which is the argument of the periastron of the transiting planet. Thus in the coordinate system (x, y) formulae <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> transform as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">˙ x = ˙ ξ cos ω − ˙ η sin ω ,<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">˙ y = ˙ ξ sin ω + ˙ η cos ω .</formula><p>Studying <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> one can find that the average velocity v tr of the transiting planet is almost equal to ˙ y, which is the velociy of the planet at the middle of the transit. Then by using Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(8)</ref> we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">v tr ≈ ˙ y = − µ p sin v sin ω + µ p (e + cos v) cos ω.<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Studying again <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>, it is also true that at the middle of the transit</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">v + ω = 360 • ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>thus the average orbital velocity of the transiting planet is</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">v tr = µ p (1 + e cos ω) .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Combining Equations (6), (10), and (11) we obtain a relation between the orbital parameters of the transiting planet and the duration of the transit:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">µ a(1 − e 2 ) (1 + e cos ω) − 2 τ R 2 − a(1 − e 2 ) 1 + e cos ω 2 cos 2 i = 0. (12)</formula><p>This equation has the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">f (a, e, i, ω, µ, R, τ ) = 0 ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where the unknown quantities are the eccentricity e, the inclination i, and the argument of the periastron ω. The other quantities, such as the semi-major axis a, the mass parameter (µ), the radius of the star (R), and the duration of the transit (τ ) are supposed to be known.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Analysis of Equation (12)</head><p>In this section we present and analyse the solutions of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> by using a model system. We shall see how the orbital eccentricity e of the transiting planet depends on its argument of periastron ω, or in other words, on the orbital position of the planet during the transit. We also study the sensitivity of the solutions to the uncertainties of the mass of the hosting star.</p><p>3.1. Solution of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> According to the last paragraph of the previous section, the unknown quantities in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> are the inclination i, the argument of periastron ω, and the eccentricity e of the transiting planet. Thus by fixing i, Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> can be solved numerically, and the (ω, e) pairs of the solution can be represented as a curve on the ω − e parameter plane. In order to study the solutions of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref>, we give specific values for the parameters in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12</ref>   By observing transits caused by the above planet, we can measure their duration τ and period T , from which the semi-major axis a can be calculated. In the first case τ = 0.488029 day, and for different values of i the corresponding ω − e curves are plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> for e &lt; 0.5. (We note that it is possible to study larger values of e as well, but for our demonstrational purpose we restrict ourselves for e &lt; 0.5.) We also mark the real (ω, e) solution by a filled circle on the curve corresponding to i = 89.95 • , but as we can see, there is no way to restrict efficiently the infinite set of solutions. The only restriction is that the solutions can not be chosen from the region above the ω − e curve corresponding to i = 90 • .</p><p>In the second case corresponding to τ = 0.563743 day, the ω − e curves are plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>. It can be seen that if the transit happens nearly at the apastron, the set of the solutions of Equation (12) is more limited than in the first case. Only those (ω − e) pairs satisfy Equation (12), which are in the region above the i = 90 • curve. The real solution is also marked by a filled circle on the curve i = 89.95 • .</p><p>Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> has an infinite set of solutions formed by pairs of (ω, e) values. If only the duration of the transit is known, it is not possible to choose which (ω, e) pair represents the real parameters of the transiting planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Sensitivity of the solutions of Equation (12) to the stellar mass' error</head><p>As mentioned in the Introduction, the mass of the hosting star is known only with limited accuracy. This uncertainty in the stellar mass affects the semi-major axis of the transiting planet and causes an error in the eccentricity estimates. The semi-major axis of the transiting planet can be calculated from Kepler's third law</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">a 3 T 2 = k 2 4π 2 (m * + m p ),<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where T is the period of the transits, m * is the mass of the hosting star, and m p is the mass of the transiting planet, respectively (k is the Gaussian gravitational constant). In the case of Earth-like planets m p &lt;&lt; m * , so m p can be neglected. Denoting the errors in a and m * by δa and δm * , respectively, and expanding Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref> around a and m * up to first order we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">3a 2 δa = k 2 T 2 4π 2 δm * .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Dividing Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(15)</ref> by a 3 and using again Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref> (by neglecting m p ) we find for the relative errors</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">3 δa a = δm * m * .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>By using Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(16)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> we calculated numerically the relative errors in the eccentricity of the transiting planet as a function of ω for the specific case when i = 89.95 • and τ = 0.488029 day.</p><p>Then we determined the maximum values (δe/e) max of the relative error in eccentricity for different values of δm * /m * . We found that for δm * /m * = 3% (δe/e) max = 12%, for δm * /m * = 6% (δe/e) max = 25%, and for δm * /m * = 10% (δe/e) max = 38%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">A possible confinement of the eccentricity of the transiting planet</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">The case of one additional giant planet</head><p>In this section we shall investigate the case when, beside the newly discovered planet, an already known giant planet also orbits around the hosting star. The presence of such a planet makes the problem nonintegrable and both ordered and chaotic regions can be found in the phase space of the system. We suppose that the most probable orbital solutions of the transiting planet are those, which emanate from the ordered regions of the phase space. Such values of the orbital parameters of the transiting planet which would result in chaotic behaviour are unlikely, since in long terms the orbit of the planet could be unstable, thus these solutions should be avoided. We expect that the presence of a second (giant) planet represents a dynamical constraint, which reduces the infinit set of solutions of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref>, and gives an upper limit for the maximum eccentricity of the transiting planet. We shall also demonstrate that by studying the solution-curves of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> together with the stability structure of the ω − e plane, a lower bound for the inclination can also be determined. In what follows we shall investigate the stability in the (ω − e) plane within the framework of the planar general three-body problem.</p><p>In order to map the stability properties of the (ω − e) plane we used the Relative Lyapunov Indicator (RLI) <ref type="bibr">(Sándor et al. 2000, 2004</ref>). The initial ω and e values are chosen from the intervals e ∈ [0, 0.5] and ω ∈ [0 • , 360 • ] with ∆e = 0.025 and ∆ω = 2 • . The initial value of the semi-major axis of the transiting planet is always a = 1 AU, while its true anomaly is calculated according to Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(10)</ref> as v = 360 • − ω (see also <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>). The masses of the planets are 1 Jupitermass and 1 Earth-mass, respectively, and the mass of the hosting star is 1 Solar-mass.</p><p>For each pair of the initial (ω, e) values we assign the RLI of the corresponding orbit calculated for 500 periods of the transiting planet. If the RLI is small (∼ 10 −12 −10 −13 ), the corresponding orbit is ordered and stable for very long time. If the RLI ∼ 10 −11 − 10 −9 the orbit is weakly chaotic. In practical sense such an orbit could be (Nekhoroshev) stable for very long terms as well, however, it can not be stable for arbitrary long time. Thus the regions characterized by these RLI values can already be the birth places of unstable orbits. Orbits having larger RLI ∼ 10 −8 − 10 −5 , are strongly chaotic, and they will be unstable after certain time. In our stability maps the ordered regions are denoted by light, the weakly chaotic regions by grey, and the strongly chaotic regions by dark shades.</p><p>In what follows we consider the cases where the parameters of the known giant planet having 1 Jupiter mass are the following: a 1 = 2.0 AU, e 1 = 0.2, and 0.3. We fix the angular elements of the giant planet to λ = ω = 0 • . In <ref type="figure">Figures 6 and 7</ref> we show the dynamical structure of the ω − e parameter plane for the two different values of e 1 . In these figures we also plot the solution curves of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> by using τ = 0.488029 day. From <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> it can be seen that there are two upper bounds for the eccentricity of the transiting planet depending on whether the transit occurs near the periastron, or near the apastron. If the transit is near the periastron ω &lt; 80 • , the upper limit of the eccentricity is e &lt; 0.27, since the ω − e curves cross the chaotic region around this value. If the transit happens around the apastron ω ∈ [150 • , 220 • ], the upper limit of the transiting planet's eccentricity is e &lt; 0.22. In this case a lower limit can also be given for the inclination, i &gt; 89. • 85. The real solution is marked (as a filled circle) on the curve corresponding to i = 89.95 • .</p><p>If the eccentricity of the giant planet is e 1 = 0.3, see <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>, the maximum upper limit of the transiting planet's eccentricity is e &lt; 0.18. However, in this case there exists a lower limit e &gt; 0.05 as well. If the Next we shall study the cases when the transit takes place around the apastron ω = 130 0 , resulting in a transit's duration τ = 0.563743 day. We used the same orbital parameters of the giant planet as in the previous case, a 1 = 2.0 AU, e 1 = 0.2 and 0.3 respectively. the eccentricity of the transiting planet is e &lt; 0.24 corresponding to ω ≈ 220 • . The lowest bound of its inclination is i &gt; 89.89 • .</p><p>Finally, when e 1 = 0.3, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 9</ref>, there are no stable solutions for the orbital parameters of the transiting planet.</p><p>We have also investigated cases, when the semi-major axis of the giant planet was smaller or larger than 2 AU. If a 1 is smaller, a smaller e 1 is enough to result in an effective dynamical constraint. If a 1 is larger, the eccentricity of the giant planet should be larger as well for an efficient dynamical constraint.</p><p>In the above cases we assumed that the giant planet and the transiting planet revolved in the same plane. This, based on Solar System examples, seems to be a reasonable assumption, however, the orbital planes of the planets may differ slightly from each other. Thus we performed numerical simulations by using a small mutual inclination I = 5 • between the orbital planes as well. Comparing the corresponding ω − e parameter planes we have not found any significant differences between the planar and the spatial cases with small mutual inclination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">The case of two additional giant planets</head><p>Among the extrasolar giant planets with long observational baselines, there is a high rate of multiple planet systems. We expect that this rate will increase further with the accumulation of the observational data. Therefore we studied a case, when beside a transiting Earth-like planet there are two additional giant planets.</p><p>The inner giant planet's initial orbital parameters are the same as in 4.1. The outer giant planet, having 1 M Jup , moves in an orbit characterized by a 2 = 4AU, e 2 = 0.05 in the same plane as the transiting and the inner giant planet. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> shows the stability properties of the ω − e parameter plane of the transiting planet. In order to study the effect of the outer giant planet on the ω − e parameter plane, we should compare <ref type="figure">Figure</ref>  The main structure of these figures is very similar to each other, however in the case of the additional outer giant planet the strongly chaotic region on the ω − e parameter plane is more enhanced. This means that the dynamical constraint on the transiting planet could be more efficient in the case of two giant planets. Of course the strongness of the dynamical constraint depends on many parameters of the outer giant planet. To explore the complete parameter space is beyond the scope of this paper, it will be the subject of a forthcoming research. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>The detection of Earth-like extrasolar planets by using ground based spectroscopic methods is beyond the present capabilities of observational astronomy. In the near future space instruments will be launched such as COROT and Kepler Mission which are devoted to observe such planets by using transit photometry. In this paper we addressed the question whether it is possible to determine the orbital elements of Earth-like planets discovered by transit photometry if, apart from the period, the duration of the transit can be measured too. We supposed that the mass and the radius of the hosting star is known. We derived an equation, which connects the stellar and planetary masses, the duration of the transit, the semi-major axis, the eccentricity, the argument of periastron and the inclination of the transiting planet. By fixing the inclination, this equation contains two unknown variables, the argument of periastron ω and eccentricity e of the transiting planet. Thus the solutions for different inclinations can be represented as curves on the ω − e parameter plane.</p><p>In the last section of the paper we assumed that beside the transiting Earth-like planet additional giant planets orbit around the star as well. This assumption is quite reasonable if we accept the formation theories of planetary systems supporting the simultaneous presence of both rocky, Earth-like and gaseous, Jupiter-like planets. Since the detection of giant planets is possible by radial velocity measurements, we assumed their orbital parameters to be known. (We note that from radial velocity measurements only m p sin i p is known, where m p and i p are the mass and inclination of the giant planet. However, based on Solar System examples, we can assume that the giant planets orbit nearly in the same plane as the transiting Earth-like planet, so its inclination is i p ≈ 90 • .) By using the framework of the general three-body problem, we investigated the influence of the known giant planet(s) on the transiting Earth-like planet's ω − e parameter plane. We found that on the ω − e parameter plane beside ordered domains chaotic regions appeared as well, where in long terms the motion of the transiting Earth-like planet may become unstable. Assuming that chaotic behaviour for an observed transiting planet is unlikely, we could determine an upper limit for the eccentricity, and a lower limit for the inclination.</p><p>In a future work we plan to extend our studies to investigate systematically the stability structure of the (ω −e) parameter plane for various values of the giant planet's semi-major axis, eccentricity, and inclination. Since the mass of the hosting star and several orbital parameters of the giant planets are known only with a limited accuracy from the radial velocity observations (see for instance <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ford et al. 2005</ref>), we also plan to follow the propagation of these errors through the method presented in this paper. In our future investigations we intend to consider cases of more massive transiting planets as well.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. The transit of a planet in front of the stellar disc. The straight sections denoted by R, ρ, and d/2 form a pythagorean triangle.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .Figure 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Side-view of the transit, where r is the distance of the planet from the star's center and i is the inclination of its orbital plane.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Let us assume that the mass of the transiting planet is 1 Earth-mass, and it revolves around a 1 Solar-mass star with radius R = 6.96 × 10 8 m, in an elliptic orbit characterized by a = 1 AU, e = 0.1, i = 89.95 • . We consider two cases: (i) ω = 30 • and (ii) ω = 130 • . It can be calculated easily that in these cases the durations of the transits are τ = 0.488029 day and τ = 0.563743 day, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Solutions of Equation (12) for different inclinations when τ = 0.488029 day. The original solution, which results in the above τ , is marked with a filled circle at ω = 30 • , e = 0.1, and i = 89.95 • .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Solutions of Equation (12) for different inclinations when τ = 0.563743 day. The original solution, which results in the above τ , is marked with a filled circle at ω = 130 • , e = 0.1, and i = 89.95 • .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .Figure 7 .Figure 8 .</head><label>678</label><figDesc>Figure 6. The stability map of the ω − e parameter plane, when a1 = 2.0 AU and e1 = 0.2. The ω − e curves for different i are also plotted when τ = 0.488029 day.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. The stability map of the ω − e parameter plane, when a1 = 2.0 AU and e1 = 0.3. The ω − e curves for different i are also plotted when τ = 0.563743 day.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>10 either to Figure 8 or to Figure 6. In these figures the initial conditions for the Earth-like and the inner giant planet are the same.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. The stability map of the ω − e parameter plane, when two giant planets are in the system. The semi-major axes and the eccentricities of the giants are a1 = 2.0 AU, e1 = 0.2, a2 = 4.0 AU, and e2 = 0.05. The ω − e curves for different i are also plotted when τ = 0.488029 day.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.1</note>

			<note place="foot">Zs. Sándor</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.2</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.3</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.4 Estimation of orbital parameters of exoplanets</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.5</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.6</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.7</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.8</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.9</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.10</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.11</note>

			<note place="foot" n="8"> shows the situation when e 1 = 0.2. The maximum upper limit of zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.12 Estimation of orbital parameters of exoplanets</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.13</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.14</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.15</note>

			<note place="foot">zs_sandor.tex; 12/10/2018; 16:55; p.16</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work has been supported by the Hungarian Scientific Research Fund (OTKA) under the grants D048424 and T043739. The author thanks the valuable help of Dr. C. Beaugé and Prof. B. ´ Erdi in improving the manuscript. The useful comments of the unknown referees are also acknowledged.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying the Uncertainty in the Orbits of Extrasolar Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1706" to="1717" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitable Zones around Main Sequence Stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whitmire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Reynolds</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Jupiter-Mass Companion to a Solar-Type Star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A ∼ 7.5M⊕ Planet Orbiting the Nearby Star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Dermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cambridge</forename><surname>Cup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Laughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Henry</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">876</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>GJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>Sándor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Erdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Efthymiopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Phase Space Structure Around L4 in the Restricted Three-Body Problem</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="123" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Relative Lyapunov Indicator: An Efficient Method of Chaos Detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>Sándor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Erdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Széll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Funk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cel. Mech. &amp; Dynam. Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
