<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">**FULL TITLE** ASP Conference Series, Vol. **VOLUME**, **YEAR OF PUBLICATION** **NAMES OF EDITORS** Pathway Toward an Infrared Interferometer</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010-02-26">26 Feb 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">LUTh -Paris Observatory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Meudon</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">**FULL TITLE** ASP Conference Series, Vol. **VOLUME**, **YEAR OF PUBLICATION** **NAMES OF EDITORS** Pathway Toward an Infrared Interferometer</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2010-02-26">26 Feb 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We propose a realistic pathway to satisfy two goals, thermal infrared studies of Earth-like exoplanets and interferometric architectures. 1. An Invitable Need for the Long Term: Interferometry. After the first low resolution spectro-imaging of exoplanets, a first obvious step will be to increase the spectral resolution and the sensitivity of space missions. But, sooner or later, higher angular resolution will also be needed. Indeed, after the images of planets as single pixels, the imaging of planetary rings and moons will be the next step and later on, in a far but not unrealistic future, multi-pixel cartography of planet surfaces will be necessary to understand the exact ocean/continents morphology of planets, importance of polar caps, geographic repartition of exo-vegetation etc. 2. A Bottleneck in the Interferometric Approach Unfortunately, the first step of the interferometric approach in the Mid Infrared, i.e. Bracewell-like nulling interferometry with a few apertures, presents some difficult aspects: it requires high contrast/nulling performances (like any other approach); the choosen nulling mechanism (Bracewell nulling) allows only a mono-pixel observation of the whole planetary system (with the subsequent problem of the background of exo-zodis); it requires high performance free flyers metrology; and by definition the sources (exoplanets) are extremely faint and contain only a few photons during the time scale of stability of the system. By themselves, each of these difficulties are not insurmountable. The difficulty comes from their occurring at the same time. One could imagine to start with a precursor. But the problem is that there seems to be no simple precursor that is technologically &quot;easy&quot; and scientifically exciting. 3. Breaking the Deadlock: a Two Step Solution Here we propose to decouple the needs for a thermal infrared approach and for future interferometers. First a large IR coronagraph for close-by Super-Earths and later on an interferometric precursor that is scientifically valuable and technically feasible. Contrary to an interferometer with a few pupils, a large coronagraphic single aperture has an advantage: it provides a full 2D 1</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">A Bottleneck in the Interferometric Approach</head><p>Unfortunately, the first step of the interferometric approach in the Mid Infrared, i.e. Bracewell-like nulling interferometry with a few apertures, presents some difficult aspects: it requires high contrast/nulling performances (like any other approach); the choosen nulling mechanism (Bracewell nulling) allows only a monopixel observation of the whole planetary system (with the subsequent problem of the background of exo-zodis); it requires high performance free flyers metrology; and by definition the sources (exoplanets) are extremely faint and contain only a few photons during the time scale of stability of the system. By themselves, each of these difficulties are not insurmountable. The difficulty comes from their occurring at the same time. One could imagine to start with a precursor. But the problem is that there seems to be no simple precursor that is technologically "easy" and scientifically exciting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Breaking the Deadlock: a Two Step Solution</head><p>Here we propose to decouple the needs for a thermal infrared approach and for future interferometers. First a large IR coronagraph for close-by SuperEarths and later on an interferometric precursor that is scientifically valuable and technically feasible. Contrary to an interferometer with a few pupils, a large coronagraphic single aperture has an advantage: it provides a full 2D Schneider image of the planetary systems instead of a single pixel signal, making the exozodi problem less severe. Other single aperture-like external occulters or Fresnel imagers are proposed, but they are better suited for the UV/Visible approach. For the same angular resolution, the collecting area is at least 10 times larger than for the Darwin/TPF-I architecture.</p><p>The science requirements are the detection of H 2 O, O 3 and CO 2 of the 70 nearest super-Earths (with a radius less that 2R ⊕ ) up to 5 pc. They translate into a 20 m telescope (a deployable set a few 3-4 m mirrors which would benefit of the JWST heritage) equipped with a coronograph and with a spectral resolution R = 20 to detect the central inversion peak of the CO2 band at 15 micron. With these characteristics the SNR would reach a value of 5 per spectral channel. This type of architecture has already been studied by the former TRW Company (presently Northrop Grumman) and submitted to JPL <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Lillie et al. 2001</ref>). The wavefront corrections and speckle calibration can be made e.g. by a "Self-Coherent Camera" ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Galicher et al 2008)</ref>. They should be adaptable to the thermal infrared. METIS, the Mid-infrared ELT Imager and Spectrograph, a proposed instrument for the European Extremely Large Telescope (E-ELT), is currently undergoing a phase-A study <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Brandl et al 2008)</ref>, and could be a ground-based precursor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">A Scientifically Valuable Space Precursor</head><p>Instead of accumulating problems due to free-flying control, faintness of exoplanets, single pixel detection, and high contrast, we propose to have a simpler precursor instrument which would still produce first class science:</p><p>-no nulling/high contrast -bright targets -no a priori wavelength constraints due to angular resolution (they are technically relaxed for free-flyers) -different science: general astrophysics (not mainly exoplanets). For instance: size and flattening of interesting stars, astrometric perturbation of stellar centroid by transiting planets, lensing (multiple quasars, stellar arcs, astrometry of planetary lensing...), super hot super-Earths.</p><p>The idea would be to start with 2 apertures, free-flying or not, interferometer with a evolution toward a multi-aperture interferometer similar to the Stellar Imager ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Carpenter et al. 2009</ref>).</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ETIS -the Mid-infrared E-ELT Imager and Spectrograph</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brandl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lenzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pantin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>SPIE 7014. astro-ph/0807.3271</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Stellar Imager (SI) project: a deep space UV/Optical Interferometer (UVOI) to observe the Universe at 0.1 milli-arcsec angular resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schrijver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karovska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planet. &amp; Spa. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavefront error correction and Earth-like planet detection by Self-Coherent Camera in space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Galicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baudoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rousset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. &amp; Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">488</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lillie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://planetquest.jpl.nasa.gov/TPF/TPFrevue/FinlReps/Trw/TRW12Fnl.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TRW TPF Architecture. Phase 1 Study</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Phase 2 Final Report</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
