<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:19+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Exoplanet Orbit Database II: Updates to exoplanets.org</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-09-26">26 Sep 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eunkyu</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sharon</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Penn State Astrobiology Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Penn State Astrobiology Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Katherina</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ming</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Onsi</forename><surname>Fakhouri</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Pivotal Labs, Cloud Foundry</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>875 Howard St., Fourth Floor</addrLine>
									<postCode>94103</postCode>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jacob</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Hancock</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>525 Davey Lab</addrLine>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16802</postCode>
									<settlement>University Park</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Exoplanet Orbit Database II: Updates to exoplanets.org</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-09-26">26 Sep 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Exoplanet Orbit Database (EOD) compiles orbital, transit, host star, and other parameters of robustly detected exoplanets reported in the peer-reviewed literature. The EOD can be navigated through the Exoplanet Data Explorer (EDE) Plotter and Table, available on the World Wide Web at exoplanets.org. The EOD contains data for 1492 confirmed exoplanets as of July 2014. The EOD descends from a table in Butler et al. (2002) and the Catalog of Nearby Exoplanets (Butler et al. 2006), and the first complete documentation for the EOD and the EDE was presented in Wright et al. (2011). In this work, we describe our work since then. We have expanded the scope of the EOD to include secondary eclipse parameters, asymmetric uncertainties, and expanded the EDE to include the sample of over 3000 Kepler Objects of Interest (KOIs), and other real planets without good orbital parameters (such as many of those detected by microlensing and imaging). Users can download the latest version of the entire EOD as a single comma separated value file from the front page of exoplanets.org.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Since the launch of NASA's Kepler mission ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Borucki et al. 2010)</ref>, the number of confirmed exoplanets has increased from about 300 to over 1490 as of July 2014. Kepler contributed to a majority of these new discoveries (&gt; 800) while providing an additional sample of over 3,000 exoplanet candidates (Kepler Objects of Interest, KOIs; e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Batalha et al. 2013</ref>). The transit method has thus surpassed the radial velocity (RV) method to become the most fruitful means of detecting exoplanets. Meanwhile, great promise lies within the new and future exoplanet surveys and instruments with direct imaging (e.g., the Gemini Planet Imager, GPI, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Macintosh et al. 2014</ref>) and microlensing (e.g., the Wide-Field InfraRed Survey Telescope, WFIRST, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Green et al. 2012</ref>), while the fronts of RV and transit exoplanet searches keep expanding (e.g., the MINiature Exoplanet Radial Velocity Array, MINERVA, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wright et al. 2014</ref>; the Habitable-zone Planet Finder, HPF, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Mahadevan et al. 2012</ref> and the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellit, TESS, Ricker 2014).</p><p>This paper describes our continuing efforts since <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Butler et al. (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref> to maintain the Exoplanet Orbit Database 1 (EOD) and the Exoplanets Data Explorer (EDE), to keep track of exoplanet discoveries, and to better catalog orbital parameters and host star properties.</p><p>There are other entities devoted to similar efforts, including the Extrasolar Planets Encyclopaedia 2 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schneider et al. 2011</ref>) and the NASA Exoplanet Archive <ref type="bibr">3 (Akeson et al. 2013</ref>). The natures of these efforts are largely complementary to the EOD, and to the degree that they are redundant provide important cross-checking and validation. As described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, the EOD is dedicated to cataloging properties of all robustly-detected exoplanets with well-determined orbital parameters published in peer-reviewed literature, and providing outstanding data exploration and visualization tools for these planets.</p><p>The EOD is hosted at the Web domain exoplanets.org, which also hosts the EDE, an interactive table with plotting tools for all the EOD exoplanets, in addition to other confirmed exoplanets without good orbital parameters, and KOIs (except for those with a "FALSE POSITIVE" disposition at the Exoplanet Archive). The entire dataset of exoplanets.org is available for download as a single comma separated value file from the Website front page. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> An example of this CSV file is available with the electronic version of this paper.</p><p>The EOD is widely used in exoplanet research (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dawson &amp; Murray-Clay 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">, Howard 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">, Kipping 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, Kane 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">, Weiss &amp; Marcy 2014</ref>, and the website exoplanets.org had over 47, 000 visits in 2013 <ref type="bibr">5</ref> . <ref type="bibr">1</ref> See http://expoplanets.org <ref type="bibr">2</ref> See http://exoplanet.eu. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> See http://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> At http://exoplanets.org/csv-files/exoplanets.csv. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> Measured as "visits" by Google Analytics</p><p>Since the documentation described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, the EOD has expanded its scope: we now do not require the host star of an exoplanet to be a normal star (e.g., exoplanets around pulsars are now included). We now ingest more parameters describing the exoplanet systems and their host stars, and some parameters have been revised or deleted. We describe our updates to the EOD in Section 2. The EDE at exoplanets.org has also expanded its scope and now includes the Kepler exoplanet candidates (KOIs). We describe these changes in Section 3. The website exoplanets.org has gone through major back-end changes since <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, which are described in Section 4. We summarize the updates and possible future improvements in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Updates on the EOD</head><p>The scope of the EOD has expanded, and there are three major changes from what was described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>. Previously, we only included exoplanets orbiting the "normal stars", but now we are not limiting the type of host stars (e.g. we included exoplanets orbiting neutron stars). Furthermore, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, we only included exoplanets that were discovered by the RV and transit methods in the EOD, but now we also include planets discovered via timing (including pulsar planets and those discovered by eclipse timing). We now include exoplanets discovered by any other methods with robust detections and good orbital parameters, such as β Pictoris b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chauvin et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Nielsen et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Macintosh et al. 2014</ref>).</p><p>Previously, we used a generous mass cutoff, recognizing that any definition of "exoplanet" will not necessarily track with the formation mechanism for an object (which may, after all, be unknown or unknowable). Our previous mass cutoff was a minimum mass (msin i) smaller than 24M Jup ; to make this cutoff more relevant to a wide range of stellar masses and detection methods, we now require the measured planet-star mass ratio to be smaller than 24 M Jup /M ⊙ (&lt; 0.023).</p><p>The rest of the selection criteria for the EOD remain unchanged. We still require the planets to have robust detections and well-determined orbits (though these are not strictly quantitative and sometimes subjective; see Section 2 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. 2011</ref>). If new evidence comes to light and we are no longer confident about a planet, we may remove it from EOD, even if the new evidence is not peer reviewed. The rationale for this scheme is, as it has been since the CNE, that the EOD represents our best, expert effort to produce a clean set of trustworthy parameters. We do not report all the announced exoplanets as we are not trying to provide "an encyclopedic presentation of every claimed detection of an exoplanet" ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. 2011</ref>). More comprehensive sets of planet parameters are available from other exoplanet compendia on the Web.</p><p>In the following subsections, we describe the newly added and revised fields since <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, and list all fields in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 1</ref>. We divide the fields into categories consistent with the individual planet page on exoplanets.org. <ref type="figure">(Figure 1</ref> is an example of individual planet page, which is presented to website users who click on a planet's name). Some fields are not explicitly tabulated on the page (e.g., the URLs for ADS pages for papers providing the underlying data), but are explicitly listed in the downloadable .csv file (see Section 1). Though we focus on the EOD in this section, the fields apply to all planets on exoplanets.org. We follow the definition of orbital elements in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Wright &amp; Gaudi (2013)</ref> unless indicated otherwise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Discovery and References</head><p>We report general information of when, by whom and how the planets were discovered and first reported and provide the references for underlying data. We describe the added or revised fields since Wright et al. (2011) below.</p><p>The DISCMETH field previously reported the method of discovery, which was either "radial velocity" or "transit". We have replaced DISCMETH with PLANETDISCMETH and STARDISCMETH to better report how exoplanet systems and individual exoplanets are first discovered. PLANETDISCMETH reports the discovery method for the planet, while STARDIS-CMETH reports the discovery method for the planetary system (i.e. the first discovered planet around the host star). These fields are stored in string format and have one of the following values: "RV", "Transit", "Imaging", "Microlensing", "Timing", or "Astrometry" (no planets have a value of "Astrometry" yet since no planet has yet been discovered via astrometry).</p><p>The MONTH field reports the integer month of the peer-reviewed paper publication date.</p><p>KEPID stands for KEPler IDentification, which is the integer number assigned for a Kepler host star. KEPID is only available for unconfirmed KOI's imported directly from the Exoplanet Archive by the exoplanets.org backend.</p><p>KOI stands for Kepler Object of Interest, which is an object with transit signals detected by Kepler that have not been validated as being due to exoplanets. The KOI field defined by the Kepler team and shown on the Exoplanet Archive is stored as a floating point number, consisting of a whole number designated to the host star followed by a decimal portion denoting a candidate planet. For example, KOI 102 is a star suspected to host two exoplanets, and KOI 102.01 is the inner planet candidate and KOI 102.02 is the outer one. Once a candidate is confirmed, the NAME field of the planet is replaced by the official Kepler ID ("Kepler" followed by a hyphen, an integer, a space, and finally a lower case letter). The KOI number is then used as OTHERNAME. For more information, see Section 3.</p><p>EOD is a Boolean which indicates whether an exoplanet is included in the EOD for having well-characterized orbital parameters, such as the orbital period (PER). We added this field because exoplanets.org now also includes robustly discovered planets that do not have well-characterized orbits, and also Kepler planet candidates (see Section 3 for more details). Planets on exoplanets.org and appearing in the EDE that are not part of the EOD have EOD set to FALSE (i.e. zero).</p><p>MICROLENSING, IMAGING, TIMING and ASTROMETRY are Boolean flags which indicate that a planet has been detected via these methods. For example, MICROLENSING = 1 means the planet is detected in a microlensing event. Note that planets may be detected with multiple methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Orbital Parameters</head><p>We report the orbital parameters that determine the shape of the planet's orbit. Depending on the detection methods, different sets of parameters are given by the literature. For instance, if a planet is detected by the radial velocity method, the semiamplitude, K, is reported, whereas the inclination of the orbit, i, is usually only known via the transit method (although planet-planet interactions and astrometry can also determine it). We describe the added fields since Wright et al.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(2011) below.</formula><p>MASS is the mass of the planet in the unit of Jupiter mass. Previously, we only reported the minimum mass, (m sin i, MSINI) of the planets. We now, additionally, report the best estimate of the true mass in a heterogeneous way. For example, if a planet is discovered by microlensing, we report the actual mass of the planet according to the literature. If a planet has both radial velocity and transit measurements, we calculate the mass from the minimum mass m sin i and the orbital inclination i. For convenience of plotting RV and other planets on a common mass scale (see Section 3), MASS is set to MSINI if the orbital inclination is not known and the reference for MASS (MASSREF) is set to "Set to MSINI; I unknown".</p><p>Also for plotting convenience, for transiting Kepler planets without m sin i measured, we estimate their mass using mass-radius relations from the literature. We follow a series of relations given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M p =                  M WM R &lt; R ⊕ (1 − x)M WM + xM L R ⊕ R &lt; 4R ⊕ M L 4R ⊕ R &lt; 6R ⊕ min (M M , M Jup ) 6R ⊕ R &lt; b M Jup R b</formula><p>where b is defined below, and we use the weight x = (R p /R ⊕ − 1) /3 to smoothly transition between M WM and M L in their overlapping regions of validity. M WM is from <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Weiss &amp; Marcy (2014)</ref> and is given by  <ref type="formula">(2012)</ref>, where Planets with masses estimated in this manner are so noted in the MASSREF field.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">M WM M ⊕ =    0.615 0.717 + Rp R ⊕ Rp R ⊕ 3 R &lt; 1.5R ⊕ 2.69 Rp R ⊕ 0.93 1.5R ⊕ R &lt; 4R ⊕ M L is given by M p /M ⊕ = (R p /R ⊕ ) 2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">M p M 0 = −w b (R p /R ⊕ ) − 1 1/p from Mordasini et al.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">a/AU 0.1 a/AU &gt; 0.1 M 0 [M ⊕ ] 1756.7 1308.7 b[R ⊕ ] 11</formula><p>SEP is a separation between the host star and the planet in units of AU. For directly imaged and microlensing planets, the literature usually reports the projected separation and we report the value accordingly. If SEP is not directly measured but the semi-major axis (A) is available, then we set SEP to A with its reference, SEPREF, set to "Set to A".</p><p>The parameter I reports the orbital inclination of the planet. Previously, only transiting systems had i measured, but now some non-transiting systems have dynamical or astrometric constraints on i (for example, the microlensing system OGLE-2006-BLG-109L by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bennett et al. 2010</ref> and the imaged system, β Pictoris by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lagrange et al. 2009</ref>).</p><p>BIGOM is the longitude of the ascending node (Ω) in units of degrees. At the moment, only β Pictoris b has this quantity listed.</p><p>LAMBDA is the projected spin-orbit misalignment (λ) in the plane of the sky in units of degrees. At the moment, λ values are only available for the transiting systems, which are measured by either the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Winn et al. 2005</ref>) or planetary transits of star spots (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Sanchis-Ojeda et al. 2012</ref>). λ is used because the true spin-orbit angle, defined as the angle between the stellar spin axis and the orbital axis, is normally not directly measurable. We follow <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Fabrycky &amp; Winn (2009)</ref> who defined the quantity as follows: the z-axis points toward the observer, the x-axis points along the intersection of the sky plane and the planet's orbital plane with the ascending node of the planet having x &lt; 0, and the y-axis completes a right handed-triad. λ is measured clockwise on the sky from the y-axis to the projected stellar rotational axis. λ is not a newly added field to the EOD but we describe it here because we did not previously report it consistently, since some literature report the "projected spin-orbit misalignment" as β = −λ instead 6 . We have sorted these cases out and made sure that our λ's are following the definition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Fabrycky &amp; Winn (2009)</ref>.</p><p>The MASSREF and MASSURL fields were used to report the reference and the URL of stellar mass but now they are used for the planet's mass; MSTARREF and MSTARURL are now used for the stellar mass, MSTAR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Transit Parameters</head><p>We have added two fields since <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>, which are used for KOI's incorporated from the Exoplanet Archive.</p><p>DR is the distance between the planet and the star during the transit in stellar radii. This is one of the parameters that goes into the transit light curve modeling (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Batalha et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>RR is the ratio of the planetary radius and the stellar radius. If the transit depth (DEPTH) is not given, we calculate DEPTH by taking square of RR, but we do not calculate RR from DEPTH.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Secondary Eclipse</head><p>We have added an entirely new set of fields for secondary eclipse depths. Previously, due to the limits of instrumentation and limited sample of exoplanets, there was not much secondary eclipse depth data available. Since Wright et al. (2011), as many different surveys have been launched, secondary eclipse depths at multiple bands have become available for many planets. Therefore, we added this entire new set of fields (see <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>).</p><p>SEDEPTHX whereas X stands for one of "J", "H", "KS", "KP", "36", "45", "58", "80": these fields are the secondary eclipse depth measured in the corresponding wavelength band. SEDEPTHJ, H, and KS are the depths measured in the 2MASS wavelength bands in the near infrared, centered at 1.25 µm, 1.65 µm, and 2.15 µm, respectively. KP is the depth measured in the Kepler photometric band which spans 400 to 865 nm. The other four represent the Spitzer IRAC bands centered at 3.6 µm, 4.5 µm, 5.8 µm, and 8.0 µm.</p><p>The SE Boolean indicates whether the system has secondary eclipse depths measured in any band. Truth indicates the system has at least one secondary eclipse measurement in the EOD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Stellar Properties</head><p>This set of parameters provides users the physical parameters of the exoplanet host stars. Most of the parameters are derived from the stellar models in the literature and we provide the readers with the references. We describe added fields since Wright et al. (2011) below.</p><p>GAMMA (γ) is the radial velocity of the center of mass of the planetary system with respect to the barycentric frame and is reported in km/s. It is typically known to far less precision than K, because it requires an absolute measurement of velocity.</p><p>RSTAR is the radius of the star in the solar units.</p><p>RHOSTAR is the density of the star in g/cm 3 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Stellar Magnitudes</head><p>We provide the brightness of the host star measured in different filters. We report optical magnitude and color (V and B − V ), 2MASS J, H, and K s magnitudes and, we have added KP for the Kepler photometric band. Note that the definitions of V and B in the literature vary, and are often Hipparcos magnitudes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Coordinates and Catalogs</head><p>We report the coordinates of the host star as well as the host star's ID as designated by different catalogs. We have added the DIST field since Wright et al. <ref type="formula">(2011)</ref>, which is the distance to the host star in the unit of pc. If only parallax (PAR) is given, we calculate DIST based on PAR and vice versa. If the literature does not report DIST or PAR, then we obtain PAR from the Hipparcos dataset by van <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leeuwen (2009)</ref> for stars with Hipparcos numbers. We na¨ıvelyna¨ıvely translate the 1-σ errors in each into asymmetric uncertainties in the other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">Uncertainties</head><p>We have changed the way of reporting uncertainties, especially asymmetric ones since <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>. We now report uncertainties for a certain field X as XUPPER, XLOWER and UX. XUP-PER and XLOWER store the upper and lower 1σ uncertainties, and they are different when the error bars are asymmetric. UX contains the 1σ uncertainty, and it equals (XUPPER + XLOWER)/2. Fields that have XUPPER, XLOWER and UX are: all the orbital parameters, all the transit parameters, all the secondary eclipse fields, and all the stellar properties and DIST and PAR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.">References</head><p>The fields XREF and XURL store the peer-reviewed reference and link to the publication for the data in field X. Previously, we reported only general references for certain sets of fields (e.g. FIRSTREF, FIRSTURL, ORBREF, and ORBURL), but now we report the references for most of the fields on an individual basis.</p><p>The following fields do not have associated REF or URL fields. Except where we record these values directly from discovery papers, RA, DEC, and PAR are usually from the Hipparcos rereduction of van <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Leeuwen (2009)</ref>; the B − V (BMV) values are from the Hipparcos catalog by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Perryman &amp; ESA (1997)</ref>; stellar magnitudes J, H, and KS (i.e. K s ) are from the 2MASS catalog ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Skrutskie et al. 2006</ref>) (as reported in SIMBAD) and the KP (i.e. K P ) magnitudes are from the Exoplanet Archive ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akeson et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>SHK and RHK represent the Mount Wilson S and R ′ HK chromospheric emission measures. These fields are poorly maintained fields and unreferenced, at the moment. We plan to include proper reference in the future. Most of the SHK and RHK values are from <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Butler et al. (2006)</ref>, and individual discovery papers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10.">Removed Fields</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>We removed 2 fields since Wright et al. (2011):</head><p>The SPTYPE field previously reported the stellar type of the host star. We have removed it since it can be difficult to verify with peer-reviewed references, and the field was not well maintained. We encourage users to use TEFF and BMV instead.</p><p>The NSTEDID field reported ID of host star in NStED, and now it is replaced by EANAME, which is the name of the star as appears on the NASA's Exoplanet Archive ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Akeson et al. 2013</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Inclusion of the Kepler Planet Candidates and Other Exoplanets on exoplanets.org</head><p>Since Wright et al. (2011), Kepler has discovered many exoplanet candidates, and more planets have been robustly discovered by various other methods, although not all have very well characterized orbits. We have expanded the EDE to include those planets for the convenience of our users, and also to keep exoplanets.org complete in terms of confirmed exoplanets.</p><p>We now provide an option for users to include the KOIs discovered by Kepler in the EDE. Although KOIs are not counted as part of the EOD due to their status of being "candidates", we include them on our website so that these KOIs are put into the context of all confirmed exoplanets. We have used broad definitions for SEP and MASS so that they may be compared to EOD planets, even though they share few strictly defined parameters. The KOIs listed in our table include three Kepler data releases (as of July 2014), and exoplanets.org always provides the most up-to-date release through a partnership with the NASA Exoplanet Archive.</p><p>To display the KOIs in the EDE table, users can check the "Kepler" option on the upper left of the table (the default selection only includes "Orbit Database", i.e. the EOD, and "Other"). They can also be displayed on plots with the interactive plotting tool of EDE (see <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> for an example plot). All KOIs with a disposition other than "FALSE POSITIVE" are included in the EDE.</p><p>We now also include robustly detected imaging, microlensing, and timing planets. Our criteria for a "robust detection" for these planets are the following:</p><p>• Imaging planets:</p><p>1. Planet-star mass ratio q &lt; 0.023 (&lt; 24 M Jup for a solar mass star); and in general we require (q + σ q ) &lt; 0.023, where σ q is the uncertainty in q.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">2. SEP &lt; 100 AU × (M * /M ⊙ ),</formula><p>where SEP is the semi-major axis a if a is known, and the projected separation otherwise.</p><p>3. Confidently detected: the detection is clearly of a real astrophysical source, and will unlikely later be found to have been spurious.</p><p>4. Confidently bound: object will clearly not be later found to be unbound or a chance alignment.</p><p>• Microlensing planets: We accept microlensing planets that appear in refereed journals as having unambiguously planetary masses (planet host mass ratio, q &lt; 0.023).</p><p>• Timing planets: Timing planets must have dynamically stable orbits and, ideally, show multiple complete orbits (e.g., see <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Wittenmyer et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">, and Wittenmyer et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>Some of the exoplanets that are primarily detected by these methods do not have well-determined orbital parameters, and thus they are categorized as "Other Planets" on exoplanets.org instead of being in the EOD. These planets can be displayed by check the 'Other' option for the EDE table.</p><p>As of July 2014, no microlensing or imaging planets (except β Pictoris) appear in the EOD, while several timing exoplanets have well-determined orbital parameters and are included in the EOD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Updates to the Website software</head><p>The software stack powering the EOD remains largely unchanged from Wright et al. (2011). The backend server is now written in Ruby, instead of Python, but the thin role it plays is largely unchanged. The JavaScript frontend that runs on the browser has recently been optimized to support the larger datasets arising from the Kepler missions. In particular, the EOD table now only renders cells that are visible on-screen.</p><p>1. Plot parameters may be saved with browser cookies, so plots may be custom reproduced easily with updated data later.</p><p>2. Tables may be generated and exported with custom fields computed.</p><p>3. Plots may be exported with a variety of resolutions and aspects, including publication-quality vector graphics (SVG format).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Summary and Future Work</head><p>We have had two major updates since <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Wright et al. (2011)</ref>. First, we expanded the scope of the EOD. We removed the requirement for the host star being normal and included the planets discovered not only by RV and transit but also by various other methods (e.g. timing) in the EOD. We also have added some new fields, most notably, we now report the secondary eclipse depths. We removed obsolete fields and revised some fields as necessary. We have included SEP and MASS with broad definitions so all planets may be plotted on common axes.</p><p>Second, we included KOIs and other planets (the ones detected by microlensing, imaging, timing, and in the future, astrometry but do not have well characterized orbits) on exoplanets.org. Although they are not included in the EOD, we reported them on our website since the users might find them useful for purposes of statistical studies and comparison.</p><p>In the future, we hope to include images of directly imaged planets and light curves for transits and microlensing planets. We plan to display RV curves whenever their RV data are available and include better incorporation of Kepler parameters in the EOD (such as KEPID).</p><p>We also plan to report the upper limits (XUL) for planet minimum mass (MSINI), eccentricity (ECC), and the radial velocity semi-amplitude (K) when the literature reports them. For example, an upper limit for ECC is reported when the orbit is consistent with a circular one, and the upper limit for K is reported when there is only a null result from radial velocities. Since not all authors define the upper limits in the same way (e.g. 1σ or some fixed percentile), we encourage the users to refer to the original references for more information. We will also include proper rendering of upper limits in the EDE <ref type="table">Table,</ref> proper upper limit symbols in the Plotter, and proper handling of upper limits in filters and queries in both cases.</p><p>Omissions and errors to the EOD can be corrected by sending us an email at datamaster@exoplanets.org.</p><p>We acknowledge NSF grant AST-1211441 which supports exoplanets.org. Parts of this work was supported by a NASA Keck PI Data Award, administered by the NASA Exoplanet Science Institute.</p><p>We also thank NASA and NExScI for support via funds associated with the award of Keck time for monitoring the orbits of long-period and multi-planet systems. SXW acknowledges support from the Penn State Astrobiology Research Center, part of the NASA Astrobiology Institute (NNA09DA76A). The Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds is supported by the Pennsylvania State University, the Eberly College of Science, and the Pennsylvania Space Grant Consortium.</p><p>This preprint was prepared with the AAS L A T E X macros v5.2. <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>.-An example page for an individual exoplanet (WASP-14b in this case). The numbers listed in each field contain links to the reference on NASA ADS. In this example for WASP-14b, we provide the plot for the phased RVs, but we have yet to implement such feature for all planets with available RV data. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-An example plot produced by the interactive plotting tools of EDE on exoplanets.org. The interactive plotting interface is shown on the right, with the mass-period plot shown on the left. The x-axis is planet orbital period in days and y-axis is planet mass in Earth's mass. The exoplanet samples being plotted are the ones in the EOD, including transit planets (blue large dots), RV planets (red triangles), and timing planets (magenta squares). The KOIs are plotted as black small dots, and their masses are calculated using their radii based on mass-radius relations from the literature (see Section 2.2). Note the apples-to-oranges comparison enabled by the hybrid MASS field on the y-axis, which blends estimated masses, minimum masses, and true masses on a single plot. <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>.-An example plot that demonstrates the current secondary eclipse measurements. Each planet has a set of circles that stand for its available secondary eclipse measurements in the database, including Spitzer 8.0, 5.8, 4.5, &amp; 3.6 µm, and ground-based J, H, and K s bands. Kepler secondary eclipse measurements are labeled as solid black dots. A few representative planets are also annotated (a feature not offered by the EDE Plotter, but trivially implemented by other image or presentation software). The planet name will appear when the user points the cursor at the corresonding data point in the interactive plotting tools. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>. 06 from Lissauer et al. (2011), and M M is given by log 10</head><label>06</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Fields of Exoplanet Orbit Database</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Field 
Data Type 
Meaning 
Related Fields a 
Ref. b 

Discovery and References 
NAME . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
String 
Name of planet 
· · · 
W11 
OTHERNAME . . . . . . 
String 
Other commonly used name of star 
· · · 
2.1 
DATE . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Integer 
Year of publication of FIRSTREF 
· · · 
W11 
MONTH . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Integer 
Month of publication of FIRSTREF 
· · · 
2.1 
PLANETDISCMETH String 
Method of discovery of planet 
· · · 
2.1 
STARDISCMETH . . . 
String 
Method of discovery of first planet in system 
· · · 
2.1 
ORBREF . . . . . . . . . . . . 
String 
Peer-reviewed origin of orbital parameters 
ORBURL 
W11 
FIRSTREF . . . . . . . . . . 
String 
First peer-reviewed publication of planetary orbit 
FIRSTURL 
W11 
JSNAME . . . . . . . . . . . . 
String 
Name of host star used in the Extrasolar Planets Encyclopaedia 
EPEURL 
W11 
ETDNAME. . . . . . . . . . 
String 
Name of planet used in the Exoplanet Transit Database 
ETDURL 
W11 
EANAME . . . . . . . . . . . 
String 
Name of planet used in the Exoplanet Archive database 
EAURL 
2.10 
SIMBADNAME . . . . . 
String 
Valid SIMBAD name of host star (or planet, if available) 
SIMBADURL 
W11 
KEPID . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Long Integer 
The unique Kepler star identifier 
· · · 
2.1 
KOI . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
KOI object number 
· · · 
2.1 
EOD . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Boolean 
If true, planet is included in the EOD 
· · · 
2.1 
MICROLENSING . . . 
Boolean 
If true, planet was detected via microlensing 
· · · 
2.1 
IMAGING . . . . . . . . . . . 
Boolean 
If true, planet was detected via imaging 
· · · 
2.1 
TIMING . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Boolean 
If true, planet was detected via timing 
· · · 
2.1 
ASTROMETRY . . . . . 
Boolean 
If true, planet was detected via astrometric motion 
· · · 
2.1 

Orbital Parameters 
MSINI . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Minimum mass (as calculated from the mass function) in M Jup 
-UL, -UPPER, etc. 
W11 
MASS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Mass of planet in M Jup 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.2 
A . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Orbital semimajor axis in AU 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
SEP . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Separation between host star and planet in AU 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.2 
PER . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Double 
Orbital period in days 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
K . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Semiamplitude of stellar reflex motion in m s −1 
-UL, -UPPER, etc. 
W11 
ECC . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Orbital eccentricity 
-UL, -UPPER, etc. 
W11 
I . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Orbital inclination in degrees 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.2 
OM . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Argument of periastron in degrees 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
BIGOM . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Longitude of ascending node in degrees 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.2 
T0 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Double 
Epoch of periastron in HJD c 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
DVDT . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Magnitude of linear trend in m s −1 day −1 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
LAMBDA . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Projected spin-orbit misalignment in degrees 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.2 
TRANSIT . . . . . . . . . . . 
Boolean 
Is the planet known to transit? 
-REF,-URL 
W11 

Transit Parameters 
R . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Radius of planet in Jupiter radii 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
TT . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Epoch of transit center in HJD c 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
T14 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Time of transit from first to fourth contact in days 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
B . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Impact parameter of transit 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
AR . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
(a/R * ) 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
DEPTH . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Transit depth, or (Rp/R * ) 2 when depth is not given 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
DENSITY . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Density of planet in g cc −1 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
GRAVITY . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
log g (surface gravity) of planet in cgs unit 
-UPPER, etc. 
W11 
DR . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
Distance during transit in stellar radii 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.3 
RR . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Float 
(Rp/R * ) 
-UPPER, etc. 
2.3 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> In some cases, (e.g. Moutou et al. 2011), other conventions entirely appear to be used.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Field</head><p>Data a "-UPPER etc." means "-UPPER, -LOWER, U-, -REF, -URL", where "-" stands for the name of the field listed in the first column. These fields store the uncertainties and references. See Section 2.8 and 2.9 for more details. "-UL" stands for upper limits for the fields (see Section 2.8 for details). </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Akeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">989</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">837</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">977</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">578</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">565</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">646</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">542</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murray-Clay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">696</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1230</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1208.4012</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Horner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wittenmyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hinse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">425</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="762" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">572</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">782</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gratadour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gemini Planet Imager instrument team</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>#229.02</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planet Imager Exoplanet Survey</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1403.7195</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A C</forename><surname>Perryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><surname>Esa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ESA Special Publication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1200</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ricker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Journal of the American Association of Variable Star Observers (JAAVSO)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">234</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanchis-Ojeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">487</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">449</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dedieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Le Sidaner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Savalle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Zolotukhin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">532</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Skrutskie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">497</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">209</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">783</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">631</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1215</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wittenmyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Horner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Butters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">419</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3258</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wittenmyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Horner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">431</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">412</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planets, Stars and Stellar Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Solar and Stellar Planetary Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">489</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>#148.31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
