<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Homogenous Study of Transiting Systems (HoSTS). II. The influence of the line list on stellar parameters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Doyle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Warwick</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gibbet Hill Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CV4 7AL</postCode>
									<settlement>Coventry</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Barry</forename><surname>Smalley</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Astrophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Keele University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ST5 5BG</postCode>
									<settlement>Staffordshire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Faedi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Warwick</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gibbet Hill Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CV4 7AL</postCode>
									<settlement>Coventry</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Don</forename><surname>Pollacco</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Warwick</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gibbet Hill Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CV4 7AL</postCode>
									<settlement>Coventry</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yilen</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maqueo</forename><surname>Chew</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Instituto de Astronomía</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ciudad Universitaria</addrLine>
									<postCode>04510</postCode>
									<settlement>Ciudad de México</settlement>
									<country key="MX">México</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Homogenous Study of Transiting Systems (HoSTS). II. The influence of the line list on stellar parameters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">MNRAS</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12"/>
							<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Accepted XXX. Received YYY; in original form ZZZ</note>
					<note>Preprint 12 September 2018 Compiled using MNRAS L A T E X style file v3.0</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>stars: abundances, stars: fundamental parameters</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The use of high resolution, high signal-to-noise stellar spectra is essential in order to determine the most accurate and precise stellar atmospheric parameters via spec-troscopy. This is particularly important for determining the fundamental parameters of exoplanets, which directly depend on the stellar properties. However, different techniques can be implemented when analysing these spectra which will influence the results. These include performing an abundance analysis relative to the solar values in order to negate uncertainties in atomic data, and fixing the surface gravity (log g) to an external value such as those from asteroseismology. The choice of lines used will also influence the results. In this paper, we investigate differential analysis and fixing log g for a set of FGK stars that already have accurate fundamental parameters known from external methods. We find that a differential line list gives slightly more accurate parameters compared to a laboratory line list, however the laboratory line list still gives robust parameters. We also find that fixing the log g does not improve the spectroscopic parameters. We investigate the effects of line selection on the stellar parameters and find that the choice of lines used can have a significant effect on the parameters. In particular, removal of certain low excitation potential lines can change the T eff by up to 50 K. For future HoSTS papers we will use the differential line list with a solar microturbulence value of 1 km s −1 , and we will not fix the log g to an external value.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Our understanding of exoplanets is strongly tied to our understanding of their host stars. The mass and radius of a transiting exoplanet cannot be determined without first knowing the mass and radius of the star (Winn 2011). Direct determinations of stellar mass and radius are only possible for those in a binary system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Andersen 1991</ref>). For other stars, the mass and radius needs to be determined indirectly. This can be done via asteroseismology once the effective temperature (T eff ) is known ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chaplin et al. 2011</ref>). The planet transit can yield the stellar density, which can be used to determine the stellar mass and radius once the T eff and metallicity are known ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Sozzetti et al. 2007</ref>). The distance to a star, which can be measured via parallax with Gaia, can also be used to determine the stellar radius, once T eff and bolometric flux are known ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Stassun et al. 2016</ref>).</p><p>⋆ E-mail: Amanda.Doyle@warwick.ac.uk</p><p>For stars without asteroseismic measurements, spectroscopy is used to determine the T eff , surface gravity (log g), and metallicity ( <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>). These parameters are then input into a calibration (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Torres et al. (2010)</ref>) or used with a grid of stellar models (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Girardi et al. (2000)</ref>) to find the stellar mass and radius.</p><p>For the spectroscopic analysis, some authors rely on differential analysis as opposed to the atomic data from the VALD database (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Meléndez et al. (2009)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bruntt et al. (2010)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Brugamyer et al. (2011)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sousa et al. (2014)</ref>). The disadvantage is that differential analysis can only be performed accurately for stars with similar parameters to the Sun. However, while it is clear that stars with properties that deviate vastly from solar should not be used in differential analysis, it is not clear what the cut-off in parameters should be for planet host stars, which are typically FGK dwarfs and subgiants, although planets have also been found around giant stars (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wittenmyer et al. (2017)</ref>). In this paper we analyse a set of 23 FGK stars and compare a line list us-ing the laboratory data from VALD with a differential line list in order to investigate if the differential list is really the best one to use and if errors are more likely for stars with parameters furthest from solar.</p><p>Due to the uncertainties inerrant in the spectroscopic log g, fixing the log g to an external value such as those obtained from the planet transit or asteroseismology can improve the spectroscopic parameters for some methods which directly compare the observed spectrum with a synthetic spectrum. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Torres et al. (2012)</ref> found that fixing log g improved the parameters when using the software SME and SPC, but when they used an equivalent width (EW) based method with the software MOOG, they found the latter to be more accurate. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mortier et al. (2014)</ref> also found the EW-based method does not require log g to be fixed to an external value.</p><p>The Homogeneous Study of Transiting Systems (HoSTS) project aims to characterise planets and their host stars consistently, and to use a homogeneous, high quality set of stellar spectra. Four spectral analysis methods were compared in the pilot study of WASP-13 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gómez Maqueo Chew et al. (2013)</ref>; hereafter Paper I) using a high resolution (R = 72 000) HIRES spectrum. Each of the methods performed three different analyses: an unconstrained analysis to obtain T eff , log g and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>, an analysis with the T eff fixed to that determined from the Hα line from a long-slit IDS spectrum, and an analysis with log g fixed from the transit value. Paper I found that the results from the unconstrained analysis agreed well between all four methods and are consistent with the transit log g and the Hα T eff , leading to the conclusion that the four different methods of spectral analysis have no systematic differences between them.</p><p>In this paper we investigate differential analysis and fixing the log g to an external value, in order to determine if there is any preferential method. We also determine the effect that line selection will have on the stellar parameters. We use the Fe-line method, where the EWs are measured for a number of Fe lines in order to determine the stellar parameters. We also obtain the log g from the pressure broadened Mg i b and Na i D lines.</p><p>The stars that we chose to analyse are a set of 23 bright, standard stars that were previously analysed by <ref type="bibr">Bruntt et al. (2010) (hereafter B10)</ref>. This selection of standard stars was chosen for this work as the parameters span the range of stars that can host exoplanets, i.e. FGK stars from dwarfs to giants. B10 determined non-spectroscopic parameters for these stars, which are a useful test of our spectroscopic parameters; the bolometric T eff , photometric T eff , the log g determined from a binary mass and interferometric angular diameter, and asteroseismic log g. The bolometric T eff from <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Heiter et al. (2015)</ref> (hereafter H15) is also used.</p><p>All of the spectra that we used were taken from the ESO HARPS archive and the spectra all have S/N ∼100. While higher S/N could be achieved by coadding several spectra, a S/N of 100 is more representative of a typical planet host star.</p><p>In Section 2, we discuss the methods used for our analysis and the selection of the line lists. Section 3 details our results where the results between the VALD and differential line lists are compared. Section 4 discusses the results and we conclude in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Measuring spectral parameters</head><p>The spectroscopic parameters can be determined using a set of Fe lines and we use the same method as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Doyle et al. (2013)</ref>. Once the equivalent widths (EWs) of the lines have been measured, the abundance is calculated for each line. The low excitation potential (EP) Fe i lines are sensitive to temperature, where as the temperature sensitivity is negligible for high EP lines. Thus requiring that there is no trend between EP and abundance will yield the T eff of the star and this is known as the excitation balance T eff . The error for the excitation balance T eff is from the 1-σ variation in the slope of abundance against excitation potential. The same principle can be applied to Fe ii lines, but in this case it is the high EP lines that are sensitive to T eff changes. However, there are usually an insufficient number of Fe ii lines present in solar-like stars to determine the T eff .</p><p>The log g of the star can be determined via the ionisation balance, which occurs when the Fe i and Fe ii abundances agree. This is because the Fe ii abundance will increase with increasing log g, where as the Fe i abundance is insensitive to log g variations ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Takeda et al. 2002)</ref>. The error for the ionisation balance log g is determined by varying the T eff by 1σ. It should also be noted that the number of Fe ii lines used is an important factor in determining the ionisation balance log g. An insufficient number of Fe ii lines will lower the log g, and likely explains the low log g found in Paper I for WASP-13 using the <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Schuler et al. (2011)</ref> line list, as this list has only 5 Fe ii lines.</p><p>The microturbulence (vmic) is a line broadening parameter required in 1D analyses that also affects abundance and thus the derived T eff and log g. Microturbulence was introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Struve &amp; Elvey (1934)</ref> so that the abundance calculated from strong lines would be the same as for weak lines. Therefore the vmic is determined by requiring that there is no slope between the abundance and EW.</p><p>The determination of parameters via the Fe lines is an iterative process. The excitation balance T eff is first determined using an initial T eff guess from the bolometric, photometric, or the B10 spectroscopic value. An initial guess of 1 km s −1 is used for the vmic. A T eff value is determined when the slope of the excitation balance plot is zero. The log g is then adjusted so that the Fe i and Fe ii abundances agree, and the vmic is adjusted until there is no trend between abundance and EW. The Fe i lines used to determine the excitation balance T eff have very little dependence on the log g so the log g will not change the excitation balance. However, T eff is sensitive to vmic, which will change the slope so that excitation balance no longer occurs. A second iteration of T eff is therefore performed using the new vmic value. The new T eff will affect the log g, therefore the ionisation balance needs to be redetermined. Several iterations are performed until the slopes of both plots have been minimised and the ionisation balance is correct.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Software</head><p>uclsyn (University College London SYNthesis) is the software we used for spectral analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Smith 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Smalley et al. 2001)</ref>. atlas 9 models without convec-tive overshooting were used <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Castelli et al. 1997</ref>) and local thermodynamic equilibrium (LTE) is assumed. Spectral lines were measured manually by using equivalent widths. A global continuum fit was performed using iSpec <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Blanco-Cuaresma et al. 2014</ref>), however the local continuum still needed to be adjusted on a line-by-line basis within uclsyn. The atomic data used to generate the synthetic spectra was obtained from <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Kurucz &amp; Bell (1995)</ref>, although lines can also be input manually using atomic data from other sources. The broadening parameters that are input are microturbulence, macroturbulence, rotational velocity, and instrumental broadening. The radiative damping constant, Van der Waals damping constant, and the Stark broadening factor are input via the line list. We used the solar abundances from <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Asplund et al. (2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Line list</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Line selection</head><p>We selected spectral lines from the Kitt Peak Solar Atlas ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kurucz et al. 1984)</ref> by looking for unblended lines. It is important to have as many low EP lines as possible for the determination of T eff via the excitation balance, however many of these lines are in "resolved blends" 1 , which meant that they were initially ignored when selecting lines from the solar spectrum. All of the low EP lines listed in the NIST database <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Fuhr &amp; Wiese 2006</ref>) were then checked in the solar spectrum. Any that were still measurable despite being in a resolved blend were added to the line list. Any lines with EW greater than 0.12Å12Å were not included as these will skew the vmic. This is because the stronger lines are affected more by vmic and also because the stronger lines are more difficult to measure due to the extent of the wings.</p><p>A line selected in the Sun may not necessarily be measurable in other stars. Stars with higher metallicity will have more blended lines, as will cooler stars. However, as we checked each line manually in each star, it is not necessary to have different line lists for different T eff and metallicity ranges for our method. The majority of the lines are measurable in all of our spectra.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">Low metallicity</head><p>Two of the stars in this sample have low metallicity; 171 Pup has [Fe/H] = −0.76, and ν Ind has [Fe/H] = −1.46. It is still possible to get a solution for these stars, although most of the lines are very weak so are more prone to errors. Ideally a separate line list should be used for low metallicity stars so as not to use only very weak lines. Lines which are easily measurable and unblended in low metallicity stars are usually too strong or blended in solar-metallicity stars. However, as most planet host stars do not have such low metallicities, we deemed it beyond the scope of this work to also create a line list for the low metallicity stars.</p><p>1 A resolved blend is where two close-by spectral lines have blended wings, but the individual lines can still be measured.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Atomic data</head><p>The oscillator strength (log gf ) will affect the derived abundance for a line, however these values are not always known to great accuracy, which can create large errors in abundance. In order to deal with this problem, some authors instead use differential log gf values, i.e. those that are normalised to the Sun. Here, we create three line lists; one using the laboratory values thus giving the absolute abundances, and two differential line lists that use two different solar vmic values.</p><p>For the laboratory line list, the atomic data were taken from the VALD III database ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ryabchikova et al. 2015</ref>) and only the laboratory values for log gf were used. VALD II data were used for the log gf values for Fe ii. This is because the Fe ii log gf values from VALD III result in Fe ii abundances that are too low in the Sun. This changes the ionisation balance log g, which in turn changes the vmic. As T eff is dependent on vmic, the resulting T eff for the Sun becomes 5701 ± 33 K. The log g and vmic are 4.48 ± 0.08 dex and 0.72 ± 0.03 km s −1 respectively. This T eff is too low compared to the known solar value of 5777 K (Gray 2008), however when using the Fe ii log gf values from VALD II ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kupka et al. 1999</ref>) the solar parameters are now 5750 ± 31 K, 4.42 ± 0.06 dex, and 0.83 ± 0.02 km s −1 for T eff , log g, and vmic respectively.</p><p>It is known that the VALD values can be poorly determined, resulting in a large (∼0.6 dex) dispersion even in the Sun ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Sousa et al. 2014</ref>). In order to have a line list that uses the VALD atomic data and still be as accurate as possible, we imposed several criteria for line selection. If a selected line did not have laboratory data available, then it wasn't used. All lines were also required to have an abundance that didn't deviate more than 0.25 dex from the mean abundance in the Sun. When these lines were used across all of the sample stars, we found that there were still a number of lines that resulted in abundances that were consistently too low or too high in all stars compared to the mean abundance of each star. If there was an alternate laboratory log gf available in VALD that gave a better abundance, then this was used. If there were no alternate values available, then the lines were deleted from the list. Our log A(Fe) for the Sun is 7.56 ± 0.07 2 and the metallicity error is from the dispersion in the abundance values.</p><p>For the two differential line lists, the log gf was adjusted so that all of the lines give the <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Asplund et al. (2009)</ref> abundance of log A(Fe) = 7.5 in the Sun. In order to calculate the abundance of each line, the solar parameters (T eff = 5777 K and log g = 4.44 dex) need to be input, along with the solar vmic. Two different lists were produced using two different assumptions of solar vmic; 1.0 and 0.85 km s −1 , as there is no standard value for the solar vmic. Throughout the paper, the two lists will be referred to as differential(1) and differential(0.85). The line list is given in the appendix and uses the differential log gf values with a solar vmic of 1 km s −1 . 4800 5000 5200 5400 5600 5800 6000 6200 6400 6600 6800</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">∆ T eff (K)</formula><p>Differential T eff (K) with v mic = 1 <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">∆T eff = T eff differential(0.85) − T eff differential(1).</formula><p>The T eff derived differentially with the solar v mic of 0.85 km s −1 is hotter for stars &gt; 6000 K compared to the differential T eff derived with solar v mic of 1 km s −1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head><p>The parameters from B10 and H15 are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The T eff , log g, metallicity, and vmic results from this work are displayed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Tables 2, 3</ref>, 4, and 5 respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Comparison between laboratory and differential line lists</head><p>In this section, we compare the results from the laboratory and differential line lists to each other, and also compare the results from each list to the external parameters, i.e. the bolometric T eff , the photometric T eff , the binary log g, and the asteroseismic log g.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Temperature</head><p>There is good agreement in T eff between the laboratory and differential lists. There is a difference of 2 ± 35 K between the laboratory and differential(1) list, and a difference of 9 ± 16 K between the laboratory and differential(0.85) list. The difference in T eff between the two different differential lists is 11 ± 26 K. The T eff derived with the solar vmic of 0.85 km s −1 has a slightly higher T eff of 36 ± 17 K for stars hotter than 6000 K, as seen in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. The most noticeable difference is Procyon, where the T eff is 67 K higher. The difference in T eff is because T eff is dependent on vmic, and the output vmic for each star is dependent on which solar value was used initially to calculate the differential log gf .</p><p>The bolometric T eff is a "direct" temperature determination in that it is almost independent of stellar models. The temperature is found from the bolometric flux and the angular diameter. The comparison between our spectroscopic T eff using the laboratory line list and the bolometric T eff is shown in the top panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>. The values from both B10 and H15 are shown. H15 compiled bolometric temperatures for their sample of 34 Gaia FGK benchmark stars. The fact that there are two different versions of the bolometric T eff , which is a direct measurement and is supposed to represent the fundamental T eff of the star, is a matter of 4800 5000 5200 5400 5600 5800 6000 6200 6400 6600 6800 4800 5000 5200 5400 5600 5800 6000 6200 6400 6600 6800</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">∆ T eff = T eff (spec) - T eff (bol) Spectroscopic T eff (K) -</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">∆ T eff = T eff (spec) - T eff (phot)</formula><p>Spectroscopic T eff (K) -this work concern. It is difficult to compare our indirect values with the fundamental T eff when even those values are not certain. Our T eff using the laboratory list is hotter on average than B10 by 81 ± 86 K, and H15 by 32 ± 74 K. There is good agreement for the stars &lt; 6000 K, particularly for the H15 values. For the three stars hotter than 6000 K, our spectroscopic T eff values using the laboratory list are significantly hotter, bringing the difference to 180 ± 30 K for B10 and 113 ± 26 K for H15.</p><p>The differential(1) T eff is hotter than B10 by 87 ± 76 K and H15 by 36 ± 67 K. The differential(0.85) T eff is hotter than B10 by 91 ± 87 K and H15 by 41 ± 78 K. Therefore there is no advantage or disadvantage to using the laboratory line list for T eff .</p><p>The comparison between our spectroscopic T eff using the laboratory list and the photometric T eff from B10, which is derived from Strömgren photometric indices, is shown in the middle panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>. Our temperatures are systematically higher by 70 ± 80 K. The differential(1) T eff is hotter than the photometric T eff by 55 ± 80 K and the differential(0.85) T eff is hotter by 76 ± 81, K suggesting that the differential(1) list offers a slight improvement with T eff over the other two lists.  171 Pup 5747 ± 37 5771 ± 38 5760 ± 35 5783 ± 36 70 Oph A 5300 ± 43 5295 ± 55 5355 ± 23 5333 ± 23 α Cen A 5799 ± 38 5792 ± 37 5825 ± 21 5826 ± 21 α Cen B 5197 ± 52 5189 ± 82 5220 ± 31 5202 ± 31 α For 6281 ± 47 6275 ± 49 6253 ± 37 6289 ± 40 α Men 5606 ± 38 5614 ± 36 5627 ± 17 5620 ± 18 β Aql 5082 ± 41 5072 ± 50 5103 ± 24 5089 ± 26 β Hyi 5870 ± 37 5875 ± 36 5864 ± 25 5874 ± 26 β Vir 6224 ± 46 6231 ± 43 6209 ± 29 6232 ± 30 δ Eri 4976 ± 48 4960 ± 55 5023 ± 31 5005 ± 33 δ Pav 5576 ± 47 5560 ± 47 5611 ± 21 5599  <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>. The log g determined in this work. The second column gives the value based on the ionisation balance using the laboratory line list. The third and fourth columns give the log g determined when using abundances calculated differentially to the Sun, with a solar v mic of 1 and 0.85 km s −1 respectively. The last two columns give the log g calculated from the pressure broadened    4800 5000 5200 5400 5600 5800 6000 6200 6400 6600 6800</p><note type="other">Mg i b and Na i D lines. Star name Laboratory Differential Differential Mg i b Na i D v mic 1 km s −1 v mic 0.85 km s −1</note><note type="other">171 Pup 0.81 1.15 1.02 70 Oph A 0.79 0.94 0.79 α Cen A 0.87 1.02 0.89 α Cen B 0.74 0.85 0.71 α For 1.19 1.37 1.28 α Men 0.74 0.96 0.80 β Aql 0.91 0.96 0.86 β Hyi 1.00 1.17 1.07 β Vir 1.12 1.29 1.18 δ Eri 0.86 0.94 0.85 δ Pav 0.80 0.94 0.80 η Boo 1.36 1.49 1.41 η Ser 1.02 1.09 1.01 γ Pav 1.00 1.29 1.19 γ Ser 1.34 1.54 1.45 HR 5803 1.17 1.34 1.25 ι Hor 0.</note><formula xml:id="formula_4">∆ log g</formula><p>Differential T eff (K) with v mic = 1 <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. ∆log g = log g differential(0.85) − log g differential(1). The log g derived differentially with the solar v mic of 0.85 km s −1 is higher for stars &gt; 6000 K compared to the differential log g derived with solar v mic of 1 km s −1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Surface gravity</head><p>There is good agreement between the laboratory and differential line lists for log g. There is a difference of 0.00 ± 0.07 dex between laboratory and differential(1) and 0.01 ± 0.05 dex between laboratory and differential(0.85). The difference between the two differential lists is 0.01 ± 0.03 dex, however this depends on T eff as seen in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Only four stars in this sample have log g known from their binary nature. There is excellent agreement between ∆log g = log g (spec) -log g (ast)</p><p>T eff (K) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>. The difference between spectroscopic and asteroseismic log g as a function of T eff . The dotted line at 0.08 dex is the mean difference between log g spec and log g ast found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bruntt et al. (2012)</ref>. The blue line is the linear trend seen in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mortier et al. (2014</ref>). There appears to be a T eff dependence in our data, but if the two outliers (δ Eri and η Boo) are removed then this no longer holds.</p><p>the binary log g for Procyon (3.976 ± 0.016 dex) our spectroscopic log g using the laboratory list (3.96 ± 0.07 dex). The differential(1) and differential(0.85) lists give slightly lower log g values, 3.90 ± 0.05 and 3.93 ± 0.05 dex respectively. The binary log g for α Cen A is 4.307 ± 0.005 dex, which agrees with the spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list of 4.25 ± 0.09 dex within the errors. The differential(1) and differential(0.85) values, which are both 4.32 ± 0.04 dex, are in much better agreement with the fundamental log g. The same is true for 70 Oph A, where the spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list (4.35 ± 0.10 dex) agrees with the binary log g (4.468 ± 0.030) within the errors, but the differential(1) and differential(0.85) values of 4.46 ± 0.06 and 4.43 ± 0.06 dex respectively are in better agreement with the fundamental value.</p><p>The spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list of 4.36 ± 0.12 dex does not agree with the binary log g for α Cen B, which is 4.538 ± 0.008 dex. The differential(1) and differential (0.85) values of 4.40 ± 0.07 and 4.38 ± 0.07 dex respectively agree within the errors.</p><p>When comparing the spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list to the asteroseismic log g, there is a lot of dispersion as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>. This figure shows the difference between the spectroscopic log g that we derived and the asteroseismic log g as a function of the spectroscopic T eff with the laboratory list. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bruntt et al. (2012)</ref> found the mean difference between log g spec and log g ast to be 0.08 ± 0.07 dex for their sample of 93 solar-like Kepler stars, shown as a dashed line. In an analysis of 76 planet host stars by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mortier et al. (2014)</ref>, the difference was found to be dependent on T eff , and this is shown with the blue line.</p><p>The mean difference between the spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list and the asteroseismic log g is 0.04 ± 0.11 dex. There is no real improvement when using the differential lists, with the differential(1) list giving a mean difference of 0.04 ± 0.10 dex when compared to the astero- seismic log g, and the differential(0.85) list giving a difference of 0.03 ± 0.10 dex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Metallicity</head><p>The difference between [Fe/H] of the two differential analyses for our sample of stars is negligible; 0.00 ± 0.01 dex, showing that the choice of initial vmic does not affect the resulting abundance. Our laboratory [Fe/H] is also systematically higher than both differential lists by 0.08 ± 0.02 dex, as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>.</p><p>The laboratory [Fe/H] is also systematically higher than the B10 [Fe/H] by 0.09 ± 0.06 dex. Both differential lists are in good agreement with the B10 values (0.01 ± 0.05 dex for differential(1) and 0.01 ± 0.06 dex for differential(0.85)), which is to be expected as the B10 line list was also created differentially to the Sun.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.4">Microturbulence</head><p>Unlike T eff and log g which are physical parameters, the vmic of the Sun is model-dependent and is also strongly dependent on the line list used. While either solar vmic can be used when creating a differential line list, it is important to remember that using log gf values calculated from the Sun will create a significant bias when trying to determine the vmic for another star. This is seen in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 5</ref>, where the differential(0.85) line list always results in a lower vmic for other stars compared to the differential(1) list, as expected. The systematic offset is 0.11 ± 0.04 km s −1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Surface gravity from pressure broadened lines</head><p>We also obtained the log g for the pressure broadened Mg i b and Na i D lines, which are listed in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>. It is important to know the abundance of these elements before measuring the log g, so the EWs of several weaker Mg i and Na i lines were measured in order to determine the abundance. These are given in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. The error for the pressure broadened log g is determined from the error in the Na and Mg abundances.</p><p>The continuum is very difficult to measure around the Mg triplet, particularly for cooler stars with high metallicity. As such, the log g from the Na i D lines should be prioritised, although it should be noted that these lines can be affected by interstellar absorption. The Ca lines used in B10 were not used here as these lines are much more sensitive to changes in other broadening factors such as macroturbulence and rotational velocity compared to the Mg i b and Na i D lines.</p><p>The log g from the Mg triplet is significantly underestimated compared to the binary log g, except for Procyon. The log g from the Na i D lines on the other hand, agrees well with all of the binary log g values.</p><p>The Mg log g does not compare well with the asteroseismic log g, giving a mean difference of 0.24 ± 0.25 dex. The Na log g is somewhat better, with a mean difference of 0.09 ± 0.19 dex compared to the asteroseismic log g.</p><p>There is no advantage to using the Mg triplet in order to get the spectroscopic log g, as the values are highly discrepant from the binary and asteroseismic log g. The Na i D returns reasonable results and can be used as an additional check of the spectroscopic log g, but it does not offer any improvement over the log g from the ionisation balance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Mass and radius</head><p>The mass and radius were determined using the ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Torres et al. 2010</ref>) calibration, which determines M and R from the T eff , log g, and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>. Two determinations of mass and radius are given in <ref type="table">Table 6</ref>. The first uses the spectroscopic parameters determined using the differential(1) list. The second uses the asteroseismic log g, but the same values of T eff and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref> as in the first determination. There is an improvement in the precision for the radius.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Line selection</head><p>The T eff derived from the excitation balance, and thus the log g and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>, is sensitive to the exact lines used. α Cen B was used a test case and 1000 temperature runs were performed with 5 random Fe i lines removed for each run. The input parameters were those derived using the full set of lines with laboratory data; T eff = 5197 K, log g = 4.34 dex and vmic = 0.74 km s −1 . The resulting T eff distribution is shown in the top panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 6</ref>. The peak of the distribution is at 5198 ± 14 K. The middle panel shows the distribution with 10 Fe i lines removed, which has a peak at 5200 ± 20 K. The bottom panel has 30 Fe i lines removed with a peak at 5199 ± 42 K. With more lines removed, the scatter obviously increases and the result is that fewer runs return the input T eff . In low S/N (∼50) CORALIE or SOPHIE spectra that are frequently used to characterise planet host stars, it is quite common for ∼30 lines to be unmeasurable when using the <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Doyle et al. (2013)</ref> line list of 72 Fe lines.</p><p>The lowest temperatures (5150 -5185 K) in the plot with 5 Fe i lines removed are caused by the removal of two low EP lines; 6120 and 6625Å6625Å. The top panel of <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the correct excitation balance for a T eff of 5197 K using all of the Fe i lines. The middle panel of <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the excitation balance for the same T eff , using the <ref type="table">Table 6</ref>. The mass and radius are given in units of M ⊙ and R ⊙ . Mspec and Rspec are the values determined using spectroscopy with the differential(1) list. Mast and Rast use the asteroseismic log g, but the same spectroscopic T eff and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Star name</head><p>Mspec Rspec Mast Rast differential <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> differential <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> set of lines that give a lower T eff of 5150 K. The hottest temperatures (5220 -5249 K) are caused by one low EP line (5250Å5250Å) being removed, as seen in the lower panel of <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> for a T eff of 5249 K. This shows the importance of including as many low EP lines as possible. For cool stars, it is extremely difficult to determine the position of the continuum for wavelengths less than ∼5200Å ∼5200Å due to the increased strength of the lines, as well as the addition of molecular lines. However, not including the lines less than ∼5200Å∼5200Å only makes the solution worse. This is due to the removal of several low EP Fe i lines, as well as some Fe ii lines. The removal of Fe ii lines, even ones that are difficult to measure, will affect the ionisation balance log g. In the Sun, removing the lines below 5200Å5200Å results in log g = 4.36 dex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Differential analysis</head><p>When comparing the laboratory line list with the differential line lists, there is good agreement for T eff and log g, however the [Fe/H] of the laboratory line list is systematically higher. In this regard, there is no clear advantage to using the differential lists, especially as it is not possible to tell which metallicity is the "correct" value.</p><p>When comparing the differential line lists to each other, there is excellent agreement in metallicity between the two lists. However, there is a difference in T eff and log g as a function of increasing T eff , most likely due to the different vmic. As these lists use different solar vmic values, the vmic determined for the stellar sample will also be different and vmic will affect the T eff and log g.</p><p>There is no advantage or disadvantage to using either the laboratory or differential lists when comparing to the bolometric T eff or asteroseismic log g, as the mean difference between the spectral parameters and the external parameters is the same for all lists. However, the mean difference between the differential(1) list and the photometric T eff is lower than for the laboratory and differential(0.85) lists. There is excellent agreement between the log g with the laboratory list and the binary log g of Procyon, but for the other three binary stars, the differential lists are in better agreement.</p><p>Using either of the differential lists does not appear to have a negative effect on the parameters for stars with low metallicity or low log g, which suggests that differential analysis could be used on a wider range of stellar parameters than originally thought, although it would be better to test this with a larger sample.</p><p>While the line list using the laboratory log gf values from VALD does result in robust stellar parameters, for future HoSTS papers we will use the differential(1) list as it does seem to produce slightly more accurate results when comparing to the binary log g and the photometric T eff .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Fixing log g</head><p>As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>, our spectroscopic log g with the laboratory list does not always agree with the asteroseismic log g. However, the offset between the values does not agree with that found by either <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bruntt et al. (2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">) or Mortier et al. (2014</ref>, showing that while there can be systematic offsets 5020 5040 5060 5080 5100 5120 5140 5160 5180 5200 5220 5240 5260 5280 5300 5320 5340 5020 5040 5060 5080 5100 5120 5140 5160 5180 5200 5220 5240 5260 5280 5300 5320 5340 5020 5040 5060 5080 5100 5120 5140 5160 5180 5200 5220 5240 5260 5280 5300 5320 5340 between the log g spec and log g ast , this depends on the specific method used for the analysis. Our results show that there might be some dependency with T eff , as hotter stars tend to have log g spec higher than log g ast , where as cooler stars have a lower log g spec . However, the trend is not as obvious as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 6</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mortier et al. (2014)</ref>. The mean difference between log g spec and log g ast for our data is 0.04 EP (eV) <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. The top panel shows the correct excitation balance at T eff = 5197 K for α Cen B using using all of the Fe i lines. The middle panel shows one of the runs with 5 of the Fe i lines removed. The T eff derived with this set of lines is 5150 K, however the plot is shown for the correct T eff of 5197 K, thus introducing a slope. The bottom panel is for a derived T eff = 5249 K, where the 5250Å5250Å line is missing.</p><p>± 0.11 dex. If the two outliers, δ Eri and η Boo are removed, this difference reduces to 0.03 ± 0.08 dex. When fixing the log g to the asteroseismic value and redetermining the T eff , we found that the mean difference between the laboratory constrained and unconstrained T eff is 3 ± 13 K, showing that there is excellent agreement between the unconstrained laboratory spectroscopic T eff and the spectroscopic T eff using the laboratory list obtained when log g is fixed to the asteroseismic value. This is because acquiring the T eff via the excitation balance has little or no dependence on the log g. The excitation balance depends on the EP and the abundance of the Fe i lines, and these lines are not sensitive to changes in surface gravity. Changing the log g will therefore have a minimal effect on the T eff derived from this method.</p><p>In contrast, Mortier et al. <ref type="formula">(2014)</ref> find a mean difference of 68 K for their sample, however they also take into account the vmic when determining their temperatures. For this method, after the excitation T eff is determined with the log g fixed, the vmic is adjusted from the Fe i lines only (as the ionisation balance will no longer be met when including the Fe ii lines). Another iteration is run of the excitation balance T eff with the new vmic. When we computed the laboratory constrained T eff using this method, there is a mean difference of 18 ± 39 K between this and our unconstrained T eff , which is still not as large as that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Mortier et al. (2014)</ref>.</p><p>While fixing log g to the asteroseismic value does not have a significant effect on the spectroscopic parameters determined with this method, it may still be better to use the asteroseismic or transit log g, if available, when determining the mass and radius of the star as this will result in a more accurate mass and radius for the planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In this paper we have used a set of standard stars with known parameters to compare laboratory with differential line lists and also to test if the log g needs to be fixed to an external value. We have shown that the laboratory log gf values from VALD can be used to obtain robust parameters, although there may be a slight advantage to using the differential(1) line list. Despite the fact that we have subgiants and low metallicity stars in our sample, the differential lists still result in robust parameters, showing that it is possible to use the differential line lists across a range of stellar parameters that deviate somewhat from the solar values.</p><p>The choice of solar vmic when creating a differential line list will create a systematic offset in vmic for the stars analysed. This should be borne in mind when comparing vmic to that derived via different methods, but it is not a problem when a homogeneous analysis is performed using only one value. The different vmic will also cause differences in T eff and log g as a function of increasing T eff . Using the differential(0.85) list will give higher values of T eff and log g for hotter stars compared to the differential(1) list.</p><p>The T eff is sensitive to the selection of Fe i lines. Randomly removing Fe i lines decreases the chances of returning the correct T eff in 1000 temperature iterations. The T eff distribution for α Cen A with 5 Fe i lines removed is 5198 ± 14 K, for 10 Fe i lines removed the T eff distribution is 5200 ± 20 K, and for 30 Fe i lines removed the T eff distribution is 5199 ± 42 K. The T eff is particularly sensitive to the number of low EP lines used and removing certain low EP lines can change the T eff by ∼50 K. Therefore it is important to use as many low EP lines as possible.</p><p>We have also shown that fixing the log g to the transit or asteroseismology value offers no improvement to the spectroscopic T eff and [Fe/H] for the EW method of spectral analysis. It is therefore sufficient to use the unconstrained values so that the spectral analysis will be self-consistent. However, fixing the log g to an external value does improve the stellar parameters in other methods which rely on comparing the observed spectrum directly to the synthetic spectrum ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Torres et al. 2012</ref>). Also, the transit or asteroseismic log g should be used when determining the stellar mass and radius, as this will improve the precision on the planetary mass and radius.</p><p>The inclusion of the log g from the pressure broadened Mg i b and Na i D lines does not improve the result, and the Mg i b log g is usually worse. The Na i D lines can still be used as a check, but this log g is not better than the ionisation balance method.</p><p>While we have chosen to use the differential(1) list and not to fix log g in future HoSTS papers, we conclude that the most important factor is to have a consistent analysis across all stars. Future analyses may also avail of the improved stellar radii, and thus planetary radii, determined from the Gaia parallaxes, which will have improved precision after the second data release <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Stassun et al. 2016</ref>). <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table A1</ref>. The line list as used in uclsyn. The log gf values are are those created differentially to the Sun with v mic = 1 km s −1 . The radiative damping constant and the Stark broadening factor are the inverse logs of the values given in VALD, as the inverse log values are required for uclsyn. The Van der Waals (VDW) damping constants are listed as they are in VALD for those with ABO values. VDW without ABO values are given as the inverse log. A temperature cutoff is given for some lines if they are too strong or blend above or below a certain T eff . Lines that consistently have an EW &gt; 0.12Å12Å are deemed to be too strong.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Element</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. The top panel shows the comparison between the spectroscopic T eff with the laboratory line list from this work and the bolometric T eff of Bruntt et al. (2010) (red circles) and Heiter et al. (2015) (blue triangles). The bottom panel shows the comparison between the spectroscopic T eff and the photometric T eff from B10. Our temperatures are hotter for stars with T eff &gt; 6000 K.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The metallicity determined in this work. All abundances are relative to Asplund et al. (2009). The second column gives the [Fe/H] using the laboratory line list. The third and fourth columns give the [Fe/H] determined when using abundances calculated differentially to the Sun, with a solar v mic of 1 and 0.85 km s −1 respectively. The fifth and sixth columns give the [Mg/H] and [Na/H] abundances respectively. Star name Laboratory Differential Differential [Mg/H] [Na/H] v mic 1 km s −1 v mic 0.85 km s −1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>∆Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. The comparison between the laboratory [Fe/H] and the differential [Fe/H] (assuming a solar v mic of 1 km s −1 ). ∆[Fe/H] = laboratory − differential. The laboratory values are systematically higher.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. The T eff distribution for 1000 temperature runs of α Cen B with random Fe i lines removed. The top panel has 5 Fe i lines removed, the middle panel has 10 Fe i lines removed, and the bottom panel has 30 Fe i lines removed. The majority of runs still return the input value of 5197 K, but the scatter obviously increases when more lines are removed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . The bolometric and photometric T eff , the binary and asteroseismic log g, and the [Fe/H] from Bruntt et al. (2010) are listed. The errors on the photometric T eff are 90 K and the errors on the [Fe/H] are 0.07 dex. The bolometric T eff values from Heiter et al. (2015) are also given.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Star name 
HD 
T eff bol 
T eff bol 
T eff phot 
log g bin 
log g ast 
[Fe/H] 
B10 
H15 

171 Pup 
63077 
5790 
4.244 ± 0.023 
−0.86 
70 Oph A 
165341 
4.468 ± 0.030 
4.555 ± 0.023 
0.12 
α Cen A 
128620 
5746 ± 50 
5792 ± 16 
5635 
4.307 ± 0.005 
4.318 ± 0.017 
0.22 
α Cen B 
128621 
5140 ± 56 
5231 ± 20 
4.538 ± 0.008 
4.530 ± 0.018 
0.30 
α For 
20010 
6105 
4.003 ± 0.033 
−0.28 
α Men 
43834 
0.15 
β Aql 
188512 
4986 ± 111 
3.525 ± 0.036 
−0.21 
β Hyi 
2151 
5840 ± 59 
5873 ± 45 
5870 
3.955 ± 0.018 
−0.10 
β Vir 
102870 
6012 ± 64 
6083 ± 41 
6150 
4.125 ± 0.018 
0.12 
δ Eri 
23249 
4986 ± 57 
4954 ± 30 
3.827 ± 0.018 
0.15 
δ Pav 
190248 
5540 
4.306 ± 0.034 
0.38 
η Boo 
121370 
6028 ± 47 
6099 ± 28 
6025 
3.822 ± 0.019 
0.24 
η Ser 
168723 
3.029 ± 0.037 
−0.11 
γ Pav 
203608 
6135 
4.397 ± 0.022 
−0.74 
γ Ser 
142860 
6245 
4.169 ± 0.032 
−0.26 
HR 5803 
139211 
6280 
4.229 ± 0.023 
−0.04 
ι Hor 
17051 
6110 
4.399 ± 0.022 
0.15 
ξ Hya 
100407 
4984 ± 54 
5044 ± 40 
2.883 ± 0.032 
0.21 
µ Ara 
160691 
5690 
4.228 ± 0.023 
0.32 
ν Ind 
211998 
3.432 ± 0.035 
−1.63 
Procyon A 61421 
6494 ± 48 
6554 ± 84 
6595 
3.976 ± 0.016 
3.972 ± 0.018 
0.01 
τ Cet 
10700 
5383 ± 47 
5414 ± 21 
5420 
4.533 ± 0.018 
−0.48 
τ PsA 
210302 
6385 
4.240 ± 0.021 
0.01 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The effective temperatures derived in this work. The second column gives the T eff based on 
the abundances from the laboratory list. The third column gives the constrained T eff after fixing the 
log g to the asteroseismic value. The fourth and fifth columns give the T eff determined when using 
abundances calculated differentially to the Sun, with a solar v mic of 1 and 0.85 km s −1 respectively. 

Star name 
Laboratory 
Fixing log g 
Differential 
Differential 
v mic 1 km s −1 
v mic 0.85 km s −1 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Table 5 . The v mic determined in this work. The errors are 0.03 km s −1 . The second column gives the v mic based on the laboratory line list. The third and fourth columns give the v mic when using abundances calculated differentially to the Sun, with a solar v</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>mic 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>Table A1 . Line list (continued)</head><label>A1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Element Wavelength 
EP 
log gf 
radiative 
VDW 
stark 
T eff cutoff 

Fe i 
5724.454 
4.28 
-2.549 6.46E+07 
914.278 
2.04E-05 
Fe i 
5741.846 
4.26 
-1.656 2.95E+08 
725.232 
2.69E-06 
Fe i 
5793.913 
4.22 
-1.642 2.95E+08 
714.231 
5.13E-06 
Fe i 
5806.717 
4.61 
-0.928 2.09E+08 
985.281 
1.95E-05 
Fe i 
5811.917 
4.14 
-2.337 4.07E+07 
1.58E-08 
9.55E-07 
Fe i 
5827.875 
3.28 
-3.226 1.66E+08 
748.245 
3.89E-06 
Fe i 
5849.682 
3.70 
-3.011 6.03E+07 
379.305 
1.32E-06 
Fe i 
5853.150 
1.49 
-5.097 2.14E+07 
1.62E-08 
7.59E-08 
Fe i 
5855.091 
4.61 
-1.575 2.14E+08 
962.279 
2.88E-05 
Fe i 
5856.083 
4.29 
-1.572 9.77E+07 
404.264 
5.50E-06 
Fe i 
5861.107 
4.28 
-2.399 2.40E+08 
854.279 
4.79E-05 
Fe i 
5905.689 
4.65 
-0.822 2.14E+08 
994.282 
1.74E-05 
Fe i 
5929.667 
4.55 
-1.237 2.14E+08 
864.275 
2.63E-05 
Fe i 
5930.173 
4.65 
-0.326 2.09E+08 
983.281 
1.95E-05 
Too strong in high [Fe/H] stars &lt; 5300 K 
Fe i 
5934.653 
3.93 
-1.184 6.03E+07 
959.247 
5.13E-06 
Fe i 
5956.692 
0.86 
-4.527 1.00E+04 
227.252 
6.76E-07 
Fe ii 
5991.376 
3.15 
-3.593 3.47E+08 
172.221 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6012.206 
2.22 
-3.845 4.79E+06 
309.27 
1.67E+02 
Blended &gt; 5800 K 
Fe i 
6024.049 
4.55 
0.014 
2.09E+08 
823.275 
8.71E-06 
Too strong in high [Fe/H] stars &lt; 5800 K 
Fe i 
6027.050 
4.08 
-1.073 1.02E+08 
1.66E-08 
9.33E-07 
Fe i 
6034.033 
4.31 
-2.397 1.95E+08 
710.223 
1.00E-05 
Fe i 
6055.992 
4.73 
-0.433 2.09E+08 
1029.286 
1.12E-05 
Fe i 
6065.482 
2.61 
-1.518 1.17E+08 
354.234 
5.13E-07 
Too strong in high [Fe/H] stars &lt; 5800 K 
Fe ii 
6084.111 
3.20 
-3.815 3.47E+08 
173.223 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6093.666 
4.61 
-1.369 2.14E+08 
866.274 
2.69E-05 
Fe i 
6096.662 
3.98 
-1.844 5.62E+07 
963.25 
5.13E-06 
Fe i 
6098.280 
4.56 
-1.786 2.75E+08 
797.269 
2.00E-05 
Fe ii 
6113.322 
3.22 
-4.184 3.47E+08 
173.228 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6120.249 
0.92 
-5.915 1.00E+04 
1.51E-08 
6.76E-07 
Fe ii 
6149.250 
3.89 
-2.750 3.16E+08 
186.269 
2.95E-07 
Blended &lt; 5700 K 
Fe i 
6151.617 
2.18 
-3.331 1.95E+08 
277.263 
6.92E-07 
Fe i 
6157.730 
4.08 
-1.135 7.76E+07 
1.62E-08 
9.33E-07 
Fe i 
6173.340 
2.22 
-2.885 2.04E+08 
281.266 
6.92E-07 
Fe i 
6187.987 
3.94 
-1.657 5.62E+07 
903.244 
4.17E-06 
Fe i 
6200.313 
2.61 
-2.330 1.20E+08 
350.235 
5.13E-07 
Fe i 
6213.429 
2.22 
-2.569 2.04E+08 
280.265 
6.92E-07 
Fe ii 
6239.366 
2.81 
-4.745 2.95E+08 
167.219 
2.95E-07 
Blended &gt; 5800 K 
Fe ii 
6239.953 
3.89 
-3.481 3.16E+08 
186.271 
2.95E-07 
Blended &gt; 6000 K 
Fe i 
6240.645 
2.22 
-3.309 6.46E+06 
301.272 
7.41E-07 
Fe ii 
6247.557 
3.89 
-2.383 3.16E+08 
186.272 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6252.554 
2.40 
-1.733 1.05E+08 
326.245 
8.51E-07 
Too strong &lt; 5800 K 
Fe i 
6265.131 
2.18 
-2.514 2.00E+08 
274.261 
6.92E-07 
Too strong 5200 K 
Fe i 
6330.838 
4.73 
-1.185 2.57E+08 
915.277 
3.16E-05 
Fe i 
6335.340 
2.20 
-2.254 2.00E+08 
275.261 
6.92E-07 
Too strong &lt; 5700 K 
Fe ii 
6369.462 
2.89 
-4.188 2.95E+08 
169.204 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6392.538 
2.28 
-3.939 2.04E+08 
310.243 
6.92E-07 
Fe i 
6400.318 
0.92 
-4.153 2.69E+04 
1.48E-08 
6.31E-07 
Fe ii 
6432.680 
2.89 
-3.555 2.95E+08 
169.204 
2.95E-07 
Fe ii 
6446.410 
6.22 
-2.001 4.37E+08 
181.214 
2.95E-07 
Fe ii 
6456.383 
3.90 
-2.028 3.16E+08 
185.276 
2.95E-07 
Fe ii 
6482.204 
6.22 
-1.830 3.31E+08 
181.212 
2.95E-07 
Fe i 
6498.938 
0.96 
-4.629 2.29E+04 
226.253 
6.17E-07 
Fe i 
6593.871 
2.43 
-2.302 1.02E+08 
321.247 
8.32E-07 
Too strong &lt; 5200 K 
Fe i 
6608.024 
2.28 
-3.958 2.00E+08 
306.242 
6.92E-07 
Fe i 
6625.022 
1.01 
-5.340 1.15E+04 
1.48E-08 
6.17E-07 
Fe i 
6627.540 
4.55 
-1.503 2.14E+08 
754.209 
4.57E-06 
Fe i 
6646.940 
2.61 
-3.957 9.12E+07 
339.243 
8.32E-07 
Fe i 
6699.150 
4.59 
-2.125 1.23E+08 
297.273 
2.34E-06 
Fe i 
6703.568 
2.76 
-3.019 1.20E+08 
320.264 
5.25E-07 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9" validated="false"><head>Table A1 . Line list (continued)</head><label>A1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Element Wavelength 
EP 
log gf 
radiative 
VDW 
stark 
T eff cutoff 

Fe i 
6710.316 
1.49 
-4.774 1.86E+07 
252.246 
7.08E-07 
Fe i 
6725.353 
4.10 
-2.209 2.51E+08 
897.241 
4.17E-06 
Fe i 
6732.070 
4.58 
-2.177 6.61E+07 
274.26 
4.27E-06 
Fe i 
6733.151 
4.64 
-1.451 2.57E+08 
781.273 
4.37E-06 
Fe i 
6745.970 
4.08 
-2.711 3.09E+07 
1.51E-08 
9.77E-07 
Fe i 
6750.150 
2.42 
-2.564 4.90E+06 
335.241 
7.41E-07 
Fe i 
6752.705 
4.64 
-1.212 2.63E+08 
778.274 
3.39E-06 
Fe i 
6806.847 
2.73 
-3.112 1.17E+08 
313.268 
8.13E-07 
Fe i 
6810.257 
4.61 
-0.980 2.63E+08 
873.275 
5.89E-06 
Fe i 
6837.016 
4.59 
-1.718 7.08E+07 
273.258 
7.59E-07 
Fe i 
6839.840 
2.56 
-3.333 1.12E+08 
330.248 
8.71E-07 
Fe i 
6842.679 
4.64 
-1.206 2.24E+08 
896.279 
2.04E-05 
Fe i 
6857.243 
4.08 
-2.067 1.70E+07 
1.51E-08 
9.33E-07 
Fe i 
6858.145 
4.61 
-0.953 2.69E+08 
765.211 
2.69E-06 
Fe i 
6862.492 
4.56 
-1.419 3.89E+08 
804.269 
1.32E-05 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot">MNRAS 000, 1-12 (2016)</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> Abundances can be given in the format of log(A) + 12, where log(A) is the number ratio of the element with respect to hydrogen, log (N el /N H ). The format [X/H] refers to the abundance of an element relative to the Sun, i.e. [Fe/H] = 0 for the Sun. MNRAS 000, 1-12 (2016)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Annelies Mortier and Dimitri Veras for helpful discussions. A.P.D. acknowledges support from the Leverhulme grant RPG-2014-082. This work has been partially funded by the Programa UNAM-DGAPA-PAPIIT IA-103215. Based on data obtained from the ESO Science Archive Facility.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: LINE LIST</head><p>This paper has been typeset from a T E X/L A T E X file prepared by the author.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Asplund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Grevesse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sauval</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">481</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">729</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blanco-Cuaresma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Soubiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Heiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jofré</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">569</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Piskunov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">805</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brugamyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dodson-Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sneden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">APJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">738</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bruntt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">405</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1907</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bruntt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">423</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Castelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gratton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">841</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">332</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">213</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Doyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3164</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fuhr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wiese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physical and Chemical Reference Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1669</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Girardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bressan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bertelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chiosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gómez Maqueo Chew</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">768</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Observation and Analysis of Stellar Photospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Heiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jofré</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gustafsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Korn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Soubiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Thévenin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">582</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kupka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Piskunov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ryabchikova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stempels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic Line Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory</title>
		<editor>R.L. Kurucz and B. Bell) Kurucz CD-ROM</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, Mass</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Furenlid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Testerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Solar flux atlas from 296 to 1300 nm</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meléndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Asplund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gustafsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">704</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mortier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Adibekyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Delgado</forename><surname>Mena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Montalto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Israelian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">558</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mortier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Adibekyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brandão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">572</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ryabchikova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Piskunov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stempels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Heiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pakhomov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Barklem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Scr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54005</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schuler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Flateau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cunha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ghezzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">732</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Smalley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dworetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.astro.keele.ac.uk/∼bs/publs/uclsyn.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C ; G</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">561</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of London Sousa S</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Ph.D. Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sozzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Laird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;donovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">664</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1190</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1609.04389</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Struve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Elvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">409</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1934" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ohkubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sadakane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">451</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sozzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">757</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">161</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Seager S., ed., Exoplanets</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>University of Arizona Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wittenmyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
