<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">THE CONTINUED IMPORTANCE OF HABITABILITY STUDIES</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ramses</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
							<email>rramirez@elsi.jp</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vladimir</forename><surname>Airapetian</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yuka</forename><surname>Fujii</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Keiko</forename><surname>Hamano</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amit</forename><surname>Levi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tyler</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robin</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wordsworth</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Earth-Life Science Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Earth-Life Science Institute and Tokyo Institute of Technology)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Earth-Life Science Institute and Tokyo Institute of Technology)</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">NASA Goddard Space Flight Center and American University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>152-8550</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Arizona State University) Eric T. Wolf (University of Colorado at Boulder)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Harvard University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Harvard University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">THE CONTINUED IMPORTANCE OF HABITABILITY STUDIES</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>A white paper submitted in response to the NAS call on Exoplanet Science Strategy Lead Author: Co-authors: Dorian S. Abbot (University of Chicago)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SECTION 1: HABITABILITY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1a) Habitable zones: extensions in space</head><p>The outer edge of the HZ is extraordinarily sensitive to the allowable greenhouse gas combinations. For instance, the solar system's outer edge extends from ~1.7 to 10 AU if young planets can accrete hundreds to thousands of bars of hydrogen, H2, from the protoplanetary disk <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. Habitable conditions (e.g. surface conditions warm enough to support liquid water) for such planets located within the classical HZ may last a few to tens of millions of years <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>, possibly longer at farther distances <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref> or if biological feedbacks can regulate H2 <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>.</p><p>Moreover, H2 can be volcanically-outgassed within a background CO2 atmosphere, increasing the classical HZ width by ~ 50% or more <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>. If mantle conditions can remain reducing enough and/or H2 escape rates to space are sufficiently slowed, habitable conditions within the classical HZ may last on Gyr timescales <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>[6].</p><p>In the latter scenario, such secondary greenhouse gases can confound carbonate-silicate cycle predictions suggesting that CO2 pressures for habitable planets should increase towards the outer edge <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. This is because additional absorbers (like H2) lower the CO2 amounts needed to support habitable surface conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>.</p><p>Related concerns: a. Would it be possible for life to subsist on a H2-based form of photosynthesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[8]</ref>? b. The effects of secondary greenhouse gases on HZ boundaries are just beginning to be explored. Other greenhouse gas combinations should also be assessed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1b) Habitable zones: changes with time</head><p>Although most HZ studies have focused on the main-sequence phase of stellar evolution, the pre-main-sequence is crucial in discussions of planetary habitability. The habitability of Mstar planets should be questioned for at least two reasons: a. Such HZ planets (e.g. TRAPPIST-1) should have lost much -if not all -of their surface water inventory following a runaway greenhouse episode during the superluminous pre-main-sequence phase <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>[10] <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref> unless they could have accreted a few tens % of their mass in water <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref> [13]. b. Large fluxes of stellar radiation (X-ray and UV) and stellar winds could significantly erode exoplanetary atmospheres over geological timescales <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref>.</p><p>Thus, M-star planets located in the HZ today may face extra challenges to their habitability. The entire spectrum of A -M stars should be observed with these caveats in mind.</p><p>Related concerns:</p><p>a. Can desiccated M-dwarf HZ planets be partially replenished by later meteoritic impacts or mantle degassing and become potentially habitable <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1c) Magma oceans as keys to understanding atmospheric evolution and habitability</head><p>In addition, the pre-main-sequence phase is crucial for understanding how worlds retain and lose volatiles during this stage of early accretion <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Moreover, high levels of abiotically-produced oxygen, O2, incorrectly linked to life, may accumulate in magma ocean atmospheres <ref type="bibr">[10]</ref>. However, the resulting magma ocean and impactinduced soil oxidation processes may be important O2 sinks <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref> <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>. Thus, the magma ocean stage may explain differences in evolutionary histories between Earth and Venus and could elucidate the conditions necessary for the emergence of life on exoplanets.</p><p>Related concerns: a. Most magma ocean studies to date have considered mostly H2O-or CO2-dominated atmospheres <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>[16] <ref type="bibr">[18]</ref>[19], but many atmospheric compositions are possible depending on impactor chemistry <ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>. These should all be explored. b. This early stage of planetary evolution could be the key to providing a more definitive HZ inner edge, improving our ability to target worlds that are likely to have sizeable water inventories <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1d) The possible habitability of ocean worlds</head><p>It has been argued that the carbonate-silicate cycle requires some land to operate, which suggests that ocean worlds (which have no land and possess total water inventories that are many times that of Earth's) may not be habitable <ref type="bibr">[21]</ref>. However, sea ice enriched in clathrates should readily form within the resulting high CO2 atmospheric environments predicted for such planets, providing conditions favorable for the initiation of life <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>. Plus, the carbonate-silicate cycle may be replaced by one in which net outgassing of CO2 is balanced by a net ocean influx <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>. High CO2 levels may also cool the stratosphere sufficiently to prevent a moist greenhouse <ref type="bibr">[22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SECTION 2: CLIMATE COMMUNITY COLLABORATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2a) 1-D and 3-D climate models as planetary habitability assessment tools</head><p>Until recently, virtually all exoplanet habitability studies had been performed using 1-D climate models. However, the types of climate models used to perform habitability assessments have significantly diversified over the past ~5 years. Exoplanet habitability studies are now routinely performed using a wide array of 1-D (including energy balance models) (e.g.</p><p>[  <ref type="bibr">[33]</ref>) climate models, with some studies employing both <ref type="bibr">[34]</ref> <ref type="bibr">[35]</ref> or even hybrid approaches <ref type="bibr">[36]</ref>.</p><p>This trend has occurred because both 1-D and 3-D climate models have complementary advantages and disadvantages. 1-D models are computationally cheap, allowing quick exploration of parameter space, more complex radiative transfer and atmospheric chemistry, and are more easily coupled to other (e.g. interior, escape, stellar, photochemical) models. For instance, atmospheric and magma ocean processes can be readily coupled in 1-D models <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref>, allowing volatile retention and O2 build-up to be quantified. Also, coupled climatephotochemical calculations are routinely performed <ref type="bibr">[24]</ref>.</p><p>In contrast, 3-D models calculate more atmospheric processes self-consistently than can be done with 1-D models, which have to make more simplifying assumptions regarding dynamics, relative humidity, and clouds. Thus, 3-D models are used to assess the subtleties of atmospheres in greater detail, which includes evaluating complex circulation patterns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2b) The need for collaborations between 1-D and 3-D modelers</head><p>Unfortunately, there is currently a lack of information exchange between the 1-D and 3-D climate modeling communities. However, community interactions are necessary for addressing recent unresolved differences in model predictions such as: SECTION 3: CURRENT LIMITATIONS AND SUGGESTED OBSERVATIONS All models have to make simplifications, however. With 3-D models, this usually means tuning poorly-understood processes or parameterizing them based on how they operate on Earth. With 1-D models, this requires making assumptions about the relative humidity and lapse rate. Unfortunately, such simplified approaches are almost certainly inadequate to study exoplanets. Plus, current observations are also woefully limited. For example, present observational capabilities are insufficient to characterize terrestrial HZ planets and their atmospheres in great detail, requiring modelers to "invent" atmospheric compositions and guess what the values for specific planetary parameters may be. Thus, major technological advances in observational techniques are necessary to produce data that is of sufficient quality to inform and substantially improve exoplanet climate models. In spite of these limitations, some examples of observations that can still be made today and in the near-future include:</p><p>a. Do M-star HZ planets have atmospheres? If they do, does O2 build up? Does O2 build up on HZ planets orbiting other star types? HabEx and LUVOIR could observe atmospheres for signs of O2 buildup at VIS/NIR wavelengths. ELTs can also detect O2 through multiple transits <ref type="bibr">[42]</ref>. b. OST and JWST <ref type="bibr">[43]</ref> could detect O3 in O2-rich atmospheres. c. The ELTs may be able to detect thermal emission from magma oceans <ref type="bibr">[44]</ref> <ref type="bibr">[45]</ref>. d. The ELTs may observe nearby M-stars for planets located in the pre-mainsequence HZ since they can work at small inner working angles <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>. e. High predicted CO2 pressures for outer edge classical HZ planets lower scale heights and increase the difficulty to observe bioindicators in transmission spectroscopy. However, H2 can increase atmospheric scale height in sufficiently high quantities, which improves bioindicator detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>[46]. JWST could target the TRAPPIST-1 planets and LHS-1140b <ref type="bibr">[47]</ref>. f. Ocean worlds with sufficient water may be deduced from other types of habitable planets. Lower computed densities for ocean worlds would distinguish them from drier ones, breaking the mass-radius degeneracy. Moreover, should such atmospheres be CO2-rich <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>, lower scale heights would distinguish them from worlds with H/He outer envelopes.</p><p>Once enough planetary atmospheres inside and outside the HZ are characterized, statistics will be available to test and improve model predictions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. In turn, improved climate models would be used to provide better interpretations of observations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FINAL SUMMARY</head><p>As the direct links between theory (Section 1) and observations (Section 3) suggest, theoretical habitability studies will remain indispensable for observations. This is because such studies, which include understanding the planetary (e.g. atmospheric, geologic) and stellar processes 1 that make a planet more or less likely to support life, provide the roadmap for making proper observations. Continued work on habitability is essential even if life elsewhere happens to be exactly like it is on Earth-which would still have appeared very differently to an extraterrestrial observer examining our world at different points in geologic history <ref type="bibr">[48]</ref>.</p><p>The likelihood of finding life can be increased by suspending some of our most cherished Earth-centric notions of habitability, whatever they may be (e.g. carbonate-silicate cycles, CO2-H2O atmospheres, oxygen biochemistries), no matter how compelling they may seem, and considering assessing alternate scenarios as well. We do not know what extraterrestrial life may be like, so it is self-restricting to generalize life elsewhere solely based on a limited understanding about this planet. Healthy scientific speculation will be key to making progress given limited observations. Both 1-D and 3-D climate models will be essential for advancing theoretical habitability studies. Community partnerships aimed at resolving model differences will lead to improved exoplanet climate models, maximizing the utility of such theoretical habitability studies. Such efforts would ultimately lead to improved observational interpretations as well.</p><p>However, improvements to theoretical modeling efforts are currently stymied by the lack of detailed exoplanetary observations. Although drawing upon knowledge from various solar system bodies to infer exoplanetary processes has been a useful tactic <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>[5] <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>[15] <ref type="bibr">[49]</ref>, having access to better observations would lead to even bigger advances in our understanding. This situation would vastly improve with technological (e.g. engineering) advancements in observational techniques, including direct imaging. Even with current limitations, we have suggested some observations that can still be made with upcoming and next generation missions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>a</head><label></label><figDesc>. Does relative humidity increase with surface temperature as 1-D models predict [37][38] or can it decrease as suggested by some 3-D models [39]? b. Is the moist greenhouse for M-star inner edge planets triggered at the low mean surface temperatures predicted in some 3-D models [28][31] or at the higher temperatures calculated in other 3-D and 1-D models [1][40]? c. Do surface temperature inversions in very warm atmospheres truly occur as predicted in recent 3-D simulations [41]? d. How valid is the 1-D moist adiabatic lapse rate assumption for planetary atmospheres [1][41]?</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> Although we have focused on climate modeling in this white paper, we also support more theoretical habitability studies in other areas (e.g. interiors, photochemistry, volatile delivery, stellar atmospheres, aeronomy, and atmospheric escape).</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>L3. [5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJL. L4. [6</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Geosci. 7</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJL</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bains</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>63. [17] Kurosawa, K. EPSL 429</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Geosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ. 18] Marcq, E.. et al. JGR</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salvador</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1002/2017JE005286</idno>
		<idno>178. [22</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">208</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">771</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Showman ; Kopparapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>L1. [31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EPSL</title>
		<editor>30] Wolf, E.T.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">804</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haqq-Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi:10.1002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">852</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">/2017je005383 ;</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Abbot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>L17. [35</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">774</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Checlair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Geosci.. 6</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">845</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5787" to="5792" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>AsBio. 40</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leconte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Geosci. 7</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nature</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
