<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Finding and Characterizing Other Worlds: the Thermal-IR ELT Opportunity</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Finding and Characterizing Other Worlds: the Thermal-IR ELT Opportunity</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Executive Summary: The next generation ground-based extremely large telescopes (ELTs) present incredible opportunities to discover and characterize diverse planetary systems, even potentially habitable worlds. Adaptive-optics assisted thermal-IR (3-14 µm) imaging is a powerful tool to study exoplanets with extant 6-12 meter telescopes. ELTs have the spatial resolution and sensitivity that offer an unparalleled expansion of the available discovery space. AO-assisted thermal-IR instruments on ELTs will be superior to JWST for high contrast imaging in the thermal-IR, and complementary to high contrast observations at shorter wavelengths, in space or with second-generation extreme AO instruments. With appropriate investments in instrumentation and precursor observations, thermal-IR equipped ELTs could image the first terrestrial and super-earth planets around nearby stars, opening the door to characterization of potentially habitable planets from the ground and space. Direct imaging and secondary eclipse measurements are two ways to directly detect light from other worlds. To date, direct detection is limited to dozens of objects beyond several AU (high contrast imaging-see Figure 1) and within a few tenths of AU (secondary eclipse). While characterizing these atmospheres provides fundamental insights, most exoplanets are found at intermediate separations which have yet to be studied (e.g. Meyer et al. 2018, A&amp;A, in press, arXiv:1707.05256). Characterizing those within the liquid-water or &apos;habitable zone&apos; of stars is clearly a priority. The probability for transit, and thus secondary eclipse, drops as a function of semi-major axis, while direct imaging of self-luminous planets is easier at larger orbital radii. Imaging can be achieved by observing reflected light or thermal emission each carrying important characterization information. Both reflect light and thermal emission of a planet depend on stellar luminosity, orbital separation, planet radius, and albedo as a Figure 1-Planet mass as a function of orbital separation (from Pepe et al. 2014, Nature, 513, 358). Orange circles are transiting planets (including those with direct detection secondary eclipse) with confirmed RV masses. Open circles are RV discovered planets, while green points represent planets detected through timing variations. Magenta points represent microlensing detections and blue diamonds are companions discovered through direct imaging (those numbered have mass ratios relative to their star &lt; 0.02 within 100 AU). Notice the gap between transits (including secondary eclipse) in orange and direct imaging in blue.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 -</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 -At left raw contrast achievable with a thermal-IR annular grove phase mask coronagraphs in the lab (Delacroix et al. 2013, A&amp;A, 513, A98). At right the achievable contrast with the MIRI four quadrant phase mask on JWST (Boccaletti et al. 2015,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 -</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4 -Detectability of terrestrial planets and super-earths from the expected performance of METIS on the E-ELT (from Quanz et al. 2015, IJAsB, 14, 279). At left are the expectation values of planets detected as a function of equilibrium temperature and planet radius (with marginal distributions for 3.58 mm L-band). At right are the estimated flux densities for one earth-radius planets as a function of planet temperature and distance in parsecs assuming thermal equilibrium.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
