<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:20+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Dusty tails of evaporating exoplanets I. Constraints on the dust composition</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-06-21">June 21, 2018 June 21, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Lieshout</surname></persName>
							<email>r.vanlieshout@uva.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Science Park 904</addrLine>
									<postCode>1098 XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Science Park 904</addrLine>
									<postCode>1098 XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dominik</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Amsterdam</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Science Park 904</addrLine>
									<postCode>1098 XH</postCode>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysics/IMAPP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Radboud University Nijmegen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 9010</postBox>
									<postCode>6500 GL</postCode>
									<settlement>Nijmegen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Dusty tails of evaporating exoplanets I. Constraints on the dust composition</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-06-21">June 21, 2018 June 21, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. tail c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>eclipses -planets and satellites: composition -planets and satellites: individual: (KIC 12557548b, KOI-2700b)</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Context. Recently, two exoplanet candidates have been discovered, KIC 12557548b and KOI-2700b, whose transit profiles show evidence of a comet-like tail of dust trailing the planet, thought to be fed by the evaporation of the planet&apos;s surface. Aims. We aim to put constraints on the composition of the dust ejected by these objects from the shape of their transit light curves. Methods. We derive a semi-analytical expression for the attenuation of the dust cross-section in the tail, incorporating the sublimation of dust grains as well as their drift away from the planet. This expression shows that the length of the tail is highly sensitive to the sublimation properties of the dust material. We compute tail lengths for several possible dust compositions, and compare these to observational estimates of the tail lengths of KIC 12557548b and KOI-2700b, inferred from their light curves. Results. The observed tail lengths are consistent with dust grains composed of corundum (Al 2 O 3) or iron-rich silicate minerals (e.g., fayalite, Fe 2 SiO 4). Pure iron and carbonaceous compositions are not favoured. In addition, we estimate dust mass loss rates of 1.7 ± 0.5 M ⊕ Gyr −1 for KIC 12557548b, and &gt; 0.007 M ⊕ Gyr −1 (1σ lower limit) for KOI-2700b.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The recently discovered exoplanet candidates KIC 12557548b (hereafter KIC 1255b) and KOI-2700b show asymmetric transit profiles, that can be explained by the occultation of stars by comet-like tails of dust emanating from evaporating exoplanets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rappaport et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. , 2014</ref>). The plausibility of this scenario has been strengthened by quantitative modelling of the transit light curve ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brogi et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Budaj 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">van Werkhoven et al. 2014</ref>), and of the Parker-type thermal wind that can eject dust grains from the planetary atmosphere ( <ref type="bibr">Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang 2013)</ref>. <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> lists the basic properties of the two systems.</p><p>If the evaporating-planet scenario is correct, KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b may provide a rare chance to probe the interiors of small exoplanets. Since the dust tails are thought to originate in the atmospheres of the planets, which are fed by the evaporating planetary surfaces, knowledge of the dust composition would provide information about the composition of the planets. This, in turn, would shed light on the origin and evolutionary history of the planets, and would therefore comprise a valuable constraint for theories of planet formation and evolution.</p><p>In this paper, we demonstrate that measurements of the length of a dust tail can be used to put constraints on the composition of the dust grains in the tail (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kimura et al. 2002)</ref>. In Sect. 2, we show how the tail length is related to the rate at which dust grains become smaller as a result of sublimation and the rate at which they drift away from the planet. In Sect. 3, we apply this theory to the two candidate evaporating planets discovered thus far, testing how well several possible dust species explain the observations. Finally, in Sect. 4 we discuss our findings, and in Sect. 5 we list our conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cross-section decay in a dusty tail</head><p>In this section, we derive an expression for the decay of extinction cross-section per unit angle W with angular separation from the planet ∆θ. This equation will describe how the depth of the transit depends on the mass loss rate of the planet, and how the length of the tail depends on the material properties of the dust. In our derivation we make use of the following assumptions, whose validity is discussed in the derivation and in Sect. 4.1:</p><p>A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. tail </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corotating frame</head><p>Fig. 1. Diagrams of the path followed by a dust grain released from an evaporating planet (ignoring sublimation of the dust grain) for 3 orbital periods of the planet, in the inertial frame and in the frame corotating with the planet. The positions of the planet and the dust particle are indicated at a time 1.6 orbital periods of the planet after release. Notes. From top to bottom: stellar effective temperature, stellar mass, stellar radius, stellar luminosity (derived from T eff,, and R ), orbital period of the candidate planet, and corresponding semi-major axis (as given by Kepler's third law). Numbers in brackets indicate the uncertainty on the last digit. The basic geometry of the system is shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. We express the collective extinction cross-section of the dust as a fraction of the area of the stellar disk. Its angular density W therefore has units <ref type="bibr">[rad −1 ]</ref>. Under the assumptions listed above, W(∆θ) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">W(∆θ) = dn d∆θ σ ext (∆θ) πR 2 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where dn/d∆θ is the number of particles per unit angle, σ ext is the extinction cross-section of a single dust grain, and R is the stellar radius. The angular number density can be expanded into</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">dn d∆θ = dn dt dt d∆θ = ˙ M d m 0 dt d∆θ .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Here, t denotes time, dn/dt is the rate at which the planet releases particles, the brackets . . . indicate averaging over the orbit of the dust grain, ˙ M d is the dust mass loss rate of the planet (i.e., excluding the mass lost in gas), and m 0 is the mass of an individual dust grain when it leaves the planet. The extinction cross-section of a single dust grain as a function of angular separation σ ext (∆θ) can be inferred from its derivative, which can be expanded into</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">dσ ext d∆θ = dσ ext ds ds dt dt d∆θ .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Here, s is the grain radius.</p><p>In the following subsections, we derive expressions for the size dependence of extinction cross-section dσ ext /ds (Sect. 2.1), the azimuthal drift rate d∆θ/dt (Sect. 2.2), and the grain radius change rate ds/dt (Sect. 2.3). These are then combined using Eqs. (1)-(3) to yield the equation for the decay of extinction cross-section (Sect. 2.4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Extinction cross-section</head><p>The extinction cross-section of a spherical dust grain with radius s can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">σ ext (s) = π ¯ Q ext (s)s 2 .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Here, ¯ Q ext is the extinction efficiency averaged over the stellar spectrum and the spectral response function of the instrument. We calculate monochromatic extinction efficiencies from (material dependent) refractive index data using <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mie (1908)</ref> theory. The sources of refractive index data are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>. For the stellar spectra we take Kurucz (1993) models. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> The Kepler response function is described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Koch et al. (2010)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 2</ref> shows the resulting extinction efficiencies. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 2</ref> shows that the extinction efficiency does not change substantially with grain size (d ¯ Q ext /ds ≈ 0) for s 0.1-0.5 µm, depending on material type. In this regime, we can make the approximation dσ ext ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">= 2π ¯ Q ext s.<label>(5)</label></formula><p>R. van Lieshout et al.: Dusty tails of evaporating exoplanets  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 2</ref>. Wavelength-averaged extinction efficiency ¯ Q ext as a function of grain radius s for the dust species considered in this study (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 13</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Croll et al. 2014</ref>). Since KIC 12557548 and KOI-2700 are of similar stellar type, these values apply to both stars.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Drift due to radiation pressure</head><p>The dynamics of small dust grains is significantly affected by radiation pressure from the star. Since the radiation pressure force scales the same way with distance from the star as gravity, it is parametrised by β, the ratio between the norms of the direct radiation pressure force and the gravitational force (i.e., β = |F rad /F grav |). For spherical dust grains, this parameter is given by (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Burns et al. 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">β = 3 16πcG L M ¯ Q pr (s) ρ d s .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Here, c is the speed of light, G is the gravitational constant, L is the stellar luminosity, M is the stellar mass, ¯ Q pr is the radiation pressure efficiency averaged over the stellar spectrum, and ρ d is the bulk density of the dust. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> shows the β ratios for dust grains of different compositions, using the stellar parameters listed in   <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>. Uncertainties (due to uncertainties in stellar parameters) are indicated by the error bar in the bottom left. The same figure for KOI-2700b is qualitatively the same, but the β values are lower by a factor of about 1.5.</p><p>After being released from a planet that follows a circular Keplerian orbit, radiation pressure-affected particles will continue on new Keplerian orbits with eccentricities e d , semi-major axes a d , and periods P d given by (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">e d = β 1 − β ; a d = a p 1 − β 1 − 2β ; P d = P p 1 − β (1 − 2β) 3/2 . (7)</formula><p>Here, a p , and P p denote the semi-major axis and orbital period of the planet, respectively. We note that particles with β ≥ 0.5 leave the system on unbound orbits.</p><p>Because of its eccentric orbit, a dust grain will drift away azimuthally from the planet and oscillate in radial distance, giving rise to a rosette-like path in the corotating frame (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Averaged over the particle's orbit (but ignoring sublimation), the azimuthal drift rate equals the synodic orbital frequency, which is given by )</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ω syn = 2π P p − 2π P d = 2π P p 1 − β − (1 − 2β) 3/2 1 − β ≈ 4πβ P p .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>The mathematical approximation in the last step gives an error of less than about 5% for all β &lt; 0.5, and less than 0.5% for all β &lt; 0.1. Compared to the actual (non-orbit-averaged) drift, this constant drift rate gives errors in ∆θ of less than 15% after the first orbit for β &lt; 0.1 (see also <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>). The azimuthal drift of a grain is described by ∆θ(t) = ω syn t. Since ω syn depends on β, a particle's drift rate will change as it becomes smaller because of sublimation. Using the assumption that the radiation pressure efficiency does not change substantially with decreasing grain size (d ¯ Q pr /ds ≈ 0, which roughly holds for s 0.1-0.5 µm, depending on material type), we find d∆θ dt</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">= ω syn + dω syn dβ dβ ds ds dt t (9) ≈ 4πβ P p 1 − t s ds dt = 4πβ P p s 0 s ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where s 0 denotes the initial grain radius. The final step uses the assumption that the orbit-averaged sublimation rate remains constant, which implies that the evolution of a grain's radius is described by s(t) = s 0 + ds/dt t.</p><p>Article number, page 3 of 10 A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. tail  <ref type="bibr">From Schaefer &amp; Fegley (2004)</ref>. <ref type="formula">(d)</ref> Where no uncertainty on sublimation parameters was reported, we arbitrarily set the standard deviation to 5%. (e) Range of temperatures for which A and B were determined. (f) These sublimation parameters were measured using a different polymorph of SiO 2 , namely high cristobalite. Furthermore, they assume the sublimation proceeds following the reaction SiO 2 (solid) → SiO 2 (gas), for which the evaporation coefficient α is close to unity <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Hashimoto 1990</ref>). (g) Using the equilibrium vapour pressure of SiC 2 . (h) At the temperatures relevant to this study, graphite sublimates mostly as C 3 -clusters, and the quoted parameters correspond to this component <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Zavitsanos &amp; Carlson 1973</ref>).</p><p>References. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Dust sublimation</head><p>While a dust particle drifts away from the planet, it will gradually sublimate because of the equilibrium temperature it reaches when illuminated by the stellar radiation. Since we consider spherical dust grain, whose mass and surface area are given by m = 4/3πs 3 ρ d and A = 4πs 2 , respectively, the orbit-averaged rate at which the grain radius changes can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">ds dt = ds dm dm dt = − ds dm A J = − J ρ d .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Here, J denotes the mass loss flux from the surface of the dust grain (units: [g cm −2 s −1 ]; positive for mass loss). According to the kinetic theory of gases, a solid surface with temperature T in vacuum loses mass at a rate of (Langmuir 1913)</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">J(T ) = αp v (T ) µm u 2πk B T .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Here, α is the evaporation coefficient that parameterises kinetic inhibition of the sublimation process (which we assume to be independent of temperature), p v is the material-specific phaseequilibrium vapour pressure, µ is the molecular weight of the molecules that sublimate, 2 m u is the atomic mass unit, and k B is the Boltzmann constant. The temperature dependence of the equilibrium vapour pressure can be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">p v = exp( −A/T + B ) dyn cm −2 ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where A and B are material-dependent sublimation parameters that can be determined experimentally. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref> lists estimates of the sublimation parameters for the materials we consider. A particle on an eccentric orbit has different temperatures T d at different parts of its orbit. When computing the orbit-averaged mass loss flux, J(T d ) has to be weighed by the time spent in each part of the orbit. This gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">J = 1 2π 2π 0 J[T d (θ d )] (1 − e 2 d ) 3/2 (1 + e d cos θ d ) 2 dθ d ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where θ d is the true anomaly of the dust grain, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">T d depends on θ d through distance r = a d (1 − e 2 d )/(1 + e d cos θ d ). The temperature T d (s, r)</formula><p>of a dust grain with size s at distance r from the (centre of the) star can be found by solving the energy balance</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Ω(r) π Q abs (s, λ) F (λ) dλ = 4 Q abs (s, λ) B λ (λ, T d ) dλ.<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Here, λ denotes wavelength, Q abs is the monochromatic absorption efficiency of the dust grain, F is the stellar spectrum, B λ denotes the Planck function, and Ω(r) is the solid angle subtended by the star as seen from a distance r, which is given by Ω(r) = 2π <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> shows the grain temperatures of dust particles made of several different materials at the orbital distance of KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b. We use Q abs values derived from the Mie calculations described in Sect. 2.1. For F (λ), we use Kurucz (1993) models (see footnote 1) scaled with the stellar luminosity. At large grain sizes, temperatures of most of the investigated materials approach the black-body temperature</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">1 − 1 − (R /r) 2 .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">T bb (r) = Ω(r) 4π 1/4 T eff,, .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>At the distance of the planet, this gives T bb (a p ) = 1577 +91 −89 K for KIC 1255b and T bb (a p ) = 1244 +69 −75 K for KOI-2700b (indicated by the horizontal bands in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">The decay equation</head><p>We can now combine the above equations into an expression for the decay of extinction cross-section. By combining Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref>  (6), (10), and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(11)</ref>, we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">dσ ext d∆θ ≈ − 8cG 3 M P p L J ¯ Q pr (s) σ 3 ext σ ext,0 ,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where σ ext,0 is a particle's extinction cross-section when it is released from the planet. Integration then yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">σ ext (∆θ) ≈ σ ext,0 1 + ∆θ 4∆θ tail −2 ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where ∆θ tail is the characteristic angle of the tail's decay (defined below). Inserting this into Eq. (1), together with Eqs. (2), (6) and (10), gives the final expression for the decay of extinction crosssection per unit angle with angular separation from the planet</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">W(∆θ) ≈ W 0 1 + ∆θ 4∆θ tail −4 (19a) W 0 = cG π M P p ˙ M d L R 2 ¯ Q ext (s) ¯ Q pr (s) (19b) ∆θ tail = 3 16cG L M P p ¯ Q pr (s) J . (19c)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Constraints from observed light curves</head><p>With the theoretical background in place, we now investigate what constraints can be derived from the observed light curves of KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b. To do this properly, one would have to use a transit model that computes the light curve resulting from the occultation of a star by a dust tail whose extinction cross-section distribution is given by Eq. (19a). Such models exist ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brogi et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Budaj 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">van Werkhoven et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>), but they generally adopt an ad hoc exponential decay for W(∆θ). While the decay predicted by Eq. (19a) is shallower than exponential, the profiles are similar enough to use the normalisation constants and e-folding angles derived from light curve fits as estimates for W 0 and ∆θ tail , respectively. 3 The literature values we adopt for the cross-section distribution parameters are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref>. KOI-2700b only has a lower limit on W 0 . This is because its ingress is not resolved well, which allows tails with higher cross-section densities at higher transit impact parameters. We determined the lower limit on W 0 from the transit depth of δ = 360 ± 29 ppm ). In the limit that the tail is short compared to the chord on the stellar disk crossed by the planet, 4 the transit depth corresponds to the total amount of extinction cross-section in the tail, which can be found by integrating <ref type="bibr">Eq. (19)</ref>. Hence, we find</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">δ ≤ ∞ 0 W(∆θ)d∆θ ≈ 4 3 W 0 ∆θ tail = 1 4π ˙ M d R 2 ¯ Q ext (s) J .<label>(20)</label></formula><p>This ignores the limb darkening of the star as well as the forward scattering of starlight into the line of sight. It also assumes that the planet does not contribute significantly to the flux deficit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Mass loss rates of the planets</head><p>The observational constraints on the normalisation constant W 0 can be used to estimate the dust mass loss rate of the evaporating planet (i.e., excluding mass lost in gas). Rewriting Eq. 4 I.e., ∆θ taiî r c , wherê r c is the angle subtended by the chord (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>   <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref>) for different materials, whose properties are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. Typical uncertainties (in temperature) are indicated by the error bars next to the legend. The horizontal lines mark the sublimation rates required to explain the observed tail lengths (Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(22)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">˙ M d ≈ 0.45 L 1 L R 1 R 2 M 1 M −1 P p 1 day −1 × W 0 0.001 rad −1 ¯ Q pr 1 ¯ Q ext 2 −1 M ⊕ Gyr −1 .<label>(21)</label></formula><p>For large grains, we can approximate ¯ Q pr ≈ 1 and ¯ Q ext ≈ 2. For KIC 1255b, this yields ˙ M d ≈ 1.7±0.5 M ⊕ Gyr −1 , which is somewhat higher than earlier (grain-property-dependent) estimates by </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Dust composition</head><p>The observed tail length can be used together with system parameters and ¯ Q pr ≈ 1 (valid for large grains) in Eq. (19c) to estimate the required orbit-averaged mass loss flux of the grains</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">J ≈ 2.1 × 10 −9 L 1 L M 1 M −1 P p 1 day −1 × ∆θ tail 1 rad −1 ¯ Q pr 1 g cm −2 s −1 .<label>(22)</label></formula><p>This gives J ≈ (4.7 ± 1.1) × 10 −9 g cm −2 s −1 for KIC 1255b and J ≈ (9.0 +4.3 −4.4 ) × 10 −10 g cm −2 s −1 for KOI-2700b. In <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>, we compare these observational constraints on the sublimation rate with laboratory J(T ) curves for different materials. Typical uncertainties on the temperature were estimated at J = 10 −8 g cm −2 s −1 using a Monte Carlo technique (i.e., by varying A and B according to their respective uncertainties, and then numerically solving Eq. (12) for T ). We also mark the black-body temperature <ref type="bibr">(Eq. (16)</ref>) at the distance of the planet for both systems. The difference in temperature between the two systems (greater than what can be explained by the trend of any of the material curves) indicates that the dust in the two systems may have a different composition, with KIC 1255b requiring a more refractory species than KOI-2700b. Furthermore, some materials reach the required sublimation rates at temperatures much lower or higher than the typical (black-body) temperatures of the systems, suggesting that the dust is unlikely to be composed of these materials. However, dust temperatures can depart considerably from black-body temperatures (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>). In addition, particles on eccentric orbits experience lower temperatures when they are farther away from the star.</p><p>To investigate the effects of size-dependent grain temperatures, we use Eq. (19c) to calculate tail lengths as a function of grain size, employing orbit-averaged sublimation rates from Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref>, realistic dust temperatures from Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(15)</ref>, and sizedependent ¯ Q pr values derived from the Mie calculations described in Sect. 2.1. The results are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 6</ref>, together with the observed tail lengths for comparison. Typical uncertainties were estimated at s = 1000 µm using Monte Carlo simulations. For some materials, particles of certain sizes sublimate entirely before completing one orbit (s 0 / ds/dt &lt; P d ), meaning that assumption 6 of our derivation is violated. In these cases, the tail length as predicted by Eq. (19c) is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 6</ref> with dashed lines (while strictly Eq. (19c) is no longer valid; also see Sect. 4.1). At small grain sizes (s 0.1 µm), assumption 5 breaks down, because ¯ Q pr then varies strongly with grain size. At the largest grain sizes considered here (s 1000 µm), grain temperatures approach the black-body temperature, and hence the results in Figure 6 displays an extremely large dynamic range in predicted tail lengths, caused by the exponential dependence of sublimation rate on grain temperature (see Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(13)</ref>). For most of this range, dust tails are probably not detectable by transit photometry. Small tail lengths (∆θ tail 0.01) effectively leave only the parent planet, which makes a regular, symmetric light curve. Large values (∆θ tail 100) occur if dust grains hardly sublimate at all, giving rise to a nearly uniform ring of dust around the star. Such a ring would scatter and absorp the same amount of light at all phases, and would therefore not produce a signal in the normalised light curve.</p><p>The tail length predictions of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 6</ref> allow us to put constraints on the composition of the dust in the tails of the two evaporating exoplanet candidates. For KIC 1255b, we find the following: (1) Iron, fayalite, and silicon monoxide give tail lengths that are smaller than the observed value, because of their low sublimation temperatures. (2) The silicate minerals quartz, forsterite, and enstatite can produce the observed tail length, but only at very large grain sizes (s 100 µm). Smaller grains have lower temperatures (owing to their transparency in the optical), and therefore sublimate much slower. (3) Corundum grains with sizes of around s ∼ 10 µm are consistent with the observations. (4) The carbonaceous materials graphite and silicon carbide generally give tail lengths that are much longer than the observed value, because of their refractory nature. An exception are very small (s ∼ 0.01 µm) graphite grains, which marginally fit the observed tail length.</p><p>The constraints for KOI-2700b, which is cooler, are somewhat different: (1) Iron, which seems to be a good candidate in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>, yields tails that are shorter than observed, because of its higher-than-black-body temperature.   forsterite, and enstatite, as well as the carbonaceous materials graphite and silicon carbide all yield tails that are much longer than indicated by the observations. (5) Corundum grains with sizes of s 1 µm give the observed tail length.</p><p>The above results are discussed in more detail in Sect. 4.3, where they are examined in the light of independent constraints on the typical size of the dust grains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Validity of assumptions</head><p>Our semi-analytical model makes use of a number of assumptions, listed at the beginning of Sect. 2. In the above derivation and analysis, we already give arguments for some of these assumptions, or discuss under what conditions they are valid. Many of the assumptions, however, warrant some further discussion, which we provide here.</p><p>Steady state (assumption 1): It is clear that the dust tail of KIC 1255b is not in steady state, because it experiences drastic changes in transit depth from orbit to orbit <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Rappaport et al. 2012</ref>). This variability is, in fact, an important argument for the evaporating-planet scenario. For KOI-2700b, the Kepler data do not have the signal-to-noise ratio required to detect orbit-to-orbit changes in transit depth, but a secular trend in transit depth was found ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>).</p><p>The results we find under the assumption of a steady-state dust tail, using the average observed light curve, reflect the properties of the system averaged over time. Optical depth (assumption 2): <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rappaport et al. (2012)</ref> argue that the star-to-planet part of the dust cloud must be optically thin or marginally so (i.e., τ 1) in order for the planet to be heated sufficiently by stellar radiation to sublimate. Indeed, <ref type="bibr">Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang (2013)</ref> find that the mass loss rate of the planet goes down for high dust abundances, and reaches a maximum at optical depths of about τ ≈ 0.1 (see their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4)</ref>. Furthermore, shielding of dust grains by each other from the stellar radiation is reduced by the large angular diameter of the star from the vantage point of the dust cloud (27 • for KIC 1255b; 19 • for KOI-2700b). Regarding the optical depth from the star to the observer, it is important to take into account that the dust cloud is inclined with respect to the line of sight (for non-zero impact parameters). This lowers the optical depth because it ensures that the radial extent of the dust cloud (which can be substantial because of the different paths followed by grains of different sizes) contributes to its vertical extent with respect to the line of sight. Single grain size (assumption 3): Without knowledge of the actual grain size distribution, our analysis assuming a single grain size can still be used to exclude many dust compositions. If a given dust species yields tail lengths that, for all plausible grain sizes, are either always longer or always shorter than the observed value (i.e., its curve in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 6</ref> lies either fully above or fully below the horizontal black line), it is not possible to create the observed tail length with a combination of different-sized grains of this composition. Constant optical efficiencies (assumption 5): <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 2</ref> shows for which grain sizes the extinction efficiency remains constant. The independence of transit depth on wavelength ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Croll et al. 2014)</ref> indicates that this assumption is at least correct for the extinction efficiency in the case of KIC 1255b, although the possible effects of the optical depth of the dust cloud should be investigated. For the emission efficiency (relevant to the energy balance of the dust grains) the assumption only becomes accurate at much larger grain sizes (see discussion of assumption 7 below). Survival timescale (assumption 6): We assume that particles survive against sublimation for at least one orbit. Arguments based on the variability timescale presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rappaport et al. (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang (2013)</ref> indicate that this is marginally the case for KIC 1255b. For KOI-2700b, dust grains with β 0.03 need to survive for longer than one dust orbit to explain the length of the tail (ignoring sublimation; see also Sect. 4.5 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>).</p><p>This assumption is needed to justify averaging over the orbit of the dust particle. For low-eccentricity orbits, however, this does not introduce a large error. Constant sublimation rate (assumption 7): Our assumption that the orbit-averaged sublimation rate does not change as particles become smaller means that we make a zeroth-order approximation in dust temperature. This is only valid at very large grain sizes, for which black-body temperatures are a good approximation. Avoiding this simplification would require a numerical approach to modelling the dust tail. Assumption 7 also means that we do not take into account the changes in orbital eccentricity that are caused by the changes in β of a shrinking dust grain. This second point is a good approximation as long as orbital eccentricities are low, such that the sublimation rate does not vary substantially from its periastron value. Dust temperatures (assumption 11): When computing dust temperatures from the energy balance Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(15)</ref>, we assume that the contribution of latent heat due to sublimation is negligible. This is valid for the materials and temperatures we consider <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Lamy 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>). Collisional heating by stellar wind particles can also be ignored <ref type="bibr">(Rappa- port et al. 2014</ref>). Radiation pressure dominated dynamics (assumption 12): For the dynamics of the dust grains, we only take into consideration the gravity and radiation pressure of the star. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. (2014)</ref> find that the ram pressure force due to the stellar wind is one or two orders of magnitude lower than the radiation pressure force, and can therefore be ignored. Assumption 12 also requires that the initial relative velocity ∆v 0 with which the grain is launched away from the planet is negligible compared to the radiation-pressure-induced drift. This holds if ∆v 0 2βv p , where v p = GM /a p is the planet's Keplerian velocity. Using Kepler's third law, this can be rewritten as β 0.002</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">M 1 M −1/3 P p 1 day 1/3 ∆v 0 1 km s −1 .<label>(23)</label></formula><p>The magnitude of the initial relative velocity ∆v 0 is very uncertain. It may be comparable to the escape speed of the planet, but this depends on the precise coupling of the dust grains to the gas flow. We do not expect ∆v 0 to be more than a few km s −1 , and therefore assumption 12 should be valid for grains with radii up to about s 10 µm. Importantly, if this condition were violated, and dust grains are launched isotropically, some particles would end up drifting ahead of the planet. The transit light curve resulting from such a configuration would display a gradual ingress. In the observed light curve, only the egress is gradual, consistent with grain dynamics that are dominated by radiation pressure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Constraints on the grain size</head><p>Section 3.2 revealed that our constraints on the dust composition are dependent on the size of the dust grains, primarily because the grain size influences the grain temperature. By using independent constraints on the grain size, it is therefore possible to make better inferences about the dust composition. Here, we list the available constraints on the grain size (most of which only concern KIC 1255b):</p><p>1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brogi et al. (2012)</ref> find that the scattering properties of the dust trailing KIC 1255b, as imprinted on the light curve, are best explained by small particles (0.04 µm &lt; s &lt; 0.19 µm). . If this feature is real, it may be related to the first periastron passage of the dust grains after launch. The periastron passage gives an enhancement in the dust density because the relative angular velocity between dust and planet vanishes when dust particles pass their periastron. This is illustrated by <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>, which shows the drift of dust particles with respect to the planet (ignoring sublimation), calculated by solving Kepler's equation (see also <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, as well as Sect. 4.1 and <ref type="figure">Fig. 11</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rappaport et al. 2014</ref>). The figure demonstrates that the angular offset of the dust density enhancement is very sensitive to β, and hence to the size of the dust grains. This also implies that, if the flux decrement feature is real and it is caused by the periastron passage of dust grains, the grain size distribution must be very narrow. Ignoring sublimation, the relation between the β ratio of the dust grains and the position of the density enhancement is</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">∆θ decr = ω syn P d = 2π 1 − β − (1 − 2β) 3/2 (1 − 2β) 3/2 . (24)</formula><p>The observed angular offset of the possible flux decrement of ∆θ decr ≈ 0.94 rad corresponds to β ≈ 0.064. This β ratio is reached by particles of various sizes, depending on material type (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>), but leads to a tentative upper limit of roughly s 2 µm, since larger grains always have lower β ratios. 5. For very small values of β, the motion of dust grains is probably dominated by the initial velocity with which they are launched away from the planet, rather than radiationpressure-induced drift (see Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(23)</ref>). Large grains may therefore result in a more symmetric distribution of dust around the planet, contrary to what is observed. For this reason, we deem dust grains with sizes of s 100 µm unlikely. 6. <ref type="bibr">Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang (2013)</ref> assume s = 1 µm for their atmospheric outflow model, and find that grains up to this size couple sufficiently to the gas to be lifted out of the planetary atmosphere by a thermal wind. Although the resulting upper limit on grain size is model-dependent (it varies with planet mass, for example), this is an additional argument against very large grain sizes.</p><p>Combined, the above pieces of evidence point to grain sizes of about s ∼ 0.1-1 µm for KIC 1255b, although some of the clues are contradictory. For both objects, there are arguments to exclude very large dust grains (s 100 µm). Future research should examine whether a uniform grain size is a good approximation. It is also important to determine the optical depth of the dust clouds, and investigate what effects it may have on the shape of the pre-ingress brightening and on the wavelength dependence of the transit depth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">The composition of the dust and the planets</head><p>Applying the above grain size constraints to the results from Sect. 3.2 allows us to exclude some of the solutions seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 6</ref>. Specifically, the silicate minerals that reproduce the observed tail length of KIC 1255b at very large grain sizes now seem unlikely. The same holds for SiO in the case of KOI-2700b. One of the remaining candidates for the dust material is corundum (Al 2 O 3 ). It yields the observed tail lengths of both KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b at plausible grain sizes. Because of the relatively low cosmic abundance of aluminium, it may seem unlikely that a minor species such as corundum accounts for all the dust in the tails of the evaporating planets. However, as already noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rappaport et al. (2012)</ref>, high Al 2 O 3 abundances can be created by a distillation of the planetary surface. This mechanism was proposed by <ref type="bibr">Léger et al. (2011)</ref> in a study of the lava ocean which is thought to dominate the dayside surface of the hot super-Earth CoRoT-7b. Starting with a silicate composition, more volatile elements such as Si, Fe, and Mg evaporate preferentially from the lava ocean, and, if these components leave the system permanently, the ocean over time consists of increasingly refractory species. After about 1.5 Gyr of steady evaporation, the ocean reaches a stable composition of 13% CaO and 87% Al 2 O 3 . A similar distillation scenario for KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b may explain the prevalence of corundum grains.</p><p>Previous work on the evaporating exoplanet candidates proposed pyroxene ([Mg,Fe]SiO 3 ) as the main constituent of the dust in the tails, and (in the case of KIC 1255b) rejected olivine ( <ref type="bibr">[Mg,Fe]</ref> 2 SiO 4 ) as too volatile <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Rappaport et al. 2012</ref>). These suggestions are based on scaling the sublimation time scales found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kimura et al. (2002)</ref> for cometary dust grains in the vicinity of the Sun to the exoplanetary systems. Here, we show that dust grains made of enstatite (the Mg-rich end-member of pyroxene) survive for too long to explain the observed tail lengths. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> Regarding olivine, the Mg-rich endmember forsterite behaves similar to enstatite, while the Fe-rich end-member fayalite gives much shorter tails. For KOI-2700b, the observed tail length is consistent with dust grains composed of fayalite, while for KIC 1255b fayalite is too volatile. Since these two end-members of olivine give tail lengths on opposite sides of the observed value for KIC 1255b, it is conceivable that an intermediate form (iron-rich, but with some magnesium) yields the right length.</p><p>The list of dust materials we tested is far from exhaustive. In addition, we only considered dust grains of a single, pure composition. This type of investigation only allows one to test whether a dust species is consistent with the observations or not, and there may be more dust species, different from the ones we found, that can also explain the data. Perhaps the most stringent constraint resulting from this work is that pure iron and carbonaceous dust compositions are not favoured.</p><p>Broadly speaking, the composition of the dust ejected by evaporating planets reflects that of the parent planet. Hence, pure iron and carbonaceous compositions are not favoured for the planets KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b. However, the relation between dust and planet composition may be complicated by processes such as preferential condensation of certain species and fractionation of a lava ocean ( <ref type="bibr">Léger et al. 2011</ref>). Therefore, to gain more insight into the planetary composition, a thorough investigation of the link between planet and dust composition is required. Roughly, this would entail the following modelling steps: (1) Given a planetary composition, temperature, and gravity, calculate the composition of the atmosphere resulting from evaporation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Schaefer &amp; Fegley 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Miguel et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Schaefer et al. 2012)</ref>. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> Determine the dynamical structure of the atmospheric outflow (see <ref type="bibr">Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang 2013)</ref>. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref> Calculate which dust species would condensate in this outflow (as has been done for stellar outflows; e.g., Gail 2010). <ref type="bibr">6</ref> By doing this for different potential planetary compositions, and as a function of temperature and gravity, it may be possible to use the dust composition as a probe for the composition of the planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>This paper describes the decay of cross-section in dusty tails trailing evaporating planets, such as KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b. The analytical expression we derive <ref type="bibr">(Eq. (19)</ref>) can be used to model transit light curves. Specifically, it provides a physical interpretation for two properties of a dust tail. The density of the tail (found from the transit depth) is related to the mass loss rate of the planet. The tail length (which can be derived from the duration of the transit) is determined by the sublimation rate of the dust in the tail. This sublimation rate depends sensitively on the optical and thermodynamical properties of the material that the dust grains in the tail are made of. Therefore, given accurate laboratory measurements of these properties, the tail length can be used to constrain the composition of the dust.</p><p>The constraints we find for the dust composition of the two evaporating exoplanet candidates are summarised in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 5</ref>. Our analysis has lead to the following conclusions about these systems:</p><p>1. The mass loss rate in dust of KIC 1255b is approximately ˙ M d ≈ 1.7 ± 0.5 M ⊕ Gyr −1 . For KOI-2700b, we find a 1σ lower limit of ˙ M d 0.007 M ⊕ Gyr −1 . 2. Dust grains composed of corundum can explain the tail lengths of both candidates. 3. The tail length of KOI-2700b is also consistent with a fayalite composition. A composition of iron-rich silicate minerals may also work for KIC 1255b. 4. Dust grains made of pure iron, graphite, or silicon carbide are not favoured for both objects.</p><p>A&amp;A proofs: manuscript no. tail </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>References.</head><label></label><figDesc>H14 Huber et al. (2014); R14 Rappaport et al. (2014); V14 van Werkhoven et al. (2014).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Radiation pressure to gravitational force ratio β as a function of grain radius s for KIC 1255b. Different colours correspond to the materials listed in Table 2. Uncertainties (due to uncertainties in stellar parameters) are indicated by the error bar in the bottom left. The same figure for KOI-2700b is qualitatively the same, but the β values are lower by a factor of about 1.5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>F04 Ferguson et al. (2004); G13 Gail et al. (2013); H90 Hashimoto (1990); K91 Kushiro &amp; Mysen (1991); L93 Lilov (1993); L08 Lihrmann (2008); M88 Mysen &amp; Kushiro (1988); N94 Nagahara et al. (1994); Z73 Zavitsanos &amp; Carlson (1973).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Dust temperatures T d at the orbital distance of the planet as a function of grain radius s for various dust materials. The horizontal black lines mark the black-body temperatures at the distances of the planets. The grey bands indicate the uncertainties on the black-body temperatures, and can be used as estimates of the typical uncertainties on the grain temperatures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(19b) et al. 2014, and see their Fig. 12): lim n→∞ 1 + ∆θ n∆θ tail −n = exp ∆θ ∆θ tail .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>of Brogi et al. 2012 Fig. 5 .</head><label>20125</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Mass loss flux as a function of temperature (Eq. (12)) for different materials, whose properties are listed in Table 3. Typical uncertainties (in temperature) are indicated by the error bars next to the legend. The horizontal lines mark the sublimation rates required to explain the observed tail lengths (Eq. (22)), with light grey bands indicating their uncertainties. The black-body temperatures (Eq. (16)) at the distance of the planets and their uncertainties are indicated by vertical line segments and dark grey patches.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Mass loss flux as a function of temperature (Eq. (12)) for different materials, whose properties are listed in Table 3. Typical uncertainties (in temperature) are indicated by the error bars next to the legend. The horizontal lines mark the sublimation rates required to explain the observed tail lengths (Eq. (22)), with light grey bands indicating their uncertainties. The black-body temperatures (Eq. (16)) at the distance of the planets and their uncertainties are indicated by vertical line segments and dark grey patches.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Rappaport et al.</head><label></label><figDesc>(2012), Perez-Becker &amp; Chiang (2013), and Kawahara et al. (2013). For KOI-2700b, we find a 1σ lower limit of ˙ M d 0.007 M ⊕ Gyr −1 , consistent with the estimate of Rappaport et al. (2014).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 6 converge to those of Fig. 5 (</head><label>65</label><figDesc>but we note that such large dust grains are not very plausible; see Sect. 4.2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>( 2 )</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fayalite grains of many different sizes are consistent with the observed tail length. (3) Silicon monoxide gives the observed tail length for very large grain sizes (s ∼ 1000 µm). (4) The silicate minerals quartz,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Characteristic angle of the tail's decay as a function of grain size (Eq. (19c)) for KIC 1255b and KOI-2700b, with different colours for different materials. Dashed lines indicate that particles sublimate entirely before completing one orbit. Gaps (neither a solid nor a dashed line) appear where particles are unbound (β ≥ 0.5). Typical uncertainties are shown by the error bars at the bottom of each panel. The horizontal black lines indicate the values of ∆θ tail derived from the observed light curves.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>2 .Fig. 7 .</head><label>27</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Angular separation between dust grains and the planet KIC 1255b as a function of time for different values of β (the ratio of radiation pressure to gravitational force on a dust grain). The horizontal grey line indicates the position of the tentative flux decrement in the egress with respect to the midpoint of the transit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Host star and system parameters of the two evaporating 
exoplanet candidates 

KIC 1255b 
KOI-2700b 
Refs. 
T eff,, [K] 
4550 +140 

−131 

4296 +131 

−146 

H14 
M [M ] 
0.666 +0.067 

−0.059 

0.546 ± 0.044 
H14 
R [R ] 
0.660 +0.060 

−0.059 

0.540 +0.048 

−0.051 

H14 
L [L ] 
0.168 +0.037 

−0.036 

0.089 +0.019 

−0.021 

P p [days] 0.6535538(1) 
0.910022(5) 
V14, R14 
a p [AU] 
0.0129(4) 
0.0150(4) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . Bulk densities and sources for optical properties of the dust species considered in this study</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Dust species 
ρ d 
Refs. for opt. prop. 
[g cm −3 ] 
Iron (Fe) 
7.87 
O88 
Silicon monoxide (SiO) 
2.13 
P85, W13 
Cryst. fayalite (Fe 2 SiO 4 ) 
4.39 
Z11, F01 
Cryst. a enstatite (MgSiO 3 ) 
3.20 
D95, J98 
Cryst. forsterite (Mg 2 SiO 4 ) 
3.27 
Z11, F01 
Quartz (SiO 2 ) 
2.60 
Z13 
Corundum (Al 2 O 3 ) 
4.00 
K95 
Silicon carbide (SiC) 
3.22 
L93 
Graphite (C) 
2.16 
D84 

Notes. (a) The optical properties at wavelengths below 8 µm use 
amorphous enstatite. 

References. D84 Draine &amp; Lee (1984); D95 Dorschner et al. (1995); 
F01 Fabian et al. (2001); J98 Jaeger et al. (1998); K95 Koike et al. 
(1995); L93 Laor &amp; Draine (1993); O88 Ordal et al. (1988); P85 Palik 
(1985); W13 Wetzel et al. (2013); Z11 Zeidler et al. (2011); Z13 Zeidler 
et al. (2013). 

Iron 
SiO 
Fayalite 
Enstatite 
Forsterite 
Quartz 
Corundum 
SiC 
Graphite 

grain radius [µm] 

0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 
100 
1000 10000 

¯ 
Q 

ext 

10 −4 

10 −3 

10 −2 

10 −1 

10 0 

10 1 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>bulk densities from Table 2, and ¯ 
Q pr values 
derived from the Mie calculations described in Sect. 2.1. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 3 . Sublimation characteristics of the dust species considered in this study</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Dust species 
µ 
α 
A 
B 
Temp. range e 
Refs. 
Notes 
[K] 
[K] 
Iron (Fe) 
55.845 1.0 
48354 ± 1151 
29.2 ± 0.7 
1573 -1973 
F04 
Silicon monoxide (SiO) 
44.085 0.04 49520 ± 1400 
32.5 ± 1.0 
1275 -1525 
G13 
Cryst. fayalite (Fe 2 SiO 4 ) 
203.774 0.1 a 60377 ± 1082 
37.7 ± 0.7 
1373 -1433 
N94 
Cryst. enstatite (MgSiO 3 ) 
100.389 0.1 a 68908 ± 8773 
38.1 ± 5.0 
1573 -1923 
M88, K91 
Cryst. forsterite (Mg 2 SiO 4 ) 140.694 0.1 b 65308 ± 3969 
34.1 ± 2.5 
1673 -2133 
N94 
Quartz (SiO 2 ) 
60.084 1.0 
69444 ± 3447 
33.1 ± 1.8 
1833 -1958 
H90 
(f) 
Corundum (Al 2 O 3 ) 
101.961 0.1 c 77365 ± 3868 d 39.3 ± 2.0 d 
L08 
Silicon carbide (SiC) 
40.10 
0.1 a 78462 ± 3923 d 37.8 ± 1.9 d 1500 -2000 
L93 
(g) 
Graphite (C) 
12.011 0.1 a 93646 ± 503 
36.7 ± 1.8 d 2400 -3000 
Z73 
(h) 

Notes. (a) For materials for which no measuments of the evaporation coefficient are available we arbitrarily adopt α = 0.1. (b) From Gail (2010). 
(c) </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>- Article number, page 4 of 10 R. van Lieshout et al.: Dusty tails of evaporating exoplanets</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Iron 
SiO 
Fayalite 
Enstatite 
Forsterite 
Quartz 
Corundum 
SiC 
Graphite 

grain radius [µm] 
dust temperature [K] 

KIC 1255b 

0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 
100 
1000 10000 

0 

500 

1000 

1500 

2000 

2500 

3000 

Iron 
SiO 
Fayalite 
Enstatite 
Forsterite 
Quartz 
Corundum 
SiC 
Graphite 

grain radius [µm] 
dust temperature [K] 

KOI-2700b 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Constraints on the dust tail cross-section distribution parame-
ters derived from transit light curve fitting 

KIC 1255b 
KOI-2700b 
W 0 [rad −1 ] 0.0227 +0.0020 

−0.0013 

&gt; 0.0004 (1σ) 
∆θ tail [rad] 0.172 ± 0.006 
0.42 ± 0.17 
Ref. 
V14 
R14 

References. R14 Rappaport et al. (2014); V14 van Werkhoven et al. 
(2014, their 1-D model fit of the average transit profile). 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="true"><head>Table 5 . Summary of the dust composition constraints</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Dust species 
KIC 1255b 
KOI-2700b 
Iron (Fe) 
too volatile 
dust temperature too high 
Silicon monoxide (SiO) 
too volatile 
required grain size implausibly large 
Cryst. fayalite (Fe 2 SiO 4 ) 
too volatile 
consistent with observed tail length 
Cryst. enstatite (MgSiO 3 ) 
required grain size implausibly large 
too refractory 
Cryst. forsterite (Mg 2 SiO 4 ) required grain size implausibly large 
too refractory 
Quartz (SiO 2 ) 
required grain size implausibly large 
too refractory 
Corundum (Al 2 O 3 ) 
consistent with observed tail length 
consistent with observed tail length 
Silicon carbide (SiC) 
too refractory 
too refractory 
Graphite (C) 
too refractory 
too refractory </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> For both stars, we use model atmospheres with an effective temperature of T eff,, = 4500 K and a surface gravity of log g = 4.5, compatible with the stellar parameters given by Huber et al. (2014).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> More precisely, µ should reflect the average molecular weight of the molecules recondensing from the gas phase in an equilibrium between sublimation and condensation. For simplicity, we use the molecular weights of the dust compound. Discrepancies may result in errors of the order of unity in the final value of J, which are negligible compared to the uncertainties on α and p v .</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> The two equations are identical to first order at ∆θ = 0, and, for a large exponent, Eq. (19a) approaches exponential decay (cf. Rappaport</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> We only considered crystalline minerals, because amorphous forms are expected to transition to crystalline on timescales much shorter than the sublimation timescale (see Sect. 4.2.3 of Kimura et al. 2002).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> This assumes that the outflow is loaded with dust grains as a result of condensation from the gas phase. Another possible origin of the dust is explosive vulcanism (see Sect. 4.2 of Rappaport et al. 2012, and references therein).</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Juan Ovelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">545</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Budaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">557</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Croll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Devore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">786</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dorschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Begemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mutschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">503</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Draine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fabian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jäger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Chemical &amp; Engineering Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">497</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Gail</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lecture Notes in Physics</title>
		<editor>T. Henning</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Berlin Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">815</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="141" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Gail</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tamanai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">555</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">53</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Silva Aguirre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Matthews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Molster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dorschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">904</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kawahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kurosaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ikoma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">776</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Biesecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jessberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kaito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ATLAS9 Stellar Atmosphere Programs and 2 km/s grid</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kurucz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Ku- rucz CD-ROM No. 13</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, Mass</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Progress in metamorphic and magmatic petrology</title>
		<editor>honour of D. S. Korzhinskiy, ed. L. L. Perchuk</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="434" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Langmuir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1913" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Laor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Draine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">441</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Léger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Grasset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fegley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Lihrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the European Ceramic Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">649</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lilov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Materials Science and Engineering: B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annalen der Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">330</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">377</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1908" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Miguel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaltenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fegley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">742</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nagahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1951</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ordal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Newquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Querry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Handbook of optical constants of solids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Palik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<editor>Perez-Becker, D. &amp; Chiang, E</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">433</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2294</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Devore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">784</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">752</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fegley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">216</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fegley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">703</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lodders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fegley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">755</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Van Werkhoven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A G</forename><surname>Snellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">561</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Klevenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Gail</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trieloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zavitsanos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Chemical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2966</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Posch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mutschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Posch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mutschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Wehrhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">526</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">68</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
