<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On the possibility of detecting ultra-short period exoplanets with LISA</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kaze</forename><forename type="middle">W K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emanuele</forename><surname>Berti</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The University of Mississippi</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>38677</postCode>
									<region>MS</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gabella</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kelly</forename><surname>Holley-Bockelmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Fisk University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On the possibility of detecting ultra-short period exoplanets with LISA</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Accepted ; Received ; in original form</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>exoplanets -gravitational waves</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Cunha et al. (2018) recently reexamined the possibility of detecting gravitational waves from exoplanets, claiming that three ultra-short period systems would be observable by LISA. We revisit their analysis and conclude that the currently known exoplanetary systems are unlikely to be detectable, even assuming a LISA observation time T obs = 4 yrs. Conclusive statements on the detectability of one of these systems, GP Com b, will require better knowledge of the system&apos;s properties, as well as more careful modeling of both LISA&apos;s response and the galactic confusion noise. Still, the possibility of exoplanet detection with LISA is interesting enough to warrant further study, as gravitational waves could yield dynamical properties that are difficult to constrain with electromagnetic observations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">10</head><p>S SA n (f ) ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. 2018</ref>). ‡ Brown triangles correspond to the sky-averaged characteristic strain ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. 2018</ref>, solid black), while cyan error bars correspond to the range of hc consistent with uncertainties in the source parameters (cf. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). The case for detectability of these three systems with either the current or Classic LISA design based on a characteristic strain calculation is, at best, inconclusive.</p><p>As discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. (2018)</ref>, plots of the characteristic strain hc are useful as rough assessments of detectability, but any conclusions must ultimately be based on a signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) calculation. For monochromatic sources, the SNR is defined as ρ = (h|h) 1/2 , where</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(h|h) = 2 Sn(f ) T obs 0 dt h(t) 2 .</formula><p>(1)</p><p>To claim detectability, the source of interest must have SNR ρ larger than a certain threshold, which for monochromatic systems is usually taken to be ρ thr = 5 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kupfer et al. 2018</ref>). This is somewhat optimistic: the Mock LISA Data Challenges suggest that ρ thr is likely to be larger than 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(BB laut et al. 2010)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Crowder &amp; Cornish (2007)</ref> even report undetected sources with ρ ∼ 10, though this will likely improve with more research in GW data analysis.</p><p>Unfortunately, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cunha et al. (2018)</ref> did not quantify the SNR of these systems. Furthermore, they used the outdated "Classic LISA" noise curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Larson et al. 2000</ref>) and they did not take into account the fact that galactic binaries produce a significant confusion noise, which is important at the frequencies of interest for exoplanetary systems. Here we revisit their analysis for the three planetary systems that are most promising for GW detection. We use updated parameters for these systems (including uncertainties, when available) and we adopt the most recent estimates for the LISA sensitivity curve, including galactic confusion noise. The parameters of the three systems under consideration are listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>.</p><p>We model the motion of the LISA detector and compute the SNR using a nonspinning, quasicircular time-domain ‡ We remark that this convention differs from the conventions used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cutler (1998)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Berti et al. (2005)</ref>, where the SNRs coming from the strain amplitudes hα (α = 1, 2) in the two channels are added in quadrature and Sn(f ) = 3 20 S SA n (f ).  <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Characteristic strain hc of the loudest exoplanetary candidates plotted along with f Sn(f ), where Sn(f ) is the effective non-sky averaged noise power spectral density for Classic LISA without galactic confusion noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Larson et al. 2000</ref>, dashed red), as adopted in ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cunha et al. 2018</ref>); Classic LISA with galactic confusion noise (solid red); and the current LISA design with galactic confusion noise ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. 2018</ref>, solid black). The galactic confusion background and hc are computed assuming T obs = 2 yrs. Cyan dots with error bars correspond to the non-sky averaged SNR, allowing for uncertainties on the source parameters; brown inverted triangles correspond to the sky-and orientation-averaged SNR.</p><p>waveform following <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cutler (1998)</ref>, so that h(t) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">h(t) = √ 3 2 2M 5/3 DL (πf ) 2/3 ˜ A(t) × cos t 0 2πf (t )dt + ϕp(t) + ϕD(t) ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where f (t ) is given in equation (1.3) of <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Poisson &amp; Will (1995)</ref>. Here˜AHere˜ Here˜A(t), ϕp(t) and ϕD(t) are the amplitude modulation, polarization phase and Doppler phase due to LISA's motion (see Appendix A for details). For a binary with component masses (m1, m2) and total mass M = m1 + m2 the waveform depends on nine parameters: luminosity distance DL, chirp mass M = η 3/5 M , symmetric mass ratio η = m1m2/M 2 , time of coalescence tc, phase of coalescence φc, sky location ( ¯ θS, ¯ φS) and orbital angular momentum direction ( ¯ θL, ¯ φL). The overbar means that the sky location and binary orientation angles are defined in ecliptic coordinates. In order to give an estimate of the possible range of SNR, for each source we create Monte Carlo samples <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. SNR for the loudest sources considered in ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cunha et al. 2018</ref>), using the noise power spectral density for Classic LISA <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Larson et al. 2000</ref>, columns 2, 3 and 4) and the current LISA design ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. 2018</ref>, columns 5 and 6). The second row indicates whether we included galactic confusion noise or not. The third row lists the assumed observation time T obs (in yrs). Numbers in square brackets are the maximum and minimum SNRs consistent with parameter uncertainties for the given source. In round parentheses we report the sky location and orientation averaged SNR. based on the parameter uncertainties listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Our waveforms depend on the sky location in the solar system barycenter frame, while the sky location (θ eq S , φ eq S ) and inclination ι are given in equatorial coordinates (electromagnetic observations do not give information on the polarization angle ψ). In order to translate the waveform from the solar system barycenter frame to an Earth-centered frame, we must solve for the geometric angles in ecliptic coordinates as functions of geometric angles in equatorial coordinates. Translating the sky location from ecliptic coordinates to equatorial coordinates is trivial, but the mapping from the orbital angular momentum direction to the inclination angle is more complicated. Therefore we draw samples in the LISA (solar system barycenter frame) coordinates, compute the SNR, and display the maximum and minimum SNRs which are consistent with the parameter uncertainties of each source. Our results, which we have checked to be in agreement with the sky-location and orientation averaged results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Robson et al. (2018)</ref>, are shown in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classic</head><p>If we fix the detectability threshold at ρ thr = 5, none of the currently known systems has ρ &gt; ρ thr , even assuming coherent integration over the nominal LISA mission lifetime, i.e. T obs = 4 yrs ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Amaro-Seoane et al. 2017</ref>). GP Com bwhose companion is a donor in an AM CVn-type interacting binary ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kupfer et al. 2016)</ref>, so it can hardly be classified as an exoplanet -would be marginally detectable with the "Classic LISA" design, and it is marginally detectable by the current LISA design in four years only if we consider the most optimistic SNR values allowed by parameter uncertainties. A more reliable assessment of the detectability of this system will require better knowledge of the system's properties, as well as more careful modeling of LISA's response and of the galactic confusion noise (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Timpano et al. 2006</ref>). For V396 Hya b and J1433 b, the SNR is always lower than the detection threshold. Detection thresholds can be lowered if we incorporate information from electromagnetic measurements into the GW search, but a quantitative assessment of this issue is beyond the scope of this paper (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Shah &amp; Nelemans 2014</ref>).</p><p>The search for ultra-short period exoplanets is certainly an exciting scientific target for LISA. We hope that our considerations will motivate further work to optimize data analysis methods, to reduce the noise power spectral density at low frequencies, and to improve our understanding of the galactic confusion noise. It will be interesting to model the exoplanet parameter space that would be detectable by LISA (including galactic exoplanets and brown dwarf populations) to better understand the potential of GW observations and their complementarity with respect to traditional detection methods. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: ANTENNA PATTERN</head><p>In this Appendix we write down, for completeness, the antenna pattern expressions used in our non angle-averaged SNR calculation. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cutler (1998)</ref>, we denote the LISA-based coordinate system by unbarred quantities, while barred quantities refer to the fixed ecliptic coordinate system. The amplitude modulation in equation 2 is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">˜ A(t) = 1 + ( ˆ L · n) 2 2 F+ 2 + 4( ˆ L · n) 2 F× 2 ,<label>(A1)</label></formula><p>wherê L and −n are the unit vector along the binary's orbital angular momentum and the GW direction of propagation, respectively. The pattern functions F+ and F× are defined as </p><p>The angles (θS, φS) specify the source location, while ψS denotes the the polarization angle:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">tan ψS(t) = ˆ L · z − ( ˆ L · n)(z · n) n · ( ˆ L × z) ,<label>(A3)</label></formula><p>where z is the unit normal to the LISA detector plane.</p><p>The scalar products can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">z · n = cos θS,<label>(A4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">ˆ L · z = 1 2 cos ¯ θL − √ 3 2 sin ¯ θL cos( ¯ φ(t) − ¯ φL),<label>(A5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">ˆ L · n = cos ¯ θL cos ¯ θS + sin ¯ θL sin ¯ θS cos( ¯ φL − ¯ φS), (A6) and n · ( ˆ L × z) = 1 2 sin ¯ θL sin ¯ θS sin( ¯ φL − ¯ φS) − √ 3 2 cos ¯ φ(t)</formula><p>cos ¯ θL sin ¯ θS sin ¯ φS − cos ¯ θS sin ¯ θL sin ¯ φL − √ 3 2 sin ¯ φ(t) cos ¯ θS sin ¯ θL cos ¯ φL − cos ¯ θL sin ¯ θS cos ¯ φS .</p><p>(A7)</p><p>The polarization and Doppler phases in equation 2 are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">ϕp(t) = tan −1 2( ˆ L · n)F×(t) (1 + ( ˆ L · n) 2 )F+(t) (A8) ϕD(t) = 2πf c R sin ¯ θS cos( ¯ φ(t) − ¯ φS),<label>(A9)</label></formula><p>where R = 1AU and ¯ φ(t) = ¯ φ0 + 2πt/T . Here T = 1 yr is the orbital period of LISA, and ¯ φ0 is a constant specifying the detector's location at time t = 0.</p><p>Assuming no precession of the orbital angular momentum, the time-dependent LISA related angles (θS, φS, ψS) can be expressed in terms of the time-independent angles defined in the ecliptic coordinates ( ¯ θS, ¯ φS, ¯ θL, ¯ φL) through the following relations: </p><p>where α0 is a constant specifying the orientation of the detector arms at t = 0. We set α0 = 0 and ¯ φ0 = 0 in our calculations, but we checked that varying α0 and ¯ φ0 has an insignificant effect on the SNR as long as the observation period T obs 1 yr.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS K.W.K.W. and E.B. are supported by NSF Grants No. PHY-1841464 and AST-1841358, and by NASA ATP Grant 17-ATP17-0225. We thank the referee (Neil Cornish), Quentin Baghi, Robert Caldwell, Tyson Littenberg, Travis Robson, Ira Thorpe, Nadia Zakamska, Hsiang-Chih Hwang, Kevin Schlaufman and all members of the NASA LISA Study Team for useful discussions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>+ cos 2 θS) cos 2φS cos 2ψS − cos θS sin 2φS sin 2ψS, F×(θS, φS, ψS) = 1 2 (1 + cos 2 θS) cos 2φS sin 2ψS + cos θS sin 2φS cos 2ψS.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kastha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mitra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Amaro-Seoane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1702.00786</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ICTP Lect. Notes Ser</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">64031</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buonanno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84025</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bb Laut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Babak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Królak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63008</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">481</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crowder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cornish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">575</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Cunha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A S</forename><surname>Lima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">480</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cutler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7089</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>D&amp;apos;andrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ashtekar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Modern Physics D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">495</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">VizieR Online Data Catalog</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Gaia Collaboration</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="page">1345</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hernández</forename><surname>Santisteban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">366</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kupfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Steeghs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Groot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nelemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H A</forename><surname>Roelofs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">457</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kupfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">480</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">302</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hiscock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hellings</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P L</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15014</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mróz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">548</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">183</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Poisson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">848</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Robson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cornish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1803.01944</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nelemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">790</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">161</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Timpano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rubbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cornish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
