<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">LIMITS TO TERTIARY ASTROMETRIC COMPANIONS IN BINARY SYSTEMS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-08-29">29 Aug 2006 September 30, 2018 September 30, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bernard</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">LIMITS TO TERTIARY ASTROMETRIC COMPANIONS IN BINARY SYSTEMS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-08-29">29 Aug 2006 September 30, 2018 September 30, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Draft version Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 6/22/04 Draft version</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: binaries:close -binaries:visual -planetary systems: formation -astrometry -meth- ods: data analysis</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Palomar High-precision Astrometric Search for Exoplanet Systems (PHASES) has monitored 37 sub-arcsecond binary systems to determine whether their Keplerian orbits are perturbed by faint astrometric companions to either star. Software has been developed to evaluate the regions in a companion mass-period phase space in which the PHASES observations can exclude the possibility of face-on orbit perturbations. We present results for 8 systems for which astrometric companions with masses as small as those of giant planets can be excluded.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>A technique has been developed to obtain high precision (10-20 µas) astrometry of close stellar pairs (separation less than one arcsecond; <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Lane and Muterspaugh 2004</ref>) using long-baseline infrared interferometry at the Palomar Testbed Interferometer (PTI; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Colavita et al. 1999</ref>). These observations provide precision visual orbits of the binaries and allow detection of tertiary components orbiting either the primary or secondary due to the reflex motion of the subsystem center-of-light.</p><p>These measurements were made at PTI as part of the Palomar High-precision Astrometric Search for Exoplanet Systems (PHASES) program. PTI is located on Palomar Mountain near San Diego, CA. It was developed by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology for NASA, as a testbed for interferometric techniques applicable to the Keck Interferometer and other missions such as the Space Interferometry Mission (SIM). It operates in the J (1.2µm), H (1.6µm), and K (2.2µm) bands, and combines starlight from two out of three available 40-cm apertures. The apertures form a triangle with one 110 and two 87 meter baselines. PHASES observations use two of the three available baselines at PTI: the NS (110 meter) and SW (87 meter) baselines.</p><p>PTI has previously contributed to exoplanet search efforts through high spatial resolution visibility "imaging" of the 51 Pegasi system( <ref type="bibr">Boden et al. 1998</ref>), which placed limits on the luminosity of its companion and support the conclusion that it is substellar, and likely planetary, in nature. Here the initial detection limits of a different effort at PTI are presented, this time based on astrometric measurements of binary systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">THE PHASES EXOPLANET SEARCH</head><p>PHASES measures the separation vectors of bright binaries that are not resolved by PTI's telescopes but are overresolved by the interferometer itself. The high spatial resolution (∼ 4 mas) of the interferometer, coupled with an hour of observations, enables extremely precise measurement of the binary separation. Phase-referencing is used to maintain coherence so that the full resolving power of the interferometer is applied to the astrometric measurement. The current limiting magnitude in phase-referencing mode is K = 4.5 for equal magnitude binaries. Work is being done to improve the sensitivity by introducing a variation in which the phase-referencing fringe tracker operates at half the current speed, to a 50 Hz duty cycle. The PHASES program has successfully obtained at least one night of data on 37 binaries. As of April 2006, observations have been attempted on 209 nights, resulting in 688 astrometric measurements.</p><p>If only the primary and secondary stars are present in the system, one expects these separation vectors to evolve according to a Keplerian model. On the other hand, if additional (faint) components are present, their presence will cause perturbations to this orbit. Distant companions simultaneously orbiting both visible components will cause only very small perturbations to the observed separation vector (the differential gravitational pull is small); the PHASES observations are not sensitive to these "circumbinary" planets (also called "P-type" or planetary-type planets, <ref type="bibr">Dvorak 1982)</ref>. However, companions orbiting just one star of the binary can cause noticeable perturbations to the separation vectors. This configuration is similar to that outlined by the Nemesis theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Harrison 1977)</ref>, which postulated the Sun has a stellar companion orbiting at a distance far from the planets. PHASES is a search for these "Nemesis-type" planetary systems (also called "S-type" or satellite-type planets).</p><p>The primary goal of the PHASES program is to find and characterize giant planets in close binary systems. In this case, "close" binary is defined as those with semimajor axis a 50AU in which one might expect binary dynamics to play a major role in system formation and evolution (see, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Pfahl and Muterspaugh 2006</ref>). The existence of such systems poses a strong challenge for models of giant planet formation. While it is possible each of the two processes currently favored-core accretion <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Lissauer 1993)</ref> and gravitational instability (Boss 2000)-contribute to giant planet formation around single stars and wide binaries, simulations show both schemes have obstacles when a second star orbits so closely that it interacts with the planet-forming circumstellar disk <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Nelson 2000)</ref>, truncating it in size and heating it. In five exoplanet hosting binaries-HD 188753 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Konacki 2005</ref>), γ Cephei ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hatzes et al. 2003</ref>), GJ 86 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Queloz et al. 2000)</ref>, HD 41004 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Zucker et al. 2004</ref>), and HD 196885 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chauvin et al. 2006</ref>)-the secondary star would have truncated the disks to less than 7 AU (for systems in which the binary orbits are not fully constrained, moderate values for the eccentricities are assumed). It is possible that some of these planets formed around single stars or in wide binaries and reached their current configurations via dynamical interactions in the short-lived star clusters in which they formed <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Pfahl 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Portegies Zwart and McMillan 2005)</ref>, though this post-formation mechanism appears to be too infrequent to explain the number found.</p><p>These systems have been identified with the radial velocity (RV) method. PHASES employs astrometry, from which the companion mass can be identified without the ambiguity of the orbital inclination. Furthermore, the relative orientations of the binary and planetary orbits can be determined in order that system dynamics can be studied. This effort and others specifically targeting close binaries will better determine the frequency of planets in binaries; if large, this will be strong motivation for a revolution in the theory of giant planet formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SYSTEMATIC ERRORS</head><p>When fit to a low-order polynomial or two-body (single) Keplerian model, the current PHASES measurements show night-to-night scatter in excess of that determined by evaluating the scatter within a given night. The timescales of this excess scatter can be evaluated by dividing observations from within a night into subsets by time and analyzing these subsets individually. It is found that within a given night the subsets agree at the level determined by the formal uncertainties obtained from the standard PHASES data reduction pipeline. Because the subsets represent observations separated by of order an hour, it is concluded that the PHASES uncertainties are consistent within a night; the variations occur on night-to-night timescales.</p><p>This excess scatter may be due to either the presence of additional companions or due to systematic errors that occur on timescales of days or longer. In order to determine limits to tertiary companions, it is assumed that any systematic errors result in true night-to-night measurement uncertainties that are related to the formal uncertainties by a multiplicative factor. Depending on the nature of potential systematics, this factor may be different for each individual system (potentially depending on contrast ratios, separations, or star color differences); it is assumed that this factor is a constant for any given system over the course of the measurements. An alternative approach would be to postulate a noise floor; this is not evaluated in the current investigation. It is assumed the uncertainties are distributed in a Gaussian manner; see section 5.4.</p><p>Potential sources of systematic instrumental errors have been identified and efforts are being made to correct them for the next stage of PHASES observations (during the 2006-2008 seasons). The first source is due to color dispersion within the interferometer, which manifests itself in two manners. The path compensation for the geometric delay at PTI has been done with movable mirrors in air, which has a wavelength-dependent index of refraction. The fringe packets of astrophysical sources are dispersed by an amount that depends on the difference in air paths between arms of the interferometer; this changes the shape and overall location of the fringe packets. If the two stars are of differing colors, each will be dispersed by a slightly different amount, and their apparent separation will be biased; see the schematic in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">figure 1</ref>. Additionally, if there is dispersion in a direction perpendicular (lateral) to the light beam (due to optics acting as prisms; atmospheric differential chromatic refraction also introduces lateral dispersion, though this amount is small) or diffraction, the color of the star's light falling on the image plane detector pixel can vary with sky position. In the presence of longitudinal dispersion, the dependence of these color shifts on location within the pixel can also introduce astrometric systematics; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">figure 2</ref>. A longitudinal dispersion compensator has been commissioned for PTI which should eliminate both systematics. A second source of potential error is drift in the "astrometric baseline" due to drifts in optical alignment which may result in variable pupil sampling at the interferometer apertures. This is remedied by introduction of an automatic alignment system. These engineering improvements will initiate a second stage of the PHASES program, in which it is anticipated the observational precisions will be improved by a factor of ∼ 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DETECTION LIMITS</head><p>It is anticipated that at least a portion of the excess noise is the result of systematic errors, though in some cases the presence of an astrometric companion also contributes. An approach to differentiate between these contributions is developed by recognizing that an astrometric perturbation will appear as a Keplerian wobble, whereas instrumental terms will be random; the Keplerian signature becomes a constraint on the nature of the excess scatter. An algorithm for determining the confidence levels of such a signal in the presence of instrumental scatter is described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Exclusion Criteria</head><p>The hypothesis is that model A correctly represents the observed system; one desires to determine the χ 2 goodnessof-fit threshold at which a different model, B, is less consistent with the data than A (for a discussion of χ 2 as a likelihood estimator for data with Gaussian uncertainties, see for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Press et al. 1992</ref>) . In the present case, model A is the simpler single-Keplerian orbit (with seven independent parameters allowed to vary freely, P 1 , e 1 , i 1 , ω 1 ,  .-Schematic of the shift in fringe positions due to coupling of longitudinal and lateral dispersion. Due to the finite distance between stars in the image plane, the detector will sample each star differently. If the stars' spectra are dispersed in the image plane, a given detector pixel will sample different colors for each star. This is normally not a problem, as the astrometric measurement is not derived from centroiding the stars on the detector, but rather from the locations of the movable mirrors at which fringes appear on the detector from either one star or the other (each star image is the overlap of images from two telescope). If there is additionally longitudinal dispersion, the delay location at which fringes form will be color dependent.</p><p>T o,1 , Ω 1 , and a 1 ), whereas model B is the double-Keplerian model with additional parameters. In the case of a second "perturbation" orbit being limited to face-on circular configurations, three new free parameters will be introduced: period P 2 , center-of-light semimajor axis a 2 , and one member of the set of the angle of periastron passage ω 2 , epoch T o,2 , and longitude of the ascending node Ω 2 , which are degenerate; constant parameters are the other two of the previous set, the inclination i 2 , which can either take value zero or 180 degrees (though nothing in between), and the eccentricity e 2 = 0. Extension to inclined orbits is discussed in §4.3. A phase space can be constructed over these additional free parameters (P 2 , a 2 , and Ω 2 ) to evaluate which combinations result in improved or worse fits. In practice, this phase space is collapsed in the Ω 2 dimension to the best-fit value, and a 2 is converted to tertiary companion mass.</p><p>Q A and Q B are defined as the number of free parameters for models A and B, respectively (here, Q A &lt; Q B ), and there are D independent measurements being considered (for astrometry, D is twice the number of measures, as each are two dimensional). Thus, the numbers of degrees of freedom are</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Z A = D − Q A and Z B = D − Q B .</formula><p>In χ 2 fitting, the best-fit model is expected to have a goodness-of-fit χ 2 equal to the number of degrees of freedom.</p><p>In the hypothesis that model A accurately describes the data, but that the data have excessive noise not included in their formal uncertainties, the noise excess factor is given by χ 2 A /Z A . Reweighting the formal uncertainties by the square root of this factor will result in a recomputed value of χ 2 A,mod = Z A . The hypothesis thus assumes that this new set of uncertainties correctly represents the scatter in the observations as a random process.</p><p>When introducing additional free parameters to a model, it is expected that the fit χ 2 will decrease. This does not mean that the model fits better, rather this must be placed in terms of the reduced χ 2 r = χ 2 /Z. If the two models represent the data equally well, one expects</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">χ 2 A /Z A = χ 2 B /Z B .</formula><p>If this relationship does not hold and B is has the larger reduced χ 2 r , B is excluded at the N σ level for the value of N that satisfies χ 2 A /Z A = χ 2 B / (Z B + δ QB,N ) where δ Q,N is the value by which a properly normalized χ 2 metric must be increased to find the N σ confidence region, given a model with Q free parameters. In this case, it is the interval computed for model B, which by assumption less accurately describes the data.</p><p>Rearrangement of terms indicates that model B is excluded at or beyond the N σ level when</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">χ 2 B ≥ Z B + δ QB,N Z A χ 2 A .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>4.2. Astrometric Detection Criteria In this hypothesis, we accept B as the correct model, and look for the χ 2</p><p>A level for which model A is excluded. Thus, we simply replace the roles of the models in equation 1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">χ 2 A ≥ Z A + δ QA,N Z B χ 2 B .</formula><p>Because it is model B for which a phase space grid is constructed (over the extra free parameters in this more complex model), it is useful to invert this expression such that it is expressed as the contours of χ 2 B for which model A is rejected: <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> lists values of δ Q,N used in the following sections. The values of δ Q,N can be found by iteratively solving the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">χ 2 B ≤ Z B Z A + δ QA,N χ 2 A .<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">P Q 2 , δ Q,N 2 = P 1 2 , N 2 2</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">P (a, x) = x 0 e −t t a−1 dt ∞ 0 e −t t a−1 dt</formula><p>is the standard incomplete gamma function, equal to the probability of a χ 2 distribution. In practice, it is often numerically better to equate Q(a, x) = 1 − P (a, x). Thus, the 1σ contour has probability 0.683, and 3σ has probability 0.9973.</p><p>One must be careful how the exclusion and detection confidence levels are interpreted. This is particularly true in the case of detections; one must not forget the effect of the data sampling function or the possibility that a third model better explains the data. To claim a true astrophysical "detection", one must also satisfy the criteria that the perturbation orbit is well constrained. The exclusion criteria are more robust to such possibilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Extension to Inclined Orbits</head><p>In order for the exclusion limits to be more broadly useful, it is important to allow for the possibility of inclined orbits for the tertiary companions. The present numerical analysis is limited to face-on orbits only due to computational limitations; including a search over a range of orbital inclinations introduces two new freely varying parameters, increasing the computational time required by roughly two orders of magnitude. Alternatively, a procedure can be developed to relate the face-on limits to those for inclined systems.</p><p>For a given face-on system of semimajor axis a F , one can determine the size a I of the inclined orbit model which results in the same χ 2 metric; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 3</ref>. Two cases are evaluated: first, when the observational uncertainty ellipses are much larger in one dimension than the other (case for model I1), and second, when the uncertainty ellipses are circular (case for model I2). These extreme cases bound the values appropriate for PHASES data. In both cases, it is assumed that no perturbation exists and the "wide" binary orbit has been removed; the residuals are centered at (x, y) = (0, 0). The χ 2 sum is divided into two terms; one summing along the axis parallel to the larger dimension of the apparent orbit of the inclined perturbation model (x), and the other along the smaller dimension (y):  where X(φ(t)) = a cos φ and Y (φ(t)) = a cos i sin φ (i is the inclination of the orbit) are the perturbation orbit model values at time t in each dimension (φ = 2πt/P +φ o ; φ o is a phase offset), and σ 2 x and σ 2 y are the respective uncertainties for each dimension. There are no x − y cross terms by choice of basis, explained below. Conditions for which the χ 2 F of the face-on orbit equals χ 2 I1 or χ 2 I2 of the inclined models are sought. In the case of non-circular uncertainty ellipses, one works in a basis for which the uncertainty ellipse major axis is oriented along the x axis. It is assumed the uncertainty ellipses share a single such basis (their orientations do not vary) such that a χ 2 minimizing algorithm will align the larger dimension of the apparent perturbation orbit with the large uncertainty axis (this also assumes there are no external limits placed on the longitude of the ascending node). For PHASES data, the orientations of the uncertainty ellipses vary slightly from night to night (depending on the hour angle of observations); this serves only to lessen the resulting conversion factor, and the present derivation is for the more extreme case. In the limit of large uncertainties in the x direction, | X(t) |≤ a I1 ≪ σ 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">χ 2 = D/2 i=1 (X (φ (t i )) − x i ) 2 σ 2 x + D/2 i=1 (Y (φ (t i )) − y i ) 2 σ 2 y (3)</formula><p>x and the first term in eq. 3 is unchanged and cancels upon setting χ 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">F = χ 2 I1 , leaving D/2 i=1 (Y F (t i ) − y i ) 2 σ 2 y = D/2 i=1 (Y I1 (t i ) − y i ) 2 σ 2 y .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>By geometry,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Y F (φ) = a F sin φ and Y I1 (φ) = a I1 cos i sin φ. By setting a F = a I1 cos i, χ 2 F = χ 2 I1 .</formula><p>Thus, inclined orbits with semimajor axis 1/ cos i times larger will fit the observations equally well as a face-on model. For circular uncertainty ellipses,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">σ 2 x = σ 2 y = σ 2 D/2 i=1 (XF (φ(ti))−xi) 2 σ 2 + D/2 i=1 (YF (φ(ti))−yi) 2 σ 2 = D/2 i=1 (XI1(φ(ti))−xi) 2 σ 2 + D/2 i=1 (YI2(φ(ti))−yi) 2 σ 2 D/2 i=1 (a F cos φ (t i ) − x i ) 2 + D/2 i=1 (a F sin φ (t i ) − y i ) 2 = D/2 i=1 (a I2 cos φ (t i ) − x i ) 2 + D/2 i=1 (a I2 cos i sin φ (t i ) − y i ) 2 .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Assuming the measurements are uniformly distributed in φ, and x i and y i have statistically similar distributions p which are even functions (such as Gaussians), this relationship becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">∞ −∞ 2π 0 (aF cos φ − x) 2 p(x)dφdx + ∞ −∞ 2π 0 (aF sin φ − y) 2 p(y)dφdy = ∞ −∞ 2π 0 (aI2 cos φ − x) 2 p(x)dφdx + ∞ −∞ 2π 0 (aI2 sin φ cos i − y) 2 p(y)dφdy ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 F cos 2 φ − 2aF cos φx + x 2 p(x)dφdx ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 F sin 2 φ − 2aF sin φy + y 2 p(y)dφdy = ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 I2 cos 2 φ − 2aI2 cos φx + x 2 p(x)dφdx + ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 I2 sin 2 φ cos 2 i − 2aI2 sin φ cos iy + y 2 p(y)dφdy ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 F cos 2 φp(x)dφdx + ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 F sin 2 φp(y)dφdy = ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 I2 cos 2 φp(x)dφdx + ∞ −∞ 2π 0 a 2 I2 sin 2 φ cos 2 ip(y)dφ (6)</formula><p>where in the last step, the second terms (linear in x and y) integrate to zero because p is even, and the third terms cancel on the right and left sides of the equation. Finally, the remaining x and y integrals are common to all terms and cancel, and the φ integrals evaluate to identical values for all terms, leaving</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">2a 2 F = a 2 I2 1 + cos 2 i .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Thus, by setting a F = a I2 (1 + cos 2 i) /2, χ 2 F = χ 2 I2 . Because orbital size is proportional to companion mass, these multiplicative factors can be directly applied to the exclusion limits for astrometric companions. To convert between the results for face-on and those including inclined models, one need multiply only by a factor between ∼ 2/(1 + cos 2 i) and ∼ 1/ cos i. The exact value of this factor depends on the distributions of observations in time and orientations and aspect ratios of the uncertainty ellipses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">δ EQUULEI</head><p>PHASES observations of the nearby binary system δ Equulei (7 Equ, HR 8123, HD 202275, ADS 14773), including an updated visual orbit, have been presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Muterspaugh et al. (2005)</ref>. The 27 observations reported there have been combined with 11 new measurements from the 2006 observing season to search for evidence of astrometric companions around either star. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows the regions in companion mass-period phase space for which the measurements are inconsistent with a perturbation caused by a hypothetical companion in a face-on circular orbit. Companions with masses greater than the lines plotted are inconsistent with the PHASES observations; the exclusion regions are those above the lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Application of Detection Limits Procedure</head><p>Implementation of the criteria described by equations 1 and 2 can be demonstrated on this system. The binary orbit is short enough that it is well constrained by the PHASES observations alone (P 1 &lt; 6 years); the elements of the visual orbit are not strongly covariant. Thus, all seven parameters of a visual orbit (P 1 , e 1 , i 1 , ω 1 , T o,1 , Ω 1 , a 1 ) are allowed to be varied in Keplerian model (Q A = 7 Model B is a double-Keplerian orbit given by superposition as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">− − → y obs = − −− → r A−B (P 1 , e 1 , i 1 , ω 1 , T o,1 , Ω 1 , a 1 ) + − −−−−−−−− → r Ba−Bb,C.O.L. (P 2 , e 2 , i 2 , ω 2 , T o,2 , Ω 2 , a 2 ) .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Here, the A-B orbit is the slow, "wide" orbit and the Ba-Bb orbit is the "narrow" perturbation orbit center-of-light motion. When converting a 2 to M Bb , assumed values for M Ba = 1.19M ⊙ and the system distance d = 18.386 pc are used, and it is assumed that component Bb is faint (i.e. the Ba-Bb center-of-light is located at Ba, and a 2 = a Ba , corresponding to just the reflex motion of the star). In δ Equ, both stellar components A and B mass roughly 1.19M ⊙ ; the model is symmetric for companions to A or B and the derived limits on companion masses are identical for the two-one search eliminates companions around both stars, in this case with nearly equal mass limits.</p><p>To evaluate whether model B (equation 8) better fits the observations, the χ 2 metric is used to evaluate the goodnessof-fit at each point in a grid of hypothetical companion masses and orbital periods. The grid was stepped logarithmically in companion mass from 10 −1 to 10 3 M J with step size log (M Bb /M J ) = 0.1. The companion period was sampled at values of P 2 = 2f T /K, where f is an excess factor (here 3) for finer sampling, T is the span of the observations (∼ 760 days), and K is a natural number up to that for which P 2 = 3 days. P 2 was additionally evaluated at values of K = 1/2, 1/3, ..., 1/9.</p><p>At each grid point, the seven parameters of the wide orbit are seeded with those from the best-fit single-Keplerian (i.e. model A); the perturbation orbit's parameters are seeded in period and (center-of-light) semimajor axis as determined by the phase-space grid. Additionally, the perturbation orbit is seeded in several values of Ω 2 (separated by 40 degrees starting at 0 and increasing up to 320), and at inclinations of either zero or 180 degrees to allow for face-on orbits with clockwise or counter-clockwise motion; all combinations of these Ω 2 and i 2 seedings are explored. The values of the other secondary orbit parameters are seeded at zero.</p><p>The model is allowed to relax from each set of initial seedings using a downhill χ 2 fitting algorithm in which the seven parameters of the "wide" orbit and Ω 2 in the "narrow" orbit are allowed to vary. Note that the narrow system inclination is not allowed to vary-this restricts the search to including only face-on orbits, and the inclination parameter does not add to the count of "free parameters" in the model. While the period and semimajor axis (and thus mass) of the perturbation orbit are not allowed to vary in the downhill fitting process, these are varied across the grid and are to be counted in the total number of model parameters. Note that with eccentricity held at zero (circular orbits) and inclinations restricted to zero and 180 degrees, Ω 2 is degenerate with T o,2 and ω 2 , thus these need not be varied. The total number of degrees of freedom in the double-Keplerian model is thus Q B = 10; seven are from the wide orbit, plus the period P 2 , orbit phase Ω 2 , and semimajor axis a 2 (or companion mass) of the perturbing orbit. From this, Z B = Z A − 3 = 66.</p><p>The N σ exclusion regions are defined as those for which the double-Keplerian model χ 2 B is greater than 1090.83 × (66+δ 10,N )/69. The N σ detection regions are calculated from equation 2 as being those for which the double-Keplerian χ 2 B is less than 1090.83 × 66/(69 + δ 7,N ). The 1σ (χ 2 B = 1226) and 3σ (χ 2 B = 1469) exclusion contours in mass-period phase space are plotted in <ref type="figure">figure 4</ref>; also shown is the 1σ detection contours at χ 2 B = 933; the smallest value of χ 2 B is 883, well above the 2σ detection criteria of χ 2 B = 864. It is concluded these detection regions are results of statistical happenstance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Comparison to Previous Work</head><p>The same procedure has been applied to the non-PHASES astrometric measurements reviewed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Muterspaugh et al. (2005)</ref>; see this work for a discussion of the relative weightings of these measurements. These 170 measurements cover a much longer time span (of a century) than the PHASES observations, but at lower precisions. In this case, the value of T used to determine the companion periods sampled was chosen to be half the period of the wide orbit found in the best fit single-Keplerian model (P 1 /2 = T ∼ 1042) days. The best fit seven-parameter single-Keplerian model results in χ 2 A = 426.5 and Z A = 340 − 7 = 333 degrees of freedom. Thus, the 1σ and 3σ exclusion level for χ 2 B of the ten-parameter double-Keplerian model are 437.5 and 457.2, respectively. For P 2 &lt; P 1 , no values of χ 2 B in the grid are less than 400, which is between the 2σ and 3σ detection thresholds (this lowest point is near P 2 ∼ 10.25 days and M Bb ∼ 800M J , which is strongly disfavored by the PHASES data).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Inclined Orbits</head><p>At this time, it is computationally prohibitive to search in additional parameters (for example, to add an array of seeds in inclination and allow this parameter to also vary, or to search for eccentric orbits). It is noted that there is always an orbit for which astrometry is completely insensitive to companions of any mass or period-high eccentricity, edge-on orbits pointing directly at the observer (i.e. periastron passage within the line of sight); combination fitting with radial velocity observations lifts this problem and can be useful when contemplating universal exclusions of perturbing companions. Evaluating the phase-space grid described above using just the PHASES astrometry and a 10 parameter model requires roughly 3 weeks on a modern processor; each additional parameter is expected to increase this by roughly an order of magnitude. A need is identified for an alternative approach than the "brute-force" algorithm described here, in combination with an evaluation of its performance and reliability in comparison to the method described here.</p><p>To test the analytical conversion factor between detection limits for face-on and inclined systems of §4.3, the PHASES observations of δ Equulei were reanalyzed allowing inclinations to vary within 45 degrees of face-on (both prograde and retrograde orbits were allowed) over a very limited subset of perturbation periodicities. The predicted conversion factor is between 4/3 and √ 2; in practice, a factor of ∼ 1.35 − 1.4 is appropriate for the PHASES observations. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> shows the continuous (integrated) distribution function of the residuals to the 2-body Keplerian fit for the δ Equulei system. For each measurement, the residuals were measured along directions parallel to the formal uncertainty error ellipse major and minor axis in order that the uncertainties are not covariant. Each were then normalized by that measurement's formal uncertainty estimate. The distribution of this normalized set of residuals can now be considered to determine whether a multiplicative scale factor is an appropriate assumption for handling the observed  <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>.-The δ Equulei Mass-Period companion phase space. Companions in the regions above the plotted exclusion curves with face-on orbits are not consistent with the observations. Companions as small as two Jupiter masses can be ruled out by PHASES observations. The most significant detections are less than 2σ significant, and are not likely astrophysical in origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Fit Residuals</head><note type="other">Previous Astrometry PHASES Astrometry 3σ Exclusion 1σ Exclusion 1σ Detection</note><p>excess scatter, in which case the residuals should have a Gaussian distribution. The continuous distribution function is fit to the integral of a Gaussian:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">1 + erf(x/ √ 2a) 2 (9)</formula><p>where a is a measure of the excess scatter over the formal uncertainties (the best fit value for a is 2.94 ± 0.01).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">KNOWN TRIPLE STARS</head><p>This procedure is tested on two binaries that each are known to host tertiary companions, κ Pegasi and V819 Herculis. The PHASES astrometric orbits of these triples have been previously examined <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Muterspaugh et al. 2006b</ref>,a); the phase space exploration algorithm detects these perturbations and their statistical significances are now presented.</p><p>6.1. κ Pegasi PHASES observations of the well-known triple system κ Pegasi (10 Peg, HR 8315, HD 206901, ADS 15281), from which the orbits of both the long and short period subsystems were determined, have been presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Muterspaugh et al. (2006b)</ref>. The 52 PHASES measurements presented there are combined with three measurements from 2005 creating a set spanning ∼ 1046 days. In the previous investigation, both a noise floor and multiplicative factor were explored for explaining excess systematic noise; the present investigation evaluates only the latter case.</p><p>A mass-period grid was constructed similar to that in the case of δ Equulei, differing in the following ways: the P 2 oversample factor f is 1 rather than 3, the companion masses explored ranged from 10 0 to 10 4 M J , and the step size in companion mass was log (M Bb /M J ) = 0.2 rather than 0.1. The 424 non-PHASES astrometry data tabulated in the previous investigation were similarly evaluated over the same grid; because these span a time much longer than the wide orbit period, T was set to half the best-fit wide system period P 1 (for evaluation of the PHASES data, T is the timespan they cover). For both the PHASES and non-PHASES data sets, the wide orbit is well-constrained without strong covariances. Thus, for both cases Q A = 7 and Q B = 10. The companion Bb mass to a 2 conversion assumed a stellar mass M Ba = 1.662M ⊙ and distance to the system of 34.60 pc, as determined by the previous investigation. Note that this analysis is only to confirm the detection of the known 5.97-day period companion Bb; at this time no attempt is made to search for fourth components to the system, which may require much more complicated modeling than the simple superpositioning of independent Keplerians that has been used here.</p><p>In the PHASES evaluation, the smallest value of χ 2 B is found at P 2 = 5.978 days; in this region the step size is ∆P 2 ∼ 0.017. This is consistent with the best-fit value of P 2 of 5.9714971 ± 1.3 × 10 −6 days. The depth of this detection corresponds to a detection at the 31.4σ level. Conversely, the smallest value of χ 2 B for the non-PHASES data is at P 2 = 19.14 days with depth not quite reaching the 3σ detection level. The smallest value with 5.9 &lt; P 2 &lt; 6.1 days is just barely smaller than the 1σ threshold (near 1.1σ). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> plots the relevant phase-space contours.</p><p>Upon removing the face-on, circular orbit criteria for the narrow orbit (seeding a χ 2 downhill fit with the best set of parameters found in the phase-space analysis), the fit is considerably improved, Q B = 14, and the second orbit improves the fit at the 106σ level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">V819 Herculis</head><p>PHASES observations have previously determined the astrometric orbit of the short-period subsystem in the V819 Herculis (HR 6469, HD 157482) triple system ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Muterspaugh et al. 2006a</ref>). The narrow (Ba-Bb) pair of the V819 Her system is oriented edge-on and show eclipses. In that analysis, 31 measurements were reported (of which six were not used in model fitting as they were taken during eclipse of the narrow pair); one additional measurement from summer 2005 is added to this set. In the present analysis, measurements taken during eclipse are not omitted to simulate a blind search.</p><p>When only the PHASES data are fit, the span of the measurements (T ∼ 476 days) is much shorter than the period of the wide orbit (P 1 ∼ 2020 days). Thus, P 1 , e 1 , and a 1 are strongly covariant; by fixing just one of these (here, P 1 = 2019.787 days) at a nominal value supported by non-PHASES observations, these covariances are lifted and the fitting algorithm converges much more rapidly. Because that parameter is not optimized for each fit, it does not count to the number of free parameters; for the PHASES analysis, Q A = 6 and Q B = 9; this is not necessary when the non-PHASES observations are included, for which Q A = 7 and Q B = 10 as normal.</p><p>As in the case of κ Pegasi, the mass-period phase space grid was modified by setting the P 2 oversample factor f to 1 rather than 3, the companion masses explored ranged from 10 0 to 10 4 M J , and the step size in companion mass was log (M Bb /M J ) = 0.2 rather than 0.1. Additionally, the smallest value of P 2 sought was 1 day rather than 3. The distance is assumed to be 67.96 pc and M Ba = 1.43M ⊙ . Again, the aim of the search is only to confirm detection of the known companion Bb, and no attempt is made to find fourth components at this time.</p><p>Because the algorithm has been developed to specialize in face-on orbits, it is not optimally suited to analysis of the V819 Her system, for which the short-period perturbation system is observed to eclipse. However, the strength of the algorithm as a "wobble-detector" is demonstrated by applying it to this system for which it is quite nonoptimally designed. The two deepest dips in the χ 2 function occur at periodicities of 2.2284 days (∆P 2 ∼ 0.0052 days; 10.5σ) and 1.8056 days (∆P 2 ∼ 0.0034 days; 10.1σ). These are the only two points at the 10σ level; the 1.8056 day periodicity appears to be only an aliasing; the RV and eclipse photometry coincide with the (more significant) 2.2284 day periodicity (the best fit period to all data is P 2 = 2.2296337 ± 1.9 × 10 −6 days, in agreement with the 2.2284 periodicity, to within the analysis step size). This short-period, 110µas perturbation is readily detected, but is far beyond the ability of other astrometric measurements; with this periodicity identified, one can better refine the fit while allowing other parameters to vary, obtaining the correct orbital configuration for the short-period pair and improving the detection to the 14.7σ level.</p><p>The 34 speckle interferometry data tabulated in the previous paper are evaluated separately (in this case P 1 is allowed to vary freely). As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">figure 7</ref>, the speckle observations are approximately two orders of magnitude away from detecting the short-period perturbation. Interestingly, the 110µas amplitude perturbation would correspond to a planetary mass companion if only its period were several months rather than several days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">β CORONAE BOREALIS</head><p>β Coronae Borealis ("Peculiar Rosette Stone", 3 CrB, HR 5747, HD 137909) is a binary whose primary is of spectral class F0p, part of the family of peculiar A stars with strong magnetic fields. β CrB is often grouped with γ Equulei and α 2 CVn as prototypes of this class. Its magnetic field has been extensively via measurements of Zeeman line splitting, and the inclination of its rotation axis and the angular offset of its magnetic field have been measured.</p><p>Neubauer (1944) studied the binary using RV measurements and found evidence for a third body with orbiting the primary with a period of nearly a year (P 2 ∼ 320 days). <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kamper et al. (1990)</ref> obtained updated RV data which did  (Bottom) The 10-, 20-, and 30-σ detection contours for PHASES observations of the κ Pegasi triple star system are plotted for the limiting case of face-on Ba-Bb subsystem orbits. While the Ba-Bb subsystem is not in fact face-on, the perturbation is detected with the same periodicity as that found by RV observations. Once this periodicity has been identified, the face-on, circular orbit constraint can be removed, and the detection becomes 106σ significant. Also plotted is the 1σ exclusion contour based on previous differential astrometry data. A "detection" at the 1σ level in the previous differential astrometry is seen in the plot; however, this is likely due only to statistical happenstance.</p><p>not show this perturbation. However, their analysis showed the periodicity in Neubauer's data is statistically different than one year. They suggested the perturbation was real rather than instrumental, and proposed that this orbit was previously nearly face-on, somehow re-orienting itself to be perfectly face-on between the two epochs. Söderhjelm (1999) concluded from Hipparcos astrometric observations that such a proposed companion cannot exist.</p><p>Forty-two PHASES measurements have been collected over a span of ∼ 804 days. Additionally, 102 non-PHASES differential astrometry measurements have been identified (when these are analyzed, T is set to half the best fit value of P 1 in the 2-body single-Keplerian case). As was the case for V819 Her, P 1 , e 1 , and a 1 are strongly covariant when only PHASES data are considered (T ∼ 804 days versus P 1 ∼ 10.27 yr). Again, P 1 is fixed at a value that is not based on the PHASES observations; P 1 = 10.27 yr is adopted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Tokovinin (1984)</ref>, and Q A = 6, Q B = 9 (7 and 10 when non-PHASES data are included).</p><p>The mass-period grid is set up in the same manner as for δ Equulei. Based on analysis of Hipparcos observations by Söderhjelm (1999), the distance is assumed to be 34.12 pc (π = 29.31 ± 0.82 mas) and the component masses are 1.77 ± 0.16 and 1.21 ± 0.11M ⊙ . The conversion of tertiary mass to semi-major axis assumes a stellar mass of 1.21M ⊙ . Radial velocity measurements are available only for one component of the binary; this prevents one from determining the masses and distance from the orbit alone.</p><p>The excess multiplicative factor is χ 2 A /Z A = 9.9 ∼ 3.2 2 for the PHASES observations. The 1σ and 3σ exclusion contours for both the PHASES and non-PHASES data sets are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">figure 8</ref>. In both cases, the P 2 ∼ 320 day perturbation is excluded; for the PHASES observations, a companion of mass as small as 4M J are excluded. The mass limits should be increased by ∼ 1.77/1.21 ∼ 1.46 when considering the primary star as the companion host (this estimate assumes the companion is an insignificant part of the total mass, reasonable in the case of the lower limit exclusion region). It appears that the perturbation in Neubauer's data set is not astrophysical in origin.</p><p>There are regions of the mass-period phase space for which perturbations from a tertiary companion improve the fit by 3σ or more. The smallest value of χ 2 B corresponds to a 5.2σ detection at P 2 ∼ 20.9 days. When the restriction to face-on, the narrow orbit's parameters are strongly covariant and poorly constrained: for example, the formal uncertainty on the eccentricity is 0.5, implying it is not constrained at all, and the Eulerian angles all have formal uncertainties greater than 360 degrees. While the double-Keplerian model can formally improve the fit compared to the single version, the double-Keplerian model is too detailed to be properly constrained by the current observations. In order to claim a true detection, multiple criteria must be met: the double-Keplerian model must better fit the data, and the perturbation orbit must be well-constrained. Thus, it is possible that the "detection" periodicities are astrophysical in nature, but the data sampling in the present set prevents conclusive study, and aliasing causes multiple periodicities to exist. The span is short compared to the binary period (P 1 ∼ 26.132 yr; <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hartkopf et al. 1989</ref>) and again P 1 , e 1 , and a 1 are covariant; in the analysis P 1 is thus held fixed at this nominal value (Q A = 6, Q B = 9). <ref type="bibr">Söderhjelm (1999)</ref> used Hipparcos measurements to determine the system parallax of 29.6 ± 0.8 mas, a total mass of 2.67M ⊙ , and photometric mass ratio M B /M A = 0.80. Computations assume a distance of 33.8 pc and the tertiary companion orbits the secondary at mass 1.19M ⊙ (the results can be scaled appropriately for the primary at mass 1.48M ⊙ .</p><p>The best fit χ 2 A = 148.8 with Z A = 44 degrees of freedom; assuming model A is correct, the multiplicative excess factor is 3.38 ∼ 1.84 2 . The median formal minor axis uncertainty of 10.2µas is thus adjusted to 18.8µas repeatability from night to night. The mass-period grid is set up as in the case of δ Equulei. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> shows that massive planets in 20 day to 3 year period face-on circular orbits would perturb this binary by more than the observed scatter in the PHASES data. Planets as small as two Jupiter masses are ruled out in ∼ 4 month period orbits. A number of regions show 1σ consistent detections, the best of these is at only the 1.7σ detection level. 3σ Exclusion 1σ Exclusion 1σ Detection <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>.-The 13 Pegasi Mass-Period companion phase space shows PHASES observations can rule out tertiary objects as small as two Jupiter masses. A few mass-period combinations introduce slight improvements over the single-Keplerian model, but none of these are more significant than 1.7σ, and are probably not astrophysical in origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">20 PERSEI</head><p>The binary 20 Persei (HR 855, HD 17904, ADS 2200) has been observed 26 times by PHASES. At K = 4.3 it is one of the fainter PHASES targets. The observations span T ∼ 877 days, a small amount compared to the orbital period of P 1 ∼ 31.528 yr. Covariances between P 1 , e 1 , and a 1 are extremely strong. Using values from <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Docobo et al. (2001)</ref>, both P 1 (31.528 yr) and e 1 (0.753) are fixed (Q A = 5, Q B = 8). The system distance is assumed to be 72.1 pc from the Hipparcos parallax; combining this with the orbital period and semimajor axis an average component mass of 2.1M ⊙ is computed and these values are used in converting tertiary mass to a 2 . The mass-period grid is set up following the same procedure as for δ Equulei. For 20 Per, χ 2 A /Z A = 6.57 ∼ 2.56 2 is a relatively small value. However, the average formal minor-axis uncertainty is 21µas; coupling this with the large distance and masses implies that the tertiary detection limits are not particularly sensitive.</p><p>The PHASES measurements rule out brown dwarf mass companions in a variety of orbital periods, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">figure 10</ref>. Detections are found for several different companion periods at the 1σ detection level. The smallest value of χ 2 B appears at the 2.9σ level; as in the case of β CrB, when the face-on and circular restrictions are lifted from the perturbation orbit, its parameters become poorly constrained. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abt and Levy (1976)</ref> proposed the existence of a tertiary companion with period P 2 = 1269 ± 70 days; this periodicity is very close to the steep cutoff in the phase space contour due to the finite span of PHASES observations; at this time no conclusions are made about the existence of such a companion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">η CORONAE BOREALIS</head><p>Seventeen PHASES observations of η Coronae Borealis (2 CrB, HR 5727, HD 137107, ADS 9617) have been collected over a span of T ∼ 680 days. As with 20 Per, P 1 and e 1 are fixed at values of ∼ 41.585 yr and 0.2620 determined by speckle interferometry ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Mason et al. 1999</ref>) to lift strong covariances with a 1 . From Hipparcos data, Söderhjelm (1999) determined a parallax of 53.5 ± 0.9 mas, total mass 2.41M ⊙ , and photometric mass ratio of 0.96. From these, the tertiary orbit to a 2 conversion is made assuming a distance of 18.69 pc and stellar mass of 1.18M ⊙ (the primary's mass is roughly 1.23M ⊙ and the tertiary companion limits are similar for primary and secondary). The mass-period grid is set up as in the case of δ Equulei.</p><p>Companions as small as 3-4M J in orbits of ∼100-700 days are inconsistent with the PHASES observations. As in the case of β CrB, detection contours deeper than 3σ appear (here at periods less than 10 days). The deepest of these is at the 4.8σ level. Similarly to β CrB, the data sampling does not allow all parameters of the perturbation orbit to be well constrained when the restrictions of face-on and circular orbits are lifted (in particular, e 2 is not constrained at all). This may be astrophysical in origin, but the current data cannot properly address the underlying orbit.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abt and Levy (1976)</ref>. Owing to the far distance of the system and higher mass stars, the PHASES observations are not particularly sensitive to planetary companions in this system. 3σ Exclusion 1σ Exclusion 3σ Detection <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref>.-The η Coronae Borealis Mass-Period companion phase space shows planets as small as three Jupiter masses are inconsistent with PHASES observations. A nearly 5σ significant detection is found at short periods, but observational coverage does not yet allow the orbit to be strongly constrained; it is unclear whether this is merely a statistical fluke, perhaps related to the data sampling function (both dips are near 7 days, a natural sampling time for PHASES observations).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">HR 7162</head><p>HR 7162 (HD 176051, ADS 11871) is a G0V primary with K1V secondary. This color difference appears to affect the PHASES data through the differential dispersion mechanism because the excess scatter χ 2 A /Z A is much larger than for other stars (∼ 88 ∼ 9.4 2 ). As with 20 Per and η CrB, both P 1 and e 1 are fixed at values of ∼ 61.15 yr and 0.258 determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Heintz (1994)</ref> to lift strong covariances with a 1 . Over a span of ∼ 773 days, 32 PHASES observations have been collected. The tertiary mass to a 2 conversion assumes a distance of 15 parsecs and star mass 0.71M ⊙ . These quantities are derived from the Hipparcos-based solution of Söderhjelm (1999), who found a parallax of 66.7 ± 0.6 mas, mass sum 1.78M ⊙ and photometric mass ratio 0.67 (the primary mass corresponds to 1.07M ⊙ ). The mass-period grid is constructed as in the case of δ Equulei. The smallest values of χ 2 B correspond to a 2.7σ detection. Companions as small as 2M J are inconsistent with the PHASES data.</p><p>The physical properties of the HR 7162 binary (low mass stars, close to Earth) make it an exciting candidate for an exoplanet search as very low mass companions can be detected for a given astrometric performance levels. Unfortunately, the PHASES excess scatter factor for this binary is currently much larger than that typical in other systems studied, and appears to be random noise. This is likely due to the large color difference of the binary components, potentially leading to differential dispersion issues. It is anticipated that the current engineering improvements will benefit this system in particular, in which case it will be an extremely exciting study for the exoplanet search, with the ability to detect (or rule out) planets as small as a fifth of a Jupiter mass orbiting either star.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="12.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>PHASES observations are able to exclude tertiary companions with masses as small as a few Jupiter masses in several binary systems. The phase-space searching algorithm correctly identifies the natures of two previously studied triple star systems and finds the correct periods for the short period pairs. While the number of systems that can 3σ Exclusion 1σ Exclusion 1σ Detection <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref>.-Contours in the companion mass-period phase space for HR 7162 show that despite high noise levels from systematic processes, companions as small as two Jupiter masses can be excluded in face-on orbits. After engineering improvements to remove these systematic noise sources, constraints will be placed on sub-Jupiter massed planets by second stage PHASES observations. currently be examined is too small to make strong conclusions about the frequency of giant planets in close binary systems, by the end of the PHASES program enough measurements will be made on all target systems to address this important question. Systematic effects currently limit the observed precision; if overcome, companions as small as a fifth of a Jupiter mass might be detected in favorable systems such as HR 7162.</p><p>PHASES benefits from the efforts of the PTI collaboration members who have each contributed to the development of an extremely reliable observational instrument. Without this outstanding engineering effort to produce a solid foundation, advanced phase-referencing techniques would not have been possible. We thank PTI's night assistant Kevin Rykoski for his efforts to maintain PTI in excellent condition and operating PTI in phase-referencing mode every week. We thank Dimitri Pourbaix for helpful conversations about astrometric orbit fitting. Part of the work described in this paper was performed at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory under contract with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Interferometer data was obtained at the Palomar Observatory using the NASA Palomar Testbed Interferometer, supported by NASA contracts to the Jet Propulsion Laboratory. This research has made use of the Washington Double Star Catalog maintained at the U.S. Naval Observatory. This research has made use of the Simbad database, operated at CDS, Strasbourg, France. MWM acknowledges the MIT Earth, Atmospheric, and Planetary Sciences department for hosting him while this paper was written. BFL acknowledges support from a Pappalardo Fellowship in Physics. PHASES is funded in part by the California Institute of Technology Astronomy Department, and by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration under Grant No. NNG05GJ58G issued through the Terrestrial Planet Finder Foundation Science Program. This work was supported in part by the National Science Foundation through grants AST 0300096 and AST 0507590.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Schematic of the shift in fringe positions due to dispersion (the effect has been exaggerated for clarity). The vacuum (no dispersion) interferograms are plotted with solid lines; those dispersed by air with dotted lines. (top) Dispersion shifts the point of zero optical path difference for a star, due to different amounts of air path in each arm of the interferometer (the effective optical path difference measured as if in vacuum). (middle) The dispersion shifts for stars of equal colors are equal and cancels; the measured separation is the same. (bottom) Stars of unequal colors are shifted by slightly different amounts by dispersion, and the resulting measured separation is different. Not shown are the shape distortions to interferograms. In a differential measurement, these cancel to first order and are insignificant at the precisions of PHASES measurements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2.-Schematic of the shift in fringe positions due to coupling of longitudinal and lateral dispersion. Due to the finite distance between stars in the image plane, the detector will sample each star differently. If the stars' spectra are dispersed in the image plane, a given detector pixel will sample different colors for each star. This is normally not a problem, as the astrometric measurement is not derived from centroiding the stars on the detector, but rather from the locations of the movable mirrors at which fringes appear on the detector from either one star or the other (each star image is the overlap of images from two telescope). If there is additionally longitudinal dispersion, the delay location at which fringes form will be color dependent.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-Inclined tertiary component (perturbation) orbits (I1 and I2) that fit observations equally well as a face-on orbit model (F). Model I1 corresponds to the case of measurements with uncertainties in dimension x much larger than y; model I2 corresponds to those with equal circular uncertainty ellipses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A one-sided Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (see for example section 14.3 of Press et al. 1992) shows the residual distribution agrees with Gaussian statistics with 95% likelihood. The distributions match well and the assumption of Gaussian errors and multiplicative uncertainty scale factors is valid. Treated as separate sets, the scale factors for the major-axis and minor-axis residuals are similar.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-The distribution of normalized residuals for a 2-body Keplerian fit to δ Equulei. Also shown is the theoretical distribution for Gaussian noise.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-κ Pegasi Mass-Period Companion Phase Space. (Top) The 1σ exclusion contour based on previous differential astrometry data, with the 20σ PHASES detection contour. Note that only at the 5.97 day companion period does the 20σ PHASES contour exist. (Bottom) The 10-, 20-, and 30-σ detection contours for PHASES observations of the κ Pegasi triple star system are plotted for the limiting case of face-on Ba-Bb subsystem orbits. While the Ba-Bb subsystem is not in fact face-on, the perturbation is detected with the same periodicity as that found by RV observations. Once this periodicity has been identified, the face-on, circular orbit constraint can be removed, and the detection becomes 106σ significant. Also plotted is the 1σ exclusion contour based on previous differential astrometry data. A "detection" at the 1σ level in the previous differential astrometry is seen in the plot; however, this is likely due only to statistical happenstance.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-The V819 Her Mass-Period companion phase space shows a 10σ significant detection in the PHASES data that is far beyond the detection threshold for previous measurements. Although the tertiary companion's orbit is in fact edge-on, the face-on code detects the wobble at the correct period. After removing the face-on orbit restraint, the double-Keplerian model is a 14.7σ improvement over the single-Keplerian model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-The mass-period phase space for tertiary companions to β Coronae Borealis shows that a proposed massive object with period ∼ 320 days does not exist. Some mass-period combinations do result in double-Keplerian fits that are an improvement over the single-Keplerian model, but the inner-body's orbit is poorly constrained and it is not clear whether these are astrophysical in origin.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10.-A range of brown dwarfs companions can be ruled out by the 20 Persei mass-period phase space. Unfortunately, the PHASES observations do not yet have long enough time coverage to confirm the 1269 day period companion of Abt and Levy (1976). Owing to the far distance of the system and higher mass stars, the PHASES observations are not particularly sensitive to planetary companions in this system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>TABLE 1 Values of δ Q,N</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Q N 
δ Q,N 

Model A 
5 
1 
5.89 
5 
3 
18.21 
6 
1 
7.04 
6 
3 
20.06 
6 
10 120.14 
7 
1 
8.18 
7 
3 
21.85 
7 
10 123.37 
7 
20 430.93 
7 
30 936.61 
Model B 
8 
1 
9.30 
8 
3 
23.57 
9 
1 
10.42 
9 
3 
25.26 
10 1 
11.54 
10 3 
26.90 

2a F 

2a I2 

2a I1 

2a 
I2 cos(i) 

2a 
F =2a 
I1 cos(i) 
x 

y φ 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplicity among solar-type stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Abt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="1976-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Boden</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Van Belle</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gubler</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Koresko</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mobley</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">PTI Collaboration</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Interferometric Search for Bright Companions to 51 Pegasi</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">39</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possible Rapid Gas Giant Planet Formation in the Solar Nebula and Other Protoplanetary Disks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Boss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">536</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A pair of planets around HD 202206 or a circumbinary planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fusco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Galland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beuzit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0606166" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>A&amp;Ain press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Palomar Testbed Interferometer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gursel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Malbet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Boden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gubler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Koresko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mobley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Van Belle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">510</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary star speckle measurements at Calar Alto. I</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Docobo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tamazian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Balega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Maximov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vasyuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="868" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Planetary orbits in double star systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dvorak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Has the sun a companion star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="1977-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary star orbits from speckle interferometry. II -Combined visual-speckle orbits of 28 close systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Hartkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcalister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1014" to="1039" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Planetary Companion to γ Cephei A</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hatzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Paulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">599</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1394" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photographic astrometry of binar and propermotion stars: 8</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heintz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2338" to="2347" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Astrometricspectroscopy binary star orbits. IV -Beta Coronae Borealis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kamper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcalister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Hartkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An extrasolar giant planet in a close triple-star system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Konacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">436</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential Astrometry of Subarcsecond Scale Binaries at the Palomar Testbed Interferometer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">601</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1129" to="1135" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary Star Orbits from Speckle Interferometry. I. Improved Orbital Elements of 22 Visual Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Lissauer ; B</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Douglass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Hartkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1036" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>AJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Konacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PHASES HighPrecision Differential Astrometry of δ Equulei</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-12" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2866" to="2875" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHASES differential astrometry and the mutual inclination of the V819 Herculis triple star system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Konacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHASES Differential Astrometry and Iodine Cell Radial Velocities of the κ Pegasi Triple Star System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Konacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wiktorowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colavita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">636</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1020" to="1032" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planet Formation is Unlikely in Equal-Mass Binary Systems with A ˜ 50 AU</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">537</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The System of β Coronae Borealis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Neubauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1944-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster Origin of the Triple Star HD 188753 and Its Planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">635</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of Stellar Dynamics on the Frequency of Giant Planets in Close Binaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pfahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Muterspaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0606645" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accepted to</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planets in Triple Star Systems: The Case of HD 188753</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Portegies Zwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L W</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">633</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical recipes in C. The art of scientific computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Cambridge: University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">1992</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CORALIE survey for southern extra-solar planets. I. A planet orbiting the star Gliese 86</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blécha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burnet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Confino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual binary orbits and masses post hipparcos</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Söderhjelm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interferometer Orbits for Seven Binaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tokovinin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soviet Astronomy Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiorder TODCOR: Application to observations taken with the CORALIE echelle spectrograph. II. A planet in the system HD 41004</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
