<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets. III. Tidal dissipation revisited and application to Enceladus</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-11-06">6 Nov 2018 November 7, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">·</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">·</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Andrade-Ines</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets. III. Tidal dissipation revisited and application to Enceladus</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-11-06">6 Nov 2018 November 7, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Noname manuscript No. (will be inserted by the editor) the date of receipt and acceptance should be inserted later</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper deals with a new formulation of the creep tide theory (Ferraz-Mello, Cel. Mech. Dyn. Astron. 116, 109, 2013 − Paper I) and with the tidal dissipation predicted by the theory in the case of stiff bodies whose rotation is not synchronous but is oscillating around the synchronous state with a period equal to the orbital period. We show that the tidally forced libration influences the amount of energy dissipated in the body and the average perturbation of the orbital elements. This influence depends on the libration amplitude and is generally neglected in the study of planetary satellites. However, they may be responsible for a 27 percent increase in the dissipation of Enceladus. The relaxation factor necessary to explain the observed dissipation of Enceladus (γ = 1.2 − 3.8 × 10 −7 s −1) has the expected order of magnitude for planetary satellites and corresponds to the viscosity 0.6 − 1.9 × 10 14 Pa.s, which is in reasonable agreement with the value recently estimated by Efroimsky (2018) (0.24 × 10 14 Pa s) and with the value adopted by Roberts and Nimmo (2008) for the viscosity of the ice shell (10 13 − 10 14 Pa s). For comparison purposes, the results are extended also to the case of Mimas and are consistent with the negligible dissipation and the absence of observed tectonic activity. The corrections of some mistakes and typos of paper II (Ferraz-Mello, Cel. Mech. Dyn. Astron. 122, 359, 2015) are included at the end of the paper.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The calculus of the energy dissipation inside a stiff body is generally done by estimating the dissipation resulting from the action of the primary tidal force in deforming the planet <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Kopal, 1963;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kaula, 1963</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kaula, , 1964</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Peale and Cassen, 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Segatz et al., 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Wisdom, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Shoji et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Frouard and Efroimsky, 2017)</ref>. Such approach involves the choice of the physical model of the forces acting on the body at the microscopic level and of the dissipation parameters inside the body. An indirect approach was discussed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kaula (1964;</ref><ref type="bibr">p.677</ref>) in which the bulk dissipation is calculated from the estimation of the total mechanical energy lost by the system. This approach was used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Yoder and Peale (1981)</ref> to estimate the tidal energy dissipated in a synchronous satellite, by <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lissauer et al. (1984)</ref> to study the melting of Enceladus, by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Ferraz-Mello et al. (2008)</ref> and  to estimate the energy dissipated in the frame of Darwin's and creep tide theories, respectively, and by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Correia et al. (2014)</ref> in the frame of a Maxwell model.</p><p>In this paper, we revisit the indirect approach to evaluate the bulk loss of mechanical energy by the system. This approach has the merit of its simplicity. If the companion body (the body responsible for the tide raised in the stiff body) is considered as a mass point, the energy tidally dissipated in the primary body (the stiff body under consideration) may only take origin in its rotation and in the orbit H.A. Folonier, S. Ferraz-Mello and E.Andrade-Ines Instituto de Astronomia Geofísica e Ciências Atmosféricas, Universidade de São Paulo, Brasil E-mail: folonier@usp.br, sylvio@iag.usp.br and eandrade.ines@gmail.com of the system. The secular variations of the semi-major axis and of the rotation of the body are the two gauges allowing us to evaluate the mechanical energy lost by the system. No other non-primeval source exists able to continuously add energy to the system. We thus consider the energy exchanged with the orbit due to the direct attraction of the two bodies, the stored rotational energy in the primary body. Several minor contributions, considered for the sake of completeness, are shown to be negligible.</p><p>We remind that the only assumption of the adopted tide theory is that self-gravitation and tidal stress permanently adjust the surface of the body to an equilibrium surface with speed given by the Newtonian creep law. The adjustment is ruled by an approximate solution of the Navier-Stokes equation for the flow of matter in the immediate neighborhood of the equilibrium surface of the body. No constitutive equation linking strain and stress is introduced at any point in the creep tide theory. All developments to reach the conclusion are the solution of the creep differential equation and the use of classical Physics to compute the force and torque acting on the companion due to the tidal deformation of the primary. The observed dissipation law results directly from the above described first principles of physics, with approximations, but no additional ad-hoc hypotheses. However, the integration of the basic equation of the creep tide theory in papers I and II assumes that the rotation of the body and the Keplerian elements of the orbit do not show significant variations in one orbital period. In the case of stiff bodies with a nearly synchronous rotation, however, it has been shown that the rotation of the bodies is not damped to a stationary value (as gaseous bodies) but is rather driven to a periodic attractor with the same period as the orbital motion and amplitude proportional to the orbital eccentricity (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Correia et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Folonier, 2016)</ref> 1 . Consequently, in such case, this physical libration needs to be considered in the integration of the basic differential equation of the creep. In this way, we propose a new model for the classical theory, assuming that the shape of the tidally deformed body may be approximated by a triaxial ellipsoid, where its flattenings and orientation are unknown functions of the time (this idea is supported by the analytical solutions of the creep equation given in previous papers as paper I and II). Then, the creep equation allows us to find the differential equations that describe the time evolution of this ellipsoidal bulge and its orientation, resulting in a very simpler and compact approach.</p><p>The results are applied to Enceladus and Mimas. These satellites are selected for this study because of the amount of observational information available. We know from Cassini's observations the seconddegree components of the gravitational field ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Iess et al., 2014</ref>). We also know that the crust of Enceladus presents a forced libration of 0.120 ± 0.014 degrees ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thomas et al. 2016)</ref> and that a huge quantity of heat flows from the satellite <ref type="bibr">(5 − 16 GW cf Howett et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Spencer et al. 2013</ref>; Le <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Gall et al. 2017</ref>). In contrast, Mimas presents a larger forced libration of 0.838 ± 0.002 degrees ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tajeddine et al., 2014)</ref> and the absence of current tectonic activity is evidence of a small dissipation (smaller than 1 GW). In addition, in both cases the three radii of the best ellipsoid representing the satellite surface are known (see <ref type="bibr">Archinal et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The presence of the physical libration affects the dissipation increasing it but the increase is not so important as to affect the order of magnitude of the dissipation and certainly not so important as some preliminary results of this investigation seemed to indicate. The amount of dissipation observed by Cassini corresponds to a relaxation factor in the range γ = 1.2 − 3.8 × 10 −7 s −1 for Enceladus and γ ∼ 10 −9 s −1 for Mimas. The difference between these values is consistent with the fact that the gravitational acceleration at the surface and the density are both much larger in Enceladus than in Mimas. On the other hand, these values of relaxation factors indicate a viscosity η = 0.6 − 1.9 × 10 14 Pa s for Enceladus and η ∼ 10 16 Pa s for Mimas. This estimation for the Enceladus viscosity has the same order as the values recently estimated by Efroimsky (2018) (0.24 × 10 14 Pa s) and as the value adopted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Roberts and Nimmo (2008)</ref> for the viscosity of the ice shell (10 13 − 10 14 Pa s). It is also close to the reference viscosity of water at 255 K (10 15 Pa s) adopted by B˘ ehounková et al. <ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref> in their modeling of the melting events at origin of the south-pole activity on Enceladus. More recent research carried out byČadekbyˇbyČadek et al. <ref type="bibr">(2019)</ref> demonstrates that the viscosity of ice at the melting temperature is equal to or higher than 3 × 10 14 Pa s, for the ice shell to remain stable.</p><p>The forced libration obtained with the creep tide theory for homogeneous bodies, in the case of Enceladus, is 3.1 times smaller than the libration amplitude obtained from Cassini's observations. However, results close to the observation were obtained in a preliminary extension of the core-shell model developed by the authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Folonier, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Folonier et al., in preparation)</ref>, in which one liquid layer is assumed to exist between the crust and the core.</p><p>In the found range of values of γ, the contribution of the satellite tides to the variations of the semi-major axis and eccentricity of Enceladus are ˙ a = −(0.4 − 1.3) × 10 −5 km/yr and ˙ e = −(1.9 − 6.0) × 10 −9 yr −1 . The eccentricity variation is very small. Nonetheless, in the case of Enceladus, we need to consider the effects of the almost 2:1 resonance between Enceladus and Dione, that produces a forced eccentricity of 0.00459 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ferraz-Mello, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Vienne and Duriez, 1995)</ref>. In the case of Mimas, we have found that the variations of the semi-major axis and eccentricity are ˙ a ∼ −10 −6 km/yr and ˙ e ∼ −10 −10 yr −1 . In both cases, the variations found are much smaller than those due to the tides on the planet. This paper is organized as follows: We first proceed, in Sections 2 to 4, to a revisit of the creep tide theory proposing a new approach in which the differential equation for the tidal deformation of the primary, and for its rotation, are integrated simultaneously. Then, in Section 5, we study the case in which the rotation of the primary is nearly synchronous but not uniform showing a forced libration. In Section 6 and 7, we do an inventory of the main mechanical processes involving the storage of mechanical energy in the system and discuss the law ruling the dissipation in stiff satellites, with application to Enceladus. In Section 8, we extend the results to obtain the average variations of the metrical elements of the orbit: semi-major axis and eccentricity. In the final sections, we extend the results to Mimas and present the conclusions. The paper is completed by two appendices, where are given some technical details of the model used to evaluate the orbital energy (Appendix 1) and the analytical approximation of the spin-orbit quasi-synchronous attractor (Appendix 2). In addition, an Online Supplement is provided, where the classical creep tide approach is also extended to include the near-synchronous, but not uniform, rotation case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">The creep tide equations</head><p>Let us consider one system formed by the extended body m (primary) and the mass point M (companion) and let r be the radius-vector in a system of reference centered on m. We assume that the primary is a homogeneous body and have an angular velocity of rotation Ω, perpendicular to the orbital plane.</p><p>In the creep tide theory, the tidal deformation of m is obtained by solving the Newtonian creep law</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">˙ ζ = γ(ρ − ζ),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where γ is the relaxation factor (see paper I), ζ = ζ( ϕ, θ, t) is the distance of the surface point of coordinates ϕ (longitude) and θ (co-latitude) to the center of gravity of the body, and ρ = ρ( ϕ, θ, t) is the surface of the static figure of equilibrium of m under the gravitational attraction of M. ρ is approximated by a triaxial ellipsoid whose major axis is oriented towards M, and whose equatorial prolateness and polar oblateness are</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ǫ ρ = a − b R e = 15M R 3 e 4mr 3 ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">ǫ z = 1 − c R e = ǫ ρ 2 + 5Ω 2 R 3 e 4Gm ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where a, b, c are the semi-major axes of the triaxial ellipsoid, R e is the mean equatorial radius, G is the gravitational constant and Ω is the spin rate of m (see <ref type="bibr">Tisserand, 1891;</ref>). Its equation is 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ρ( θ, ϕ, t) = R 1 + 1 2 ǫ ρ sin 2 θ cos (2 ϕ − 2ϕ) + ǫ z 1 3 − cos 2 θ ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where ϕ is the true longitude of the companion in its equatorial orbit around the primary and R is the mean radius of the primary. The angles are such that the major axis of the ellipsoid is always oriented towards the companion (left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). The right-hand side is a time function depending on the longitude ϕ (such that d ϕ/dt = Ω(t)) and on the polar coordinates of the companion, r and ϕ. The radius vector of M, r, is introduced in the equation by the flattenings ǫ ρ and ǫ z .</p><p>In previous papers (papers I and II) the forced terms in the solution of Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref> were approximated by the sum of an arbitrary number of ellipsoidal bulges over one sphere of radius R (see papers I and II), where each bulge has different flattenings and orientation. To the first order in the flattenings, the sum of two or more ellipsoidal bulges can be expressed by a new ellipsoidal bulge with its flattenings and orientation (see <ref type="bibr">Appendix 3 of Folonier and Ferraz-Mello, 2017)</ref>. For this reason, ζ can be approximated by a homogeneous ellipsoid:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ζ( θ, ϕ, t) = R 1 + 1 2 E ρ sin 2 θ cos (2 ϕ − 2ϕ B ) + E z 1 3 − cos 2 θ ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where the instantaneous flattenings E ρ , E z and the orientation longitude of the bulge ϕ B = ϕ + δ are unknown functions of the time. Here, δ is the orientation angle of the bulge vertex with respect to M (right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> Equatorial sections of the ellipsoids ρ( θ, ϕ, t) and ζ( θ, ϕ, t) corresponding to the tide on m generated by M. Angles: ϕ and ϕ are the longitudes, in a fixed reference system, of the companion and of one point on the surface of the primary, respectively. δ is the orientation angle of the tidal bulge (labeled B) with respect to the companion.</p><p>In order to find the time evolution of these unknown functions, we differentiate (5) with respect to the time and replace the result into the creep equation (1). We obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">˙ E ρ + γE ρ cos 2δ + E ρ (2Ω − 2 ˙ ϕ − 2 ˙ δ) sin 2δ 1 2 R sin 2 θ cos (2 ϕ − 2ϕ) + −E ρ (2Ω − 2 ˙ ϕ − 2 ˙ δ) cos 2δ + ˙ E ρ + γE ρ sin 2δ 1 2 R sin 2 θ sin (2 ϕ − 2ϕ) +R ˙ E z + γE z 1 3 − cos 2 θ = 1 2 R sin 2 θγǫ ρ cos (2 ϕ − 2ϕ) + Rγǫ z 1 3 − cos 2 θ .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Since the flattenings E ρ , E z and the angle of orientation δ cannot depend on one specific point on the surface of m (that is θ, ϕ), we can decompose Eq. (6) into three equations, one for each trigonometric argument, which may be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">˙ δ = Ω − ˙ ϕ − γǫ ρ 2E ρ sin 2δ ˙ E ρ = γ ǫ ρ cos 2δ − E ρ˙ E z = γ ǫ z − E z .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>This system of differential equations of first order allows us to calculate the time evolution of the instantaneous flattenings and the instantaneous orientation angle, when the orbital motion of the companion (that is, r and ˙ ϕ) and the spin rate Ω are known. This new version of the creep equations is formally analogous to the one used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Correia et al. (2014)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boué et al. (2016)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Correia et al. (2018)</ref> and Beaugé (personal communication).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The disturbing potential</head><p>The disturbing potential created by the homogeneous triaxial ellipsoid m, the bulge of which is rotated of an angle ϕ B with respect to the axis x, at the companion M(r, θ = π/2, ϕ), neglecting the harmonics of degree higher than 2, is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">δU (r) = − G(B − A) 2r 3 3 cos 2 Ψ B − 1 − G(C − B) 2r 3 ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where G is the gravitational constant, Ψ B is the angle between the direction of the point where the potential is taken and the direction of the bulge vertex, labeled by B (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>), and A, B, C are the moments of inertia of the ellipsoid with respect to its principal axes (A &lt; B &lt; C).</p><p>The cosine can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">cos Ψ B = r · r B ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where r and r B are the unitary vectors oriented towards the companion and the bulge direction, respectively. The differences B −A and C −B, to the first order in the flattenings, can be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">B − A ≈ CE ρ ; C − B ≈ C E z − 1 2 E ρ .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>The moment of inertia with respect to the polar axis is C = m(a 2 +b 2 )/5 or, introducing the flattenings of the ellipsoid resulting from the integration of the creep differential equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">C = 2 5 mR 2 1 + 2 3 E z + O(E 2 ) .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Hence, using the definition of ǫ ρ , the resulting disturbing potential is</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">δU (r) = − 2Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25M R E ρ 2( r · r B ) 2 − 1 − 4Gm 2 ǫ ρ 75M R E z .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>It is important to emphasize that, since the beginning of this paper, we have used the same notation r to indicate the radius vector of the companion in all situations. We have thus broken with the tradition of using r * (or r ′ ) to indicate the radius vector of the companion in the equations used to calculate the tidal deformation of the primary <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kaula, 1964;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">MacDonald, 1964;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Efroimsky, 2012)</ref>. The dichotomy r, r * was introduced by Darwin for the only reason that, in the calculus of the force as the gradient of the potential U , the derivatives of the potential must be done with respect to the coordinates of the mass point where the force is applied. Thus, it was important to use a different notation for the radius vector and its components in the calculation of the flattenings, and to write the potential as a function U (r, r * ) making explicit which of the radii vectors was to be considered when the force is calculated. But, physically, there is only one radius vector being considered and, after the gradient calculation, r and r * are identified. As in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Correia et al. (2014)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Boué et al. (2016)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ragazzo and Ruiz (2017)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Correia et al. (2018)</ref>, in the approach proposed in this paper, the potential does not depend explicitly on both instances of the radius vector. The radius vector used in the calculation of the flattenings is substituted by the time functions E ρ and E z and the only radius vector r appearing in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> is the radius vector of the point where the force is being applied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">The tidal force and torque</head><p>To calculate the tidal force F acting on the mass M located in M, we take the negative gradient of the disturbing potential of m and multiply it by the mass placed in the point. Hence</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">F = −M ∇ r δU.<label>(13)</label></formula><p>The sign in this expression comes from the fact that we are using the conventions of Physics (δU is a potential not a force-function). It is important to stress that in agreement with Newton laws, there exists a reaction force −F acting on m due to the attraction of M (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ferraz-Mello et al. 2003</ref>). This fact is generally neglected in studies where one of the masses is negligible when compared to the other but its neglect in general problems is an error. Then, we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">F = − 2Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25Rr 2 E ρ 10( r · r B ) 2 r − 4r( r · r B ) r B − 3r − 4Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25Rr 2 E z r.<label>(14)</label></formula><p>The unitary vector r B can be decomposed in terms of the unitary vectors r and ( z × r), where r and z are the unitary vectors oriented towards M and along the z-axis, respectively:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">r B = cos δ r + sin δ ( z × r).<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Hence, the resulting tidal force acting on M can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">F = − 2Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25Rr 2 E ρ 3 cos 2δ r − 2 sin 2δ ( z × r) − 4Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25Rr 2 E z r.<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Finally, the tidal torque acting on M is M = r × F, or:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">M = 4Gm 2 ǫ ρ 25R E ρ sin 2δˆz2δˆ2δˆz.<label>(17)</label></formula><p>It is important to note that, in order to calculate the angular acceleration of the primary, we need to consider the reaction on the primary, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">−M = C ˙ Ω + ˙ CΩ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where the time variation of the axial moment of inertia is</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">˙ C ≈ 4 15 mR 2 ˙ E z .<label>(19)</label></formula><p>We note that, at this order of approximation, the equatorial tidal prolateness does not affect the moment of inertia (the deformations inward and outward compensate themselves). The scheme considered in this approach differs from the scheme used in papers I and II. Here, the equations of the instantaneous ellipsoidal bulge and its orientation may be integrated together with the rotational equation, while, in papers I and II, the shape of the primary is calculated assuming Ω as a known time function through the longitude ϕ = Ω(t − t 0 ). Once the shape has been determined, it is used to obtain the rotational evolution of the deformed body.</p><p>The model presented here allows us also to calculate the orbital evolution of the companion, as well as the evolution of the ellipsoidal bulge, its orientation and the rotational evolution of the primary. However, in general, the variation of the orbital elements is much slower and, for short time spans, we may assume a Keplerian motion for the companion. The instantaneous shape, orientation and rotation of the primary are then calculated using Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> and the classical two-body expressions for r and ˙ ϕ. 5 Solution in the neighborhood of the synchronous rotation.</p><p>In the neighborhood of the synchronization, the rotation of close-in satellites and exoplanets is generally damped towards a final stable state which depends on the nature of the body. The rotation of gaseous planets, of fast relaxation (high γ, low viscosity), tends to a stationary rotation slightly faster than the orbital motion (a.k.a. supersynchronous motion). The excess of angular velocity is ∼ 6ne 2 (see paper I). On the other end, the rotation of planetary satellites and Earth-like planets, of slow relaxation (low γ, high viscosity), is damped to attractors with the same period as the orbital period and the final rotations are not uniform. They are forced oscillations (physical librations) around one center. In this case, the solution of the creep equation can no longer be calculated as in papers I and II. The use of the uniform approximation for Ω is no longer appropriate because the rotation is, in this case, affected by a significant short-period oscillation <ref type="bibr">3</ref> . It is important to emphasize that in the approach adopted in this paper, no hypotheses on the rotation behavior are necessary since all equations are integrated simultaneously. The synchronous attractor may be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">ν def = 2(Ω − n) ∼ = B 0 + B 1 cos ℓ + B 2 sin ℓ,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where ℓ is the mean anomaly of the companion; the mean value B 0 and the amplitudes B 1 , B 2 are constants (for the details of the calculation of the synchronous attractor, see Appendix 2).</p><p>In the case of Enceladus, the numerical solution of the exact equations for low values of γ is an almost symmetric oscillation of ν. The semi-amplitude of this oscillation depends on the adopted relaxation factor (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>). If γ &lt; 10 −5 s −1 , the forced oscillation amplitude is 0.36 deg/d. This value may be compared to the observed values (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). Measurements of control points on the surface of Enceladus accumulated over seven years of Cassini's observations allowed <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thomas et al. (2016)</ref> to determine the satellite's rotation state. They have found a libration of 0.120 ± 0.014 degrees. If we assume that these oscillations follow a harmonic law we obtain, correspondingly, for the oscillation of the velocity of rotation: 0.56 ± 0.06 deg/day, and for the semi-diurnal frequency 1.12 ± 0.12 deg/day. The immediate conclusion from the comparison of these values is that it is not possible to reproduce exactly the observed forced libration of Enceladus with a homogeneous body model. The predicted oscillation is smaller. However, results close to the observation were obtained in a preliminary extension of the core-shell model developed by the authors, when one liquid layer is assumed to exist between the crust and the core <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Folonier, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Folonier et al., in preparation)</ref>.</p><p>For the sake of comparison, we may note that viscoelastic models adopting a permanent triaxiality give a result yet smaller: 0.03 deg depending on the adopted triaxiality ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Rambaux et al., 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">The energy balance</head><p>In this section, we examine the various manifestations of the mechanical energy in a system formed by two mutually attracting bodies: the extended body m and one mass point M. Let their masses be respectively, m and M . We consider only the case where M lies on the equatorial plane of m. Our aim is to evaluate the amount of the energy dissipated by the body 4 .</p><p>Let us first review some known facts of a system formed by the extended body m and the mass point M (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Scheeres, 2002</ref>). Let r, V be the radius-vector and the velocity of M in a system of reference centered on m. The kinetic energy referred to the center of gravity of the system formed by the two bodies and the rotational energy of M are</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">E kin = 1 2 M m M + m V 2 ; E rot = 1 2 CΩ 2 ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>the time-dependent gravitational potential generated by the primary in the point r is</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">M U r; t = − GM m r − 2Gm 2 25R ǫ ρ E ρ cos 2ϕ − 2ϕ B − 2 3 ǫ ρ E z ,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>and E int is the internal gravitational energy of the primary. Using the explicit formulas given by Essén (2004) (see Appendix 1), we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">E int = − 3Gm 2 5R 1 − 1 15 E 2 ρ − 4 45 E 2 z .<label>(23)</label></formula><p>The time derivatives of the energies are</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">˙ E kin = M m M + m V · ˙ V = f · V; ˙ E rot = −M · Ω − 1 2 ˙ CΩ 2<label>(24)</label></formula><p>(since in Newton's law the acceleration must be referred to the barycenter, that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">f = Mm M+m ˙ V) M ˙ U = M grad r U · V + M ∂U ∂t = −f · V + M ∂δU ∂ϕ B ˙ ϕ B + M ∂δU ∂E ρ ˙ E ρ + M ∂δU ∂E z ˙ E z ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">˙ E int = ∂E int ∂E ρ ˙ E ρ + ∂E int ∂E z ˙ E z .<label>(26)</label></formula><p>Hence,</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">˙ E tot = ˙ E kin + M ˙ U + ˙ E int + ˙ E rot ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>or</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">˙ E tot = M ∂δU ∂ϕ B ˙ ϕ B + M ∂δU ∂E ρ ˙ E ρ + M ∂δU ∂E z ˙ E z + ∂E int ∂E ρ ˙ E ρ + ∂E int ∂E z ˙ E z + ˙ E rot ,<label>(28)</label></formula><p>that is, the energy variation associated with the power f · V is exchanged with the kinetic energy and cannot account for the dissipation of the system energy (see Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(24)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(25)</ref>). This is a well-known fact in the study of the motion of satellites around non-spherical rigid bodies 5 . Using Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref>, the time derivative of the total mechanical energy can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">˙ E tot = − 6 5 Gm 2 γR 1 15 ˙ E 2 ρ + 1 15 E 2 ρ 2Ω − 2 ˙ ϕ − 2 ˙ δ 2 + 4 45 ˙ E 2 z ≤ 0.<label>(29)</label></formula><p>The time derivative of the total mechanical energy is always negative. Finally, the orbital energy is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E orb = E kin + M U r; t ,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>and, using Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(24)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(25)</ref>, the time derivative of the orbital energy is</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">˙ E orb = ˙ E kin + M ˙ U r; t ,<label>(31)</label></formula><p>This definition of the orbital energy variation is the same as adopted by Correia et al (2014).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Dissipation</head><p>The actual variation of the main components of the mechanical energy is shown in the left panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.  3</ref>. It is large, indicating a great periodic energy exchange between the rotational energy (labeled rot ) and the sum of the orbital energy and the internal gravitational energy (labeled sum). The amplitudes of variation of the orbital and rotational energies have the same order of magnitude and the variation of the total energy (labeled tot in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>), shows only a very small variation (of the order of one part in 10 5 of the variation of the two components). This very small periodic variation of the time derivative of the total mechanical energy is always negative (right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>).</p><p>In the long run, the only sources for the energy dissipated by the tides are the orbital and the rotational energies. The usual operation to get rid of periodic variations is the averaging of the total mechanical energy. The canonical tool to separate conservative and dissipative terms is the analysis of the differential form expressing the variation of the orbital energy. However, in the adopted model, only the attraction of the external body M by the deformed body m is available. The dynamics of the action of M creating the deformation in m is concealed by the creep equation used to determine the shape of m. The averaging to zero of the periodic variations may be considered as the equivalent of the zero variation of the energy on a closed path characteristic of the conservative phenomena.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Analytical approximation</head><p>The variable characterizing the variation in a short time interval is the mean anomaly ℓ and the averaging operation is just 1 2π 2π 0 ˙ E tot dℓ. In the case of Enceladus, the result is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>. We note that the resulting ˙ E tot = ˙ E orb + ˙ E rot + ˙ E int (black solid line) is negative, hence, the system is losing mechanical energy, as expected. Using the analytical solution detailed in Appendix 2, the time average of the total mechanical energy (given by Eq. 29), for the synchronous attractor, can be approximated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">˙ E tot sync = − 21GM mR 2 ǫ ρ e 2 5a 3 n 2 γ n 2 + γ 2 ,<label>(32)</label></formula><p>to the first order in the flattenings. For sake of completeness, it is worth repeating some properties of this result: (1) the result is always negative (energy is lost); (2) the variation of the dissipation with the relaxation factor has the inverted V-shape, characteristic of the Maxwell rheology; (3) in the neighborhood of the stationary solution, the quantity defined by Eq. (32) is of the order O(e 2 ).  8 Semi-major axis and eccentricity average perturbations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Semi-major axis</head><p>The variation of the osculating semi-major axis due to the tides raised on m may be obtained using the corresponding Lagrange variational equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">˙ a = 2 na ∂R ∂ℓ ,<label>(33)</label></formula><p>where the disturbing function is R = −(1 + M/m)δU (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brouwer and Clemence, 1961</ref>, Chap. XI).</p><p>The minus sign is included because δU is a potential (not a force-function) and the factor (1 + M/m) is introduced to account for the fact that the disturbing force is not of external origin but an interaction between the two bodies. We thus consider the force per unit mass acting on one body minus its reaction on the other body (see discussion in Ferraz-Mello et al. 2008, Section 18). Hence, considering the third Kepler law (n 2 a 3 = G(M + m)) and comparing to the work calculated above,</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">˙ a = 2a 2 GmM ˙ E orb .<label>(34)</label></formula><p>This is the same equation obtained when taking the time derivatives of both sides of the two-body classical equation relating the orbital energy and the osculating semi-major axis, E orb = −GmM/2a (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brouwer and Clemence, 1961)</ref>, which has been used in previous papers (see paper I). It shows that ˙ E orb is equal to the time derivative of the Keplerian orbital energy of the system. The variation of the semi-major axis due to the tidal deformations of the primary is given by Eq. It is important to emphasize that this is not the actual rate of change of the semi-major axis. This is only the part of it due to the tides on the satellite. To obtain the actual rate of change of a, it is necessary to consider also the part of it due to the tides raised on the planet, which is given by the same equations but where the variables are interchanged to express the dissipation on the planet instead of the satellite. In the case of Enceladus, the two effects appear to have similar orders of magnitude; according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lainey et al. (2012)</ref>, the variation of the semi-major axis due to the tides raised by Enceladus on Saturn is 4.2 × 10 −5 km/yr. The variation of the semi-major axis of Saturnian satellites is important for some theories of the formation of these satellites (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lainey et al. 2012</ref>). The orbital variations due to the tides raised on the planet are more important than the variations due to the tides raised on the satellite and correspond to a present expansion of the satellite's orbit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2">Eccentricity</head><p>The variation of the eccentricity is given by the corresponding Lagrange variational equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">˙ e = − √ 1 − e 2 na 2 e ∂R ∂ω + 1 − e 2 na 2 e ∂R ∂ℓ ,<label>(35)</label></formula><p>(see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Brouwer and Clemence, 1961)</ref>. This equation is equivalent to where L = GMm na √ 1 − e 2 is the orbital angular momentum. In order to use the averages given in the previous sections, we may introduce a change in this equation reminding that ˙</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">˙ e = 1 − e 2 e ˙ a 2a − ˙ L L ,<label>(36)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">γ [1/s]</formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">L = M z = − ˙ E rot /Ω. Hence ˙ e = 1 − e 2 e ˙ a 2a + 1 L ˙ E rot Ω .<label>(37)</label></formula><p>The variation of the averaged de/dt as a function of the relaxation factor γ is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5  (Right )</ref>. When γ = 1.2 − 3.8 × 10 −7 s −1 , the averages are very small (less than 10 −10 yr −1 ). In general, the eccentricity variation may become important in long-term studies but, in the case of Enceladus, the effects of the almost 2:1 resonance between Enceladus and Dione produces a forced eccentricity of 0.00459 that must be considered (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ferraz-Mello, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Vienne and Duriez, 1995)</ref>. We remind that the proper eccentricity of Enceladus is only 0.00012.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3">Analytical approximations</head><p>Proceeding similarly to the previous section, the average of the variation of the osculating semi-major axis due to the tide in the primary can be approximated, in the neighborhood of the synchronous rotation, as</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">˙ a sync = 2a 2 GM m ˙ E tot sync = − 42R 2 ǫ ρ e 2 5a n 2 γ n 2 + γ 2 ,<label>(38)</label></formula><p>and the approximation of the average of the variation of the osculating eccentricity, in the neighborhood of the synchronous rotation, is</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">˙ e sync = 1 − e 2 2ae ˙ a sync = − 21R 2 ǫ ρ e(1 − e 2 ) 5a 2 n 2 γ n 2 + γ 2 .<label>(39)</label></formula><p>In both cases, the averages vanish when e → 0. We may easily see that, when the quasi-synchronous rotation is assumed, both da/dt as de/dt become proportional to ˙ E tot sync .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Extension to Mimas</head><p>One challenge to every theory for the dissipation of the Enceladus is that it shall work also for the neighbor Mimas. Mainly, it must be coherent with the absence of tectonic activity in Mimas, evidence of a much smaller dissipation. The results obtained with the theory developed in this paper are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6</ref>.   The first result concerns the physical libration. Measurements of control points on the surface of Mimas accumulated over seven years of Cassini's observations allowed <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tajeddine et al. (2014)</ref> to determine the satellite's rotation state. They found several libration components including one shortperiod oscillation of 50.3 ± 1 arcmin. If we assume that these oscillations follow a harmonic law, we obtain, correspondingly, for the oscillation of the velocity of rotation: 5.6 ± 0.1 deg/day, and for the semi-diurnal frequency 11.2 ± 0.2 deg/day (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Tables 1 and 2</ref>). The comparison of these results to those shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6 (left)</ref> is that, like in the case of Enceladus, the observed value is larger than the tidal forced libration of Mimas (1.45 times) predicted by using a homogeneous body model. It is worth mentioning that this factor is not very different from the one obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tajeddine et al. (2014)</ref> using models founded on the observed quadrupole moments of the gravitational potential of Mimas. In that case the relationship between the observed and the calculated amplitudes is 1.93 instead of 1.45 (compare with the 3.1 factor obtained in the case of Enceladus).  The absence of current tectonic activity in Mimas is evidence of a small dissipation. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6 (right)</ref> shows that a small dissipation indicates that the relaxation factor γ of Mimas is much smaller than that of Enceladus. Let us consider it as γ ∼ 10 −9 s −1 , that corresponds a dissipation smaller than 1 GW. The difference with the value found for Enceladus is surprising but it is consistent with the fact that  the gravitational acceleration at the surface and the density are both much larger in Enceladus than in Mimas. Thus, the viscosity corresponding to the considered γ is ∼ 10 16 Pa s, which is a reasonable value.</p><p>For the sake of completeness, we may add the results on the contribution of the satellite tides to the orbital evolution of Mimas. With the relaxation factor considered above, we obtain ˙ a sat ∼ −10 −6 km/yr and ˙ e sat ∼ −10 −10 yr −1 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig. 7)</ref>. These variations are much smaller than those due to the tides on the planet. Anyway, the current eccentricity of Mimas cannot be explained by tidal effects alone and is rather related to the crossing of mean-motion resonances in the past evolution of the satellite <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Meyer and Wisdom, 2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10">Conclusions</head><p>In this paper we propose an improved approach of the original creep tide theory. Supported by the analytical solutions given in the previous papers (papers I and II), we assume that the tidally deformed body has a triaxial ellipsoidal shape, where the flattenings and orientation are unknown functions of the time to be determined. The creep tide equation allows us to find the differential equations that describe the time evolution of this ellipsoidal bulge and its orientation, resulting in a very simpler and compact approach.</p><p>The other main result of the present investigation is the dissipation law and its application to quasisynchronous homogeneous bodies discussed in sections 6 and 7. It is important to stress that the only hypothesis done in the theory is that the surface of the body permanently adjust itself to an equilibrium surface with speed given by the Newtonian creep law. No constitutive equation linking strain and stress is introduced at any point in the creep tide theory. All developments to reach the conclusion are the solution of the creep differential equation and the use of classical Physics to compute the force and torque acting on the external body due to the tidal deformation of the considered extended body. The observed dissipation law results directly from the above described first principles of Physics, with approximations but no additional ad-hoc hypotheses.</p><p>In the case of Enceladus, used in this paper as example of application, the estimations of the heat dissipated in the SPT (south polar terrain) area based on the observations with Cassini are in the range 5 − 16 GW (cf <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Howett et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Spencer et al. 2013</ref>; Le <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Gall et al. 2017</ref>). In addition, a recent study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Kamata and Nimmo (2017)</ref> showed that a value about ten times higher than the old estimate of 1.1 GW is necessary if the ice shell is in thermal equilibrium. The given values correspond, using the creep tide theory, to a relaxation factor γ = 1.2 − 3.8 × 10 −7 s −1 . The viscosity corresponding to this relaxation factor is 0.6 − 1.9 × 10 14 Pa s. It is of the same order as the value recently estimated by Efroimsky (2018) (0.24 × 10 14 Pa s) and as the value adopted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Roberts and Nimmo (2008)</ref> for the viscosity of the ice shell (10 13 − 10 14 Pa s). This value is also close to the reference viscosity of water at 255 K (10 15 Pa s) adopted by B˘ ehounková et al. <ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref> in their modeling of the melting events at origin of the south-pole activity on Enceladus. More recent research carried out byČadekbyˇbyČadek et al. <ref type="bibr">(2019)</ref> demonstrates that the viscosity of ice at the melting temperature is equal to or higher than 3 × 10 14 Pa s, for the ice shell to remain stable.</p><p>For this range of values of γ, we can calculate the variation of the semi-major axis ˙ a = −(0.4 − 1.3) × 10 −5 km/yr. For the variation of the eccentricity, we obtained a very small value ˙ e = −(1.9 − 6.0) × 10 −9 yr −1 . However, in the case of Enceladus, the effects of the almost 2:1 resonance between Enceladus and Dione produces a forced eccentricity of 0.00459 that must be considered (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ferraz- Mello, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Vienne and Duriez, 1995)</ref>.</p><p>In contrast with Enceladus, the absence of current tectonic activity in Mimas is evidence of a small dissipation. A dissipation ∼ 1 GW, corresponds to a relaxation factor γ ∼ 10 −9 s −1 and a viscosity η ∼ 10 16 Pa s, which are reasonable values. The difference with the values found for Enceladus is consistent with the fact that the gravitational acceleration at the surface and the density are both much larger in Enceladus than in Mimas. The different dissipations of Enceladus and Mimas may be simply associated with the fact that the outer layers of Enceladus have low viscosity (ice near the melting point) while Mimas, with no tectonic activity due to internal heating has a viscosity at least one order of magnitude larger (ice at temperatures well below the melting point).</p><p>Rough models of heat conduction considering the known conductivity of the ice at low temperatures show that the crust ability to convey heat produced in the interior is of some 10 −2 W/m 2 and can be larger or smaller than the values discussed in this paper, depending on the ice crust width and properties. The temperature measurements of the surface of Enceladus ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Spencer et al., 2006)</ref> show that most of the internally produced heat is flowing through the faults existing in the SPT and this confirms the inability of the existing crust ice to fully convey the produced heat. This behavior is a clue for a non-stationary process in which an increase in temperature means a decrease in the viscosity and a larger dissipation. In Enceladus, such a process may have been triggered by some transitory event enhancing the eccentricity of Enceladus and may have been progressing slowly, subsisting even after the eccentricity was damped to its current value. The transient increase of the eccentricity may have happened at any moment because of the small distance separating the inner satellites of Saturn (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Nakajima et al, 2018</ref>).</p><p>Finally, measurements of control points on the surface of the satellites accumulated over seven years of Cassini's observations allowed <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Thomas et al. (2016)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Tajeddine et al. (2014)</ref> to determine their rotation state. They had found a libration of 0.120 ± 0.014 degrees for Enceladus and 50.3 ± 1 arcmin for Mimas. Assuming that these oscillations follow a harmonic law, we obtain, correspondingly, for the oscillation of the semi-diurnal frequency 1.12 ± 0.12 deg/day for Enceladus and 11.2 ± 0.2 deg/day for Mimas. These observed values are larger than the tidal forced libration predicted by using a homogeneous body model (0.36 deg/day and 7.7 deg/day for Enceladus and Mimas, respectively). These disagreements between theory and observations are mainly due to the assumed homogeneity of the satellites. Indeed, the Enceladus libration can be obtained using a multi-layered model <ref type="bibr">(Folonier et al., in preparation)</ref>, in which one liquid layer is assumed to exist between the crust and the core. All these results are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p><p>The gravitational energy of an ellipsoid of mass m and semi-axes a &gt; b &gt; c is explicitly given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Essén, 2004</ref>) where the Taylor expansion of X around ξ = 1, τ = 0 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">E int = − 3 5 Gm 2 R X(ξ, τ ),<label>(40)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">X(ξ, τ ) = 1 − 4 5 (ξ − 1) 2 − 4 15 τ 2 + · · · ,<label>(41)</label></formula><p>and ξ, τ are functions of the flattening such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">a = (ξ + τ )R; b = (ξ − τ )R; c = (ξ 2 − τ 2 ) −1 R.<label>(42)</label></formula><p>Hence, to the first-order,</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">τ = 1 2 E ρ ; ξ − 1 = 1 3 E z ,<label>(43)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">E int = − 3 5 Gm 2 R 1 − 1 15 E 2 ρ − 4 45 E 2 z .<label>(44)</label></formula><p>The variation of the binding energy then is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">˙ E int = 3 5 Gm 2 R 2 15 E ρ ˙ E ρ + 8 45 E z ˙ E z .<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(44)</ref> agrees with the result of the direct integration showing that the difference between the binding gravitational energy of an ellipsoid and that of the corresponding sphere is of the order of the square of the flattenings E ρ , E z . It is worth mentioning that the alternative formulation due to <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Neutsch (1979)</ref>, does not agree neither with the results of Essén <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2004)</ref> nor with the results of a direct integration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 2: Near-synchronous analytical approximation</head><p>In order to find an analytical approximation to the instantaneous flattenings E ρ , E z , the rotation angle δ and the semi-diurnal frequency ν = 2Ω − 2n in the quasi-synchronous attractor, let us first consider a Keplerian motion for the companion M. Then, we consider the approximations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">a r 3 ≈ 1 + 3e 2 2 + 3e cos ℓ n − ˙ ϕ ≈ −2ne cos ℓ.<label>(46)</label></formula><p>Since, the rotation is quasi-synchronous, we may assume δ ≪ 1. Hence</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">cos 2δ ≈ 1 − 2δ 2 ; sin 2δ ≈ 2δ.<label>(47)</label></formula><p>Introducing these approximations into the creep tide and torque equations, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> (using that ν = 2Ω − 2n, and ˙ ν = 2 ˙ Ω) and neglecting the term ˙ CΩ, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">˙ ν = −6κn 2 1 + 3e 2 2 + 3e cos ℓ E ρ δ ˙ δ = ν 2 − 2ne cos ℓ − γǫ ρ E ρ 1 + 3e 2 2 + 3e cos ℓ δ ˙ E ρ = γǫ ρ 1 + 3e 2 2 + 3e cos ℓ (1 − 2δ 2 ) − γE ρ ˙ E z = γǫ ρ 2 1 + 3e 2 2 + 3e cos ℓ + γǫ z Ω 2 n 2 − γE z ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>where κ = M/(M + m), and</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">ǫ ρ = 15M R 3 e 4ma 3 ; ǫ z = 5n 2 R 3 e 4Gm .<label>(49)</label></formula><p>It is important to note that both ǫ ρ as ǫ z are constants. Let us assume the particular solution</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">ν = B 0 + B 1 cos ℓ + B 2 sin ℓ δ = D 0 + D 1 cos ℓ + D 2 sin ℓ E ρ = E 0 + E 1 cos ℓ + E 2 sin ℓ E z = Z 0 + Z 1 cos ℓ + Z 2 sin ℓ,<label>(50)</label></formula><p>the derivatives of which are</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">˙ ν = −nB 1 sin ℓ + nB 2 cos ℓ ˙ δ = −nD 1 sin ℓ + nD 2 cos ℓ ˙ E ρ = −nE 1 sin ℓ + nE 2 cos ℓ ˙ E z = −nZ 1 sin ℓ + nZ 2 cos ℓ.<label>(51)</label></formula><p>Finally, replacing (50) and (51) into the system (48), collecting the terms with same trigonometric argument and neglecting terms of higher order, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">B 0 = 12ne 2 1 + p 2 1 + αp 2 1 + α 2 p 2 D 0 = 3pe 2 1 + p 2 2 + (1 + α)p 2 1 + α 2 p 2 E 0 = ǫ ρ 1 + 3e 2 2 − 4p 2 e 2 1 + α 2 p 2 Z 0 = ǫ ρ 2 1 + 3e 2 2 + ǫ z 1 + 12e 2 1 + p 2 1 + αp 2 1 + α 2 p 2 + 2(1 − α) 2 p 2 e 2 1 + α 2 p 2 ,<label>(52)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">B 1 B 2 = 12κǫ ρ npe 1 + α 2 p 2 −αp 1 D 1 D 2 = − 2pe 1 + α 2 p 2 1 αp E 1 E 2 = 3ǫ ρ e 1 + p 2 1 p Z 1 Z 2 = 1.5ǫ ρ e 1 + p 2 1 − 16κp 2 ǫz 1+α 2 p 2 p + 8κp(1−αp 2 )ǫz 1+α 2 p 2 ,<label>(53)</label></formula><p>where α = 1 − 3κǫ ρ and p = n/γ. We mention that the mean values B 0 , D 0 , E 0 , Z 0 are given to the second order in eccentricity while the amplitudes B i , D i , E i , Z i (i = 0) are given to the first order in eccentricity. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 8</ref> shows the comparison of the near-synchronous attractors as given by the complete nonlinear system defined by Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> and the approximate analytical solution given above in the case of one body like Enceladus, in function of the viscosity η. The dashed red lines show the maximum, minimum and mean values of ν, δ, E ρ and E z (from top left to bottom right ) given by the approximate solution, while the solid black lines show the maximum, minimum and the mean values of ν, δ, E ρ and E z when the complete non-linear system is integrated. The approximate solution is in excellent agreement with numerical integration of the equations.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_54">δζ rad = − 1 3 R k∈Z C ′′ k cos σ ′′ k cos(kℓ − σ ′′ k )</formula><p>are missing. (N.B. They are torqueless and conservative and do not affect the results. </p><formula xml:id="formula_55">˙ e = − 3GM R 2 e ǫ ρ 10na 5 e k∈Z E 2,k cos σ k j∈Z 2 1 − e 2 − (2 − k − j)(1 − e 2 ) E 2,k+j sin(jℓ + σ k ) − GM R 2 e 10na 5 e k∈Z (ǫ ρ E 0,k + 2δ 0,k ǫ z )(1 − e 2 ) cos σ ′′ k j∈Z (k + j)E 0,k+j sin(jℓ + σ ′′ k ).</formula><p>8. Mistakes in Eq. (71). The correct equation is</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">˙ e = − 3GM R 2 e ǫ ρ 20na 5 e k∈Z 2 1 − e 2 − (2 − k)(1 − e 2 ) E 2 2,k sin 2σ k − GM R 2 e ǫ ρ 20na 5 e k∈Z (1 − e 2 )kE 2 0,k sin 2σ ′′ k .</formula><p>9. Mistake in Eq. (B.6) (Online Supplement). The sign in front of 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">√ 1 − e 2 E (5)</formula><p>2,k should be changed to −.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The creep equation, in the original version of the creep tide theory (Ferraz-Mello 2013 a.k.a. paper I), was solved assuming that, for short time spans, the rotation of the primary body may be considered as uniform. One of the consequences of the theory was to show that, in near-synchronous motions, the tide creates a short-period non-uniformity in the rotation of the primary, the physical libration (Ferraz-Mello 2015 a.k.a.paper II). Far from the spin-orbit synchronization, the physical libration is just a minor perturbation of the motion and the uniform rotation may be considered as a good approximation. However, in near-synchronous rotations, this is no longer the case and in order to have a self-consistent theory, it is necessary to consider ab initio the physical libration of the primary. This is done in this supplement 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">The creep tide equation</head><p>Let us consider one system formed by the extended body m (primary) and the mass point M (companion) and let r be the radius-vector of the companion in a system of reference centered in the primary. Since Darwin (1880), the problem of the tidal interaction of the two bodies is split into two parts: First, we consider the deformation of the primary due to an external body (M*) -the body called Diana by Darwin. Then, we consider the disturbing potential due to this deformation on the companion, a mass point (M) placed at a generic point of coordinates (r, ϕ, θ). Eventually, we identify M and M*. The result is that the companion M is moving in a time-dependent potential field</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">U (r, r * ),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>generated by m in the point r. The vector r * is the radius vector of Diana. Even if M and Diana are physically the same body, the formulation should remain valid even if they were different bodies. Thus, the force acting on M due to the attraction of m is</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">f = −M grad r U (r, r * ), (2)</formula><p>where we included the subscript r to make clear that the derivatives in the evaluation of the gradient are done exclusively with respect to r.</p><p>In the creep tide, the first half of Darwin's model -the tidal deformation of m -is obtained by solving the Newtonian creep law</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">˙ ζ = γ(ρ − ζ), (3)</formula><p>where γ is the relaxation factor (see paper I), ζ = ζ( ϕ, θ, t) is the distance of the surface point of coordinates ϕ (longitude) and θ (co-latitude) to the center of gravity of the body, and ρ = ρ( ϕ, θ, t) is the surface of the static figure of equilibrium of m under the gravitational attraction of M. ρ is approximated by a triaxial ellipsoid whose major axis is oriented towards M</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">ρ = R e 1 + 1 2 ǫ ρ sin 2 θ cos(2 ϕ − 2ω * − 2v * ) − ǫ z cos 2 θ ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>(see <ref type="bibr">Tisserand, 1891;</ref>) where ω * + v * is the true longitude of Diana in its equatorial orbit around the primary (ω * is the argument of the pericenter and v * is the true anomaly) and ǫ ρ and ǫ z are the equatorial prolateness and polar oblateness, respectively. The angles are such that the major axis of the ellipsoid is always oriented towards Diana. The right-hand side is a known time function depending on the longitude ϕ and on the polar coordinates of the companion, r * and v * . The radius vector of Diana, r * , is introduced in the equation by the flattenings ǫ ρ and ǫ z .</p><p>If the Keplerian expansions of r * and v * are introduced (see papers I and II), the above equation becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">ρ = R + R k∈Z C k sin 2 θ cos Θ k + C ′′ k cos 2 θ − 1 3 cos Θ ′′ k ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">C k = 1 2 ǫ ρ E 2,k C ′′ k = − 1 2 ǫ ρ E 0,k − δ 0,k ǫ z ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">Θ k = 2 ϕ + (k − 2)ℓ * − 2ω * Θ ′′ k = kℓ * . (7)</formula><p>R is the mean radius of the primary (constant), ℓ * is the mean anomaly,</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">ǫ ρ = 15 4 M m R e a 3 ; ǫ z = ǫ z − 1 2 ǫ ρ ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>δ 0,k is the Kronecker delta function and E p,q (e) are the Cayley coefficients. Eqn. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref> is then a non-homogeneous ordinary differential equation of first order with constant coefficients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Integration. The free rotating case</head><p>When the body is in free rotation (not trapped into a spin-orbit resonance), the angles Θ k , Θ ′′ k are linear functions of the time and, after integration, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">ζ = Ce −γt + R + δζ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where C = C( ϕ, θ) is an integration constant. The forced terms arising from the non-homogeneous part of the differential equation are 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">δζ = R k∈Z C k sin 2 θ cos σ k cos(Θ k − σ k ) + C ′′ k cos 2 θ − 1 3 cos σ ′′ k cos(Θ ′′ k − σ ′′ k ) ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">tan σ k = ˙ Θ k γ ; cos σ k = γ ˙ Θ 2 k + γ 2 ; sin σ k = ˙ Θ k ˙ Θ 2 k + γ 2 ; tan σ ′′ k = ˙ Θ ′′ k γ ; cos σ ′′ k = γ ˙ Θ ′′2 k + γ 2 ; sin σ ′′ k = ˙ Θ ′′ k ˙ Θ ′′2 k + γ 2 .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>2.2 Integration. The spin-orbit or synchronous resonance.</p><p>The synchronous attractor is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">ν def = 2(Ω − n) = B 0 + A cos(ℓ * + ℓ 1 ),<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where the mean value B 0 , the amplitude A and the phase ℓ 1 are constants. In this case, the longitude of the the generic point on the surface of the primary is</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">ϕ = ϕ F + t 0 Ωdt, that is ϕ = ϕ F + nt + 1 2 B 0 t + δϕ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where ϕ F is a constant and</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">δϕ = A 2n sin(ℓ * + ℓ 1 ),<label>(14)</label></formula><p>is the periodic component in the variation of Ω. Therefore,</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">Θ k = 2ϕ F + 2nt + B 0 t + 2δϕ + (k − 2)ℓ * − 2ω * ,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>and, expanding cos Θ k in the powers of δφ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">cos Θ k = cos Θ k − 2δϕ sin Θ k + · · · ,<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">Θ k = 2ϕ F + B 0 t + kℓ * − 2ω * .<label>(17)</label></formula><p>If the definition of A is considered, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">cos Θ k = cos Θ k − A n sin(ℓ * + ℓ 1 ) sin Θ k + · · · ,<label>(18)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">or cos Θ k = cos Θ k − A 2n cos(Θ k−1 − ℓ 1 ) + A 2n cos(Θ k+1 + ℓ 1 ) + · · · .<label>(19)</label></formula><p>2 The term</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">δζ rad = − 1 3 R k∈Z C ′′ k cos σ ′′ k cos(kℓ − σ ′′ k ),</formula><p>was discarded, in paper II, on the grounds of a heuristic reason: Radial terms in δζ were considered as artifacts resulting from the model, since the volume of the body must remain unchanged. Besides, the contribution of radial terms is torqueless and conservative. However, these terms correct the non-conservation of the volume introduced by the zonal terms in the equation for ζ and, for the sake of completeness, they must be kept in the expression of δζ.</p><p>Thus, the original term in cos Θ k is decomposed into several terms whose arguments are linear functions of t and the creep differential equation can be integrated following the same simple rules as before.</p><p>The forced terms then become</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">δζ res = R k∈Z C k sin 2 θ cos σ k cos(Θ k − σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k−1 cos(Θ k−1 − ℓ 1 − σ k−1 ) − cos σ k+1 cos(Θ k+1 + ℓ 1 − σ k+1 ) + R k∈Z C ′′ k cos 2 θ − 1 3 cos σ ′′ k cos(Θ ′′ k − σ ′′ k ),<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">tan σ k = ˙ Θ k γ = B 0 + kn γ .<label>(21)</label></formula><p>3 The disturbing potential δU (r, r * )</p><p>As in previous papers (papers I and II), the tidally deformed shape of the primary is composed of a series of added ellipsoidal bulges and the corrections to the potential due to the tidal forces in one point of space whose spherical coordinates are r, ϕ, θ may be easily calculated. The resulting disturbing potential is</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">δU = − GC 2r 3 k∈Z 3C k sin 2 θ cos σ k cos(2ϕ + (k − 2)ℓ * − 2ω * − 2δϕ − σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k−1 cos(2ϕ + (k − 3)ℓ * − 2ω * − ℓ 1 − 2δϕ − σ k−1 ) − cos σ k+1 cos(2ϕ + (k − 1)ℓ * − 2ω * + ℓ 1 − 2δϕ − σ k+1 ) +C ′′ k cos σ ′′ k (3 cos 2 θ − 1) cos(kℓ * − σ ′′ k ) ,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where ℓ * , ω * and e are, respectively, the mean anomaly, the argument of the pericenter and the eccentricity of the body source of the tidal potential: M* (i.e. Diana) (to stress the origin of ℓ * , we marked this anomaly with one star), and G is the gravitational constant. The above equation corresponds to the case where the rotation is following the near synchronous attractor; in the more usual case where the primary has a free rotation, the equation is similar and can be obtained by just making B 0 = A = 0 in the above equation.</p><p>We notice that the first terms of Eqn. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(22)</ref> are associated with sectorial components of the tidal displacement while the last term is associated with zonal terms (terms independent of the longitudes). We emphasize that the correction due to the neglected radial term in the solution of the creep equation in paper II (see footnote 2) is considered in Eqn. (22) using the mean radius R instead of the mean equatorial radius R e . The corresponding correction in the energy is of second order in the flattening.</p><p>The variable elements in δU are r, ϕ, θ and ℓ * . Strictly speaking, there are other variable parameters in δU , as, for instance, n, e, but their derivatives are first-order infinitesimals and thus, their contribution to the variation of δU will be of second-order. The variation of Ω is important when k = 0 and is considered in the given equations.</p><p>We may substitute the variables r and ϕ by the Keplerian variables of the motion of M around m. Also, since we are only studying the planar case, we adopt θ = π/2 and ϕ = v + ω * (v is the true anomaly). If we introduce the two-body expansions via Cayley coefficients 3 , and for the sake of having a simpler expression, we expand δU in the powers of A and discard the quadratic terms, there follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">δU = − GC 2a 3 k∈Z k+j∈Z 3C k E 2,k+j cos σ k cos((k + j − 2)ℓ + (2 − k)ℓ * + σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k cos((k + j − 2)ℓ + (1 − k)ℓ * − ℓ 1 + σ k ) − cos((k + j − 2)ℓ + (3 − k)ℓ * + ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k−1 cos (k + j − 2)ℓ + (3 − k)ℓ * + ℓ 1 + σ k−1 ) − cos σ k+1 cos((k + j − 2)ℓ + (1 − k)ℓ * − ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) −C ′′ k E 0,j+k cos σ ′′ k cos((k + j)ℓ − kℓ * + σ ′′ k ) ,<label>(23)</label></formula><p>where the subscripts in the infinite summations were adjusted to mimic those used in paper II.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">The rotation. Forced libration</head><p>When the time variation of the moment of inertia is neglected, the rotation of the body m is ruled by the differential equation C ˙ Ω = M z where M z is the torque acting on the primary 4 and C is the moment of inertia. The numerical integration of this equation shows that the rotation is tidally damped to a stationary solution which, when γ is small, is a forced libration around a nearly synchronous center as in paper II. That is, a periodic attractor. Using the definition of C k , we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">M z = −M ∂δU ∂ϕ = − 3GM Cǫ ρ 2r 3 × k∈Z E 2,k cos σ k sin(2ϕ + (k − 2)ℓ * − 2ω * − 2δϕ − σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k−1 sin(2ϕ + (k − 3)ℓ * − 2ω * − ℓ 1 − 2δϕ − σ k−1 ) − cos σ k+1 sin(2ϕ + (k − 1)ℓ * − 2ω * + ℓ 1 − 2δϕ − σ k+1 ) .<label>(24)</label></formula><p>Hence, after introducing the two-body expansions, making ℓ * = ℓ, dividing by the moment of inertia C and expanding in the powers of A, (neglecting the terms of order O(A 2 )), we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">˙ Ω = − 3GM ǫ ρ 2a 3 k∈Z j+k∈Z E 2,k E 2,k+j cos σ k sin(jℓ + σ k ) + A 2n cos σ k sin((j + 1)ℓ + ℓ 1 + σ k ) − sin((j − 1)ℓ − ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k−1 sin((j + 1)ℓ + ℓ 1 + σ k−1 ) − cos σ k+1 sin((j − 1)ℓ − ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) .<label>(25)</label></formula><p>The average over one period is</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">˙ Ω = − 3GM ǫ ρ 2a 3 k∈Z E 2,k E 2,k cos σ k sin σ k + A 2n cos σ k E 2,k−1 sin(ℓ 1 + σ k ) − E 2,k+1 sin(−ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n E 2,k−1 cos σ k−1 sin(ℓ 1 + σ k−1 )E 2,k+1 cos σ k+1 sin(−ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) .<label>(26)</label></formula><p>For small amplitudes, the mean value B 0 , the amplitude A and the phase ℓ 1 of the variation of ν may be calculated using the approximate formulas B 0 = 12nγ 2 e 2 n 2 + γ 2 ; A = 12n 2 eǫ ρ n 2 + γ 2 ; ℓ 1 = arctan γ n .</p><p>which are simplifications of the formulas given by Folonier and Ferraz-Mello, 2017 (Online Supplement, Section B).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">The energy balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">The orbital energy</head><p>In the adopted Darwinian model of Sections 2-3, δU (r, r * ) is the disturbing potential due to the deformation of the mass (m) acting on a generic point of coordinates (r, ϕ, θ) where the body M is placed. Thus, actually M is moving in a time-dependent potential field and the energy of the system is</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">E orb = E kin + M U (r, r * ),<label>(28)</label></formula><p>whose time variation is</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">˙ E orb = ˙ E kin + M n ∂U ∂ℓ + M n ∂U ∂ℓ * ,<label>(29)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_88">or ˙ E orb = M n ∂U ∂ℓ * .<label>(30)</label></formula><p>The term ˙ E kin is canceled by an opposite term − ˙ E kin coming from the derivative with respect to ℓ. The variations of the slow variables a, n are not considered in the differentiation because they do not give significant contributions at the order considered.</p><p>From Eqn. </p><formula xml:id="formula_89">ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) − k 3 E 0,k E 0,j+k cos σ ′′ k sin(jℓ + σ ′′ k ) .<label>(31)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Rotational energy</head><p>The variation of the rotational energy is given by the derivative of the kinetic energy: CΩ ˙ Ω where the moment of inertia C is considered as a constant. If we remember that, because of the forced libration, Ω is not constant, that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">Ω = n 1 + B 0 2n + A 2n cos(ℓ + ℓ 1 ) ,</formula><p>expanding in the powers of A, neglecting the terms of order O(A 2 ), and using the definition of C k , we obtain: </p><formula xml:id="formula_91">˙ E rot = − 3GM Cnǫ ρ<label>2a</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Dissipation</head><p>The variable characterizing the variation in a short time interval is the mean anomaly ℓ and the averaging operation is just 1 2π 2π 0 ˙ E tot dℓ. The other elements are assumed to remain constant along one period. The averages of the variation of the orbital and rotational energies over one orbital period are, respectively,</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">˙ E orb = 3GM Cnǫ ρ 4a 3 k∈Z E 2,k E 2,k (2 − k) cos σ k sin σ k + A 2n cos σ k E 2,k+1 (1 − k) sin(ℓ 1 − σ k ) + E 2,k−1 (3 − k) sin(ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n E 2,k−1 (3 − k) cos σ k−1 sin(ℓ 1 + σ k−1 ) − E 2,k+1 (1 − k) cos σ k+1 sin(−ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) + k 3 E 2 0,k cos σ ′′ k sin σ ′′ k ,<label>(33)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">˙ E rot = − 3GM Cnǫ ρ 2a 3 k∈Z E 2,k E 2,k cos σ k sin σ k 1 + B 0 2n + A 4n cos σ k 3E 2,k−1 sin(ℓ 1 + σ k ) − E 2,k+1 sin(−ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n E 2,k−1 cos σ k−1 sin(ℓ 1 + σ k−1 ) − E 2,k+1 cos σ k+1 sin(−ℓ 1 + σ k+1 ) .<label>(34)</label></formula><p>The energy variations obtained by using these equations coincide numerically with those obtained with the equations given in the main paper. It is worth mentioning that, in the case of Enceladus, the dissipation obtained with the above equations taking the actual value of A given in this Supplement is 27 percent larger than the results obtained when making A = 0, i.e., when neglecting the contribution of the physical libration (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 10</ref>). Thus, indeed, the physical libration contributes to increase the dissipation of a stiff body in near-synchronous rotation, but this contribution is not as large as indicated by some previous calculations using the uniform rotation approximation in the solution for the creep equation.</p><p>The variations of the semi-major axis and eccentricity may be obtained in the same way as the equations given in Section 8 of the main paper.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Tidal forced oscillation of the semi-diurnal frequency of one body like Enceladus in function of the viscosity η and the relaxation factor γ (shown on the upper axis). The black lines are the limits of the oscillation. The red dashed line is the mean value of ν. In the right axis we show the corresponding limit of the physical libration when a harmonic oscillation is assumed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Left: Tidal variation of the mechanical energy (after the vanishing of the transients): the sum of the orbital energy and the internal gravitational energy (black line labeled sum), the rotational (blue line labeled rot), and the total mechanical energy (red line labeled tot). Right: ˙ Etot in a magnified scale. N.B. γ = 2 × 10 −7 s −1 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4 Dissipation curve: Average of the net variation of the mechanical energy. The body and orbital parameters used correspond to a homogeneous Enceladus. The actual range of the observed dissipation and the corresponding ranges for the viscosity (and for the relaxation factor) are shown by a red box.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>( 34 )</head><label>34</label><figDesc>. The results corresponding to a homogeneous Enceladus are shown in Fig. 5 (Left). In that figure the average variation of da/dt is shown for a wide range of values of γ. The average has the same aspect as the dissipation law shown in Fig. 4. This similarity happens because, near the stationary solution, the dissipated energy comes almost totally from ˙ E orb (the average variation of rotational energy ˙ E rot is several orders of magnitude smaller). When γ = 1.2 − 3.8 × 10 −7 s −1 , we obtain ˙ a = −(0.4 − 1.2) × 10 −5 km/yr (the red box in Fig. 5 Left ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 Variation of the averages of −da/dt (Left) and −de/dt (Right) in function of the viscosity η (or γ, see the top axis) for a body like Enceladus. In each plot the red box indicates the values corresponding to the actual range of the observed dissipation of Enceladus.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6 Left: Tidal forced oscillation of the semi-diurnal frequency (and the corresponding limits of the physical libration) of one body like Mimas in function of the viscosity η and the relaxation factor γ (shown on the upper axis). The black lines are the limits of the oscillation and the red dashed line is the mean value of ν. Right: Average of the net variation of the mechanical energy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7 Variation of the averages of −da/dt (Left) and −de/dt (Right) in function of the viscosity η (or γ, see the top axis) for a body like Mimas.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8 Tidal forced oscillation of the semi-diurnal frequency ν (top left), of the orientation angle of δ (top right), of the equatorial prolateness Eρ (bottom left) and of the polar oblateness Ez (bottom right) of one body like Enceladus in function of the viscosity η. The black solid lines are the limits of the oscillations and the mean values given by the numerical integration of Eqs. (7) and (17). The red dashed lines are the limits of the oscillations and the mean values given by the analytical approximation given by Eqs. (50), (52) and (53).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>) 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Typo in Eq. (31). The argument should be kℓ − σ ′′ k . 4. Mistake in Eq. (61). In the last line the arguments should be v + kℓ − σ ′′ k and v − kℓ + σ ′′ k . 5. Mistake in Eqs. (62-68) The sign in front of the zonal part is wrong. The sign in front of C ′′ k in Eqs. (62-63) should be +, the sign in front of kE 2 0,k in Eqs. (64-66) should be − and the sign in front of knE 2 0,k in Eq. (68) should be +. 6. Typo in Eq. (69). The sign in front of the right-hand side should be changed to −. 7. Mistakes in Eq. (70). The correct equation is</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9 Darwin's model. The gravitational attraction of Diana deforms the primary and the deformed primary attracts a mass placed at the point P. Afterwards, P and Diana are identified one with the other.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>( 23 )</head><label>23</label><figDesc>, and making ℓ * = ℓ, we obtain ˙ E orb = 3GM Cnǫ ρ 4a 3 k∈Z k+j∈Z E 2,k E 2,k+j (2 − k) cos σ k sin(jℓ + σ k ) − A 2n cos σ k (1 − k) sin((j − 1)ℓ − ℓ 1 + σ k ) − (3 − k) sin((j + 1)ℓ + ℓ 1 + σ k ) − A 2n (3 − k) cos σ k−1 sin (j + 1)ℓ + ℓ 1 + σ k−1 ) − (1 − k) cos σ k+1 sin((j − 1)ℓ −</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 10 Dissipation curves when the body and orbital parameters used correspond to a homogeneous Enceladus (Eqs. 33 and 34). Solid line: Average of the net variation of the mechanical energy obtained assuming for A the value corresponding to the observed physical libration of Enceladus. Dashed blue line: Average of the energy variation when making A = 0. The actual range of the observed dissipation values and the corresponding range for the relaxation factor are shown by a red box.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 Satellites data used in the calculations Enceladus Mimas</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Mass (10 20 kg) 
1.08 
0.379 
Mean Radius (km) 
252.1 
198.2 
Sidereal Period (d) 
1.370218 
0.942422 
Semi-major axis (10 3 km) 
238.02 
185.52 
Eccentricity 
0.0045 
0.01986 
Mean-motion (10 −5 s −1 ) 
5.300508 
7.696292 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 2 Observed libration and dissipation and results of the homogeneous model</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> This forced libration is related to the asymmetries of the tides raised on the body; it is different from the asymmetries resulting from the assumption of a permanent triaxiality of the body (see Frouard and Efroimsky, 2017).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> In paper II (Ferraz-Mello, 2015), the variation of Re has been neglected. However, when the equatorial prolateness varies due to a variation in the distance of m to M, the polar flattening and Re vary accordingly: Re ≃ R(1 + 1 3 ǫz) where R is the mean radius of the primary (constant).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> The extension of the theory of papers I and II to the case in which the rotation is trapped in a periodic attractor is given in the Online Supplement linked to this paper.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> The dissipation in each one of the two bodies may be considered separately. Within the order of approximation generally adopted (first order in the tidal deformations), the variation of the energy can be split into two parts, each one associated with the tidal deformation in one of the bodies while the other -source of the tidal potential -is kept as a mass point. Therefore, only the dissipation in one of the two bodies need to be explicitly considered.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> It is worth stressing that we are referring to the actual energy of the system. At variance with it, the energy of the osculating Keplerian motion may vary (as well as the osculating semi-major axis) but such variation is only a consequence of the way in which osculating variables are defined.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> According with the relation γ = wR/2η given in papers I and II.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1">e+09 1e+10 1e+11 1e+12 1e+13 1e+14 1e+15 1e+16 η [Pa s] 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03 1e-02 γ [1/s] 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03 &lt;-da/dt&gt; [km/yr] 1e+09 1e+10 1e+11 1e+12 1e+13 1e+14 1e+15 1e+16 η [Pa s] 1e-11 1e-10 1e-09 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 &lt;-de/dt&gt; [1/yr] 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03 1e-02</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1">e+09 1e+10 1e+11 1e+12 1e+13 1e+14 1e+15 1e+16 η [Pa s] 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03 1e-02 1e-01 &lt;-da/dt&gt; [km/yr] 1e-09 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03 γ [1/s] 1e+09 1e+10 1e+11 1e+12 1e+13 1e+14 1e+15 1e+16 η [Pa s] 1e-10 1e-09 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 &lt;-de/dt&gt; [1/yr] 1e-09 1e-08 1e-07 1e-06 1e-05 1e-04 1e-03</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> In the new version of the theory presented in the paper to which this supplement is linked, a new formulation was adopted, where the rotation and the creep equations are solved simultaneously, and it is no longer necessary to make any preliminary hypothesis on the rotational state of the primary.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> For practical formulas using the Cayley coefficients, see the Online Supplement linked to paper II.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Mz is equal to the second component of the torque acting on the companion due to the tides of m. To transform one into the other it is enough to change the sign twice. One because of the action-reaction principle and the other because in the used coordinates, the co-latitude θ is reckoned downward. The minus sign appearing in Eqn. (24) comes from the construction of the vector product r × F.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Archinal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Acton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>A&amp;apos;hearn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Conrad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Report of the IAU Working Group on Cartographic Coordinates and Rotational Elements</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidally-induced melting events as the origin of south-pole activity on Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>B˘ Ehounková</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tobie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Choblet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Cadek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">219</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete spin and orbital evolution of close-in bodies using a Maxwell viscoelastic rheology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boué</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Clemence</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods of Celestial Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961" />
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term stability of Enceladus&apos; uneven ice shell</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Cadek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Souček</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>B˘ Ehounková</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Choblet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tobie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">319</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ellipsoidal Figures of Equilibrium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
			<publisher>Yale Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deformation and tidal evolution of close-in planets and satellites using a Maxwell viscoelastic rheology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boué</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">571</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of deformation inertia (kinetic energy) in the orbital and spin evolution of close-in bodies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ragazzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the secular change in the elements of the orbit of a satellite revolving about a tidally distorted planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Darwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="1880" />
			<publisher>repr. Scientific Papers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal dissipation compared to seismic dissipation: In small bodies, Earths, and super-Earths</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Efroimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">746</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal Viscosity of Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Efroimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The physics of rotational flattening and the point core model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Essén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Preprint ArXiv: 0403328v1 astro-ph.EP</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First-order resonances in satellite orbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Resonances in the motion of planets, satellites and asteroids</title>
		<editor>S.Ferraz-Mello, ed., IAG-USP</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="52" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of Migrating Planet Pairs in Resonance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Michtchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal friction in close-in satellites and exoplanets.The Darwin theory re-visited</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hussmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ArXiv: 0712.1156 astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Errata: Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets. A rheophysical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ArXiv: 1204.3957 astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>paper I</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets: II. Spin dynamics and extension to Mercury and exoplantes host stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1505.05384astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>paper II</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The flattenings of the layers of rotating planets and satellites deformed by a tidal potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kholshevnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1503.08051astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tide on differentiated planetary satellites. Application to Titan</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>IAG/Univ. São Paulo</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of an anelastic multi-layered satellite. Titan&apos;s synchronous rotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1706.08603astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tides in a body librating about a spin-orbit resonance. Generalization of the Darwin-Kaula theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frouard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Efroimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High heat flow from Enceladus&apos; south polar region measured using 10 -600 cm −1 Cassini/CIRS data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Howett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>id. E03003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Planets</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Parisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hemingway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Gravity Field and Interior Structure of Enceladus</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interior thermal state of Enceladus inferred from the viscoelastic state of the ice shell</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nimmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal dissipation in the moon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kaula</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4959" to="4965" />
			<date type="published" when="1963" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal dissipation by solid friction and the resulting orbital evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kaula</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Geophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gravitational heating of the moon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="412" to="421" />
			<date type="published" when="1963" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strong tidal dissipation in Saturn and constraints on Enceladus thermal state from astrometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lainey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Karatekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Desmars</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Charnoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Arlot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">752</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermally anomalous features in the subsurface of Enceladus south polar terrain</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Gall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leyrat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Choblet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tobie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ring torque on Janus and the melting of Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stanton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Cuzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal friction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Geophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="541" />
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal evolution of Mimas, Enceladus, and Dione</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wisdom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orbital evolution of Saturn&apos;s mid-sized moons and the tidal heating of Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nakajima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="570" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the gravitational energy of ellipsoidal bodies and some related functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Neutsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contribution of tidal dissipation to lunar thermal history</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscoelastic tides: models for use in Celestial Mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ragazzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Librational response of Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rambaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Castillo-Rogez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">¨</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Karatekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geoph. Res. Let</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4202</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal heating and the long-term stability of a subsurface ocean on Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nimmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="689" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability in the full two-body problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Scheeres</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface Heat Flow, and Figure of Viscoelastic Models of Io</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Segatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T;</forename><surname>Spohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tidal Dissipation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Icarus</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ice rheology and tidal heating of Enceladus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shoji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hussmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kurita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">226</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cassini Encounters Enceladus: Background and the Discovery of a South Polar Hot Spot</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Flasar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mamoutkine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Romani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Buratti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hendrix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spilker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">311</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1401" to="1405" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enceladus Heat Flow from High Spatial Resolution Thermal Emission Observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Howett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Verbiscer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hurford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EPSC Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2013" to="840" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tajeddine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rambaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lainey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Charnoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Constraints on Mimas&apos; interior from Cassini ISS libration measurements</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">346</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="324" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enceladus&apos;s measured physical libration requires a global subsurface ocean</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tajeddine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tiscareno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">264</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Traité de Mécanique Céleste, tome IV, chap</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tisserand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1896" />
			<publisher>Gauthier-Villars</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TASS 1.6: Ephemerides of the major Saturnian satellites</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vienne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Duriez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">297</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="588" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal dissipation at arbitrary eccentricity and obliquity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wisdom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online Supplement A self-consistent version of the creep tide theory valid for near-synchronous rotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The tides of Io</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets. III. Tidal dissipation revisited and application to Enceladus</title>
		<editor>H.A. Folonier, S. Ferraz-Mello and E. Andrade-Ines</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online Supplement to</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ellipsoidal Figures of Equilibrium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
			<publisher>Yale Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the secular change in the elements of the orbit of a satellite revolving about a tidally distorted planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Darwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="1880" />
			<publisher>repr. Scientific Papers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets. A rheophysical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ArXiv: 1204.3957 astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>paper I</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of close-in satellites and exoplanets: II. Spin dynamics and extension to Mercury and exoplanets host stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1505.05384astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>paper II</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The flattenings of the layers of rotating planets and satellites deformed by a tidal potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kholshevnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1503.08051astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tidal synchronization of an anelastic multi-layered satellite. Titan&apos;s synchronous rotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Folonier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferraz-Mello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1706.08603astro-ph.EP</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Traité de Mécanique Céleste, tome IV, chap</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tisserand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1896" />
			<publisher>Gauthier-Villars</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
