<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:10+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Climate instability on tidally locked exoplanets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-09-13">13 Sep 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kite</surname></persName>
							<email>4kite@berkeley.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Gaidos</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Integrative Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology and Geophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hawaii at Manoa</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7 Michael</addrLine>
									<postCode>96822</postCode>
									<settlement>Honolulu, Manga</settlement>
									<region>HI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Integrative Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Climate instability on tidally locked exoplanets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2011-09-13">13 Sep 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1013 10, CoRoT-7, GJ1214, 55 Cnc, Kepler-9, Kepler-11) 14</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: planetary systems -planets and satellites: general-stars: individual(Kepler-</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>11 12 Feedbacks that can destabilize the climates of synchronously-rotating rocky planets may arise on planets with strong day-night surface temperature contrasts. Earth-like habitable planets maintain stable surface liquid water over geological time. This requires equilibrium between the temperature-dependent rate of greenhouse-gas consumption by weathering, and greenhouse-gas resupply by other processes. Detected small-radius exoplanets, and anticipated M-dwarf habitable-zone rocky planets, are expected to be in synchronous rotation (tidally locked). In this paper we investigate two hypothetical feedbacks that can destabilize climate on planets in synchronous rotation. (1) If small changes in pressure alter the temperature distribution across a planet&apos;s surface such that the weathering rate goes up when the pressure goes down, a runaway positive feedback occurs involving increasing weathering rate near the substellar point, decreasing pressure, and increasing substellar surface temperature. We call this feedback enhanced substellar weathering instability (ESWI). (2) When decreases in pressure increase the fraction of surface area above the melting point (through reduced advective cooling of the substellar point), and the corresponding increase in volume of liquid causes net dissolution of the atmosphere, a further decrease in pressure will occur. This substellar dissolution feedback (SDF) can also cause a runaway climate shift. We use an idealized energy balance model to map out the conditions under which these instabilities may occur. In this simplified model, the weathering runaway can shrink the habitable zone, and cause geologically rapid 10 3-fold atmospheric pressure shifts within the habitable zone. Mars may have undergone a weathering runaway in the past. Substellar dissolution is usually a negative feedback or weak positive feedback on changes in atmospheric-2-pressure. It can only cause runaway changes for small, deep oceans and highly soluble atmospheric gases. Both instabilities are suppressed if the atmosphere has a high ra-diative efficiency. Our results are most relevant for atmospheres that are thin, have low greenhouse-gas radiative efficiency, and have a principal greenhouse gas that is also the main constituent of the atmosphere. These results identify a new pathway by which habitable-zone planets can undergo rapid climate shifts and become uninhabitable.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>141</head><p>The horizontally uniform atmospheric boundary layer temperature, T a , is set by the total 142 energy balance of the atmosphere, where the integral gives the average flux from the surface. This reduces to T a = 1 /2 π 0 T s (ψ) sin ψ dψ 144 because of our particular choice of LW↓. In effect, we assume that the boundary layer only interacts <ref type="bibr">145</ref> with the ground through turbulent fluxes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>146</head><p>For a given P Λ , we iterate to find T a and T s (ψ). ψ resolution is 5 degrees. The initial 147 condition has the surface in radiative equilibrium, and the atmosphere in equilibrium with this surface temperature distribution. Convergence tolerance is ≈ 2 × 10 −6 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>149</head><p>Throughout the paper, we assume k T F = C p (T a )C D U , where C p (T a ) is the temperature-  is not absorbed by the upper atmosphere and escapes to space, and T = 250K is the atmospheric 171 temperature, the radiative equilbrium temperature on the darkside being zero. <ref type="bibr">Picking = 0.5, 172</ref> this gives τ advect ∼ 2 days and τ rad ∼ 50 days. (4) The treatment of T a is crude. (5) We assume 173 the atmosphere is transparent to stellar radiation, which is a crude approximation under M-dwarf</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>174</head><p>(or cloudy) skies. (6) We neglect condensation within the atmosphere.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>175</head><p>Representative temperature plots are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, for Λ = 0.1 and L * = 900 W/m 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>176</head><p>At low pressures, nightside temperatures are close to absolute zero, and substellar temperature is 177 close to radiative equilibrium. Increasing pressure cools ψ &lt; 60 • , and warms ψ &gt; 70 • . This is 178 beause the atmosphere is warmer than the surface on the nightside, and cooler than the surface 179 on the dayside. Therefore, the increase in P (∝ β) increases the β(T s − T a ) term, which warms the 180 nightside, but cools the dayside. For positive Λ, LW ↓ will increase with P and warm the entire 181 planet. However, for the relatively small value of Λ shown here, the substellar point still undergoes 182 net cooling with increasing pressure. This cooling with increasing P is what makes the ESWI and 183 SDF possible. When the surface becomes nearly isothermal, as for the "10-bar" curve in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, 184 the entire surface warms with increasing pressure, and the ESWI and SDF cannot occur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>185</head><p>For Λ ≥ 0, ¯ T s must increase with P . Even if there is no greenhouse effect, the homogenization of the atmosphere will warm the planet on average because of the nonlinear dependence of T on 187 energy input ( <ref type="bibr">Edson et al. 2011</ref>). For small optical depth, nightside T s ∝ ln(P </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">W ψ W 0 = P P 0 0.5 exp [k ACT (T s (ψ) − T o )] direct T dependence [1 + k RU N (T s (ψ) − T o )] 0.65 hydrology dependence (3)</formula><p>where W ψ is local weathering rate, W 0 is a reference weathering rate, P is atmospheric pressure, P 0 198 is a reference pressure, T o = 273K is a reference temperature, k ACT = 0.09 is an activation energy 199 coefficient, and k RU N is a temperature-runoff coefficient fit to Earth GCMs. Equation 3 is widely <ref type="bibr">200</ref> used, but uncertain and controversial ( §5.2.1). In our model, the strong temperature dependence </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">W t (P ) = 1 4π π 0 W ψ A ψ dψ (4)</formula><p>Climate is in equilibrium ( ∂P ∂t = 0) when planet-integrated weathering of greenhouse gases, W t , is 205 equal to net supply V n by other processes. The climate equilibrium is stable if dW t /dP &gt; 0 -206 in this case, carbonate-silicate feedback enables long-term climate stability ( <ref type="bibr">Walker et al. 1981</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>207</head><p>Climate destabilization occurs when dW t /dP &lt; 0. The weathering feedback that underpins the 208 Circumstellar Habitable Zone concept ( <ref type="bibr">Kasting et al. 1993</ref>) changes sign, and acts to destabilize 209 these climates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">ESWI results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>211</head><p>Figure 3 shows weathering rates corresponding to the temperatures in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The lines show 212 equilibria between weathering consumption of greenhouse gases and net supply by other processes</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>213</head><p>( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">Figure 3</ref>). is set by the (P/P o ) term in Equation 5 -for small P , τ ∝ ln(P ) and β ∝ P are small and the 221 atmosphere has little effect on T s . On the intermediate pressure unstable branch -dashed in <ref type="figure">Figure   222</ref> 2 -the atmosphere is important to energy balance but β outcompetes τ . The homogenizing effect of 223 β cools the substellar region, and planet-integrated weathering decreases with increasing pressure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>224</head><p>In the high-pressure stable branch, the planet is close to isothermal. Further increases in β have 225 little effect on ∆T s , but τ warms the whole planet and now is able to increase W t . Catastrophic    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>264</head><p>For the almost radiatively inert gas <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">(Figure 4b</ref>), geologically stable equilibria usually have  dissolve into this warm little pond, approaching Henry's-law equilibrium:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">288 P pond = g P Earth D pond 1 2 (1 − cos ψ max ) global−equivalent liquid depth P d m ρ l k H (T o ) exp C 1 T pond − 1 T o</formula><p>mass of gas per unit liquid volume</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(5)</formula><p>where P pond (in bars) is the equivalent atmospheric pressure of gases dissolved in the ocean, g is is a reference temperature. Here, the first term in brackets is the depth of the pond in global-294 equivalent meters, and the second term in brackets is the mass of gas per unit volume of pond.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>295</head><p>We have neglected the distinction between fugacity and partial pressure. The pond is assumed to   and precipitation of carbonates or salts (such as sulfates).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>325</head><p>As an example of SDF, consider the partitioning of an initial 1-bar total inventory of CO 2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>326</head><p>(blue-green contour labelled '0' in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">Figure 6</ref>) with increasing L * . Initially, the planet's surface is the ocean covers almost the entire lightside hemisphere, and stores ∼ 5 /6 of the initial CO 2 inventory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>336</head><p>Further small increases in L * cause a global ocean.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>337</head><p>Three main effects control this system:- <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>  erates weathering, and may be unique to <ref type="bibr">Earth (Taylor et al. 2009</ref>). All geologically important surface weathering reactions require a liquid phase <ref type="bibr">(White &amp; Brantley 1995)</ref>. We assume weather-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>430</head><p>ing reactions do continue below the freezing point (due to microclimates, or monolayers of water).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>431</head><p>However, the results shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 4</ref> and 5 did not change qualitatively when we set W = 0 for 432 Planets could undergo ESWI early in their history if they form in the unstable region. In addition, an instability for a planet orbiting an M-star, by reducing P <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">(Figure 4a</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>496</head><p>• Tectonics and volcanism: Volcanic activity decays with radioactivity ( <ref type="bibr">Kite et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sleep 2000, 497</ref> 2007; Stevenson 2003), so in the absence of tidal heating the equilibrium pressure will gradually 498 fall (on a stable branch where W t increases with P ) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">(Figure 4a</ref>). Superimposed on this decline <ref type="bibr">499</ref> are pulses in volcanic activity due to mantle plumes, and perhaps planetwide volcanic overturns 500 as seem to have occurred on Venus. This will cause spikes in equilibrium pressure. The rate of 501 resurfacing is very sensitive to mantle composition, tidal heating, and tectonic style (Kite et al.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>502</head><p>2009; <ref type="bibr">Valencia &amp; O'Connell 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Korenaga 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">B˘ ehounková et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">, 2011</ref><ref type="bibr">van Summeren et al. 2011</ref>). Shutdown of volcanism (such that V n ≤ 0) extinguishes the possibility of a stable climate 504 equilibrium; P will fall monotonically. ESWI can accelerate this decay, and Mars may be an example 505 of this ( §5.1). Mountain range uplift exposes fresh rock and may provide a O(10 7 ) yr increase in 506 weathering rate that cools the planet (as arguably and controversially may have occurred for Tibet,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>507</head><p>Earth: Garzione <ref type="formula">(2008)</ref>). This may trigger ESWI by lowering pressure. More speculatively, drift 508 of continents can cause very large atmospheric pressure fluctuations if greenhouse-gas drawdown 509 occurs mainly on land and is strongly focussed in a high-weathering patch near ψ = 0. A continent 510 drifting over the patch will increase planet-averaged weatherability, and pressure will go down. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>516</head><p>These searches are driven in part by the hope that planets orbiting M-dwarves can maintain surface 517 liquid water and be habitable. Maintaining surface liquid water over geological time involves 518 equilibrium between greenhouse-gas supply and removal. Balance is thought to be maintained on    ∂P ∂t = 0 at equilibrium, and W t equals net supply by other processes, V n . For both the lowest and highest P , W t ↑ as P↑. Equilibria on these branches are stable. Climates that approach the unstable zone from below will jump up to the dashed gray line. Climates that approach the unstable zone from above will jump down to the solid gray line. These jumps can be extreme; for example, in (b) the solid gray line is everywhere &lt; 0.001 bars (and so is not visible). See the text for discussion of the speed of jumps. The hysteresis loop does not exist for high L * and and high Λ, and so the thick gray lines vanish towards the right of (d). The thin lines correspond to previously-described challenges to habitable-zone climate stability: moist runaway greenhouse (thin solid line); nightside atmospheric condensation of CO 2 (dash-dotted line); boiling of surface water (thin dashed line). The jump in pressure due to ESWI can cause a runaway wet greenhouse (for a jump upwards in P ), or a decrease in P to the triple point of water (for a jump downwards in P ). To account for microclimates and solid-state greenhouse effects, we conservatively define "P &lt; triple point" as "P &lt; 1 mbar", which is below the boiling curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 4</ref>. Some curves have been smoothed with a 5th-order polynomial in order to remove small wiggles due to numerical artifacts. The arrow shows the change in stellar flux at 1AU for a solarmass star over 8 Gyr of stellar evolution in the model of <ref type="bibr">Bahcall et al. (2001)</ref>, and the circle marks the current solar flux. .-Substellar dissolution feedback, for CO 2 /seawater equilibria, Λ = 0.03 (note that Λ = 0.03 is unrealistically low for all-CO 2 atmospheres), and a 100km-deep ocean. The vertical axis is P . Colored solid lines correspond to log10(P + P pond ), i.e. the sum of the atmospheric and ocean inventory. Where these are equal to P , there is no ocean. Fractional ocean coverage is shown by the red dashed contours (contour interval is 0.1 in units of planet fractional surface area). Because nightside temperature is constant, fractional ocean coverage jumps from 0.5 (hemispheric ocean) to 1.0 (global ocean). The outermost black line encloses the area where SDF is a positive feedback on small changes in P . Outside this area,</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>[</head><label></label><figDesc>LW↑ (ψ) + β(T s (ψ) − T a )] sin ψ dψ − OLR − LW↓= 0 (2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>150 dependent specific heat capacity of CO 2 (≈850 J/kg/K at 300K), C D is a drag coefficient, and U is 151 characteristic near-surface wind speed. C D = k 2 V K ln(z 1 /z 0 ) 2 where k V K = 0.4 is von Karman's constant, z 1 = 10m is a reference altitude, and z 0 is the surface roughness length (10 −4 m, which is bracketed 153 by the measured values for sand, snow, and smooth mud flats; Pielke (2002)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>201 leads to a strong concentration of weathering near the substellar point. For example, for a 1-bar 202 atmosphere with Λ = 0.1 (shown in Figure 2), 93% of the weathering occurs in 10% of the planet's 203 area. The planet-averaged weathering rate is 204</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4 shows habitable-zone climate regimes as a function of equilibrium pressure and stellar</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>256 does not include fluxes of latent heat or the greenhouse effect of water vapor, so the position of 257 this line is notional. The maximum pressure and minimum pressure of the bifurcation loop (Figure 258</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>3</head><label></label><figDesc>) are shown by thick gray lines in figure 4. In some cases, the lower end-of-transition pressures 259 are so low that water boils (thin dashed line). This would initiate the boiling of a global ocean. If 260 boiling continued, the eventual fate could be a steam ocean, or restriction of liquid water stability 261 to a thin belt near the terminator. The upper end-of-transition pressures are often &gt;10 bars, with 262 a nearly isothermal T s . Such planets would have weak and perhaps undetectable phase curves in 263 the absorbing bands (Selsis et al. 2011).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>265 P</head><label>265</label><figDesc>Figure 5 summarizes the effects of ESWI in a stability phase diagram (against axes of gas</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>280 4.</head><label>280</label><figDesc>Climate destabilization mechanism #2: Substellar dissolution feedback (SDF) 281 Water ice and basalt are the most common planetary surface materials in the Solar System, and 282 are expected to be common elsewhere.When these melt (around 273K for ice and 1300K for basalt), 283 atmosphere can dissolve into the melt. Counterintuitively, a decrease in P and in average surface 284 temperature ¯ T s can favor melting if ∆T s is large, as pointed out for Mars by Richardson &amp; Mischna 285 (2005). For a synchronously-rotating planet entirely coated in condensed material (ice, rock, or carbon-rich ceramic), surface liquid will first appear near the substellar point. Atmosphere will 287</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>289 surface gravity, P Earth = 1.01 x 10 5 Pa is a normalization constant, D pond is pond depth, ρ l is 290 liquid density, ψ max is the angular radius of the pond, P is the surface pressure, d is a dissolution 291 exponent (∼0.5 for water in silicate liquids and ∼1 for gases in water), m is the molecular mass 292 of the atmosphere, k H and C are Henry's-law coefficients, T pond is the pond temperature, and T o 293</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>296 be well-mixed so that T pond = 1 1−cos ψmax ψmax 0 T s,ψ sin ψ dψ. This relation assumes a uniform heat 297 transfer coefficient between the surface and the pond.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>298 Instability occurs when a decrease (increase) in surface pressure results in an uptake (release) 299 of gases from the pond that exceeds that which is consistent with that change in pressure, i.e. 300 ∂P pond ∂P &lt; −1. In this case the feedback has infinite gain (Roe 2009</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>327 below freezing.</head><label>327</label><figDesc>As stellar flux is increased to 800 W/m 2 , a small sea forms and dissolves some of 328 the CO 2 . The system is within the area where SDF is a positive feedback on small changes in P 329 (outermost black contour in Figure 6), which accelerates sea growth. A small further increase in L * 330 leads to runaway SDF (innermost black contour in Figure 6), and ocean area quickly grows with 331 from ∼5% to ∼15% of planet surface area with no change in L * . After this change the atmospheric 332 inventory is reduced to 1 /4 bar with the remaining 3 /4 bar dissolved in the ocean. Further pond 333 growth requires further increase in L * . Increasing T pond decreases solubility and shallows the slope 334 of increasing volatile inventory stored in the ocean. By L * = 3800 W/m 2 (the highest considered), 335</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>477 many common geodynamic and astronomical processes can shift the equilibrium between W t and 478 V n (Figure 4a), causing a secular drift of the equilibrium across the phase space {L * , Λ, V t } (Figures 479 3 and 5). This drift can take a planet from a stable equilibrium to an unstable equilibrium via a 480 saddle-node bifurcation (Strogatz et al. 1994). 481 • Dynamics and stellar evolution: Theory predicts that the secular increase in solar flux should 482 have gradually shifted the position of Earth's climate equilibrium. This is consistent with the 483 sedimentary record of the last 2.5 x 10 9 yr (Grotzinger &amp; Kasting 1993; Grotzinger &amp; James 2000; 484 Ridgwell &amp; Zeebe 2005; Kah &amp; Riding 2007). For Kepler field (Sunlike, rapidly evolving) stars, 485 this could also occur and potentially cause the ESWI for planets with initially thick atmospheres 486 (Figure 4a). For M stars, main-sequence insolation changes little over the lifetime of the Universe. 487 • Atmospheric evolution: Λ can change as atmospheric composition evolves. For example, the rise 488 in atmospheric oxygen following the emergence of oxygenic photosynthesisers probably oxidized 489 atmospheric CH 4 and may have caused a catastrophic decline in Λ (Kopp et al. 2005; Domagal- 490 Goldman et al. 2008). Even gases with negligible opacity, such as N 2 , alter Λ through pressure 491 broadening (Li et al. 2009). Carbonate-silicate weathering equilibrium is impossible for planets 492 where atmospheric erosion exceeds geological degassing. For these planets, V n is negative. Strong 493 stellar winds and high XUV flux are observed for many M stars. Removal of atmosphere by strong 494 stellar winds (Mura et al. 2011) or, for smaller planets, high XUV flux (Tian 2009) could trigger 495</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>511 6.</head><label>511</label><figDesc>Summary and conclusions 512 Nearby M-dwarfs are targeted by several planet searches:-MEarth (Charbonneau et al. 2009); the 513 VLT+UVES M-dwarf planet search (Zechmeister et al. 2009); the VLT+CRIRES M-dwarf planet 514 search (Bean et al. 2010); HARPS (Forveille et al. 2011); M2K (Apps et al. 2010); and proposed 515 space missions TESS (Deming 2009); ELEKTRA; PLATO; and ExoplanetSat (Smith et al. 2010).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>519 habitable planets through temperature-dependent weathering reactions. Climate stability can be 520 undermined by several previously-studied climate instabilities. These include atmospheric collapses 521 (Haberle et al. 1994; Read &amp; Lewis 2004), photochemical collapses (Zahnle et al. 2008; Lorenz et 522 al. 1997), greenhouse runaways (Kasting 1988; Lorenz et al. 1999; Sugiyama et al. 2002), ice- 523 albedo feedback (Roe &amp; Baker 2010), and ocean thermohaline circulation bistability (Stommel 524 1961; EPICA Community Members 2006</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Geometry of the idealized energy balance model for an exoplanet in 1:1 spin-orbit resonance. Uneven distribution of starlight (L * ) on the planet leads to a hot (white shading, high T s ) dayside surface and a cool (black shading, low T s ) nightside surface. The atmosphere (uniform gray shading), with horizontally uniform boundary-layer temperature T a , tends to reduce this temperature gradient (∆T s ). When T s &gt; T melt , a melt pond can form around the substellar point ψ = 0, with angular radius ψ max and depth D pond . Because rotation is slow, meridional winds are as fast as zonal winds, so T s depends only on the angular distance from the substellar point (ψ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-Bifurcation diagram to show the enhanced substellar weathering instability for radiative efficiency Λ = 0.1, stellar flux L * = 900 W/m 2 . The thick black line shows the planet-integrated weathering, W t , corresponding to the temperature maps shown in Figure 2. If V n = 0, W t ∝ − ∂P ∂t .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-(a) Mechanisms that can cause secular change in the location of the climate equilibrium W t = V n . (b,c,d) Habitable zone (HZ) stability diagrams for (b) Λ = 0.01, (c) Λ = 0.3, (d) Λ = 1.0. (Climates with Λ &gt;&gt; 1 are always stable against the enhanced substellar weathering instability). The climate states at intermediate pressure within the thick black line labelled with zeros are unstable to ESWI ∂Wt ∂P &lt; 0 . Climates that approach the unstable zone from below will jump up to the dashed gray line. Climates that approach the unstable zone from above will jump down to the solid gray line. These jumps can be extreme; for example, in (b) the solid gray line is everywhere &lt; 0.001 bars (and so is not visible). See the text for discussion of the speed of jumps. The hysteresis loop does not exist for high L * and and high Λ, and so the thick gray lines vanish towards the right of (d). The thin lines correspond to previously-described challenges to habitable-zone climate stability: moist runaway greenhouse (thin solid line); nightside atmospheric condensation of CO 2 (dash-dotted line); boiling of surface water (thin dashed line).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Stability phase diagram, showing the effects of the enhanced substellar weathering instability as a function of L * and Λ. The jump in pressure due to ESWI can cause a runaway wet greenhouse (for a jump upwards in P ), or a decrease in P to the triple point of water (for a jump downwards in P ). To account for microclimates and solid-state greenhouse effects, we conservatively define "P &lt; triple point" as "P &lt; 1 mbar", which is below the boiling curves in Figure 4. Some curves have been smoothed with a 5th-order polynomial in order to remove small wiggles due to numerical artifacts. The arrow shows the change in stellar flux at 1AU for a solarmass star over 8 Gyr of stellar evolution in the model of Bahcall et al. (2001), and the circle marks the current solar flux.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-Substellar dissolution feedback, for CO 2 /seawater equilibria, Λ = 0.03 (note that Λ = 0.03 is unrealistically low for all-CO 2 atmospheres), and a 100km-deep ocean. The vertical axis is P . Colored solid lines correspond to log10(P + P pond ), i.e. the sum of the atmospheric and ocean inventory. Where these are equal to P , there is no ocean. Fractional ocean coverage is shown by the red dashed contours (contour interval is 0.1 in units of planet fractional surface area). Because nightside temperature is constant, fractional ocean coverage jumps from 0.5 (hemispheric ocean) to 1.0 (global ocean). The outermost black line encloses the area where SDF is a positive feedback on small changes in P . Outside this area,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>). The fractional</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>188 

area of the planet over which liquid water is stable is 27% at radiative equilibrium, decreasing with 

189 

pressure and vanishing at ∼0.7 bars. As P increases the greenhouse effect further, liquid stability 

190 

reappears at ∼2.4 bars, rapidly becoming global. 

191 

3. Climate destabilization mechanism #1: 

192 

Enhanced substellar weathering instability (ESWI) 

193 

3.1. Weathering parameterisation 

194 

. 

195 

The Berner &amp; Kothavala (2001) weathering relation, which is specific to CO 2 weathering of Ca-Mg 

196 

silicate rocks, states 

197 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Increasing L * pushes the the high pressure branch to higher values. Other instabilities 250 that contain the habitable zone are shown by thin lines. The dash-dotted line corresponds to</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>). The thick black line labelled with 

243 

zeros corresponds to marginally stable climate equilibrium. Increasing L  *  widens the range of P 

244 

that sits within the low-pressure stable branch. That is because higher L  *  produces higher absolute 

245 

temperatures, and higher absolute temperatures favor radiative exchange between atmosphere and 

246 

surface (∝ 4(T s − T a ) 3 for small (T s − T a ) ) versus turbulent exchange (∝ (T s − T a ) 1 ). Therefore, a 

247 

given equilibrium value of P on the low pressure branch is more stable at low L  *  than high L  *  :-for a 

248 

small increase in P the radiative warming will be less counteracted by the cooling of the substellar point. 251 

pressures in excess of the nightside CO 2 saturation vapor pressure. CO 2 atmospheres to the left of 

252 

this line condense on fast, dynamical timescales. Increasing Λ couples the horizontally-isothermal 

253 

atmosphere more strongly to the nightside surface, and causes the CO 2 collapse threshhold to move 

254 

to the left. The thin solid line corresponds to mean surface temperatures above 40 • C, which is the 

255 

lower edge of the moist runaway greenhouse zone (Kasting 1988; Pierrehumbert 1995) -our model 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>feedback (or a negative feedback) for most gases which dissolve simply according 360 to Henry's Law. The buffering effect is not sufficient to allow ocean area to give a strong positiveb). Alongside carbonate formation, atmospheric escape, polar cold trapping and 395 volcanic degassing are the four main processes affecting P on Mars over the last 3 Ga. However,</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Cosine fall-off of starlight weakens the ability of 

338 

decreasing pressure to increase ocean area beyond a relatively small ψ max . Following a line of 

339 

decreasing pressure, the dashed red lines (fractional ocean area) become more widely spaced with 

340 

decreasing pressure. Cosine falloff of stellar radiation is responsible. This restricts the scope of 

341 

the instability, which tends to lead to Eyeball states (Pierrehumbert 2011). We do not find any 

342 

cases where the SDF can turn a dry planet into an ocean-covered planet or vice versa. (2) Ocean 

343 

instability disappears above ∼5 bars, when the surface is nearly isothermal. Because decreases in 

344 

pressure always decrease ¯ 
T s (except when there is an antigreenhouse), decreases in pressure can only 

345 

cause oceans to freeze over. Below ∼5 bars, ∆T s is not negligible. If a decrease in pressure allows 

346 

the substellar temperature to rise above freezing, an ocean can form. (3) Rectification of starlight 

347 

by the terminator, and of ocean area by the melting point, divides the phase diagram into 'no 

348 

ocean', 'substellar ocean' and 'global ocean' zones. On the nightside T s is constant, so ocean area 

349 

jumps from 50% to 100%. Notice the change in sign of L  *  dependence below and above the dashed 

350 

red line corresponding to 50% ocean area. In the substellar ocean zone, increasing L  *  increases 

351 

ocean area and the ocean inventory increases. However, in the global ocean zone, increasing L  *  

352 

cannot increase ocean area. The decrease in gas solubility with increasing temperature dominates, 

353 

and the ocean inventory decreases. 

354 

Figure 6 does show unstable regions in parameter space for which substellar dissolution is a 

355 

positive feedback on changes in P (solid black lines). These always correspond to small oceans 

356 

(&lt;10% of planet surface area). But the gain of the feedback is small, and runaways cannot occur 

357 

unless ocean depth &gt;10km. Factor-of-3 decreases (or increases) in atmospheric pressure can occur 

358 

with no change in the total (atmosphere + ocean) inventory of volatile substance. The SDF is a minor positive 361 

feedback. Finally, Λ = 0.03 is unrealistically low for all-CO 2 atmospheres. Setting Λ = 1 would 

362 

shut down the instability. We conclude that the CO 2 SDF is unlikely to be important for planets 

363 

in synchronous rotation, and is important in fewer cases than is the ice-albedo feedback (Roe &amp; 

364 

Baker 2010; Pierrehumbert et al. 2011). 

365 

5. Discussion 

366 

5.1. Solar system climate stability -is Mars a solar system example of ESWI? 

367 

Although ESWI is most relevant for planets in synchronous rotation, it can work for any planet 

368 

with sufficiently high ∆T s . Therefore, in order to test ESWI against available data, we compare the 

369 

requirements for ESWI to Solar System data (Table 1). After correcting for the distorting effects of 

370 

life, all of the Solar System's non-giant atmospheres are overwhelmingly one gas. Except for Earth, 

371 

the principal gas is also the main greenhouse gas. Venus' atmospheric composition is not controlled 

372 

by the abundance of surface liquid (nor in solid-state equilibrium with surface minerals; Hashimoto 

373 

&amp; Abe (2005); Tremain &amp; Bullock (in press)), and Triton's atmosphere is too thin to stabilize 

374 

liquid nitrogen. Climate regulation on Titan is not well understood. Currently, the greenhouse 

375 

effect of CH 4 outcompetes the antigreenhouse effect of the organic haze layer (McKay et al. 1991). 

376 

The production rate of the organic haze layer depends on [CH 4 ] (McKay et al. 1991; Lorenz et al. 

377 

1997). ESWI is not currently possible on Titan because ∆T s is too small, 2.5-3.5K (Jennings et al. 

378 

2009). Therefore, out of 5 nearby worlds with atmospheres and surfaces, only Mars is a candidate 

379 

for ESWI ( §5.1). Solar System data suggest that the conditions for the ESWI are quite restrictive, 

380 

and that most planets will not be susceptible to the ESWI. 

381 

Mars may have passed through ESWI in the past. The main climate-controlling greenhouse 

382 

gas (CO 2 ) can dissolve in liquid water and be sequestered as carbonate minerals. Mars has low P 

383 

(95% CO 2 ). It has widespread deposits of carbonate minerals (Bandfield et al. 2003; Wray et al. 

384 

2011), but little or no surface liquid water. It currently sits at the gas-liquid sublimation boundary 

385 

(Kahn 1985), with ∆T s ∼100K , and GCMs show that ∆T s ↓ as P↑ (Richardson &amp; Mischna 2005). 

386 

These geologic and climatic observations are all consistent with a past rapid transition via ESWI 

387 

from an early thicker atmosphere to the current state, as follows. Increasing solar luminosity could 

388 

have permitted transient liquid water, allowing carbonate formation. The corresponding drawdown 

389 

in P would increase noontime temperature, allowing a further increase in liquid water availability 

390 

and the rate of carbonate formation. The runaway would slow as P approached the triple-point 

391 

buffer: loss of liquid water stability may have throttled weathering and buffered the climate near 

392 

the triple point (Kahn 1985; Halevy et al. 2007). However, ice is not ubiquitous on the surface 

393 

and can migrate away from warm spots, so unusual orbital conditions are neccessary for melting (Kite et al. 2011a,396 

recent volcanism has been sluggish and probably CO 2 -poor (Hirschmann &amp; Withers 2008; Werner 

397 

2009; Stanley et al. in press), and present-day atmospheric escape appears slow (Barabash et al. 

398 

2007). Polar cold traps hold ∼1 Mars atmosphere of CO 2 as ice today (Phillips et al. 2011), but 

399 

this trapping should be reversable at high obliquity. Therefore, it is quite possible that substellar 

400 

(≡ noontime) carbonate formation has been the dominant flux affecting the secular evolution of 

401 

Mars' atmosphere since 3.0 Gya. This hypothesis deserves further investigation. 

402 

5.2. Application to exoplanets 

403 

5.2.1. How general is our feedback? 

404 

ESWI requires: 

405 

-Strong temperature dependence of the weathering drawdown of greenhouse gases. Decreasing 

406 

k ACT to 0.03 (from the nominal 0.09) eliminates the ESWI except for radiatively inert atmospheric 

407 

compositions. On the other hand, increasing k ACT to 0.27 causes a large unstable region even for Λ 

408 

= 1.0, with at least a 1 dex range of atmospheric pressure unstable to ESWI for all habitable-zone 

409 

luminosities. 

410 

Earth data on the value of k ACT are consistent with k ACT ∼ 0.1. However, deep-time calibra-

411 

tion of weathering-temperature relations such as Equation 3 is difficult. There is only one planet 

412 

(Earth) to use as laboratory, with constantly drifting boundary conditions, and rather few natural 

413 

experiments. Chemical weathering rates of silicate minerals in the lab are definitely temperature-

414 

dependent (White &amp; Brantley 1995), but erosion-rate dependence is also important at the scale 

415 

of river catchments (West et al. 2005). Confirming temperature dependence on geological scales 

416 

is difficult, in part because today's weathering rate contains echoes of glacial-interglacial cycles 

417 

(Vance et al. 2009). Regression of present-day river loads on watershed climatology by West et al. 

418 

(2005) suggests an e-folding temperature of 8.5(+5.5/-2.9)K. 187 Os/ 188 Os data suggest continental 

419 

weathering rates increased 4-8x in 10 6 yr during a Jurassic hyperthermal (∆T ≤ 10K) 0.183 Gya 

420 

(Cohen et al. 2004), implying an e-folding temperature &lt;(5 -7)K. Analysis of the apparent time 

421 

dependence of weathering rate gives support to a hydrological control on weathering rates (Maher 

422 

2010), but on a planetary scale precipitation always increases when T s increases (O'Gorman &amp; 

423 

Schneider 2008). That is, DW 
Dt = ∂W 
∂Ts + ∂W 

∂R 

∂R 

∂Ts with ∂R 
∂Ts &gt; 0. 

424 

Overall, Equation 3 is consistent with deep-time, present-epoch, and laboratory estimates for 

425 

Earth. Though Equation 3 is used in this paper as a general rule for Earth-like planets, the 

426 

weathering-temperature relation is shaped by biological innovations. For example, the symbiosis 

427 

between vascular plants and root fungi (arbuscular mycorrhizae) acidifies soil, profoundly accel-

428 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>-radius exoplanets in multi-planet systems are in mean-motion resonance (Lissauer et al. 468 2011), but that most are close to resonance and could maintain nonzero eccentricity. This would</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>T &lt; T melt . 

433 

Strong temperature dependence could break down in several ways. For example, erosion is 

434 

needed to expose fresh mineral surfaces for weathering. On a tectonically quiescent planet (and 

435 

for tectonically quiescent regions of an active planet) weathering may be limited by supply of fresh 

436 

surfaces, with weathering going to completion on all exposed silicate minerals. On tectonically very 

437 

active planets with little or no land, hydrothermal alteration and rapid seafloor spreading maintain 

438 

low greenhouse gas levels with little or no temperature dependence (Sleep &amp; Zahnle 2001). A 

439 

planet with weathering rates that are limited by the availability of liquid water (like Mars) can 

440 

have effectively temperature-dependent weathering, but only if the atmospheric pressure is well 

441 

above that fluid's triple point. 

442 

-Large ∆T s . The high-∆T s requirement cannot be met if the atmosphere is thick. A deep global 

443 

ocean circulation behaves like a thick atmosphere -Earth abyssal temperatures vary &lt;2K from 

444 

tropics to poles (Schlitzer 2000). Therefore, the climate destabilization mechanism cannot operate 

445 

on a planet with a deep global ocean circulation -at least some land is necessary. Evaporation 

446 

will dry out land at the substellar point if ¯ 
T s is high, so weathering activity may be concentrated 

447 

at cooler ψ in this case. ∆T s varies little, or even increases, with rotation frequency (Merlis &amp; 

448 

Schneider 2010; Edson et al. 2011). Therefore, ESWI could work for rapidly-rotating planets such 

449 

as Mars ( §5.1). However, the isothermal approximation does not apply when the Coriolis force 

450 

prevents fast equator-to-pole winds. For rapid rotators, T s is a function of latitude and longitude, 

451 

and our idealized energy balance model is not appropriate. 

452 

-Small Λ. Strong greenhouse gases have high Λ, which suppresses ESWI. On the other hand, 

453 

Λ can be negative if there is an antigreenhouse effect (Λ &lt; 0). M-dwarfs later than M4, with 

454 

fully convective interiors, seem to remain active with high UV fluxes for much longer than do 

455 

Sunlike stars. High UV fluxes broadly favor CH 4 accumulation (Segura et al. 2005) and perhaps 

456 

antigreenhouse haze effects. When Λ &lt; 0, ESWI will apply for all P and L  *  . 

457 

-Surface-atmosphere coupling. This consists of radiative and turbulent coupling. Turbulent cou-

458 

pling requires a nonzero near-surface wind speed, and that the global near-surface atmosphere is 

459 

not stably stratified. A sensitivity test with a 10-fold reduction in U showed that the pressure 

460 

range unstable to ESWI moves to ∼ 10× higher pressure. The range of Λ subject to ESWI was 

461 

significantly reduced. We assume U is not a function of P , but simulations show that U increases 

462 

as P decreases (Melinda A. Kahre, via email). This would strengthen the instability. 

463 

SDF has very similar requirements to ESWI, but the constraint on rotation rate is stricter. Large-

464 

amplitude libration or nonsynchronous rotation would prevent the development of a deep pond around the substellar point. (A low-latitude liquid belt can be imagined, but the idealized EBM 

466 

of  §2 is not appropriate to that case). Kepler data show that only a small proportion of close-in small469 

allow for significant nonsynchronous rotation if the planet's spin rate adjusts to keep the substellar 

470 

point aligned with the star during periapse passage (pseudo-synchronous rotation). In addition, 

471 

SDF requires very soluble gases: by contrast, the N 2 content of even a 100km deep ocean at 298K 

472 

is only ∼0.2 bar per bar of atmospheric N 2 . In this paper we assume that volatiles are excluded 

473 

from the ice when the ice freezes. If clathrate phases form, they could absorb volatiles and make 

474 

the SDF irreversible. 

475 

5.2.2. Climate evolution into the unstable region 

476 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Roe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Climate</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4694</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Compilation of Henry&apos;s Law Constants for Inorganic and Organic Species of 670</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schlitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eos. Trans. AGU</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ewoce.org</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reviews of Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Segura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">706</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wordsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Forget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1051/0004-6361/201116654</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A accepted</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sleep</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17563</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sleep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ch.9.06 in Treatise on Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sleep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zahnle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1117/12.856559</idno>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7731</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">773127</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Atmospheric Circulation of Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Showman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J. Y-K</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page">680</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Exoplanets, U. Arizona Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hirschmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Withers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Geochim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Et Cosmochimica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Acta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1016/j.gca.2011.07.027</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">682</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear dynamics and chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Perseus Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Comptes Rendus de l&apos;Acadamie</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">335</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
