<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:23+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A New Empirical Constraint on the Prevalence of Technological Species in the Universe</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">-­-A</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>III</roleName><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><forename type="middle">W T</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A New Empirical Constraint on the Prevalence of Technological Species in the Universe</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this paper we address the cosmic frequency of technological species. Recent advances in exoplanet studies provide strong constraints on all astrophysical terms in the Drake Equation. Using these and modifying the form and intent of the Drake equation we show that we can set a firm lower bound on the probability that one or more additional technological species have evolved anywhere and at any time in the history of the observable Universe. We find that as long as the probability that a habitable zone planet develops a technological species is larger than ~10-­-24 , then humanity is not the only time technological intelligence has evolved. This constraint has important scientific and philosophical consequences.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We can generalize these results for structural scales (of size Rs) within the Universe: galaxies, cluster of galaxies, and superclusters of galaxies ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fukugita et al 2004)</ref>. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> provides typical values for these entities, and lists the corresponding values of fbt for each of them, as well as for the entire Universe. For instance, for our own Galaxy fbt is 1.7 x 10 -­-11 , meaning that another technical species has likely occurred in the history of the Milky Way if the probability of a technological species arising on a given planet in a habitable zone is greater than one in 60 billion.  <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. The number A of technological species that have ever occurred over the history of the Universe, versus the scale size Rs of different hierarchial structures in which their host stars are found: galaxies, clusters of galaxies, superclusters of galaxies, and the entire Universe. Reference values of A = 0.01, 1 and 100 are marked. The four curves represent different values of fbt , the probability of a technological species arising on a given habitable zone planet. Only if fbt falls as low as 2.5 x 10 -­-24 to 2.5 x 10 -­-22 is it likely that no other technological species has ever arisen in the entire Universe. some trajectories to collapse and others to long-­-term sustainability.</p><p>In conclusion we have shown that recent advances in astrobiology and exoplanet studies mean that an empirically derived lower limit can now be placed on the probability that even one other technological species has ever evolved in the Universe. This limit provides a framework for discussions of both life in its cosmic context and questions about trajectories of technological species relevant to our own issues of global sustainability.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>:</head><label></label><figDesc>We now turn to the specific question: "Has even one other technological species ever existed in the observable Universe?" We take N* = 2 x 10 22 for the total number of stars in the Universe (Silburt et al 2015) To address our question, A is set to a conservative value ensuring that Earth is the only location in the history of the cosmos where a technological civilization has ever evolved. Adopting A = 0.01 means that in a statistical sense were we to rerun the history of the Universe 100 times, only once would a lone technological species occur. A lower bound í µí± !" on the probability is then í µí± !" = A / Nast = 0.01 / 4 x 10 21 = 2.5 x 10 -­-24</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1 presents these results for given values of fbt . The figure allows one to see the corresponding number of technological species that have ever arisen on various scales for various assumptions of the difficulty of biology and technology to evolve.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Discussion and Conclusions:</head><label></label><figDesc>These results have wide implications. First, the long history of debate over extraterrestrial intelligence can be characterized as one of pessimists versus optimists relative to choices for the various factors in the Drake equation (Vakoch et al 2015) These debates have, however, been unconstrained in terms of how pessimistic one can be. With our approach we have, for the first time, provided a quantitative and empirically constrained limit on what it means to be pessimistic about the likelihood of another technological species ever having arisen in the history of the Universe. We have done so by segregating newly measured astrophysical factors from the fully unconstrained biotechnical ones, and by shifting the focus towards a question of "cosmic archaeology" and away from technological species lifetimes. Our constraint addresses an issue that is of particular scientific and philosophical consequence: the question "Have they ever existed?", rather than the usual narrower concern of the Drake equation, "Do they exist now?" Perhaps in the long term we should contemplate undertaking a field survey in cosmic archaeology, seeking possible evidence for such past technical species (Stevens et al 2015) Finally, we note that sample sizes A of order 100 or 1000 have a particular importance in current discussions over efforts to create a sustainable, energy-­- intensive, high-­-technology civilization here on Earth (Frank &amp; Sullivan 2014) Given the challenges human society faces from climate change, resource allocation, and loss of species diversity, it is not clear if the kind of long-­-term global culture we hope to build is even sustainable. However A &gt;100 in our formulation implies that the evolution of technological species has occurred enough times that the ensemble of their histories (or trajectories in a suitably defined phase space) is statistically meaningful . In particular, for large enough values of í µí± !" the average longevity &lt;L&gt; of such a sample of technological species does, in principle, exist. Thus if í µí± !" is such that A &gt; 1000, it is reasonable to consider that different versions of humanity's current technological experiment in the alteration of our planetary system has occurred before. Note that many aspects of the feedback between an energy intensive, technological species and their host planet would depend solely on physical processes and constraints (atmospheric chemistry changes, hydrological cycle distruptions, etc; Frank &amp; Sullivan 2014). Thus modeling ensembles of such species to understand the broad classifications of their planetary feedback histories is theoretically well-­-grounded for large enough values of í µí± !" . Such a project would be an attempt to understand both average properties like &lt;L&gt;, as well as what led</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Impey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Frontiers of Astrobiology</title>
		<editor>&amp; Funes, J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cambridge Univ. Pr.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Baross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Planets and Life: The Emerging Science of Astrobiology</title>
		<editor>J.A.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cambridge Univ. Pr.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Drake Equation: Estimating the Prevalence of Extraterrestrial Life through the Ages</title>
		<editor>Vakoch, D.A. &amp; Dowd, M.F.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cambridge Univ. Pr.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One or more bound planets per Milky Way star from microlensing observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">481</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of Earth-­-size planets orbiting sun-­-like stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Petigura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19273" to="19281" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstruction of the Planet Population around Kepler Stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Silburt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gaidos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">799</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cosmic energy inventory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fukugita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peebles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">616</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="643" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Observational signatures of self-­-destructive civilisations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Forgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>O&amp;apos;malley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ArXiv 1507.08530</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainability and the astrobiological perspective: Framing human futures in a planetary context</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anthropocene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
