<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:07+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">HAT-P-13: a multi-site campaign to detect the transit of the second planet in the system (Research Note)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010-09-19">19 Sep 2010 November 6, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gy</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Experimental Physics and Astronomical Observatory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Szeged</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H-6720</postCode>
									<settlement>Szeged</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Hungarian Eötvös Fellow</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 University Station</addrLine>
									<postCode>78712</postCode>
									<settlement>Austin</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kiss</surname></persName>
							<email>kiss@konkoly.hu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sydney Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Physics A28</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2006</postCode>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benk˝</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gy</forename><surname>Mez˝</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nuspl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>Regály</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sárneczky</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Experimental Physics and Astronomical Observatory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Szeged</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H-6720</postCode>
									<settlement>Szeged</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Leto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">INAF -Osservatorio Astrofisico di Catania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Santa Sofia 78</addrLine>
									<postCode>I-95123</postCode>
									<settlement>Catania</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zanmar Sanchez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">INAF -Osservatorio Astrofisico di Catania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Santa Sofia 78</addrLine>
									<postCode>I-95123</postCode>
									<settlement>Catania</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Ngeow</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate Institute of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Central University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>No. 300, Jhongda Rd, Jhongli City</addrLine>
									<postCode>32001</postCode>
									<region>Taoyuan County</region>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zs</forename><surname>K˝ Ovári</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Konkoly Observatory of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>PO Box 67</postBox>
									<postCode>H-1525</postCode>
									<settlement>Budapest</settlement>
									<country key="HU">Hungary</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">HAT-P-13: a multi-site campaign to detect the transit of the second planet in the system (Research Note)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2010-09-19">19 Sep 2010 November 6, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. hatp13.arxiv c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>stars: planetary systems -stars: individual: HAT-P-13</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Aims. A possible transit of HAT-P-13c has been predicted to occur on 2010 April 28. Here we report on the results of a multi-site campaign that has been organised to detect the event. Methods. CCD photometric observations have been carried out at five observatories in five countries. We reached 30% time coverage in a 5 days interval centered on the suspected transit of HAT-P-13c. Two transits of HAT-P-13b were also observed. Results. No transit of HAT-P-13c has been detected while the campaign was on. By a numerical experiment with 10 5 model systems we conclude that HAT-P-13c is not a transiting exoplanet with a significance level from 65% to 72%, depending on the planet parameters and the prior assumptions. We present two times of transit of HAT-P-13b ocurring at BJD 2455141.5522±0.0010 and BJD 2455249.4508 ± 0.0020. The TTV of HAT-P-13b is consistent with zero within 0.001 days. The refined orbital period of HAT-P-13b is 2.916293±0.000010 days.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Multiple planetary systems analogous to our Solar System play a key role in understanding planet formation and evolution. If planets in multiple systems display transits as well (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Kepler- 9, Holman et al. 2010</ref>), a very detailed analysis becomes possible, resulting in a set of dynamical parameters; and even the internal density distribution of the planets ( <ref type="bibr">Batyigin et al. 2009</ref>). As of this writing, three multiple systems with a transiting component have been discovered. The CoRoT-7 system has two orbiting super-Earths, one showing transits <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Léger et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr">(Léger et al. , Queloz et al. 2009</ref>); HAT-P-7 hosts a hot Jupiter in a polar or retrograde orbit and a long-period companion that can either be a planet or a star ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pál et al. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr">Pál et al. , Winn et al. 2009</ref>). But the most prominent example of such systems is HAT-P-13 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">, Winn et al. 2010</ref>). The central star of this system is a G4 dwarf with 1.22 M ⊙ mass and 1.56 R ⊙ radius. HAT-P-13b is a 0.85 M J hot Jupiter on a 2.9 day orbit that has almost been circularized. HAT-P-13c has a minimum mass of Msin i=15.2 M J in a 428 day orbit with 0.69 eccentricity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Winn et al. (2010)</ref> predicted a possible transit for the second planet, which, if confirmed, would make HAT-P-13 an extremely special system.</p><p>In multiple planetary systems, the most important question is whether the orbital planes are aligned. If this is the case for HAT-P-13 b and c, the exact mass of companion c can be derived. The ∆i mutual inclination may be derived from the Transit Timing Variations of HAT-P-13b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al. 2009)</ref>. A more stringent constraint on coplanarity would be delivered if HAT-P-13c also transits. In this case the coplanarity is highly probable, and the radius and the orbit of planet c can be measured. If the apsides are also aligned, tidal dynamics can reveal planet b's internal structure, which is a fascinating opportunity to extract unique information on an exoplanet ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Batygin et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr">, Fabricky 2009</ref>.</p><p>It has been unknown whether HAT-P-13c transits. Dynamical models of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Mardling (2010)</ref> suggest that the HAT-P-13 system is likely to be close to prograde coplanar or have a mutual inclination between 130 • and 135 • . She interpreted the system geometry as a result of early chaotic interactions. A hypothetical d companion has been invoked at the early stages of evolution that should have escaped later and could explain the vivid scattering history. Her argument for coplanarity is that lower masses are favoured because of dynamical reasons, although c's high inclination itself favours a large mutual inclination. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Winn et al. (2010)</ref> points to the observed small stellar obliquity ψ * ,b as an indirect evidence of orbital alignment: in Mardling's model, after having planet d escaped, ψ * ,b oscillates about a mean value of ∆i. Thus, observing small value for ψ * ,b at any time, e.g. now, is unlikely unless ∆i is small.</p><p>The refined orbital elements suggested that the transit -if it happened -should have occurred around 2010 April 28, 17 UT, (JD 2455315.2) with 1.9 days FWHM of transit probability and a maximal duration of 14.9 hours <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Winn, 2010)</ref>. We started mon-   itoring of HAT-P-13 for further transits in November 2009 and organised an international campaign in the 2 weeks surrounding the expected transit of HAT-P-13c.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Observations and Data Reduction</head><p>The seasonal visibility of HAT-P-13 is quite unfavourable in April. Hence the longest possible run at mid-northern latitudes may last 3-4 hours after twilight with observations ending at high (X&gt;2) airmass. Our data were collected at 5 observing sites with 6 telescopes, and, due to the weather conditions, 30% time coverage was reached. The telescope parameters and the log of the observations is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> and 2, respectively.</p><p>The observing strategy was the same in most observatories: a sequence of RRRVVV was repeated continuously, while Tenagra Observatory measured the first half of the light curve in R, and the second half in V. Integration time was adjusted all along the night to compensate for the air mass variation in an effort to take advantage of the full dynamic range of the camera. The average exposure time was about 65 s and 35 s in the V and R bands, respectively. Each night several bias, dark and sky flat images were taken for calibration.</p><p>Before the multisite campaign, we observed HAT-P-13 on 8 additional nights. Two nights <ref type="bibr">(2009-11-05/06 and 2010-02- 21/22</ref>) included a transit of HAT-P-13b, the rest acquired as out-of-transit observations. In these observations, the K100 telescope was also involved. No transit signal exceeding a depth of 0.005 (3-sigma level) was observed during the following outof-transit observation runs Transits of HAT-P-13b were analyzed with an automated image processing and aperture photometry pipeline developed in gnu-r 1 environment. The flat image was constructed as the median of the normailzed flat frames (i.e. each acquired images were divided by the mean of their pixel values), and that similar procedures were performed for darks and bias. After the standard calibrations, star identification was performed. Comparison stars were selected iteratively for attaining the best S/N in the light curve. Finally, 3 comparison stars were used in all images (2MASS J08392449+4723225, 2 MASS J08392164+4720500, 2MASS J08391779+4722238), to ensure the consistency of the entire dataset. J − K colors of the comparison stars are 0.419, 0.384 and 0.337, quite close to J − K = 0.353 of HAT-P-13.</p><p>The data were corrected for systematics with the wellknown parameter decorrelation technique (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Robinson et al. 1995)</ref>, in our case applying the specific implementation of the External Parameter Decorrelation (EPD) in constant mode ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bakos et al. 2010</ref>). The observed external parameters were the PSF of stellar profiles and the local photometry of the flat field image at the same X, Y position where the stars were observed. The variation of stellar profile is a known error source which has been involved in most standard reduction pipelines of exoplanet photometry. Considering the flat field image intensities as an error source means assuming that dividing with the flat field under/overestimates the neccessary correction by a factor of a few 0.1%. We experienced that most of the artificial patterns of 1 r-project.org the light curves is due to systematic residuals of flat field correction and could be well eliminated this way. In the end, 6585 raw photometric points were extracted. We omitted points out of the 5-95% quantile interval of the measured fluxes and averaged the surviving points by 3. This resulted in 1952 data points submitted to further analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Significance analysis of the null detection</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> we plot sample light curves from the multisite campaign. The panels show the combined light curves from <ref type="bibr">April 26, 27, 28, 29 and 30</ref>. Neither signs of ingress or egress nor significant deviations from the average brightness have been observed. These features strongly suggest that all observations are out of transit, and HAT-P-13c is likely to be a non-transiting exoplanet.</p><p>What is the significance of this conclusion? The time coverage of our data is 30%. Thus the first answer could be that a transit could happen anytime in 70% of the time, i.e. when observations were not done, and this null result is essentially insignificant. But this conclusion is not correct and in fact, our observations rule out the majority of transiting orbits for HAT-P-13c.</p><p>We did a numerical experiment to determine the quantitative measure of the significance. A set of 10 5 exoplanets were simulated on a similar orbit to HAT-P-13 (428 days period around an 1.22 R ⊙ , 1.56 R ⊙ star). The radius of the planet was assumed to be 1.2 R J , which is the typical size for the most massive known exoplanets. With this choice, the density of HAT-P-13c is 8.7 times of the Jupiter. The orbital eccentricity of the model was e = 0.691, the argument of periastron was ω = 176.7 • , coefficients for quadratic limb darkening were γ 1 = 0.3060, γ 2 = 0.3229 (planet and orbit parameters from <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al. 2009</ref>). To include grazing transits, the value of the impact parameter b was allowed to be &gt; 1 and was drawn from an uniform distibution between 0 and 1.08. The transit time followed a uniform distribution in the April 26.5 UT and April 30.5 UT interval. In some possible planet configurations it is probable that data of a given run could have included only the bottom of the transit. This should be seen as a slight offset from the rest of the runs, but that this cannot be detected because of non-photometric conditions. What we are sure about is that ingress and egress phases were not detected within our time coverage. Solely this information constrains the possible orbits seriously in the transit time-impact parameter space.</p><p>Model transit light curves were sampled at the times of observation points (all data in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>), sorted to observation runs and the average level was individually subtracted. We added bootstrap noise to the individual points (the measured light curve errors were randomly added to the simulated values with subtitution). Then a χ 2 test was applied to check whether the simulations are inconsistent with zero at the 99% significance level. This way we identified those configurations of HATP-P-13c which should have been observed in our measurements (we call these observable configurations in the following). Because our observations are consistent with zero variation, observable configurations are explicitelly excluded by our data.</p><p>We identified that 72% of the 10 5 model transit configurations would have been observable. Therefore the hypothesis of HAT-P-13c to be a transiting exoplanet can be rejected with 72% confidence. By allowing the mean transit times to be distributed normally around April 28 17 UT with 1.9 days standard deviation, the level of significance turns out to be 70%. The level of significance does not vary significantly in the range of orbits allowed by the parameter uncertainties in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al (2009)</ref>, because the errors are rather small (3% in e and 0.3% in ω). We reduced the model light curves in amplitude to define the size limit where the detection efficiency starts decreasing significantly. The resulting significance was 65% when the amplitude was reduced by 0.45. The planet size corresponding to this signal amplitude is 1.04 R J , which is our detection limit. The conclusion is that roughly three quaters of all possible transiting configurations are excluded by our observations. This result does not mean that HAT-P-13c could not orbit on an aligned orbit with HAT-P-13b. HAT-P-13c is quite far from the central star, hence the star's apparent diameter is 0.6 degrees as seen from the planet. Thus, transiting configurations require the orbit to be in a thin region, very close to our line of sight. There is a huge set of configurations with HAT-P-13c on an orbit close to that of planet b, without displaying any transits. In this case, Transit Timing Variation (TTV) of HAT-P-13b can reveal the orientation of HAT-P-13c's orbital plane ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al. 2009</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Transit Timing Variations of HAT-P-13b</head><p>Before the suspected transit of HAT-P-13c, two transits of HAT-P-13b were observed to refine the period and to search for  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>) and 2010-02-21/22 (K60 telescope) are plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig 2.</ref> In November (upper panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>), the sky was photometric during the transit, but it was foggy in the evening and from 40 minutes after the egress phase. In February, 2010, cirri were present that significantly affected the V band data, but the R light curve was well reconstructed with constant EPD (see lower panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2)</ref>.</p><p>Times of minima were determined by fitting a model light curve, similarly to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Szabó et al. (2010)</ref>. For the November 2009 transit, both V and R data were included in the fitting, while we used only the R curve for the February 2010 transit. (However, even including the more noisy V curve does not change the midtransit time by more than 0.0004 days.)</p><p>To reduce the degrees of freedom in the fit, the shape of the model was not adjusted; we used previously published parameters ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Winn et al. 2010)</ref>. The model light curve was calculated with our transit simulator ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Simon et al. 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon et al. , 2010</ref>. The model was shifted in time, minimising the rms scatter of the measurements. We determined new transit times as: BJD 2455141.5522±0.001 and 2455249.4508±0.002. Seven transit times were published by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bakos et al. (2009)</ref> which were included in the TTV analysis. Combining all data, we refined the period of HAT-P-13b to be 2.916293±0.000010 days, while the determined TTV diagram is plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>. All points are consistent with zero within the error bars. It has to be noted that HAT-P-13b must exhibit some TTV, because of the perturbations by HAT-P-13c. HAT-P-13c causes 8.5 s light-time effect (LITE) and perturbations in the orbit of HAT-P-13b. On short (≈1 yr) time scales, the LITE is dominant. But the expected LITE is smaller than the ambiguity of our transit times by a factor of 5, and therefore there is no chance for a positive detection at this level of accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary</head><p>-A multisite campaign has been organised to observe HAT-P-13 around the expected transit of HAT-P-13c. Two transits of HAT-P-13b were also observed. -HAT-P-13c was not observed to transit. We concluded that HAT-P-13c is not a transiting planet with 75% significance. -The refined period of HAT-P-13b is 2.916293±0.000010 days. The determined TTV is consistent with zero variation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Observations of HAT-P-13 between April 26-30. Observations are shifted with +0.01 (V points) and −0.01 (R points) as indicated. Different symbols are applied for the different observatories: square: Langkawi, stars: Konkoly, triangles: INAF-OACt, circle: Tenagra. The typical standard deviation is 0.0013 in R and 0.0014 in V. A ±0.0015 error bar is indicated in the upper right corner of the top panel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>: 2009-11-05/06, 23:03-03:45 UT (1 RCC), 2010-01-11/12, 01:41-04:29 (1 RCC), 2010-01-14/15, 21:41-23:19 (0.6 Schmidt), 2010-01-16/17, 22:20-03:39 (0.6 Schmidt), 2010-02-21/22, 18:32-02:19 (0.6 Schmidt), 2010- 03-18/19, 19:08-00:03 (0.6 Schmidt), 2010-03-18/19, 20:08- 23:37 (1 RCC) 2010-03-19/20, 21:38-00:11 (0.6 Schmidt), 2010-03-28/29, 18:30-00:16 (0.6 Schmidt).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Model fit to the transit on November 05/06, 2009 (upper panel) and February 21/22, 2010 (lower panel). V and R band data are plotted with open and soild dots, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Transit Timing Variation of HAT-P-13b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Code Telescope 
CCD 
FoV 
resolution 
K60 
Konkoly 0.6 Schmidt, Piszkéstet˝ o, Hungary 1526×1024 KAF 
25 ′ ×17 ′ 
1.0 ′′ /pixel 
K100 Konkoly 1.0 RCC, Piszkéstet˝ o, Hungary 
1340×1300 PI VersArray 1300b NTE 7 ′ ×7 ′ 
0.32 ′′ /pixel 
SLN 
INAF-OACt 0.91, Fracastoro, Italy 
1100×1100 KAF1001E 
13 ′ ×13 ′ 
0.77 ′′ /pixel 
TEN 
0.8 RCC Tenagra II, Arizona, USA 
1024×1024 
14.8 ′ ×14.8 ′ 0.81 ′′ /pixel 
LNO Langkawi 0.5 RCC, Malaysia 
1024×1024 SBIG 1001E CCD 
20 ′ ×20 ′ 
1.2 ′′ /pixel 
SLT 
Lulin 0.4 RCC, Taiwan 
3056×3056 Apogee U9000 
50.7 ′ ×50.7 ′ 0.99 ′′ /pixel 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Observations during the HAT-P-13c campaign. Telescope codes: K60: Konkoly 60 cm Schmidt, TEN: Tenagra, SLT: Lulin, 
LNO: Langkawi, SLN: INAF-OACt. Observation windows and the number of photometry points are indicated. 

Date 
K60 
TEN 
SLT 
LNO 
SLN 
2010-04-22 20:23-22:23 (80) 
04-25 18:40-23:33 (190) 
03:01-05:17 (101) 
12:17-15:03 (108) 
04-26 18:43-21:27 (134) 
04:44-07:01 (100) 
14:28-14:56 (34) 
04-27 
03:10-05:26 (85) 
20:46-23:56 (162) 
04-28 18:41-22:53 (139) 
05:30-06:52 (61) 
13:34-14:55 (23) 20:37-00:08 (116) 
04-29 18:45-23:15 (349) 
04:55-06:49 (84) 
13:42-15:32 (58) 20:53-23:58 (128) 
04-30 18:43-23:17 (342) 
04:55-06:55 (51) 
05-01 19:21-20:32 (66) 
05:39-06:17 (45) 
11:48-14:16 (55) 
12:42-14:45 (60) 
05-03 19:25-22:50 (252) 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">707</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">446</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">710</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1724</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Batygin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Laughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">704</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Transiting Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>E. Pont, D. Sasselov, M. J. Holman</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">173</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">DOI:10.1126/sci-ence.1195778</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-08-26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Léger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">287</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mardling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pál</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4079</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1450</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">303</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1094</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EM&amp;P</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">385</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2038</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gy</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Szabó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">IBVS</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5919</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">703</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">718</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">575</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
