<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:35+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Lowest Earth&apos;s atmosphere layers probed during a lunar eclipse</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-10-21">21 Oct 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kiyoe</forename><surname>Kawauchi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-12-1 Ookayama, Meguro-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>152-8551</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Norio</forename><surname>Narita</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-0033</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">National Astronomical Observatory of Japan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1 Osawa</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-8588</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitaka</settlement>
									<region>Tokyo</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Astrobiology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NINS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1 Osawa</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-8588</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitaka</settlement>
									<region>Tokyo</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bun&amp;apos;ei Sato</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-12-1 Ookayama, Meguro-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>152-8551</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Teruyuki</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-12-1 Ookayama, Meguro-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>152-8551</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yui</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Earth and Planetary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Graduate School of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7-3-1 Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-0033</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Earth-Life Science Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-12-1 Ookayama, Meguro-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>152-8550</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Taishi</forename><surname>Nakamoto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tokyo Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-12-1 Ookayama, Meguro-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>152-8551</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Takuya</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-0033</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">National Astronomical Observatory of Japan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1 Osawa</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-8588</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitaka</settlement>
									<region>Tokyo</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Motohide</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-0033</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">National Astronomical Observatory of Japan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1 Osawa</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-8588</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitaka</settlement>
									<region>Tokyo</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Astrobiology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NINS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1 Osawa</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-8588</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitaka</settlement>
									<region>Tokyo</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Lowest Earth&apos;s atmosphere layers probed during a lunar eclipse</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-10-21">21 Oct 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received reception date; Accepted acception date</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>planets and satellites: atmospheres -Earth -eclipses</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We report the results of detailed investigation of the Earth&apos;s transmission spectra during the lunar eclipse on UT 2011 December 10. The spectra were taken by using the High Dispersion Spectrograph (HDS) mounted on the Subaru 8.2 m telescope with unprecedented resolutions both in time and wavelength (300 s exposure time in umbra and 160,000 spectral resolution, respectively). In our penumbra and umbra data, we detected the individual absorption lines of O 2 and H 2 O in transmission spectra and found that it became deeper as the eclipse became deeper. It indicates that the sunlight reaching the Moon passed through lower layers in the Earth&apos;s atmosphere with time because we monitored a given point on the Moon during the full eclipse duration. From the comparison between the observed and theoretically constructed 1 transmission spectra, the lowest altitude at which the sunlight actually passed through the atmosphere is estimated to be about 10 km from the ground, which suggests the existence of sunlight blocking clouds below that altitude. Our result would be a test case for future investigations of atmospheric structure of Earth-like exoplanets via transmission spectroscopy including the refraction effect of the planetary atmosphere.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Observations</head><p>We observed a total lunar eclipse on UT 2011 December 10 with the Subaru 8.2 m telescope and the High Dispersion Spectrograph (HDS; <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Noguchi et al. 2002)</ref>, which is placed at a Nasmyth focus. The wavelength range was set to cover 5500-8200Å8200˚8200Å, which is a non-standard format of HDS, and the slit width was set to 0.2" corresponding to a spectral resolution (R = λ/∆λ) of ∼160,000. This resolving power is higher than those of the previous works.</p><p>We started to observe the Moon prior to the eclipse and terminated the observation in the middle of the eclipse. We alternately obtained a series of spectra of the sunlight reflected by two points of the lunar surface; one is Ocean of Storms (Point A) and the other is Sea of Fertility (Point B) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2</ref>). Reflectance difference of these two points is known to be small, corresponding to less hubby regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Wilhelms &amp; McCauley 1971)</ref>. On point A, we took a total of 13 exposures of 30 s prior to the eclipse (i.e. full-Moon), 10 exposures of 30-300s in penumbra, and 5 exposures of 300s in umbra. On point B, we took a total of 15 exposures of 30 s prior to the eclipse (i.e. full-Moon), 6 exposures of 100-300 s in penumbra, and 11 exposures of 300 s in umbra. The sequence of the observations is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>.  We here note that the light reaching the observation point comes from an arc of the Earth's limb seen from the Moon. We found that the point which the sunlight passes in the Earth's atmosphere is over the region from the center of Southern Indian ocean (∼ 20 • S, 80 • E) to the Northern coast of Antarctica (∼ 65 • S, 100 • E) at the time of our run. The calculation method of the longitude and latitude at each time is described in APPENDIX 1 and these results are specified in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The reduction of echelle data (i.e., bias subtraction, flat-fielding, scattered-light subtraction, spectrum extraction, and wavelength calibration with Th-Ar spectra) was performed using the IRAF 1 software package in the standard way. The reduced spectra of full-Moon, Penumbra and Umbra have SNRs of ∼ 173, ∼ 89 and ∼ 60 per pixel, respectively. These SNR values (for point A at least) are probably biased by light scattered from the bright moon (Penumbra or full-Moon) and that it is discussed in Section 5.1.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">✁ ✂ ✄ ☎ ✆ ✝ ✞ ✟ ✠ ✡ ☛ ☞ ✌ ✍ ✎ ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★ ✩ ✪ ✫ ✬ ✭ ✮ ✯</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Extraction of Telluric Transmission Spectra</head><p>A lunar-eclipse spectrum is composed of three kinds of spectra: solar spectrum S(λ, t), telluric transmission spectrum T 1 (λ, t), and telluric spectrum above a telescope T 2 (λ, t) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). Since we are interested in telluric transmission spectrum T 1 (λ, t), we need to eliminate the unnecessary spectra (T 2 (λ, t) and S(λ, t)) from the lunar-eclipse spectrum.</p><p>3.1 Eliminating T 2 (λ, t)</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">3.1.1 A Template Spectrum of T2(λ, t)</formula><p>We used a high-resolution spectrum of the rapid rotator HR8634 (B8V, v sin i =185 kms −1 ; Glebocki et al. 2000), which was taken on the same night as the lunar-eclipse observations, as a template of T 2 .</p><p>Since the star is rapidly rotating, stellar absorption lines in the spectrum are largely broadened and the spectrum is almost featureless. Thus the spectrum basically conveys only the telluric spectrum above a telescope, and we can use it as a template of T 2 . HR8634 is also known to have fewer interstellar absorption lines, which makes the star an appropriate target for this purpose. Using this obtained template spectrum, we next evaluate the dependence of T 2 (λ,t) on airmass and wavelength shift of T 2 in order to match the template spectrum with actual T 2 in lunar-eclipse spectra.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Airmass Variation</head><p>T 2 (λ, t) is dependent on airmass, AM (= sec(z); z is zenith distance). Assuming the plane parallel atmosphere of the Earth, T 2 can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T 2 (λ, t) = T 2 (λ, t 0 ) AM/AM 0 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where T 2 (λ,t 0 ) is the template spectrum taken at time t 0 and airmass AM 0 , and T 2 (λ,t) is an expected telluric spectrum above a telescope taken at time t and airmass AM assuming that T 2 was constant for the rest of the night. Based on that relation, we can estimate line depth of T 2 inherent to each lunar-eclipse spectrum. The time variation of the precipitable water vapour (PWV) can cause the depth variation in H 2 O absorption lines. This effect, however, is negligible in this case as the value of PWV obtained from the data of Caltech Submillimeter Observatory 2 is small and has little change during observation (PWV ∼ 0.64 -1.70 mm).</p><p>We adopted a high-S/N spectrum of HR8634 as T 2 (λ, t 0 ), which was obtained by averaging 8 spectra of the star taken prior to the lunar eclipse in a short period of time with negligible change in airmass &lt; 0.02. The mean time and airmass were 8:35 UT and 1.03, respectively, which were attributed to the T 2 (λ, t 0 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Wavelength shift</head><p>Variations of absorption lines in T 2 (λ, t) are found not only in line depth but also in wavelength of the lines. The wavelength variation can be caused by wind in the atmosphere, error of wavelength calibration, instability of the spectrograph, and so on. The Earth's rotation velocity is about 0.5 kms −1 . The wavelength variation caused by the velocity (Doppler shift) is about ± 0.0055Å0055˚0055Å at a wavelength of 6000Å6000˚6000Å. The typical error of wavelength calibration is about 0.0011Å0011˚0011Å for HDS and there could also be temporal variation due to instrumental instability. Unfortunately, we cannot discriminate among these causes, and cannot directly derive the wavelength shift in umbra spectra since the telluric transmission spectrum T 1 is easily confused with T 2 in umbra spectra.</p><p>Alternatively, we estimated wavelength shifts of T 2 in umbra spectra by using those in the full-Moon spectra taken outside of the eclipse. We measured wavelength shifts of telluric O 2 lines between 6306.45Å45˚45Å and 6306.66Å66˚66Å in full-Moon and Penumbra spectra relative to those in the template T 2 , and tried to extrapolate the values in umbra by using polynomials. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> shows the derived wavelength variations of T 2 together with the fitted polynomials as a function of time and these results are specified in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. We found that all the polynomials gave reasonable estimates of the wavelength shifts in umbra for Point A, but this was not the case with Point B. Thus we adopted the values derived by a quintic equation for Point A, and the value of -0.1 kms −1 , which is the average of the 4 data closest to umbra, for Point B. These choices of the fitting functions have less impact on the subsequent analyses and results.   orange, green, and blue lines are the best-fit quintic, quartic, cubic, and quadratic curves to the black pluses, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Eliminating S(λ, t)</head><p>A full-Moon spectrum from which T 2 (λ, t) is eliminated is equivalent to solar spectrum S(λ, t) assuming the moon has a perfect flat reflectance spectrum. The effect of the moon characteristic can be negligible as our observation points has little reflection characteristic. We obtain T 1 (λ, t) by dividing the T 2 -eliminated lunar-eclipse spectrum by S(λ, t). In practice the wavelength of S(λ, t) temporally varies according to the mutual velocities of the Sun, Earth, and Moon. Thus we correct the variations by measuring wavelength shifts of some unblended solar absorption lines in 6260.93-6261.25Å 25˚25Å, 6327.39-6327.78Å78˚78Å, and 6470.5-6472.5 ˚ A, relative to the full-Moon spectrum <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">(Table 3)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 6</ref> and 8 show resultant T 2 -and S-eliminated full-Moon and lunar-eclipse spectra. We successfully eliminated S from the spectra well below the signal level of T 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">O 2 and H 2 O transmission spectrum</head><p>Figure 9 and 10 show thus extracted T 1 spectra of penumbra, and umbra. We can clearly see O 2</p><p>absorption lines in 6275-6330Å6330˚6330Å, and H 2 O absorption lines in 5870-5930Å5930˚5930Å and 6465-6495Å6495˚6495Å. We can also see that the absorption lines become deeper as the eclipse becomes deeper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Model Spectra</head><p>We found that the telluric transmission spectra vary in depth with time. This is because we see the sunlight passing through a lower-altitude region in the Earth's atmosphere as the eclipse becomes deeper. In order to evaluate the variations quantitatively, we construct theoretical transmission spectra of the Earth and compare them with the observed ones.             </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">☞ ✌ ✍ ✎ ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">✷ ✸ ✹ ✺ ✻ ✼ ✽ ✾ ✿ ❀ ❁ ❂ ❃ ❄ ❅ ❆ ❇ ❈ ❉ ❊ ❋ • ❍ ■ ❏ ❑ ▲ ▼ ◆ ❖  ◗ | ❙ ❚ ❯ ❱ ❲ ❳ ❨ ❩ ❬ ❭ ❪ ❫ ❴ ❵ ❛ ❜ ❝ ❞ ❡ ❢ ❣ ❤ ✐ • ❦ • ♠ ♥ ♦ ♣ q r s t ✉ ✈ ✇ ① ② ③ ④ ⑤ ⑥ ⑦ ⑧ ⑨ ⑩ ❶ ❷ ❸ ❹ ❺ ❻ ❼ ❽ ❾ ❿ ➀ ➁ ➂</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">☞ ✌ ✍ ✎ ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">✷ ✸ ✹ ✺ ✻ ✼ ✽ ✾ ✿ ❀ ❁ ❂ ❃ ❄ ❅ ❆ ❇ ❈ ❉ ❊ ❋ • ❍ ■ ❏ ❑ ▲ ▼ ◆ ❖  ◗ | ❙ ❚ ❯ ❱ ❲ ❳ ❨ ❩ ❬ ❭ ❪ ❫ ❴ ❵ ❛ ❜ ❝ ❞ ❡ ❢ ❣ ❤ ✐ • ❦ • ♠ ♥ ♦ ♣ q r s t ✉ ✈ ✇ ① ② ③ ④ ⑤ ⑥ ⑦ ⑧ ⑨ ⑩ ❶ ❷ ❸ ❹ ❺ ❻ ❼ ❽ ❾ ❿ ➀ ➁ ➂ ➃ ➄ ➅ ➆ ➇ ➈</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">Wavelength (✁) 6450 ✂ ☎ ✆ ✝ ✞ ✟ ✠ ✡ ☛ ☞ ✌ ✍ ✎ ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★ ✩ ✪ ✫ ✬ ✭ ✮ ✯ ✰ ✱ ✲ ✳ ✴ ✵ ✶ ✷ ✸ ✹ ✺ ✻ ✼ ✽ ✾ ✿ ❀ ❁ ❂ ❃ ❄ ❅ ❆ ❇ ❈ ❉ ❊ ❋ • ❍ ■ ❏ ❑ ▲ ▼ ◆ ❖  ◗ |</formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">Wavelength (✎) ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★ ✩ ✪ ✫ ✬ ✭ ✮ ✯ ✰ ✱ ✲ ✳ ✴ ✵ ✶ ✷ ✸ ✹ ✺ ✻ ✼ ✽ ✾ ✿ ❀ ❁ ❂ ❃ ❄ ❅ ❆ ❇ ❈ ❉ ❊ ❋ • ❍ ■ ❏ ❑ ▲ ▼ ◆ ❖  ◗ | ❙ ❚ ❯ ❱ ❲ ❳</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Altitude</head><p>The lowest surface altitude of the Earth's atmosphere, z min , through which the sunlight passes towards the Moon can be calculated from the positional relation between the Sun, Earth, and observation point on the lunar surface by using the Geometric Pinhole Model <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Vollmer &amp; Gedzelman 2008)</ref>.</p><p>However, the model only works for umbra (not penumbra), and assumes that the refraction angle in the Earth's atmosphere is 70 arcmin for z min = 0 km. The value is based on analytical approximation, but in fact it is not valid in the case of such a small z min (i.e. large refraction angle).</p><p>Alternatively we calculate z min for both umbra and penumbra with use of the 4th order Runge Kutta method following <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Tsumura et al. (2014)</ref>. However, as the sun has a finite size, the sunlight that passes the minimum altitude actually illuminates a finite area, ω, on the lunar surface ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>). The area can be considered to be circular because of the projection of the Sun. In this case, we can estimate the range of d whose corresponding ω include the observation point with various position angle φ <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 11</ref>) using the same method as the pinhole model. The minimum and the maximum d is calculated as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">d max,min (φ) = d 0 · cos φ ± r 2 − (d 0 sin φ) 2 ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where d 0 is the distance between the center of the Earth shadow and the observation point, and r is the radius of the Earth shadow on the lunar surface. The d max and d min are converted into the maximum and minimum of z min , respectively, by using the relation presented in the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. ing time. In this figure, we can see that (1) the sunlight reaching the observation point is transmitted through lower layers of the Earth's atmosphere with time, (2) the sunlight that is transmitted through the opposite side with respective to the Earth center also reaches the observation point at the middle of the eclipse, and (3) the bottom of the range of z min is not 0 km but 1.8 km <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 4</ref>) due to refraction.</p><p>We can also see that the sunlight passed through the similar layers of the atmosphere for point A and B. However, the line depth of the transmission spectrum for point A is much shallower than that for point B <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">(Figure 9</ref>). We discuss this difference in section 5.1. </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">✁ ✂ ✄ ☎ ✆ ✝ ✞ ✟ ✠ ✡ ☛ ☞ ✌ ✍ ✎ ✏ ✑ ✒ ✓ ✔ ✕ ✖ ✗ ✘ ✙ ✚ ✛ ✜ ✢ ✣ ✤ ✥ ✦ ✧ ★ ✩ ✪ ✫ ✬ ✭ ✮ ✯ ✰ ✱ ✲ ✳ ✴ ✵ ✶ ✷ ✸ ✹ ✺ ✻ ✼ ✽ ✾ ✿ ❀ ❁ ❂ ❃ ❄ ❅ ❆ ❇ ❈ ❉ ❊ ❋ • ❍ ■ ❏ ❑ ▲ ▼ ◆ ❖  ◗ | ❙ ❚ ❯ ❱ ❲ ❳ ❨ ❩ ❬ ❭ ❪ ❫ ❴ ❵ ❛ ❜ ❝ ❞ ❡ ❢ ❣ ❤ ✐ • ❦ • ♠ ♥ ♦ ♣ q r s t ✉ ✈ ✇ ① ② ③ ④ ⑤ ⑥ ⑦ ⑧ ⑨ ⑩ ❶ ❷ ❸ ❹ ❺ ❻ ❼ ❽ ❾ ❿ ➀ ➁ ➂ ➃ ➄ ➅ ➆ ➇ ➈ ➉ ➊ ➋ ➌ ➍ ➎ ➏ ➐ ➑ ➒ ➓ ➔ → ➣ ↔ ↕ ➙ ➛ ➜ ➝ ➞ ➟ ➠ ➡ ➢ ➤ ➥ ➦ ➧ ➨ ➩ ➫ ➭ ➯ ➲ ➳ ➵</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Creating modeled spectrum</head><p>A theoretical transmission spectrum (T 1 (λ, t)) is obtained from the Beer-Lambert law: </p><formula xml:id="formula_11">T 1 (λ, t) = e − (u·σ)dx ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where u, σ and x are the number density, cross section of each species and path length in the atmosphere, respectively. Hereafter we only calculate O 2 absorption lines because H 2 O absorption lines largely depend on the climate variation in the transmitted atmosphere. The O 2 absorption line (T 1O 2 (z min )) made by the light passing at an altitude z min is expressed as;</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">T 1O 2 (z min ) = e − (u O 2 (z)·σ O 2 (z))dx ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where u O 2 (z) and σ O 2 (z) are the number density and cross section of O 2 in the atmosphere, respectively, and the summation in the exponent is taken along the ray.</p><p>The cross section has been developed with the rational polynomial of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kuntz (1997)</ref> which is revised by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ruyten (2003)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">γ D = ν 2kT mc 2 ≈ 7.6 · 10 −8 ν T [K] (m = 32 amu),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where k is Boltzmann's constant and c is speed of light.</p><p>Number density is calculated from the equation of state using temperature (T ), pressure (P )</p><p>and O 2 abundance at each point along the ray. As the cross section and number density depend on T and P , these values are calculated at each altitude assuming the vertical structure of Earth atmosphere based on the MIPAS model. As T , P , and molecule abundance are given for every 1 km in height from 0 to 120 km from the surface in the MIPAS model, we calculate the number density every km.</p><p>The number density at an arbitrary altitude is obtained by linear interpolation between these values.</p><p>We divide the ray into small segments and calculate z, u, σ and x for each segment. Then we take summation of the product of u, σ and x along the ray, and obtain the transmission spectrum as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">T 1O 2 (z min ) = e − i u O 2 (z i )·σ O 2 (z i )·∆x(z i ) ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where z i is the altitude of the i-th segment and ∆x(z i ) is the length of the i-th segment.</p><p>Then, we also consider O 3 absorption and O 2 · O 2 Collision Induced Absorption (CIA), which contribute to the spectra at broad band wavelength, around the O 2 absorption lines (6275-6330Å6330˚6330Å) and</p><p>Rayleigh scattering which prevents all sun light from passing through the lowest layer of Earths atmosphere. We calculate these transmission spectra by combining each cross section and number density along the ray. The cross sections of O 3 for various temperatures (193K -293K in steps of 10K)</p><p>are taken from the ASCII data at IUP Bremen ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gorshelev et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Serdyuchenko et al. 2014</ref>).</p><p>According to these data, O 3 absorption cross section has only little temperature dependence at our observational waveband (Chappuis band). Therefore, we use the cross section for 223K, which corresponds to the altitude where the number density of O 3 reaches a maximum in the Earth's atmosphere.</p><p>The number density is calculated from the equation of state using temperature (T ), pressure (P ) and O 3 abundance. The O 2 · O 2 absorption cross sections are taken from HITRAN database ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Richard et al. 2012</ref>).</p><p>For Rayleigh scattering, we utilize the number density of all particles in the atmosphere and the cross section of the Rayleigh scattering for the Earth's atmosphere from <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bodhaine et al. 1999</ref>;</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">σ Rayleigh = 1.054 − 341.29λ −2 − 0.9023λ 2 1 + 0.002706λ −2 − 87.9686λ 2 (×10 −28 cm 2 ),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where λ is in µm.</p><p>Finally, we calculate all the transmission spectra attributed to the various rays that reach the observation point on the lunar surface, and integrate them weighted by the limb darkening (quadratic law; u1 = 0.5524, u2 = 0.3637) on the solar disk. The synthetic spectrum thus obtained is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>. As seen in the figure, it is deeper and wider than the observed one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>We conducted spectroscopic observations of a eclipse using Subaru/HDS with higher resolutions in time and wavelength than previous works. As a result, we successfully detected temporal variations in individual absorption lines of O 2 and H 2 O in Earth's transmission spectra.</p><p>The lines, however, show large difference in depth between those obtained at Point A and Point B as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9</ref>. Furthermore, there is apparently a discrepancy between observed and synthetic transmission spectra as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>. We discuss these issues in the following sections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Transmission spectra at Points A and B</head><p>We alternately observed Points A and B during the lunar eclipse, and obtained a series of telluric transmission spectra for each point. As clearly seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 9</ref>, the depth of absorption lines in the transmission spectra largely differs between the two points despite the fact that the sunlight passed through nearly the same atmospheric layers of the Earth before reaching the lunar surface ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref>).</p><p>Considering the fact that the difference is not seen in the solar spectra S but in the transmission spectra Actually, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>, Point A is ahead of the rest of the lunar surface toward the shadow of the Earth. Therefore, when Point A enters into the Earth shadow, the rest of the lunar surface, which is a part of the full-Moon, is still bright. On the other hand, Point B is located at the back end edge of the lunar surface, and thus the rest of the lunar surface is already faint in the shadow when Point B enters into the shadow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Comparison between observed and modeled transmission spectra</head><p>In this section, we deal with the transmission spectra obtained at both points in umbra. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> shows a comparison between the observed and the synthetic transmission spectrum of O 2 (section 4.2). As seen in the figure, the synthetic absorption line is deeper and wider than observed one. Considering that the observed spectrum may be affected by background scattered light, we first adjusted the line depth of the synthetic spectrum by adding a constant to it and renormalizing it to the continuum level. However, the width of the absorption line still shows discrepancy between the observed and the modeled spectrum. We discuss possible causes of the discrepancy in more details below.  Observation Spectra Model Spectra The first one is uncertainty in the adopted vertical structure of the Earth's atmosphere. We used that of mid-latitude of MIPAS model since the lowest altitude at which the sunlight passed is from the center of Southern Indian ocean to the Northern coast of Antarctica. However, the actual region where the sunlight passed through is much wider (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12)</ref>. In order to evaluate how the vertical structure affects the resultant transmission spectrum, we tested five different thermal structure models; polar-winter, polar-summer, and equatorial model of MIPAS, and mid-latitude summer and subarctic-summer model of FASCODE/ICRCCM ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Clough et al. 1992)</ref>. As a result, the vertical structures cannot account for the difference between the modeled and observed spectrum.</p><p>The second possibility is uncertainty in the model spectrum. HITRAN has the uncertainty of intensity, air-broadened half-width, self-broadened half-width, and the coefficient for the temperaturedependence of the air-broadened half-width. In our observational wavelength, the uncertainty range of intensity is 5-10% and that of air-broadened half-width, self-broadened half-width, and the coefficient for the temperature-dependence of the air-broadened half-width is 10-20% or over 20%. The uncertainty in final model spectra caused by the factors described above was shown by <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>.</p><p>This shows that we cannot explain the difference between model and observation by the uncertainty in HITRAN database. We omit the absorption lines which has the uncertainty range of over 20%</p><p>in HITRAN database from following discussion since we cannot estimate uncertainty in final model spectra.</p><p>Furthermore, in order to validate our calculation of the model spectrum, we tried to reproduce T 2 spectra, telluric spectra above the telescope, which are extracted from spectra of rapid rotators (section 3.1.1.). As a result, the modeled T 2 spectra are well matched with the observed ones ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 14)</ref>, and thus the uncertainty in the model spectra cannot account for the discrepancy, either.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model Spectra</head><p>Observation spectra Finally, we consider effect of clouds on transmission spectra. If clouds exist in the atmosphere, the sunlight may be blocked by the clouds and cannot reach the lunar surface. Since clouds can exist up to ∼13 km in the Earth's atmosphere, we may have not seen the sunlight passing the lower atmosphere, i.e. denser and higher-pressure layers. To examine this effect, we created theoretical transmission spectra that only pass through the atmosphere above some critical elevation,below which no sunlight transmits.</p><p>As seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 15</ref>, the model spectrum with the critical elevation of 9-10 km well reproduce the observed one. In this figure, we show only one absorption line but we obtain the same results from all observed absorption lines and all observing times. In addition, the model spectra with critical elevation lower than 4-5 km are identical to the original one without considering any critical elevations ( purple dotted line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 15</ref> ). This indicated that the Rayleigh scattering can prevent the sunlight from probing the lowest layer ( &lt; 4-5 km ) of Earth's atmosphere regardless of the existence of clouds.</p><p>The result is apparently inconsistent with the previous works <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Vidal-Madjar et al. 2010 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arnold et al. 2014)</ref> showing that the Rayleigh scattering prevent the sunlight from probing the lower layer of the atmosphere of about &lt; 20 km/s at 6300Å6300˚6300Å. The inconsistency probably comes from the fact that we observed different altitude of Earth's atmosphere from the previous observations. As these previous works observed the limb of the Earth shadow, they can observe the upper atmosphere and most of the sunlight come from altitude higher than ∼20 km where extinction by Rayleigh scattering is smaller. On the other hand, as we observed the center of the Earth shadow, we can only observe the sunlight passed through the atmosphere under about 20 km. Although the amount of sunlight that pass through the atmosphere below 20 km is lower than that through above 20 km due to Rayleigh scattering, it is still detectable as shown by our observations and we can reveal detailed structure of the lower atmosphere by only probing this part. We also prove the existence of These data indicate that the cloud top pressure is about 200-450 hPa (i.e. cloud top height was about 6-11km), which is consistent with our results. Observation Spectra Model Spectra Model Spectra above 10km Model Spectra above 7km Model Spectra above 5km <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 15</ref>. The O2 absorption line of observation and models. This observation line (black) was observed at 14:47 UT when whole lunar disk moved into the Earth's shadow and the effect of the scattered light is the lowest, and these model lines are developed and corrected so that the depth fits the observation's, assuming that the sunlight only can transmit the atmosphere above 5 (blue), 7 (green) and 10 (red) km.</p><p>transmitted in the Earth's atmosphere, was calculated by taking account of the atmospheric refraction at each observation time. We found that the sunlights are transmitted on the lower altitude range with time at both observation points. We also found that the spectra of Point A, which show much shallower absorption lines than those of Point B, are probably affected by the scattered light from other bright parts of the lunar surface.</p><p>Furthermore, we made a synthetic transmission spectrum of the Earth with Voigt function by taking account of the limb-darkening, refraction and dependence of the spectrum on atmospheric altitude at which the sunlight passes. The model spectra turned out to show wider absorption lines than those of the observed ones even after the correction of the line depth that may be suffered from the scattered light. We found that the width is matched with the observed one if we assume that the sunlight only transmits above 9-10 km of the Earth's atmosphere. The result suggests the existence of clouds below 9-10 km that may block the sunlight.</p><p>Our results will be useful for the investigation of atmospheric structure of an Earth-like exoplanet when the time variation of its transmission spectra can be obtained in the future. ADC, of the National Astronomical Observatory of Japan. This work was supported by Japan Society for Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.1.2 Longitude</head><p>The longitude of the Point Z <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 12)</ref> at the Earth's terminator also changes with time because of the Earth's spin. Here we try to know the longitude of the point Z g , which is on the earth surface just beneath the Point Z, at a given point in time.</p><p>The altitude h and azimuth A of a celestial object at a time t is expressed with the following three equations as ✸ ✹ sin h = sin φ · sin δ + cos φ · cos δ · cos H,</p><p>where δ and H are the declination and hour angle of the object, and here φ is the latitude of the point Z g . H is expressed as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">H = θ 0 + t × 1.0027379 + λ − α,<label>(A4)</label></formula><p>where λ is the longitude of the point Z g , θ 0 is Greenwich sideral time when Universal time is 0 h , t is observation time in UT, and α is the right ascension of the object. Here we regard the Point 2 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 17</ref> as the celestial object, which is a point on the Moon that the sunlight passing through Point Z reaches. The α and δ of the Point 2 are given by JPL's HORIZONS system 5 at the time t, and θ 0 is also given by 'chronological Scientific Tables'. The φ is given by the method described above.</p><p>Therefore, if we know h and A for the Point 2, we can know H and thus λ.</p><p>The h is derived in the following way. The refraction angle at Point Z is the largest because</p><p>Point Z is at the minimum of the lowest altitude from the surface. The ray passing through Point Z comes from the bottom of the Sun since the ray enters into the Earth's atmosphere with the largest incident angle. Therefore, at Point Z on the terminator, we see the point 2 on Moon and the bottom of the Sun in the exact opposite direction in a horizontal fashion. In addition, since the effect of atmospheric refraction makes the elevation of the point 2 seen from the point Z g higher, we should subtract the refraction angle (Φ) from the parallax (p) of the point 2 to correct h. Assuming that Point Z is z km high from the earth surface, we obtain the h as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">h = p − Φ = z 38400 − Φ ( p = z P oint Z d EM ≈ z 38400 [rad] ),<label>(A5)</label></formula><p>where d EM is the distance between the Earth and the Moon.</p><p>Next A and H are calculated as follows. We rewrite the equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(12)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(14)</ref> as, We finally obtain λ, the longitude of the point Z g , from the equation (10). <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> lists thus determined latitude and longitude of the point Z g , just beneath the Point Z on the earth, for Point A and B. The results show that the Point Z is above the center of Indian Ocean at Southern Hemisphere during our observations.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">sin A = C sin H,<label>(A6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">cos H = F,<label>(A7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">cos A = D cos H + E = D · F + E,<label>(A8)</label></formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) A configuration of a lunar eclipse and (b) a configuration for transmission spectroscopy of a transiting exoplanet. S(λ, t), T1(λ, t), and T2(λ, t)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The position of points A and B on the lunar surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Positional relation between Earth's shadows and the observation points on the lunar orbit from hour to hour.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 and</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5 and 7 shows a resultant full-Moon and a lunar-eclipse spectrum divided by the matched T 2 . As shown in the figure, we successfully eliminated T 2 from the spectra down to the photon noise level.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Black pluses: temporal wavelength (velocity) shifts of T2(λ, t) in full-Moon and Penumbra spectra relative to the T2(λ, t) template spectrum. The red,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Left: a full-Moon spectrum around O2 lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which T2(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). Center,Right: a lunar-eclipse spectrum around O2 lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which T2(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Left: a full-Moon spectrum around O2 lines (black line in upper panel) from which T2(λ, t) is eliminated, and the spectrum from which S(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). Center,Right: a lunar-eclipse spectrum around O2 lines (black line in upper panel) from which T2(λ, t) is eliminated, and the spectrum from which S(λ, 0) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). A telluric transmission spectrum, T1(λ, t), is clearly seen in the bottom panel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Left: a full-Moon spectrum around H2O lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which T2(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). Center,Right: a lunar-eclipse spectrum around H2O lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which T2(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Left: a full-Moon spectrum around H2O lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which S(λ, t) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). Center,Right: a lunar-eclipse spectrum around H2O lines (black line in upper panel), and the spectrum from which S(λ, 0) (red line in upper panel) is eliminated (bottom panel). A telluric transmission spectrum, T1(λ, t), is clearly seen in the bottom panel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Transmission spectrum (T1(λ, t)) of O2 (left). O2 absorption lines of 6305.80Å80˚80Å and 6306.56Å56˚56Å are zoomed-in on the right panels. Upper figures show the spectra observed at Point A and lower figures show the spectra observed at Point B.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Transmission spectra (T1(λ, t)) of H2O (left). H2O absorption lines of 6487Å6487˚6487Å and 6489.5 ˚ A are zoomed-in on the right panels. Upper figures show the spectra observed at Point A and lower figures show the spectra observed at Point B.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>First</head><label></label><figDesc>of all, we calculate and trace refraction of the sunlight that enters into the Earth's at- mosphere in parallel to the line connecting the center of Earth shadow on the lunar surface with the center of the Earth (Figure 11). Refractive index at each point in the atmosphere is calculated from geometric optics, and rays with a variety of incident altitudes (i.e. impact parameter) are traced. The calculation is based on the assumption that the Earth's atmosphere is spherically symmetric. The number-density distribution in vertical direction is given by the T-P profile for mid-latitude in MIPAS Model Atmosphere of the Earth (2001) 3 because we observed the sunlight passing over the center of Southern Indian ocean and the Northern coast of Antarctica this time. As a result of the calculation, we obtain a distance (d) from the center of the Earth shadow to the point that the refracted sunlight reaches the lunar orbit. The distance, d, is related to the lowest surface altitude (z min ) on the Earth at which the sunlight passes. The relation between d and z min is shown in Figure 11. Since we know the distance from the center of the Earth shadow to the point A and B on the lunar surface from hour to hour (Appendix 1), we can determine z min at each observing time.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 12 showsFig. 11 .</head><label>1211</label><figDesc>Figure 12 shows the derived ranges of z min for point A (left) and point B (right) at each observ-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. The solar images as observed from the Moon at different times during lunar eclipse on point A (left) and point B (right). These images mean the ranges of the altitudes, zmin, at which the sunlight pass in the Earth's atmosphere. Point Z is the lowest point of each images.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>used for the approximation of the Voigt profile function. The FWHM of Stokes function is estimated using the data of HITRAN 2012 (Rothman et al. 2013) and the FWHM of Doppler function (γ D ) is determined by the line position ν, the molecular mass m and the temperature T as,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>T</head><label></label><figDesc>1 , full-Moon and Penumbra light were scattered into Point A and increased the background making the transmission absorption lines shallower.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Comparison between observational and modeled O2 absorption line for 14:47 UT when whole lunar disk moved into the Earth's shadow and the effect of the scattered light is the lowest. The thickness of these line shows the uncertainty of model spectrum.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. The modeled (red) and observed (black) O2 absorption lines of the Earth atmosphere (T2). The synthetic lines are only 1.1 deeper than observed ones.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>O 2 · O 2 and O 3 spectra have little influence with O 2 absorption lines. To verify our results, we examine the cloud top pressure in the sunlight-transmitted area (from the center of Southern Indian ocean to the Northern coast of Antractica) during observation time using Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) data acquired from the Level-1 and Atmosphere Archive &amp; Distribution System (LAADS) Distributed Active Archive Center (DAAC) 4 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Grant</head><label></label><figDesc>Number JP16K17660, JP18H01265 and 15H02063. Y.K. is supported by the Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellow (JSPS KAKENHI No.15J08463) and Leading Graduate Course for Frontiers of Mathematical Sciences and Physics. The cloud top pressure above limb Earth region of interest during observation time is based on Terra and Aqua MODIS Cloud Subset 5-Min L2 Swath 5km and 10km data. These data were acquired from the Level-1 and Atmosphere Archive &amp; Distribution System (LAADS) Distributed Active Archive Center (DAAC), located in the Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland (https://ladsweb.nascom.nasa.gov/). We acknowledge LAADS Web search. We acknowledge the very significant cultural role and reverence that the summit of Mauna Kea has always had within the indigenous people in Hawai'i. Appendix 1 Terrestrial coordinates of the sunlight-transmitting regions in Earth's atmosphere A.1.1 Latitude Earth's spin axis is inclined at about 23.4 degrees from the perpendicular to the ecliptic (Figure 16). Therefore, latitudes on the Earth are projected onto the shadow of the Earth as shown in Figure 17. The sunlight that passes through the Earth's atmosphere at minimum lowest altitude (point Z; Figure 12) on the terminator (Point 1 on Figure 17) finally reaches a point (Point 2 on Figure 17) on the line connecting the center of the Earth's shadow and Point 1. Thus we can know the latitude on the Earth where the sunlight passes through at the lowest altitude by reading the projected latitude of Point 1 on the Earth shadow.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16. A schematic view showing a relation between the axis of the Earth and the RA of the shadow of the Earth.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17. A schematic view showing the projected latitude on the shadow of the Earth. The light blue lines are the projected latitude on the shadow of the Earth, the black point is the center of shadow of the Earth, and the red and pink points are the Point A (Point 2) at 13:21 UT set on the lunar surface and the point corresponding to that the sunlight passes at the terminator of the Earth, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>where</head><label></label><figDesc>C = − cos δ/ cos h, D = −(sin φ · cos δ)/ cos h, E = (cos φ · sin φ)/ cos h, F = (sin h − sin φ · sin δ)/(cos φ · cos δ). Now all of the C, D, E, and F are functions of the known variables. We here assume that A takes the value between 0 and π because the Moon is seen in the east from the terminator at the beginning of the lunar eclipse. It should be noted that the value of H depends on the signs of sin H and cos H in the following way, i) cos H &gt; 0, sin H &gt; 0 ii) cos H &lt; 0, sin H &gt; 0 0 • &lt; H &lt; 90 • W 90 • W &lt; H &lt; 180 • W iii) cos H &gt; 0, sin H &lt; 0 iv) cos H &lt; 0, sin H &lt; 0 0 • &lt; H &lt; 90 • E 90 • E &lt; H &lt; 180 • E</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Latitude and longitude at the 

typical Universal Time during eclipse 

Universal Time Latitude 
Longitude 

(UT) 
( • ) 
( • ) 

pointA 

12:47 
15.9 S 
81.6 E 

12:54 
17.2 S 
80.4 E 

13:01 
18.8 S 
79.7 E 

13:07 
20.4 S 
78.6 E 

13:14 
22.5 S 
77.9 E 

13:21 
24.9 S 
77.5 E 

13:27 
28.1 S 
77.5 E 

pointB 

13:48 
28.8 S 
72.7 E 

13:54 
30.8 S 
72.3 E 

14:01 
33.5 S 
72.1 E 

14:08 
36.6 S 
72.4 E 

14:14 
39.6 S 
73.0 E 

14:21 
43.6 S 
74.3 E 

14:27 
47.4 S 
76.3 E 

14:34 
52.3 S 
80.0 E 

14:41 
57.5 S 
86.2 E 

14:47 
61.7 S 
93.9 E 

14:54 
65.6 S 
106.5 E 

15:01 
67.1 S 
114.6 E 

15:07 
65.9 S 
104.9 E 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . The relation between the period elapsed from the first full-Moon data and the variation in wavelength of T 2 (λ, t)</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>from HR8634 data 
Universal Time Variation of Wavelength 

(UT) 
at O 2 spectra (kms −1 ) 

10:54 
-0.11 

10:56 
-0.12 

10:58 
-0.12 

11:01 
-0.13 

11:03 
-0.14 

11:05 
-0.14 

11:22 
-0.15 

11:24 
-0.14 

11:26 
-0.13 

11:28 
-0.12 

11:30 
-0.13 

11:32 
-0.13 

11:34 
-0.12 

11:36 
-0.11 

11:38 
-0.12 

11:40 
-0.11 

11:43 
-0.11 

11:45 
-0.11 

11:47 
-0.10 

11:49 
-0.10 

11:51 
-0.09 

12:14 
-0.07 

12:16 
-0.08 

12:18 
-0.07 

12:20 
-0.06 

12:22 
-0.07 

12:24 
-0.07 

12:26 
-0.07 

12:29 
-0.07 

12:31 
-0.05 

12:33 
-0.06 

12:36 
-0.07 

12:39 
-0.05 

12:42 
-0.06 

13:33 
-0.10 

13:36 
-0.09 

13:39 
-0.09 

13:43 
-0.11 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 3 . The relation between the time elapsed from the first full-Moon data and the variation in wavelength of S(λ,t) from the first full-Moon data</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Universal Time 
Wavelength shift 
Wavelength shif 

(UT) 
at O 2 spectra (kms −1 ) 
at H 2 O spectra (kms −1 ) 

12:29 
-0.84 
-0.83 

12:31 
-0.90 
-0.89 

12:33 
-0.97 
-0.95 

12:36 
-1.03 
-1.01 

12:39 
-1.10 
-1.08 

12:42 
-1.17 
-1.12 

12:47 
-1.16 
-1.13 

12:54 
-0.56 
-0.51 

13:01 
-0.50 
-0.43 

13:07 
-0.56 
-0.46 

13:14 
-0.61 
-0.45 

13:21 
-0.66 
-0.52 

13:27 
-0.59 
-0.53 

13:33 
-0.94 
-0.93 

13:36 
-0.98 
-0.97 

13:39 
-1.05 
-1.02 

13:43 
-1.11 
-1.09 

13:48 
-1.05 
-1.02 

13:54 
-0.35 
-0.35 

14:01 
-0.18 
-0.15 

14:08 
-0.12 
-0.07 

14:14 
-0.09 
-0.09 

14:21 
-0.04 
-0.05 

14:27 
0.00 
-0.01 

14:34 
0.11 
0.10 

14:41 
0.12 
0.05 

14:47 
0.16 
0.30 

14:54 
0.51 
0.46 

15:01 
0.41 
0.62 

15:07 
0.57 
0.65 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="true"><head>Table 4 . Altitude range at the typical Universal Time</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>during eclipse 

observation point 
observation time 
altitude range 

A or B 
(UT) 
(km) 

A 
12:47 
8.1 -(penumbra) 

A 
12:54 
7.3 -82.4 

A 
13:01 
6.6 -22.4 

A 
13:07 
6.0 -18.0 

A 
13:14 
5.5 -15.2 

A 
13:21 
5.0 -13.6 

A 
13:27 
4.5 -12.2 

1.8 -2.0 (other side) 

B 
13:48 
7.7 -(penumbra) 

B 
13:54 
7.1 -35.4 

B 
14:01 
6.5 -21.6 

B 
14:08 
5.9 -17.7 

B 
14:14 
5.6 -15.7 

B 
14:21 
5.1 -14.1 

B 
14:27 
4.9 -13.2 

B 
14:34 
4.6 -12.3 

1.8 -2.0 (other side) 

B 
14:41 
4.3 -11.5 

1.8 -2.2 (other side) 

B 
14:47 
4.2 -11.2 

1.8 -2.3 (other side) 

B 
14:54 
4.1 -11.0 

1.8 -2.3 (other side) 

B 
15:01 
4.1 -10.9 

1.8 -2.4 (other side) 

B 
15:07 
4.1 -11.0 

1.8 -2.3 (other side) </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> IRAF is distributed by the National Optical Astronomy Observatories, which is operated by the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc. under cooperative agreement with the National Science Foundation, USA.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> http://cso.caltech.edu/tau/</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> http://eodg.atm.ox.ac.uk/RFM/atm/</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> https://ladsweb.modaps.eosdis.nasa.gov/search/</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> https://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/horizons.cgi</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We thank the referee Dr. Luc Arnold for many valuable comments that greatly improved this paper. We thank the support of our Subaru/HDS observation by Akito Tajitsu, Naruhisa Takato, Daigo Tomono and Ruka Misawa. We also acknowledge the people who supported the proposal of observation and the people who discussed this study, especially Masato Katayama, who adviced how to obtain the longitude of the lowest point in Earth's atmosphere. The part of our data analysis was carried out on common use data analysis computer system at the Astronomy Data Center,</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Astudillo-Defru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rojo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">557</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bétrémieux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaltenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">791</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bodhaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Slusser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Atmos. Oceanic Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1854</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">568</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">377</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Iacono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moncet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">774</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>García Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Montañés-Rodírguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">755</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Glebocki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gnacinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stawikowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronomica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">509</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gorshelev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Serdyuchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chehade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atmos. Meas. Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuntz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Quant. Spectrosc. Radiat. Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">819</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Crouzet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Madhusudhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">791</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mclaughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Meadows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1924" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Noguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">855</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barrena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Montañés-Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">814</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Platnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">MODIS Atmosphere L2 Joint Atmosphere Product</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Processing System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nasa</forename><surname>Modis Adaptive</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">10.5067/MODIS/MODATML2.006</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MODATML2.006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Goddard Space Flight Center</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Richard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Quant. Spectrosc. Radiat. Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1276</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rossiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Quant. Spectrosc. Radiat. Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1924" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ruyten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Quant. Spectrosc. Radiat. Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Serdyuchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gorshelev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chehade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atmos. Meas. Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="636" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">720</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">904</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A G</forename><surname>Snellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J W</forename><surname>De Mooij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Le Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">487</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">357</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A G</forename><surname>Snellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Kok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Le Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Birkby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">764</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">182</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tsumura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">789</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ugolnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Punanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Krushinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Quant. Spectrosc. Radiat. Transfer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">143</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">523</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vollmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gedzelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3481</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wilhelms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mccauley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">U.S. Geol. Survey Misc. Geol. Inv. Geol. Map I</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">703</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A E</forename><surname>Fosbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Petr-Gotzens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zaho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">255</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A E</forename><surname>Fosbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Petr-Gotzens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pallé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">806</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
