<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:23+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">OPTICAL HYDROGEN ABSORPTION CONSISTENT WITH A THIN BOW SHOCK LEADING THE HOT JUPITER HD 189733B</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Wilson</forename><surname>Cauley</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Seth</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Travis</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Wesleyan University and Astronomy Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Van Vleck Observatory, 96 Foss Hill Dr</addrLine>
									<postCode>06459</postCode>
									<settlement>Middletown</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics &amp; Physical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">University of Arizona and Department of Planetary Sciences and Lunar and Planetary Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska-Kearney</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>24011 1th Avenue, 1629 E University Blvd</addrLine>
									<postCode>68849, 85721</postCode>
									<settlement>Kearney, Tuscon</settlement>
									<region>NE, AZ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy and McDonald Observatory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2515, C1400, 78712</postCode>
									<settlement>Speedway, Austin</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">OPTICAL HYDROGEN ABSORPTION CONSISTENT WITH A THIN BOW SHOCK LEADING THE HOT JUPITER HD 189733B</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Accepted to ApJ: 7/21/2015 Accepted to ApJ: 7/21/2015</note>
					<note>Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 5/2/11</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Bow shocks are ubiquitous astrophysical phenomena resulting from the supersonic passage of an object through a gas. Recently, pre-transit absorption in UV metal transitions of the hot Jupiter exoplanets HD 189733b and WASP12-b have been interpreted as being caused by material compressed in a planetary bow shock. Here we present a robust detection of a time-resolved pre-transit, as well as in-transit, absorption signature around the hot Jupiter exoplanet HD 189733b using high spectral resolution observations of several hydrogen Balmer lines. The line shape of the pre-transit feature and the shape of the time series absorption provide the strongest constraints on the morphology and physical characteristics of extended structures around an exoplanet. The in-transit measurements confirm the previous exospheric Hα detection although the absorption depth measured here is ∼50% lower. The pre-transit absorption feature occurs 125 minutes before the predicted optical transit, a projected linear distance from the planet to the stellar disk of 7.2 R p. The absorption strength observed in the Balmer lines indicates an optically thick, but physically small, geometry. We model this signal as the early ingress of a planetary bow shock. If the bow shock is mediated by a planetary magnetosphere, the large standoff distance derived from the model suggests a large planetary magnetic field strength of B eq =28 G. Better knowledge of exoplanet magnetic field strengths is crucial to understanding the role these fields play in planetary evolution and the potential development of life on planets in the habitable zone.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Hot Jupiters (HJs) are Jupiter-mass planets that are orbiting within ∼10 stellar radii of their host stars and have orbital periods of a few days. The large insolation of these planets results in extreme heating of their bound atmospheres and inflated radii ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Burrows et al. 2007</ref>). These objects provide a view into planetary atmospheric physics that do not occur in our solar system. Some HJs are believed to be losing mass via hydrodynamic blowoff <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Vidal-Madjar et al. 2003</ref>). The close proximity of a HJ to its parent star can result in star-planet-interactions (SPIs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cuntz et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Shkolnik et al. 2005</ref>) and, potentially, the formation of bow shocks around the planet as it moves supersonically through the stellar wind or corona ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Vidotto et al. 2010)</ref>. If the bow shock around a HJ is mediated by the planetary magnetosphere, absorption by material compressed by the shock can be used to estimate the strength of the planetary magnetic field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>pcauley@wesleyan.edu</head><p>One of the closest of these HJs to our solar system, HD 189733b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bouchy et al. 2005</ref>), has been studied extensively due to the relative brightness of its host star. Various molecules and atoms in both the bound and unbound atmosphere of HD 189733b, including (but not limited to) CH 4 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Swain et al. 2008</ref>), H 2 0 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Grillmair et al. 2008</ref>), Na I ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Redfield et al. 2008</ref>), O I (Ben-Jaffel &amp; Ballester 2013), and neutral hydrogen ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Jensen et al. 2012</ref>; Lecavelier des <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Etangs et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Etangs et al. , 2012</ref>, have been detected using transmission spectroscopy, where stellar photons are absorbed by the planetary atmosphere while the planet transits its host star.</p><p>In addition to in-transit absorption, hints of pre-transit absorption have been observed in HD 189733b <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ben- Jaffel &amp; Ballester 2013;</ref>) and WASP12b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Fossati et al. 2010</ref>) and provided early indications that material exterior to an exoplanet's atmosphere could have sufficient optical depth to cause an absorption signature. The WASP-12b result, a single 2-sigma absorption of a 41Å41Å region in the near-UV, was interpreted and modeled as a transiting bow shock ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Vidotto et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Llama et al. 2011</ref>).  measured pretransit absorption in Si III 1206.5 ˚ A for one of two analyzed HD 189733b transits. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ben-Jaffel &amp; Ballester (2013)</ref> report two pre-transit UV absorption measurements for HD 189733b, observed in C II, but not O I, and they model the result as a transiting bow shock <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ben-Jaffel &amp; Ballester 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>Here, we present a time-resolved pre-transit signal detected in the high-resolution transmission spectra of the Balmer lines Hα, Hβ, and Hγ of HD 189733b. The observations and data reduction procedures are given in section 2. The transmission spectrum analysis and our procedure for estimating uncertainties in the absorption signal is presented in section 3. In section 4 and section 5 we discuss the absorption signals and the effect of star spots and active regions. The bow shock and exosphere models are described in section 6. We discuss the planetary magnetic field strength estimate in section 7 and provide a brief conclusion in section 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">OBSERVATIONS AND DATA REDUCTION</head><p>Two transits of HD 189733b were obtained on the two half nights of June 3 and July 4, 2013 using HiRES on Keck I ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Vogt et al. 1994)</ref>. The approximate resolving power of the observations is R∼68,000, or 4.4 km s −1 at Hα. The B2 decker was employed which has a slit size of 7.0 × 0.57 . Exposure times ranged from 3 to 5 minutes. The average signal-to-noise of the extracted spectra is 400 at Hα, 180 at Hβ, and 120 at Hγ.</p><p>The observations from June 3 begin at first contact and so add no significance to the pre-transit detection. In addition, the cadence of the June observations was twice as long, due to intermittent terrestrial clouds and haze, providing less detail on the shape of the transit. For these reasons we do not include the June data in the analysis. We note that the in-transit absorption values measured for the June data are similar to the values measured from the July data.</p><p>The data were reduced using the HiRES Redux package written by Jason X. Prochaska 1 . Standard reduction steps were taken including bias subtraction, flat fielding, and the removal of cosmic rays and hot pixels. The spectra were extracted using a 6.6 boxcar. All images were examined manually for order overlap in the blue chip. HiRES Redux also performs 2D wavelength solutions using Th-Ar lamp exposures taken at the beginning of each night. The residuals for the wavelength fits are ∼0.05 pixels, or ∼0.02Å02Å, in all orders. When applied to an individual observation, all wavelength solutions are corrected for Earth's heliocentric velocity and for the radial velocity of HD 189733. This places the spectrum in the rest frame of the star.</p><p>Telluric absorption is removed from the Hα spectra using the telluric fitting program Molecfit ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kausch et al. 2014</ref>). We first remove the strong Hα line absorption from a telluric standard. The telluric absorption in the standard is then fit using Molecfit. The best telluric fit is then shifted appropriately in wavelength, scaled, and subtracted from each individual observation. This process results in transmission spectra with residuals in the telluric lines of ∼0.25%. Telluric absorption from Mauna 1 http://www.ucolick.org/∼xavier/HIRedux/ Kea is negligible in the Hβ and Hγ orders. Telluric removal is not performed for these lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">TRANSMISSION SPECTRUM AND EMC ANALYSIS</head><p>The transmission spectrum is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S T = F i F out − 1 (1)</formula><p>where F i is a single observation and F out is the master post-transit spectrum. In order to obtain the final transmission spectra all observations must be normalized and aligned in wavelength space. Changes in spectral resolution due to temperature or instrument flexure are minimal and do not affect the spectra over the course of one half night. All spectra are initially normalized using a 4th order polynomial. A single out-of-transit spectrum is then chosen as the comparison spectrum in order to apply a wavelength correction to all spectra. A number of stellar absorption lines in each spectrum are cross correlated with the same lines in the comparison spectrum. We tested three different types of fits to the resulting wavelength shifts: constant, linear, and spline fits. The spline and linear fits perform no better, and in some cases worse, than a constant offset in wavelength. Thus the constant offsets are used to rectify the wavelength vectors for each spectrum relative to the comparison spectrum. This results in precisely aligned spectra where the largest residuals occur across 1-2 pixels at the cores of narrow spectral lines. Cores of identified stellar absorption lines in the normalized spectra are ignored when calculating the absorbed flux in each line so these residuals do not contribute to the transmission signal. Once spectra have been normalized and wavelength shifted they are divided by the master out-of-transit spectrum, a co-addition of the selected out-of-transit spectra. The resulting spectrum is renormalized to remove slowly varying continuum shapes leftover from the division. This occurs because the original normalization is slightly different for each spectrum. The line of interest is ignored when determining the renormalization so as to avoid introducing offsets from the true continuum. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows the average transmission spectrum for the pre-transit (first column), in-transit (second column), and post-transit (third column) observations for Hα (top row), Hβ (middle row), and Hγ (bottom row). The model line profiles are over plotted with solid lines (see section 4). The number of spectra used to create each spectrum is give in the bottom-right of the top-row windows. The fourth and fifth columns shows the results of an empirical Monte Carlo (EMC) process that we utilize to produce estimates for the absorption uncertainties ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Redfield et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Jensen et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Wyttenbach et al. 2015</ref>). The EMC distributions are given in terms of W λ , the equivalent width of absorption across the line. W λ is calculated by integrating the line profile from −200 to +200 km s −1 . Values of W λ do not change by more than 25%, for any measurement, if the integration width is extended to ±500 km s −1 .</p><p>The in-transit EMC distributions are generated by randomly selecting 5000 subsets of in-transit spectra and comparing them to either the master out-of-transit spectrum (the In-Out method) or the master in-transit spectrum (the In-In method). The standard deviations of  the resulting distributions are taken to be the 1σ uncertainties for the reported in-transit absorption. Each line is clearly detected at &gt;3σ. We note that propagated Poisson errors result in very similar estimates (∼20% less than the EMC estimates) for the absorption uncertainties in each line. We choose to use the uncertainty derived from the EMC due to its ability to highlight systematic errors, which can dominate the measurement if not taken into account. The small number of pre-transit observations (N =4) does not allow sufficient combinations of spectra to be generated for the EMC process described above. Instead, we compare the average pre-transit spectrum to all possible combinations of the nine post-transit spectra (N =511). The standard deviation of the resulting distribution, shown in the fifth column of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>, is taken as the 1-σ uncertainty for the measured absorption. This process is also used to estimate an average uncertainty for the individual points in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>.</p><p>As an additional test of the EMC procedure and to verify that we are actually measuring absorption in the Balmer lines, we perform the same in-transit EMC analysis for three control lines of Ca I. One line is chosen each for Hα, Hβ, and Hγ from the same spectral order that the Balmer line is located in. Ca I is expected to condense out of the atmospheres of hot Jupiter exoplanets and thus should not exist in atomic form in large quantities <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Lodders 1999</ref>). If systematics from the reduction procedure are resulting in absorption in the Balmer lines we are likely to see similar artifacts in the Ca I control lines. The results of the control line transmission and EMC analyses are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. As expected, these lines show no evidence of absorption and the resulting uncertainties are similar to the uncertainties measured for the Balmer lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">IN-TRANSIT ABSORPTION</head><p>The second column of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows the average intransit absorption profiles for the July transit. The intransit EMC is shown in the fourth column. The absorbed fluxes measured in the line profiles of Hα, Hβ, and Hγ are all detected at &gt;3σ. The Hβ and Hγ detections are the first reported measurements for an exoplanet atmosphere. The absorption that we measure is ∼50% lower than that from <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Jensen et al. (2012)</ref>. This may be due to variability in the surface features of HD189733 (e.g., spots and active regions). We model the in-transit profiles as arising in the planetary exosphere (see subsection 6.2). The possible contribution of star spots and active regions to the absorption profile is discussed in subsection 5.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">PRE-TRANSIT ABSORPTION</head><p>Absorption values, which are the negative of W λ , determined from individual exposures are shown as a function of time in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>. The gap in the data from ∼ −115 minutes until −70 minutes was, unfortunately, used to obtain telluric standards. The strong pre-transit signal was not anticipated. The absorption is calculated by integrating the flux from −200 to +200 km s −1 . The error bars represent the average standard deviation of the EMC process using all combinations of the post-transit The pre-transit absorption exhibits a few important properties. First, the ratio of the absorbed flux between Hα and Hβ is ∼ 1.6 − 2.0, which is much lower than in the optically thin limit. This indicates that the absorbing material is optically thick. Indeed, the line morphologies of the pre-transit observations appear saturated, i.e., flat bottomed and broad. Secondly, the absorption abruptly begins to decrease between t − t mid = −70 and −66 minutes. This requires that the material causing the pretransit absorption must begin to exit the stellar disk before the time of first optical contact (labeled t I in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig- ure 3)</ref>. This suggests that the distribution of absorbing material is asymmetric with respect to the planet, a point that is supported by the lack of any significant absorption seen at similar times post-transit (in contrast to GJ 436, for example; <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kulow et al. 2014</ref>). Finally, the integrated absorption never exceeds ∼1.3% which requires that the optically thick absorbing material cover a similar fraction of the stellar surface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">The Effects of Star Spots, Active Regions, and</head><p>Stellar Activity Star spot crossings are not unusual for HD 189733b <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Pont et al. 2013</ref>). The transit of a star spot or active region can change the relative amount of stellar light being absorbed by the occulting material. The transit of a spot-free chord can also change the relative amount of stellar light being absorbed, even for specific spectral features, if there is a non-negligible fraction of the stellar surface covered by spots ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Berta et al. 2011</ref>). Stellar activity can also mimic transit features when comparing spectra from different times: if the star brightens or dims relative to the time of comparison, this signal can appear as the absorption of stellar flux when in truth it is merely variation in the amount emitted by the star. For our case, stellar variability due to time-dependent Balmer line emission from active regions can mimic the spectral line absorption: if the star is more active during the times when the out-of-transit spectra are measured, the filling in of the stellar Balmer line cores will appear as an absorption signature for any spectrum measured at a time when the star is less bright.</p><p>There is ample evidence that the absorption signatures we measure are not caused by stellar variability. Both pre-and in-transit spectra are compared to the same out-of-transit spectra. This requires that any absorption signal caused purely by stellar variability have the same absorption strength in both the pre-and in-transit spectra. This is clearly not the case. In fact, the pretransit measurements are significantly stronger than the in-transit measurements despite the fact that the exosphere, by way of the occulting planet, transits an effectively smaller stellar disk than the bow shock. If the pretransit absorption is entirely due to stellar variability, the in-transit absorption would necessarily be stronger than the pre-transit absorption. Since this relationship is not seen in the data, the absorption cannot be solely due to stellar Balmer line variability. This means that the pre-transit signal must be caused by absorbing material occulting the stellar disk.</p><p>An indicator of stellar activity level is the S-index mea-sured from the Ca II H and K lines ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Duncan et al. 1991)</ref>. The index, shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> for the July transit, has similar values pre-transit compared to post-transit, although there appears to be a decrease about halfway through the transit. The similar S-index values both before and after transit also indicate that the pre-transit absorption is not caused by variable stellar emission. The strength of spectral features can be affected by the relative contributions of the stellar photosphere and spots or active regions ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Berta et al. 2011</ref>). While the transiting bow shock, which is transparent to continuum photons, is not subject to this affect, the opaque transiting planet certainly is. If the planet transits a spotfree chord, the stellar spectrum will be weighted towards the spot spectrum and the relative strength of spectral features between in and out-of-transit observations can change, even at the 1−2% level. As a result, this effect is capable of producing spurious in-transit features. We do not believe this to be the case for our in-transit absorption measurements. In general, spotted active regions will fill in the Balmer line cores with emission, causing the line strength to effectively decrease. When the planet is transiting, this produces weaker absorption lines since the observed spectrum is weighted towards the active spotted regions. When compared to out-of-transit measurements, this will produce in-transit emission features. The fact that we see the opposite, i.e., strong in-transit absorption features, indicates that we are measuring absorption through the atmosphere of the planet. However, the absolute strength of the measured absorption is almost certainly affected. The contribution of spotted active regions most likely causes us to underestimate the strength of the in-transit exospheric absorption. This may be the cause of the difference between the in-transit absorption strength measured here and that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Jensen et al. 2012</ref>), who measure the in-transit line depth to be two times deeper.</p><p>The arguments given above apply to the general features of the absorption time series. It is difficult, however, to determine how individual absorption measurements are affected by a nonuniform stellar disk. Some absorption measurements may well be affected by spots or bright regions on the stellar surface. For example, in between 3rd and 4th contact the absorption varies between the expected values from the exiting exosphere and much stronger absorption not accounted for by the model. These points could be due to the transitory occultation by the exosphere of bright chromospheric regions on the limb of the star. Modeling of these variable features is beyond the scope of this study but they provide a plausible explanation for the departure of individual points from the model estimates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">MODELING THE ABSORPTION</head><p>We model the pre-transit absorption as arising in a thin bow shock orbiting ahead HD 189733 b. The intransit absorption is modeled as arising in the exosphere of the planet. We neglect limb darkening in our model calculations since we are measuring the absorption across a very narrow (∼1.0 ˚ A) portion of the stellar line. This portion of the Balmer lines forms in a very thin layer in the stellar atmosphere with a small temperature gradient and thus suffers negligibly from limb darkening <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Mihalas 1978</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Bow shock model</head><p>We construct a simple model of the pre-transit absorption as arising in a bow shock orbiting ahead of the planet. While a bow shock is not the only possible cause of the absorption, it is a plausible one and has been successful at explaining the pre-transit UV observations of WASP12-b and HD 189733b ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Llama et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ben- Jaffel &amp; Ballester 2013</ref>). We do not attempt to model the full physical conditions of the stellar wind/corona and the resulting bow shock conditions. Instead, we assume a bow shock geometry and require that the n = 2 hydrogen density assigned to the bow shock produce the necessary absorption. We assume that the standoff distance of the magnetosphere, r m , is equal to the distance of the nose of the shock from the planet.</p><p>The bow shock model is constructed using the shock geometry of <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wilkin (1996)</ref>. A density is assigned to the nose of the shock and then scaled along the bow according to the scaling law</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ρ (r) = ρ 0 r m r α (2)</formula><p>where r is the linear distance from the planet to the bow shock and α is the exponent describing how quickly the density changes with distance from the density at the nose, ρ 0 . The distance r is always greater than r m so the density decreases monotonically from the nose. A 3-D density grid is then filled according to the prescription of the density law with the chosen value of α. The bow shock is rotated around the z-axis with angle θ sh from the tangent to the planet's orbital motion. The column density of the material covering the stellar disk is then calculated. The cell size in the grid is 0.01 R p , the same size as the shock thickness. We find that a cell size of this magnitude is required in order to reproduce the relatively small absorption values from the data. Larger cells, which necessarily result in a larger shock width, result in too much of the stellar disk being covered by optically thick material. We find values of W λ to within ∼5% of the reported values if we decrease the grid cell size to 0.005 R p , indicating that the shock thickness of 0.01 R p is not an artifact of the resolution. The optical depth in the Balmer lines is approximated by a Doppler-broadened delta function, τ v = τ 0 e −(v/b) 2 , where b = √ 2σ v and σ v is the dispersion of a 1-D Gaussian velocity distribution (Draine 2011). The optical depth at line center is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">τ 0 = √ πe 2 f lu N l λ lu m e cb (3)</formula><p>where f lu is the oscillator strength of the transition, λ lu is the central wavelength, m e is the electron mass, e is the electron charge, c is the speed of light in vacuum, and N l is the column density of the lower energy level of the transition. We use the optical depth as a function of velocity from line center to approximate an absorption line profile for each grid point using the column density calculated from the 3D bow shock. The final line profile for a single model iteration (i.e., a single time of the bow shock transit) is the sum of each individual line profile for each grid point on the stellar disk. Examples of the pre-transit model line profiles are overplotted on the   <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Ca II H and K S-index measurements taken simultaneously with the Balmer lines. Propagated Poisson uncertainties are smaller than the plot symbols. Transit contact times are marked with the vertical green lines. There is no direct correlation with the transit, although there appears to be a decrease in the activity index at t − t mid = 0 minutes. measured spectra in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> We find that b = 4.1 km s −1 is able to adequately reproduce the line profile shapes. The final model W λ values are calculated identically to the measured values of W λ . We point out that the model seems to poorly reproduce the pre-transit Hγ line profile and absorption values. We believe this is due to the blending of Hγ with a nearby Fe I line which causes the red wavelength side of the Hγ profile to show weaker absorption. This can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> where the model line profile matches the blue side of the line very well. A similar effect is seen for the in-transit Hγ profiles. Based on the line profile shapes of Hα and Hβ we have no reason to believe the shallow red-ward portion of the Hγ line is representative of anything physical.</p><p>The model absorption values are shown as solid lines in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref> and the model line profiles are shown as solid lines in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. A to-scale snapshot of the system is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. The large standoff distance and the observed absorption time series are representative of the double transit suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vidotto et al. (2011)</ref>. This model was calculated using values of r m =12.75 R p , θ sh = 15 • , the angle between the planet's trajectory and the nose of the shock, and ρ 0 = 9×10 −20 g cm −3 , the mass density of excited hydrogen at the nose of the shock. A scaling factor of α = 400 is required to sufficiently concentrate the density at the nose which is necessitated by the loss of absorption near t I . The model reproduces the main features of the observed pre-transit time series: 1. the approximate ratio of Hα to Hβ absorption; 2. similar absorption values at −125 and −70 minutes; and 3. the steep decrease in the absorption immediately after t − t mid = −70 minutes. The model also predicts an absorption maximum at t − t mid = −85 minutes and ingress of the bow shock at t − t mid = −175 minutes. View of the orbital plane <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. To-scale projections of the planet and bow shock in the orbital plane (top panel) and the view from Earth (bottom panel) for time t − t mid = −50 minutes, soon after the bow shock has exited the stellar disk. The planet is in between first and second contact. The exosphere and bow shock are scaled to the same density. The density in the bow shock can be seen to fall off rapidly away from the nose of the shock.</p><p>The model parameters reported here are fairly tightly constrained. For example, setting θ sh = 40 • results in too large of a projected area of the bow shock and requires the density to become even more highly concentrated at the nose. Similarly, smaller values of α do not concentrate the material enough at the nose and the absorption values are too large. The standoff distance must also increase to allow the shock to exit the stellar disk at t − t mid = −70 minutes. We note that the values of r m = 12.75 R p and θ sh = 15 • derived in our favored model are similar to those found by Ben-Jaffel &amp; Ballester (2013) (16.7 R p and 10-30 • , respectively) for their bow shock model of a pre-transit C II absorption signal. However, a value of r m = 16.7 R p is too large for our data since this would imply egress of the bow shock from the stellar disk earlier than observed, assuming a similar value of θ sh . Variability related to the stellar wind and/or corona, which has likely been observed to cause variations in the exospheric absorption signature from HD 189733b (Lecavelier des <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Etangs et al. 2012</ref>), could account for this difference. Thus we believe our values represent a plausible scenario for producing the measured absorption.</p><p>The incoming material in a bow shock is not stopped by the magnetosphere: momentum is conserved and the material flows around the bow <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Wilkin 1996)</ref>. Our model does not incorporate the bulk flow of material along the bow. The excited hydrogen density we find from our model is thus representative of the physical state of the gas at the nose of the shock. The rapid falloff of the density from the nose implies that the shocked material cools as it moves away from the nose and that the increase in temperature and density caused by the shock at distances far from the nose is insufficient to produce a significant amount of excited hydrogen.</p><p>The large values of r m and small values of θ sh found here and in the study of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ben-Jaffel &amp; Ballester (2013)</ref> contrast with the relatively small values of r m (∼3.8 R p ) and large values of θ sh (∼65-70 • ) predicted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. (2013)</ref> using a full 3D MHD simulation of the stellar wind from HD 189733 and assuming a dipolar magnetic field strength of 14 G at the pole. The large discrepancies suggest that these simulations overestimate the stellar wind speed and/or temperature or that the planetary magnetic field is underestimated.</p><p>The physical conditions in the bow shock are expected to fluctuate as the stellar wind speed, density, and temperature likely vary with time. For example, as the stellar wind speed increases the angle θ sh will increase, moving the nose of the shock closer to the star-planet line. The low value of θ sh = 15 • reported here indicates that the planet is moving through a relatively slow moving wind, ∼30-40 km s −1 , or perhaps a hydrostatic corona if the true angle is even smaller ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Vidotto et al. 2010</ref>). This may indicate that the planet is moving through a quiet or slow region in the stellar wind. Assuming that the planetary magnetic field strength remains constant, the standoff distance r m will also change depending on the varying thermal and ram pressure from the stellar wind. Even if the conditions for a shock to form are not met, the incoming stellar wind may still undergo some compression and heating as it is slowed by the magnetosphere ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lai et al. 2010</ref>). Fluctuations in the pre-transit signal could be used as a probe of stellar wind variability.</p><p>As a first attempt at using our measurement to estimate properties of HD 189733's wind, we can use our derived model parameters to calculate a mass loss rate for the star. If we assume a spherical outflow of constant velocity, the density we estimate at the orbital distance of HD 189733b translates into a density at the stellar surface of ρ 0 =1.8×10 −18 g cm −3 . Assuming a wind velocity of 40 km s −1 , we estimate a mass loss rate of ˙ M =2.5×10 11 g s −1 , or ∼4×10 −15 M yr −1 . This value is ∼100× lower than that predicted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. (2013)</ref> (4.5×10 −13 M yr −1 ). This suggests that a small fraction of the stellar wind material ends up as excited hydrogen in the bow shock. This estimate is a lower limit: the density from our model is the density of the excited hydrogen in the bow shock and does not include ground state hydrogen or other elements. This mass loss estimate has other obvious limitations. For example, the stellar wind is likely not spherically symmetric. In addition, this estimate is essentially a snapshot in time. HD 189733 is an active star and likely has a variable wind. Our estimate is also lower than the mass loss rate suggested by the X-ray flux versus ˙ M relationship given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wood et al. (2014)</ref>. Using an average X-ray flux of F X =6.3×10 5 taken from the NEXXUS2 catalog 2 , we calculate a mass loss rate of ˙ M =1.1×10 −12 M yr −1 . Although the <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wood et al. (2014)</ref> relationship is fairly uncertain, this value is more in line with the <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. (2013)</ref> prediction than the value estimated from our model. Thus the low mass loss rate estimated here should be considered a rough lower limit for HD 189733. Future observations will help constrain the variability and potentially measure changes in the stellar mass loss rate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Exosphere model</head><p>The exosphere model consists of an isothermal gas in hydrostatic equilibrium above the planet. We calculate the density in the exosphere out to 10H exo where H exo is the exospheric scale height given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H exo = k b T / (m h g)</formula><p>where k b is Boltzmann's constant, T is the exospheric temperature, and g is the acceleration due to gravity at the planetary surface. The exobase is taken to be at R p =1.0. In order to roughly match the in-transit absorption, we find H exo = 0.04 R p and T exo = 7, 000 K with a base number density of n 0 = 300 cm −3 . This simple model produces systematically low estimates for the Hβ absorption. This likely indicates that the exosphere does not follow a simple hydrostatic pressure law and a more realistic treatment is necessary to more closely match the line ratios. We note that the exospheric parameters derived here and very similar to those derived by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Christie et al. (2013)</ref> who give a detailed treatment of the n = 2 hydrogen level population in the exosphere of HD 189733b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">ESTIMATING THE PLANETARY MAGNETIC FIELD</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STRENGTH</head><p>Our measurements can be used to estimate the planetary magnetic field strength by considering some limiting cases of pressure balance between the interplanetary material (i.e., stellar wind or corona) and the planetary magnetosphere. Rewriting equation <ref type="formula">(9)</ref> from <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. (2013)</ref> we see that the magnetic field strength of the planet at the pole is</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">B p = 2 r m R p 3 8π ρ w ∆u 2 w + P w + B 2 w 1/2 (4)</formula><p>where ρ w is the mass density of the stellar wind or corona, ∆u w is the relative velocity of the planet and the wind, P w is the thermal pressure of the wind, and B w is the interplanetary magnetic field strength (i.e., the stellar magnetic field strength at the orbital radius of the planet). All of the pressure terms are the values at the orbital radius of the planet. Equation 4 neglects any pressure from the planetary atmosphere or wind. The equatorial magnetic field strength, assuming the field is purely dipolar, is one-half the polar value.</p><p>We adopt our favored model parameters and assume that the bow shock is mediated by a magnetosphere. If we neglect the pressure due to the stellar magnetic field, the dipolar magnetic field strength of the planet can be estimated by assuming pressure balance between the stellar wind and the planetary magnetosphere (Vidotto et al.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Llama et al. 2013</ref>). By neglecting the stellar magnetic pressure we are essentially estimating a lower limit for the field since any addition to the pressure will require a larger planetary field strength for the inferred standoff distance. We choose a stellar wind temperature of T w = 1 × 10 6 K which is roughly consistent with a wind of velocity of &lt;100 km s −1 at 0.03 AU ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Matsakos et al. 2015</ref>). The wind is assumed to be traveling radially at 40 km s −1 . The azimuthal wind velocity is neglected. The stellar wind is taken to be an ideal gas composed purely of protons to provide an estimate for P w . We also assume that the material in the shock has been compressed by a factor of 4, i.e., the shock is adiabatic, resulting in a stellar wind density of ρ w =2.5×10 −20 g cm −3 . We note that this density is very similar to the stellar wind density derived by  (∼3×10 −20 g cm −3 ) to reproduce observed Lα absorption in HD 189733b.</p><p>Given these assumptions we estimate an equatorial magnetic field strength of B eq = 28 G for HD 189733b, similar to the upper limit of 24 G derived by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Vidotto et al. (2010)</ref> for WASP12-b. The estimated field strength is ∼7 times larger than Jupiter's equatorial field (∼4 G) and is driven by the large value of r m . The scaling relation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Reiners et al. (2009)</ref> is used by <ref type="bibr">Reiners &amp; Chris- tensen (2010)</ref> to estimate the magnetic field strength of HD 189733b at ∼14 G. The factor of two difference between our estimates and those from the scaling relation indicate a factor of ∼8 difference in the internal heat flux used in the scaling relation estimate. The additional heat source suggested by our estimates could have significant implications for models of hot Jupiter interiors.</p><p>While we have focused on a planetary bow shock as the mechanism for producing the pre-transit absorption, alternate scenarios exist for producing similar signals. The effects of charge exchange between a hot stellar wind and a planetary wind are investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Tremblin &amp; Chiang (2013)</ref>. Their model, which has a similar geometry to the bow shock approximation, produces a layer of hot, dense neutral hydrogen at a similar standoff distance (∼10 R p ) as found in our model and shows decent agreement with Lyman α absorption measurements. Their model likely predicts too large of an excited hydrogen density over too large a volume to match the low absorption values found here. However, a more detailed investigation of excited hydrogen absorption in this context would be informative. Indeed, charge exchange may be occurring in the bow shock between stellar wind protons and neutral hydrogen that has escaped from the planet, contributing to the n=2 hydrogen density. Transiting accretion streams from the planet, which is overflowing its Roche lobe, to the star can produce sufficient column density and coverage of the stellar disk to result in pre-transit absorption <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Lai et al. 2010</ref>). This scenario, however, should produce red-shifted absorption which is not observed in our data. In fact, we find no absorption centroids shifted by more than ±5 km s −1 from line center. This suggests that the excited hydrogen has a symmetric bulk velocity along the line of sight.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented our detection of resolved pre-transit line absorption around HD 189733b in the first three members of the hydrogen Balmer series. A bow shock model is able to reproduce the important features of the absorption time series. The physical parameters derived from our model suggest an equatorial planetary magnetic field strength of B eq = 28 G. This large value is driven mainly by the large standoff distance of the magnetosphere r m = 12.75 R p , a parameter that is well constrained by the model. For the derived standoff distance, this field strength is likely a lower limit due to the multiple simplifying assumptions employed in the estimate. More detailed models which include the stellar magnetic field pressure and a full treatment of the stellar wind will prove insightful. The expected variability of the bow shock signal can also be tested by observing multiple transits across many epochs. Observations of this type could be useful probes of stellar wind variability for HJ hosts.</p><p>The magnetic field of a HJ plays an important role in determining the planetary mass loss rate: the stronger the magnetic field, the lower the outflow rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Owen &amp; Adams 2014</ref>). Planetary magnetic fields also provide a potential source of energy for SPIs via reconnection events with the stellar corona <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cuntz et al. 2000</ref>). This energy flux scales as B pl <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cuntz et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lanza 2013</ref>) so larger magnetic field strengths can potentially induce more energetic SPIs. If the field strengths estimated above are common for HJ exoplanets, this regime needs to be more fully explored by mass loss and SPI models which have generally considered field strengths similar to or less than that of Jupiter <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Lanza 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Trammell et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Strugarek et al. 2014</ref>).</p><p>Planetary magnetospheres are a revealing diagnostic of planetary interiors and the first line of defense against energetic stellar wind particles which can have a devastating impact on planetary atmospheres and life near the surface of the planet. While considered to be a critical property in understanding a planet, its evolution, and habitability, the prospects of measuring an exoplanetary magnetic field were thought to be remote. However, if independent measurements can be made of the planet hosts' stellar wind, observations such as those presented here may provide important constraints on exoplanetary magnetic fields. The large field strength we estimate implies that lower magnetic field strengths, as found in our solar system, may not be ubiquitous among other exoplanet systems. A population study of magnetic field properties of exoplanets that display bow shock-like structures will complement measurements of solar system magnetospheres and be used to better understand planetary interiors and the intertwined relationship of magnetic fields, planetary atmospheres, and habitability.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. The averaged transmission spectra for the pre-, in-, and post-transit spectra for Hα (top row), Hβ (middle row), and Hγ (bottom row). The cores of identified stellar lines other than the lines of interest are masked in gray. These points are not included in the calculation of the absorbed flux. The colored lines are the average model line profiles at the times of the average measured absorption (see section 6). The fourth frame in each row shows the in-transit empirical Monte Carlo (EMC) W λ distributions for each line. Each absorption measurement is detected above the 3σ level. The fifth column shows the EMC for the average pre-transit signal.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Master line profiles for the Ca I control lines. The format is the same as Figure 1. Each line is consistent with no absorption indicating that systematics do not contribute to the absorption measured in the Balmer lines. spectra. The average pre-transit signal shown in Figure 1 is detected at &gt; 3σ for Hα and Hβ. The Hγ signal is detected slightly below the 3σ level. The pre-transit absorption exhibits a few important properties. First, the ratio of the absorbed flux between Hα and Hβ is ∼ 1.6 − 2.0, which is much lower than in the optically thin limit. This indicates that the absorbing material is optically thick. Indeed, the line morphologies of the pre-transit observations appear saturated, i.e., flat bottomed and broad. Secondly, the absorption abruptly begins to decrease between t − t mid = −70 and −66 minutes. This requires that the material causing the pretransit absorption must begin to exit the stellar disk before the time of first optical contact (labeled t I in Figure 3). This suggests that the distribution of absorbing material is asymmetric with respect to the planet, a point that is supported by the lack of any significant absorption seen at similar times post-transit (in contrast to GJ 436, for example; Kulow et al. 2014). Finally, the integrated absorption never exceeds ∼1.3% which requires that the optically thick absorbing material cover a similar fraction of the stellar surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Absorption as a function of time from transit midpoint for a single transit of HD 189733b. First through fourth contact are marked with the vertical green dashed-dotted lines. A sharp decrease in the absorbed flux can be seen from −70 min&lt; t &lt; −40 min. The gap in the data from −115 minutes to −70 minutes was used for telluric standard observations. The absorption does not appear post-transit. The model is shown with solid lines. The uncertainties in the absorbed flux for each individual spectrum are shown in the upper-left. Each bar shows the average of the standard deviations of W λ obtained from the EMC for each point.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>2</head><label></label><figDesc>http://www.hs.uni-hamburg.de/DE/For/Gal/Xgroup/nexxus/ 2010;</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ben-Jaffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ballester</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A52 [1, 6.1, 6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">736</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bourrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dupuy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">551</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bourrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">557</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hubeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Budaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">661</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">502</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Christie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Arras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z.-Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">772</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6.2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cuntz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Saar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Musielak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L151 [1, 8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Draine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Physics of the Interstellar and Intergalactic Medium</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">383</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fossati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Haswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Froning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">714</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">222</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grillmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">456</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">767</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">743</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">751</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1, 4, 5.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kausch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Noll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASPC</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">485</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">403</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kulow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>France</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Linsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O P</forename><surname>Loyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">786</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">132</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ch</forename><surname>Helling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Van Den</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P J</forename><surname>Heuvel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">721</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6.1, 7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">557</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ehrenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">514</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bourrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wheatley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">543</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L4 [1, 6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Llama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">416</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L41 [1, 6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Llama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vidotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">436</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2179</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1, 6.1, 7, 7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lodders</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">519</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">793</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uribe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Königl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">578</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mihalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Stellar Atmospheres</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>W. H. Freeman and Co</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3761</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2917</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Koesterke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">673</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L87 [1, 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">697</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">522</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shkolnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bohlender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-G</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kürster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">622</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1075</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Strugarek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Brun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Matt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Réville</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Swain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vasisht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">452</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Trammell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Arras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z.-Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">728</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">152</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tremblin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2565</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">143</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vidotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Helling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>722L, 168 [1, 6.1, 7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vidotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ch</forename><surname>Helling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1573</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bigelow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SPIE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">362</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wilkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>6.1, 6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Redfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Edelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">781</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>L33 [6.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wyttenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ehrenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">577</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A62 [3</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
