<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:23+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Earth Similarity Index with two free parameters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-07-17">17 Jul 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Suresh</forename><surname>Chandra</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Physics Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lovely Professional University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>144411 (</postCode>
									<settlement>Phagwara, Punjab)</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Subas</forename><surname>Nepal</surname></persName>
							<email>nsubas11@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Physics Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lovely Professional University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>144411 (</postCode>
									<settlement>Phagwara, Punjab)</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mohit</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
							<email>mohitkumarsharma32@yahoo.in</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Studies in Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jiwaji University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gwalior 474011 (M.P.)</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Earth Similarity Index with two free parameters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-07-17">17 Jul 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We have derived Earth Similarity Index (ESI) with two free parameters m and T. These free parameters are optimized with the consideration that the planet Mars is almost similar to the Earth. For the optimized values of free parameters, the interior-ESI, surface-ESI and ESI for some planets are calculated. The results for m = 0.8 and T = 0.8 are compared with the values obtained by Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011). We have found that the exoplanet 55 Cnc f is within 10% away from the threshold value T. The exoplanets HD 69830 c, 55 Cnc c, 55 Cnc f, 61 Vir d and HIP 57050 b are found to have ESI within 10% from the threshold value.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In 1584, Catholic Monk Giordano Bruno asserted that there are countless suns and countless earths, and all these earths are revolving around their respective suns. When he said this in public, he was removed from the Church by charging that he was against the religion. But, this fact was found true when the confirmation of the first extra-solar planet was announced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Mayor &amp; Queloz (1995)</ref>, revolving around a sun-type. 51 Pegasi. Detection of new planets is progressing continuously and as of 9 July 2015, there are 1858 exoplanets, including 468 multiple planetary systems (http://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu/).</p><p>The number of known exoplanets is increasing each day as the detection methods used for both the ground based and space missions have improved in terms of technology and more scientists are getting interested in this field. There are many ground based and space missions to detect the exoplanets. The Search for Extra Terrestrial Intelligence (SETI) is the name of mission for searching life-forms outside the Earth. Radio telescopes having large antennas are being used to investigate the exoplanets. In Arizona, the Large Binocular Telescope Interferometer (LBTI) is being used for advanced interferometry for detection of exoplanets. These instruments are bound to advance and improve our understanding and detection of a number of exoplanets which may be similar to our Earth or not. The Kepler mission is aimed for detection of earth-like planets and the space missions such as CHEOPS (CHaracterizing ExOPlanet Satellite) and James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) are in progress. With the new generation of telescopes and missions, detection of a large number of exoplanets is expected. The exoplanets need to be classified if one is similar to the Earth or not. We therefore need a scheme which can be used for classification on the basis of data available to us. The data contain the information about planets, such as mass, radius, surface temperature, etc. These planetary parameters can be used to know about the probability of existing life-forms some where other than the Earth. The probability of existing life-forms outside the Earth is given as a concept of 'circumstellar habitable zone' by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Kasting et al. (1993)</ref>. It suggests that the focus should be made on those worlds which can hold atmosphere and liquid water. Some life-forms are most likely to be found on those planetary bodies which have similar Earth-like conditions. A two-tiered classification scheme of exoplanets is suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011)</ref>. The first tier consists of Earth Similarity Index (ESI), which decides about the worlds with respect to their similarity to the Earth. The ESI was calculated on the basis of data for exoplanets, such as mass, radius and temperature. The second tier of the scheme is the Planetary Habitability Index (PHI), based on the presence of a stable substrate, available energy, appropriate chemistry and potential for holding liquid solvent.</p><p>In the present investigation, we have derived the ESI with two free parameters. These free parameters have been optimized with the consideration that the planet Mars is almost similar to the Earth. For the optimized values of free parameters, the interior-ESI, surface-ESI and ESI for some planets are calculated. The results are compared with the available data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Earth similarity index</head><p>The similarity index is a mathematical tool that can be applied for a set of data. It is used in various fields of science, such as Mathematics (e.g., Set Theory), Ecology (e.g., Sorensen similarity index), Computer imaging (e.g., structural similarity index) and many others <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Schulze-Makuch et al., 2011)</ref>. This method is a measure of deviation from a reference system, usually on a scale lying between zero and one. The ESI is a quantitative measure of Earth-likeness.</p><p>The ESI, we have proposed, may be understood in the following manner. Consider a physical quantity having value x 0 on the surface of our Earth. Suppose, the value of this quantity varies from x a to x b , such that x a &lt; x 0 &lt; x b , on the Earth. Then, the percentage variations p and q are expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">p = x 0 − x a x 0 × 100 and q = x b − x 0 x 0 × 100</formula><p>Now, we define a threshold value T as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">T = 1 − x 0 − x a x 0 + x a m wa<label>(1)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T = 1 − x b − x 0 x b + x 0 m w b (2)</formula><p>where w a and w b denote the weight exponents and m is a free parameter. The threshold is the limiting value of ESI above which a planet is considered similar to the Earth. Further, the threshold value T can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">T = 1 − t 100</formula><p>where t can assume positive values between zero and 100, so that T is positive, having the value between zero and 1. Thus, we have taken T also as another free parameter. In the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011)</ref>, t is taken as 20, so that T = 0.8, and m as 1. In our investigation, we have considered m to assume the values from 0.6 to 1.2.</p><p>From equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula">(2)</ref>, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">w a = lnT ln[1 − ( p 200−p ) m ]</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">w b = lnT ln[1 − ( q 200+q ) m ]</formula><p>We finally take the weight exponent w x as the geometrical mean of w a and w b . That is</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">w x = √ w a × w b</formula><p>Here, the subscript x denotes a physical quantity.</p><p>The basic ESI x for a physical quantity x is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ESI x = 1 − x − x 0 x + x 0 m wx</formula><p>For the planetary property x, the terrestrial reference is x 0 . The ESI x can assume a value between zero (no similarity with the Earth) and one (identical to the Earth). We have calculates ESI r , ESI ρ , ESI e and ESI T corresponding to radius, density, escape velocity and temperature, respectively.</p><p>The ESI r and ESI ρ , for mean radius r and bulk density ρ, respectively, are used to define the interior earth similarity index ESI I , expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">ESI I = (ESI r × ESI ρ ) 1/2<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Thus, the ESI I is the geometrical mean of ESI r and ESI ρ . The ESI e and ESI T for escape velocity v and mean surface temperature T , respectively, are used to define the surface earth similarity index ESI S , expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">ESI S = (ESI e × ESI T ) 1/2<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Thus, the ESI S is the geometrical mean of ESI e and ESI T . The ESI (sometimes called the global ESI) is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">ESI = (ESI I × ESI S ) 1/2<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Using equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(3)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">(4)</ref> in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">(5)</ref>, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ESI = (ESI r × ESI ρ × ESI e × ESI T ) 1/4</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Analysis</head><p>In our investigation, we have considered two values of T as 0.8 and 0.9. The value of T can never be greater than 1, as we are considering the Earth to be the most superior In <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>, we have given the values of physical parameters, interior-ESI, surface-ESI and ESI for 31 objects. For 21 objects, the values of physical parameters are the same as given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011)</ref>. In their calculations, there are m = 1 and T = 0.8. In the last column of <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>, we have given the values of Schulze-Makuch et al.</p><p>(2011) for the ESI. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> gives the similar results for m = 0.8 and T = 0.9.</p><p>Most of the exoplanets are detected by transit photometry method and radial velocity method. The transit photometry method cannot measure the mass of exoplanet whereas the radial velocity method cannot measure the radius of exoplanet ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Jones et al., 2008)</ref>. So, for the exoplanets for which either mass or radius was not measured, the mass or radius is calculated with the help of mass-radius relation, given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Sotin et al. (2007)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>From <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>, we have found that for each object, the present value of ESI, in general, larger than that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011)</ref>. It is due to the change in the value of m. We have also found that the exoplanet 55 Cnc f is within 10% limit from the threshold value T . The exoplanets HD 69830 d, 55 Cnc c, 55 Cnc f, 61 Vir d and HIP 57050 b have the ESI within 10% limit from the threshold value. This supports the opinion for existence of life in the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>We have derived the ESI with two free parameters, the threshold value T and m. After     </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>planet.</head><label></label><figDesc>The variations of parameters, relative to those of the mean values on the Earth, are taken as the following. The definitional limits for radius are from 0.5 to 1.5 times the Earth's radius (Sotin et al., 2009). The limit for the mass of an existing planet is from 0.1 to 10 times that of the Earth (Gaidos et al., 2005). For the density, the definitional limits are 0.7 and 1.5 times the Earth's density. The temperature variation is taken from 273 K to 232 K. The definitional limits for the escape velocity are considered as 0.4 and 1.4 times that of the Earth. For these limits, we have calculated earth similarity indexes corresponding to radius, density, escape velocity and temperature. For the given values of parameters for the planets in our solar system, we have calcu- lated ESI, where m and T are considered as the free parameters. The values of ESI are found large for the Mars, Mercury and Venus. For these three planets, in Figure 1, we have plotted ESI versus m for T = 0.8 and T = 0.9. In the figure, solid line is for the Mars, dashed line for the Mercury and dotted line for the Venus. For other solar planets, the ESI is small and therefore is not shown in the figure. We have also drawn a line for ESI = 0.8 and ESI = 0.9 in the respective figure. For the optimization of free parameter m, we have considered that the Mars has the ESI equal to the terminal value T . For both, T = 0.8 and T = 0.9, we have found m = 0.8, where the ESI of Mars is equal to the terminal value T . Hence, in the further calculations of the ESI S , ESI I and ESI for various solar planets and satellites, and exoplanets, we have taken two values of T as 0.8 and 0.9, and the value of m as 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>optimization that the ESI of Mars is equal to the threshold value T , we got the value of m as 0.8. In the paper of Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011), the value of m is 1. For the present value of m = 0.8, some exoplanets have come in the range up to the threshold value. It enhances the probability of finding life in the interstellar medium.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>6333 *</head><label>6333</label><figDesc>Values reported by Schulze-Makuch et al. (2011) for m = 1 and T = 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Variation of ESI versus m for T = 0.8 and T = 0.9. Solid line is for the Mars, dashed line for the Mercury and dotted line for the Venus. We have also plotted line for ESI = 0.8 and ESI = 0.9 in the respective figure. For other solar-planets, the value of ESI is very small.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Values of various ESI for some solar planets and satellites and exoplanets with m = 0.8 
and T = 0.8. 
S.No. 
Body 
Radius Density Esc. Vel. Temp ESI I 
ESI S 
ESI 
ESI* 
(EU) 
(EU) 
(EU) 
K 
1 
Earth 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
288. 1.0000 1.0000 1.0000 
1.000 
2 
Mars 
0.532 
0.713 
0.449 
227. 0.8643 0.7394 0.7994 
0.700 
3 
Mercury 
0.382 
0.984 
0.379 
440. 0.8773 0.6143 0.7341 
0.600 
4 
Moon 
0.272 
0.606 
0.212 
220. 0.7509 0.6235 0.6842 
0.560 
5 
Venus 
0.949 
0.950 
0.925 
730. 0.9849 0.4381 0.6568 
0.440 
6 
Io 
0.285 
0.639 
0.228 
130. 0.7660 0.3941 0.5494 
0.360 
7 
Callisto 
0.378 
0.352 
0.218 
134. 0.6916 0.4022 0.5274 
0.340 
8 
Jupiter 
10.973 
0.240 
5.379 
152. 0.4800 0.4387 0.4589 
0.290 
9 
Ganymede 
0.412 
0.352 
0.244 
110. 0.7009 0.3375 0.4864 
0.290 
10 
Ceres 
0.074 
0.376 
0.045 
167. 0.5225 0.3447 0.4244 
0.270 
11 
Europa 
0.244 
0.546 
0.180 
102. 0.7194 0.2925 0.4587 
0.260 
12 
Saturn 
9.140 
0.124 
3.225 
134. 0.4049 0.4318 0.4181 
0.250 
13 
Titan 
0.404 
0.341 
0.235 
94. 0.6928 0.2836 0.4432 
0.240 
14 
Uranus 
3.980 
0.230 
1.910 
76. 0.5728 0.2604 0.3862 
0.190 
15 
Neptune 
3.864 
0.297 
2.105 
72. 0.6200 0.2409 0.3865 
0.180 
16 
Titania 
0.123 
0.301 
0.069 
60. 0.5433 0.1295 0.2652 
0.100 
17 
Enceladus 
0.039 
0.291 
0.021 
75. 0.4271 0.1255 0.2315 
0.094 
18 
Pluto 
0.180 
0.371 
0.109 
40. 0.6180 0.0878 0.2329 
0.075 
19 
Triton 
0.212 
0.379 
0.130 
38. 0.6402 0.0856 0.2341 
0.074 
20 
HD69830 d 
4.190 
0.250 
2.100 
312. 0.5818 0.8439 0.7007 
0.600 
21 
55 Cnc c 
5.680 
0.250 
2.840 
310. 0.5510 0.8031 0.6652 
0.560 
22 
55 Cnc f 
4.910 
0.390 
3.060 
310. 0.6405 0.7918 0.7121 
0.614 
23 
61 Vir d 
3.680 
0.460 
2.500 
375. 0.7028 0.7093 0.7060 
24 
HIP 57050 b 
6.640 
0.320 
3.780 
250. 0.5743 0.7217 0.6438 
25 
Mu Ara d 
8.380 
0.280 
4.450 
327. 0.5292 0.7059 0.6112 
26 
HD 142 b 
11.120 
0.240 
5.430 
286. 0.4787 0.7397 0.5951 
27 
HD 96167 b 
9.360 
0.260 
4.810 
334. 0.5070 0.6833 0.5886 
28 
HD 108874 b 12.490 
0.220 
5.890 
294. 0.4558 0.7197 0.5728 
29 
HD 210277 b 11.980 
0.230 
5.720 
275. 0.4658 0.7109 0.5754 
30 
HD 147513 b 10.990 
0.240 
5.380 
263. 0.4798 0.6970 0.5783 
31 
HD 69830 c 
2.820 
0.540 
2.070 
549. 0.7636 0.5253 0.</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Same as Table 1 with m = 0.8 and T = 0.9. 
S.No. 
Body 
ESI I 
ESI S 
ESI 
1 
Earth 
1.0000 1.0000 
1.0000 
2 
Mars 
0.9334 0.8671 
0.8997 
3 
Mercury 
0.9401 0.7945 
0.8642 
4 
Moon 
0.8735 0.8001 
0.8360 
5 
Venus 
0.9928 0.6773 
0.8200 
6 
Io 
0.8817 0.6442 
0.7537 
7 
Callisto 
0.8402 0.6505 
0.7393 
8 
Jupiter 
0.7071 0.6777 
0.6923 
9 
Ganymede 
0.8455 0.5988 
0.7115 
10 
Ceres 
0.7360 0.6048 
0.6672 
11 
Europa 
0.8560 0.5597 
0.6922 
12 
Saturn 
0.6525 0.6726 
0.6625 
13 
Titan 
0.8409 0.5515 
0.6810 
14 
Uranus 
0.7686 0.5298 
0.6381 
15 
Neptune 
0.7980 0.5106 
0.6383 
16 
Titania 
0.7497 0.3809 
0.5344 
17 
Enceladus 
0.6692 0.3753 
0.5012 
18 
Pluto 
0.7968 0.3170 
0.5026 
19 
Triton 
0.8101 0.3133 
0.5038 
20 
HD69830 d 
0.7744 0.9230 
0.8454 
21 
55 Cnc c 
0.7547 0.9016 
0.8249 
22 
55 Cnc f 
0.8103 0.8956 
0.8519 
23 
61 Vir d 
0.8466 0.8503 
0.8484 
24 
HIP 57050 b 0.7696 0.8573 
0.8123 
25 
Mu Ara d 
0.7404 0.8483 
0.7926 
26 
HD 142 b 
0.7062 0.8673 
0.7826 
27 
HD 96167 b 
0.7256 0.8354 
0.7786 
28 
HD 108874 b 0.6901 0.8562 
0.7686 
29 
HD 210277 b 0.6971 0.8512 
0.7703 
30 
HD 147513 b 0.7070 0.8433 
0.7721 
31 
HD 69830 c 
0.8804 0.7379 
0.8060 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>Financial support from the Department of Science &amp; Technology is thankfully acknowledged. Thanks are due to Lovely Professional University, Punjab for encouragements.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the principle of plentitude: a review of terrestrial planet habitability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gaidos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Deschenes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dundon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exoplanets search methods, discoveries, and prospects for astrobiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Earth&apos;s early atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="926" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Jupiter-mass companion to a solar type star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A two-tiered approach to assess the habitability of exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schulze-Makuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mendez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fairen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Paris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Davila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R D S</forename><surname>Antonio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Catling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1041" to="1052" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mass-radius curve for extrasolar earth like planets and ocean planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sotin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Grasset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mocquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
