<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Data Analysis on the Extra-solar Planets Using Robust Clustering</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-10-24">24 Oct 2006</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ing-Guey</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing-Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hsin-Chu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Li-Chin</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Hsinchu University of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hsin-Chu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wen-Liang</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Hsinchu University of Education</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hsin-Chu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Miin-Shen</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chung Yuan Christian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chung-Li</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Data Analysis on the Extra-solar Planets Using Robust Clustering</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-10-24">24 Oct 2006</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>data analysis</term>
					<term>cluster analysis</term>
					<term>planetary systems</term>
					<term>stellar dynamics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We use both the conventional and more recently developed methods of cluster analysis to study the data of extra-solar planets. Using the data set with planetary mass M, orbital period P , and orbital eccentricity e, we investigate the possible clustering in the lnM, lnP , lnP − lnM, e, and lnP − e spaces. There are two main implications: (1) mass distribution is continuous and (2) orbital population could be classified into three clusters, which correspond to the exoplanets in the regimes of tidal, ongoing tidal and disc interaction, respectively.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Astronomers' observational efforts have led to the detection of more than 160 extrasolar planets <ref type="bibr">(exoplanets)</ref>. These discoveries open a new window to astronomy, which could eventually lead to answers to the fundamental questions about the formation of planetary systems, including our Solar System. In fact, some of the work has already been done to address the important questions about planetary evolution. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Zakamska &amp; Tremaine (2004)</ref> tried to explain the high eccentricities of exoplanets by possible stellar encounters. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Ji et al. (2002</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ji et al. ( , 2003</ref> have studied the orbital evolutions of a few known resonant planetary systems. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Veras &amp; Armitage (2004)</ref> proposed the possible mechanisms to make exoplanets migrate outward. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jiang &amp; Ip (2001)</ref> investigated the origin of orbital elements of the planetary system of upsilon Andromedae. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Yeh &amp; Jiang (2001)</ref> studied the orbital migration of scattered planets. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Jiang &amp; Yeh (2004a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, 2004b</ref>) did some analysis on the orbital evolution of systems with planet-disc interaction.</p><p>While the number of detected planets keep increasing, it is important to study the distributions of their masses, periods, and other orbital elements. The details of these distributions could have crucial implications for the formation and evolution of planetary systems. It is quite common that we use a simple function, say, a power law, to model the distribution of a quantity in our system <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Tabachnik &amp; Tremaine 2002)</ref>. It also happens that, after a further study, we find that a single power-law is not good enough and we make the change to a double-power-law. This process will eventually help us to understand the properties of the system.</p><p>On the other hand, cluster analysis, which is a data analysis tool to find clusters of a data set with the most similarity in the same cluster and the most dissimilarity between different clusters, might also help us to distinguish a double-power-law from a single power-law for a particular study from another point of view. When we find that there is only one group (or a huge number of groups) through cluster analysis, it is likely that a simple function (say, a single power-law) could be a good approximation. When there are two or more groups in cluster analysis, we might need a combination of several functions (say, double-power-law) to model the data set. In this way, we can be more confident of the results derived from the usual conventional process. Another advantage of cluster analysis is that it can also be used to study the distributions of multi-variables easily.</p><p>Clustering is a powerful exploratory approach to find groups in data and to reveal the structure information of a given data set. It is a data driven procedure to classify a datum in one of a few classes by looking at proximity and homogeneity in feature space. Conventional approaches to clustering can be grouped into two categories namely partitional and hierarchical. The k-means (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">MacQueen 1967</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">, Hartigan 1975</ref> algorithm is a popular example of partitional clustering whereby the data is partitioned into k classes with the value of k known a priori. Single linkage algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Gower and</ref><ref type="bibr">Ross 1969, Hartigan 1967)</ref> is an example of hierarchical agglomerative clustering where for n data a hierarchy of clusters ranging from n to 1 is formed.</p><p>The single linkage algorithm was used in asteroid studies ( <ref type="bibr">Zappala et al. 1995)</ref> and in many meteoroid stream searches <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Baggaley &amp; Galligan 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, Galligan 2003a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Galligan 2003b</ref>). <ref type="bibr">Zappala et al. (1995)</ref> identified the dynamical families from a sample of 12,487 asteroids. They divided the main asteroid belt into three different zones (the inner, intermediate, and outer zone) and study the hierarchical structures of the orbital families. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baggaley &amp; Galligan (1997)</ref> first used the single linkage algorithm to work on meteoroid stream data from the Advanced Meteoroid Orbit Radar (AMOR). They probed the structure of the orbital distributions and determined the extent of dynamical families or clusters in the population. Moreover, in order to determine a reasonable cut-off level, they also introduced the combination of the single-linkage method with a randomization technique. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Galligan (2003a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Galligan ( , 2003b</ref> further studied more recent AMOR data by these methods.</p><p>From the previous work, we can see that the cut-off level in the conventional single linkage method would influence the results of clustering and therefore the number of clusters. In Section 2, we first briefly review the single linkage algorithm. We then review the much more advanced method called the similarity-based clustering method (SCM) proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang &amp; Wu (2004)</ref> in Section 3. Some numerical examples and comparisons between the single linkage algorithm and the SCM are made in Section 4. Section 5 starts our applications of the single linkage algorithm and the SCM on the data of exoplanets. The implications of these results on the formation and evolution of planetary systems will also be given in Section 5. Section 6 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The Single Linkage Algorithm</head><p>The clustering process begins with measures of the distance of the objects from one another. Several measures are available, but we shall use simple Euclidean distance in most cases. Usually, the distances can be summarized in a symmetric n × n matrix D = (d ij ), where d ij is the Euclidean distance between objects i and j. We illustrate the single linkage algorithm with the artificial distance matrix given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Johnson &amp; Wichern (1988)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">D =        0 9 0 3 7 0 6 5 9 0 11 10 2 8 0        .</formula><p>The minimum distance occurs between objects 3 and 5, so the first cluster, labelled as (35), will consist of those objects. The second matrix of distances is formed by deleting the rows and columns of D corresponding to objects 3 and 5, and adding a row and column with the distances of the remaining objects from the cluster (35). Those distances are found from the rule Therefore, clusters (135) and (24) are merged to form a single cluster of all five objects, (12345), when the minimum distance reaches 6.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d (35),1 = min{d 31 , d 51 } = min{3, 11} = 3 d<label>(</label></formula><p>The clusters are illustrated in the dendrogram of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 1</ref>. The dendrogram is formed by plotting the minimum distances for each cluster in a tree configuration leading to the single cluster of all 5 objects. The objects should be ordered so that the branches of the dendrogram stand alone without crossing. The dendrogram clearly suggests that the sample may contain two sets of objects: (135) and <ref type="bibr">(24)</ref>.</p><p>In general, single linkage algorithm, which combines the original n single-object clusters hierarchically into one cluster of n objects, cab be summarized as:</p><p>Single Linkage Algorithm S1. Start with n single-object clusters. The distances are described by the initial distance matrix D = (d ij ).</p><p>S2. Search for the nearest pair of clusters from the distance matrix. When there are more than one candidate pairs, randomly pick one of them. Let the distance between this pair of clusters, U and V , be d U V , where</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">d U V = min u∈U,v∈V {d uv }.</formula><p>S3. Merge clusters U and V . Label the newly formed cluster as (UV ). Form a new distance matrix by (i) deleting the rows and columns corresponding to clusters U and V and (ii) adding a row and column giving the distances between cluster (UV ) and the remaining clusters. The distances between cluster (UV ) and any other cluster W are computed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">d (U V )W = min{d U W , d V W },</formula><p>where d U W and d V W are the distances between clusters U and W and clusters V and W , as defined in S2.</p><p>S4. Repeat S2 and S3. All objects will be in a single cluster at the termination of the algorithm. Record the identity of clusters that are merged and the levels at which the mergers take place.</p><p>The above clustering results of single linkage algorithm can be graphically displayed in the form of a dendrogram, which shows the clustering structure at various levels of the hierarchy. The branches in the tree represent clusters. The branches come together (merge) at nodes whose positions along a distance axis indicate the level at which the fusions occur. Therefore, the vertical axis indicates the distance and the horizontal axis simply shows the data identity numbers.</p><p>Please note that the dendrogram plotted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baggaley &amp; Galligan (1997)</ref> is slightly different from what we just described here. In their plot, the meaning of the horizontal axis is different from ours. Due to the huge number of orbits, their horizontal axis shows the scale of number of clustering members. The meaning of their vertical axis is the same as ours.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The Similarity-Based Clustering Method</head><p>Let the data set be X = {x 1 , · · · , x n } where x j is a feature vector in the s-dimensional Euclidean space ℜ s and c is the specified number of clusters. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang and Wu (2004)</ref> considered maximizing the objective function J(z) with</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">J(z) = c i=1 n j=1 exp − ||x j − z i || 2 β γ ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where exp(−</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">||x j −z i || 2 β</formula><p>) is the similarity measure between x j and the ith cluster center z i , ||x j − z i || is the Euclidean norm, γ &gt; 0 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">β = n j=1 ||x j − ¯ x|| 2 n , where ¯ x = 1 n n j=1 x j .</formula><p>Since the clustering result is influenced by γ, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang and Wu (2004)</ref> proposed correlation comparison algorithm (CCA) to select γ. According to the fact that the parameter γ controls the location of the peaks of J(z), they considered the total similarity functioñ J(x k ) γm for each data point x k with</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">˜ J(x k ) γm = n j=1 exp − ||x j − x k || 2 β γm , k = 1, · · · , n,</formula><p>where γ m = 5m, m = 1, 2, 3, · · ·. The correlation between the values of˜Jof˜ of˜J (x k ) γm and˜J and˜ and˜J(x k ) γ m+1 are calculated. That is, CCA is based on a correlation comparison procedure with "γ 1 = 5, γ 2 = 10", "γ 2 = 10, γ 3 = 15", "γ 3 = 15, γ 4 = 20", · · · etc. The CCA then is summarized as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Correlation Comparison Algorithm (CCA)</formula><p>S1. Set m = 1 and give a threshold ǫ 1 .</p><p>S2. Calculate the correlation of the values of˜Jof˜ of˜J(x k ) γm and˜Jand˜ and˜J(x k ) γ m+1 .</p><p>S3. If the correlation is greater than or equal to the threshold ǫ 1 THEN choose γ m to be the estimate of γ;</p><p>ELSE m = m + 1 and GOTO S2.</p><p>Since Yang and Wu (2004) suggested a threshold around 0.97 ∼ 0.999, we choose 0.99 for the threshold in this paper. After the parameter γ is estimated using CCA, the next step is to find a z i that maximizes the SCM objective function J(z). Differentiating J(z) with respect to all z i , we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">dJ ( z) dz i = n j=1 2 γ β (x j − z i ) exp − ||x j − z i || 2 β γ<label>(2)</label></formula><p>and set (2) to zero. The necessary condition that maximizes J ( z) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">z i = n j=1 x j exp(− ||x j −z i || 2 β ) γ n j=1 exp(− ||x j −z i || 2 β ) γ .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>This necessary condition can be decomposed into two conditions. First, we take the similarity relation S(x j , z i ) with</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">S ij = S(x j , z i ) = exp − ||x j − z i || 2 β<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and then the necessary condition (3) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">z i = n j=1 S γ ij x j n j=1 S γ ij .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>This forms the similarity clustering algorithm (SCA). Thus, after the CCA is implemented to get an estimate γ, the SCA will be used to find the peaks of the SCM objective function is then summarized as follows:</p><p>Similarity Clustering Algorithm (SCA) by Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(5)</ref>;</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Increment ℓ; Until max i ||z (ℓ+1) i − z (ℓ) i || &lt; ǫ.</formula><p>When one processes SCA, all the cluster centers, z i , will change positions for each iteration. If the data set has only one peak on the SCM objective function, all the centers will gradually centralize to that unique peak. In this case, we will claim there is only one cluster for this data set. When the data set has more than one peak on the SCM objective function, we can randomly give more initial cluster centers to process SCA and these centers will then centralize to the peaks of the SCM objective function. The problem here is what kind of the initialization can guarantee that all peaks (clusters) will be found simultaneously. To solve this problem, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Yang and Wu (2004)</ref> suggested to set all data points to be the initial centers (i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">z (0) = (z (0) 1 , · · · , z (0) n ) = (x 1 , · · · , x n ))</formula><p>. They successfully showed that all peaks (clusters) will be found for this initialization.</p><p>Next, we present an example to illustrate the CCA and SCA. In the data set of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 2</ref>, there are one large cluster and two small clusters. By the CCA, we find that γ = 10 is a good estimate. Then we process SCA with this data set by initializing</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">z (0) = (z (0) 1 , · · · , z (0) n ) = (x 1 , · · · , x n ).</formula><p>We show the positions of these cluster centers after 1, 5 and 10 iterations as the full circles in <ref type="figure">Fig</ref> Therefore, we can completely cluster the data set in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 2</ref> into three clusters shown in the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 5</ref>. The process includes that: (i) process CCA to estimate the parameter γ, (ii) process SCA with</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">z (0) = (z (0) 1 , · · · , z (0) n ) = (x 1 , · · · , x n )</formula><p>, and (iii) process the single linkage algorithm with the final positions of n cluster centers to find the optimal cluster number c * and identify these c * clusters. This forms the structure of SCM which is summarized as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">Similarity-Based Clustering Method (SCM) S1. Estimate γ using CCA; S2. Process SCA with z (0) = (z (0) 1 , · · · , z (0) n ) = (x 1 , · · · , x n );</formula><p>S3. Process the single linkage algorithm with the final n cluster centers; S4. Find the optimal cluster number c * according to the dendrogram; S5. Identify these c * clusters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The Numerical Examples and Comparisons</head><p>In this section, we consider the bivariate normal mixtures of three classes in order to assess the performance of the single linkage algorithm and SCM. Let N 2 (a, Σ) represent the bivariate normal with mean vector a and covariance matrix Σ, we consider the random sample of data drawn from</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">α 1 N 2 (a 1 , Σ 1 ) + α 2 N 2 (a 2 , Σ 2 ) + α 3 N 2 (a 3 , Σ 3 )</formula><p>with α 1 + α 2 + α 3 = 1, 0 &lt; α i &lt; 1, i = 1, 2, 3. We design various bivariate normal mixture distributions shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. In each test, we consider the sample size n = 200. The data set generated for Test 1 is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 6</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">From Fig. 6</ref>, it seems there are 2 or 3 clusters. Thus, a precise method to determine the cluster number is necessary. We process the single linkage algorithm and SCM with this data set. The clustering results are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>. In the left panel, it is clear that different cut-off level of distances would give different number of clusters for the single linkage algorithm's result. In the right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>, SCM clearly indicates that there are three well-separated clusters. Furthermore, the cluster centers are (1.2784, 1.3323), (5.9372, 5.7933), (9.4804, 9.0544). These results reflect the original structure of the data set designed for Test 1. <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref> shows the data set generated for Test 2. <ref type="figure">From Fig. 8</ref>, the cluster number seems to be 3. In the same way, we implement the single linkage algorithm and SCM on this data set. The dendrogram of the single linkage algorithm cannot classify this data set well. But the SCM clearly indicates that there are three well-separated clusters. Furthermore, the cluster centers are (1.2096, 1.3824), (4.9835, 4.6876), <ref type="bibr">(10.6420, 10.3181)</ref>. These results reflect the structure of the data set designed for Test 2. For all the above three tests, SCM gave the optimal cluster number c * = 3 which is exactly the actual cluster number but the single linkage algorithm fails. It shows the superiority of SCM over the single linkage algorithm. As supported by these experiments, SCM produces satisfactory results with the artificially generated data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">The Results</head><p>In this section, both the single linkage algorithm and the SCM will be used to cluster the data of extrasolar planets. Our data is from the Extrasolar Planets Catalog maintained by Jean Schneider (http://cfa-www.harvard.edu/planets/catalog.html). We use the data of April 2005 and exclude the incomplete ones. There are 143 planets (see the Appendix) available for our work and each of them have the values of Msin i, orbital period P , semimajor axis a and also orbital eccentricity e, where M is the planetary mass and i is the unknown orbital inclinations. We set sin i = 1, for simplicity ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Trilling et al. 2002)</ref>. This assumption shall not have a significant impact on the results of our clustering analysis because it is not the absolute mass that matters but the structures of the mass distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">The Planetary Masses and Periods</head><p>Since there is a possible mass-period correlation for extrasolar planets <ref type="bibr">(Zucker &amp; Mazeh 2002</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">, Pätzold &amp; Rauer 2002</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">, Jiang et al. 2003</ref>), it should be interesting to see whether there are groups for extrasolar planets on the lnP -lnM plane. The results of this clustering analysis would give hints about the formation conditions of these planets.</p><p>To investigate the problem step by step, we first study the possible clustering on the space of lnM. The dendrogram illustrating the hierarchical clustering for lnM space is shown in the left panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 12</ref>. From the dendrogram, we find that clustering (or mergers) takes place at different levels. For example, there are two clusters with the distance of about 0.48. One of them can actually be divided into two with the distance of about 0.38. Thus, the number of clusters keeps increasing and becomes very large when a smaller distance is chosen as the condition to group the data. Consequently, it is difficult to identity the final configuration of clusters. Please note that because there are too many data points, the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis of all dendrograms in this section are not clear. They can be ignored here. To obtain a better partition for this data, we use the SCM to do the analysis. The corresponding dendrogram is shown in the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 12</ref>. From this dendrogram, the vertical axis indicates that the largest level is at 2.4×10 −4 , which is less than our chosen ǫ in SCA (We set ǫ = 0.001.). It means that the minimum distance between pairs of clusters is negligible. Therefore, all objects are merged to form a single cluster. That is, by SCM, the data of discovered exoplanets shall be regarded as a continuous distribution in the lnM space.</p><p>Indeed, the histogram of the exoplanets in the lnM space in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 13</ref> indicates that there is only one strong peak around lnM = 0 and the whole distribution seems to be continuous. Thus, the Jupiter-mass exoplanets dominate the population. Of course, there are many factors that influence the mass distribution. For example, the observational selection effect and perhaps also the orbital instability of close-in massive planets. Nevertheless, the clustering result showing there is only one group statistically confirms that there is no particular constraint on the possible planetary masses except their boundaries, i.e. the maximum and minimum masses.</p><p>We then study the clustering on the lnP space. In the same way, we implement both the single linkage algorithm and SCM in the lnP space. The left and right panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 14</ref> show the dendrogram of these two methods, respectively. From the left panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 14</ref>, there are no meaningful well-separated clusters. But there are two well-separated clusters in the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 3</ref>. Thus, the SCM shows that there are 2 clusters, and the corresponding clustering results are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. The cluster with smaller average value of lnP is called Cluster P 1 and the other one is called Cluster P 2 . The center of Cluster P 1 is at 1.4552 and the center of Cluster P 2 is at 6.5455. We also make a histogram of our data in the lnP space. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 15</ref>, for this case, it is difficult to group the data by eye. The two crosses in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 15</ref> indicate the cluster centers determined by SCM. They are very close to the peaks of the histogram, so the result of SCM is indeed reasonable and correct. Thus, we have statistically shown that there are two clusters for exoplanets in the lnP space. The distribution of orbital periods is unlikely to be a continuous function. In fact, there is a statistical gap between two continuous distributions.</p><p>How could that gap form? There could be two possibilities: (1) it is difficult to form the planets at particular distances from the central stars, (2) planetary migrations did happen. The possible planetary migrations as studied in many theoretical papers are good candidates to affect the results of observed period distribution. However, if there is only one migration mechanism, the resulting distribution is probably still continuous, unless that the rate of this migration mechanism varies as a sharp function of the orbital period. If there is a period for which the migration rate is fastest, we might expect much less systems would end up there. Another simple interpretation is that there are two important migration mechanisms to make the exoplanets have two clusters in the lnP space. Indeed, the center of Cluster P 1 , 1.4552, is within the regime in which the tidal interaction with the central star is important ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Jiang et al. 2003</ref>) and the center of Cluster P 2 , 6.5455, is within the regime in which the disc interaction is important ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Armitage et al. 2002</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">, Trilling et al. 2002</ref>. The migrations caused by these two mechanisms, tidal interaction and disc interaction, might produce the two clusters in our statistical results.</p><p>Next, we consider the clustering on the lnP -lnM space. In the same way, we implement both the single linkage algorithm and the SCM on the data in the lnP -lnM space. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 16</ref> shows the dendrogram of these two methods. The right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 16</ref>   <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref> shows the members of these three clusters.  It is not surprising that there are more than one cluster here as there are already two clusters in the lnP space. From <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 15 and 17</ref>, we can see that Cluster P M 1 is very much overlapping Cluster P 1 and Cluster P M 3 is overlapping Cluster P 2 . The reason why the Cluster P M 2 exists is that there is a very massive close-in planet, HD 162020 b (data 29), with mass (Msini) 13.75 M J and period 8.42 days. This planet together with a few other massive close-ins stand out as a new class. If some of the members of Cluster P M 2 fall into the central stars and thus disappear in the plot, this cluster might be absorbed by the other two clusters. Cluster P M 2 might represent the temporary group with members falling into the stars in the near future. Thus, we speculate that this cluster experiences on-going tidal interaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Orbital Eccentricities</head><p>To understand more about the orbital properties of these exoplanets, we study the possible clustering in the eccentricity e space. We shall also study the clustering of exoplanets' semi-major axes. Because lna is simply a constant times lnP , the clustering of the data in the lna space is the same as in the lnP space. Thus, we use lnP to represent lna and study the clustering in the lnP − e space. In the same way, we implement the single linkage algorithm and SCM on the data in the e space. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 18</ref> shows the resulting dendrogram by these two methods. The right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 18</ref> clearly indicates that there are four well-separated clusters but the left panel fails. Therefore, the SCM shows that there are 4 clusters, and the corresponding clustering results are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>. Furthermore, the cluster centers of Cluster e 1 , e 2 , e 3 , and e 4 are at 0.0486, 0.3177, 0.6562, and 0.9207, respectively. We also plot the histogram of the data in the e space as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 19</ref>. From the histogram, it looks as though there is more than one cluster but it is difficult to determine the number of clusters by eye. The result of SCM seems to be reasonable, particularly after we add the crosses to indicate the centers of these four clusters. Even though there are four clusters in the e space, there is only one member in the Cluster e 4 and this planet has a very large orbital eccentricity 0.927.</p><p>Finally, we consider the single linkage algorithm and the SCM in the lnP − e space. In the same way, we implement the single linkage algorithm and SCM on the data. The left and right panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 20</ref> show the dendrogram of these two methods, respectively. The right panel clearly indicates that there are three well-separated clusters. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref> shows the SCM's clustering results. The cluster centers of Cluster P e 1 , P e 2 , and P e 3 are given by (lnP, e) = (1.2860, 0.0446), (2.7573, 0.1206), and (6.3061, 0.3396), respectively.  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">107 108 109 110 111 112 113 114 115 116  117 118 119 120 121 122 123 124 125 126  127 128 129 130 131 132 133 134 135 136  137 138 139 140 141 142 143</ref> In the lnP − e space as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 21</ref>, there are two data points in Cluster P e 2 with a particularly large e and thus form a class. They are data 35 and data 41. We find that these two are also in the Cluster P M 2 , so they are likely to be the temporary cluster, in which some of the members will fall into their central stars in the near future. In general, the exoplanet data in the lnP − e space shows that there is a strong eccentricity-period correlation. That is, the planets with larger orbital periods might have larger eccentricities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Speculations and Implications</head><p>To statistically investigate the properties of the distributions of the mass, period, and orbits of exoplanets, we have used both the conventional method, single-linkage algorithm, and the advanced SCM of Cluster Analysis to study the possible clusters of the exoplanets in the lnM, lnP , lnP − lnM, e, and lnP − e space. In general, the SCM gives very good and reasonable results.</p><p>We find that there is only one cluster in the lnM space, so a continuous mass function <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Tabachnik and Tremaine 2002)</ref> would be a good approximation. We find that there are two clusters in the lnP space and this could be due to two migration mechanisms; tidal and disc interactions. In addition to the two clusters associated with the above two mechanisms, there is one more cluster which might present the massive close-in exoplanets with on-going tidal interaction in the lnP − lnM space. Our SCM found that there are four clusters in the e space. However, there is only one member in the Cluster e 4 , which is an unusual case with an extremely large eccentricity 0.927. The other three clusters, Cluster e 1 , e 2 , and e 3 might associate with the tidal, on-going tidal, and disc interactions, respectively. The three clusters in the lnP − e space, Cluster P e 1 , P e 2 , and P e 3 could associate with the same things, respectively. Finally, the eccentricity-period correlation is strong and obvious.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>We would like to thank the anonymous referee for their helpful comments and suggestions to improve the presentation of the paper. We are also grateful to the National Center for High-performance Computing for computer time and facilities. This work is supported in part by the National Science Council, Taiwan, under Ing-Guey Jiang's Grants: NSC 94-2112-M-008-010, Li-Chin Yeh's Grants: NSC 94-2115-M-134-002, Wen-Liang Hung's Grants: NSC 92-2213-E-134-001 and Miin-Shen Yang's Grants: NSC 93-2118-M-033-001.</p><p>Zappala, V., Bendjoya, P., Cellino, A., Farinella, P., <ref type="bibr">Froeschle, C., 1995, Icarus, 116, 291</ref> Zucker, S., Mazeh, T., 2002, ApJ, 568, L113</p><p>This preprint was prepared with the AAS L A T E X macros v5.0.        <ref type="bibr">155 197 145 193 198 118 179 154 191 196</ref>    <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">104 108 122 148 169 164 181 106 158 190 113 157 133 192 101 111 115 105 107 123 151 124 135 155 147</ref>  <ref type="bibr">166 197 198 145 193 187 118 191 179 196 154 129 140 177 194</ref>  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">186 141 150 182 189 143 110 168 152 142 114 126 160 178 195 184 117 138 103 161 163 172 183 131 171 167 112 134 121</ref>    <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">104 108 122 148 169 164 181 106 158 190 30 91 31 40 90 43 87 64 95 86 46 79 66 77 48 49 59 69</ref>       In the plot, the left cross indicates that the center of Cluster P 1 is at 1.4552 and the right cross indicates that the center of Cluster P 2 is at 6.5455.         </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. 3 and the left of Fig. 4, respectively. The final convergent positions of all cluster centers are shown as the full circles in the right of Fig. 4. Please note that all the data points, (x 1 , · · · , x n ), are also plotted as the dots in Fig. 3 and 4. It is obvious that there are only three full circles because all cluster centers centralize to the three peaks of the SCM objective function. There are three clusters for this data set by the view of sight. However, a precise method to determine the cluster number from these final n cluster centers should be provided. We use the single linkage algorithm with the final positions of all cluster centers to find the optimal cluster number c * . The result is shown as the dendrogram in the left panel of Fig. 5. This dendrogram clearly indicates that there are three well separated clusters and hence the optimal cluster number c * = 3. At the same time the identified clusters will be found. The identified clusters are shown in the right panel of Fig. 5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 10 shows the data set generated for Test 3. It is difficult to know the cluster number from Fig. 10. We also implement the single linkage algorithm and SCM on this data set. The dendrogram of the single linkage algorithm looks very complicated. However, the SCM clearly indicates that there are three well-separated clusters. Furthermore, the cluster centers are (1.2373, 3.8693), (5.3338, 7.2524), (9.3596, 11.2041). These results reflect the original structure of the data set designed for Test 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>clearly indicates that there are three well-separated clusters. Three clusters are called Cluster P M 1 , P M 2 and P M 3 and their centers are at (lnP, lnM) = (1.2750, −0.6980), (2.8093, −0.3710) and (6.1522, 0.4857), respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 17</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17 shows the distribution of exoplanet in the lnP -lnM space. The triangles are the members of Cluster P M 1 , the open squares are the members of Cluster P M 2 , and the full circles are the members of Cluster P M 3 . There are two are reasons for the crosses going from the bottom-left to the top-right. The observational selection effect explains the absence in the bottom-right corner and the tidal interaction (Jiang et al. 2003) explains the absence in the top-left corner.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-The dendrogram for distances between five objects in the example of Section 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2.-The data set with one larger cluster and two small clusters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-The positions of cluster centers (full circles): the left panel is after 1 iteration and the right panel is after 5 iterations. Please note that the original data points are indicated by dots.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-The positions of cluster centers (full circles): the left panel is after 10 iteration and the right panel is the convergent. Please note that the original data points are indicated by dots.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-The left panel is the dendrogram through the SCM. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear. The right panel is the identified clusters through the SCM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-The data set generated for Test 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 7 .Fig. 8 .</head><label>78</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-The dendrogram of Test 1: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .</head><label>910</label><figDesc>Fig. 9.-The dendrogram of Test 2: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12.-The dendrogram of exoplanets in the lnM space: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13.-The histogram of exoplanets in the lnM space.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14.-The dendrogram of exoplanets in the lnP space: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15.-The histogram of exoplanets in the lnP space. In the plot, the left cross indicates that the center of Cluster P 1 is at 1.4552 and the right cross indicates that the center of Cluster P 2 is at 6.5455.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16.-The dendrogram of exoplanets in the lnP − lnM space: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17.-The distribution of exoplanets in the lnP − lnM space. There are three crosses indicating the centers of three clusters. The triangles indicate the members of the Cluster P M 1 , the open squares indicate the members of the Cluster P M 2 , and the full circles indicate the members of the Cluster P M 3 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. 18 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Fig. 18.-The dendrogram of exoplanets in the e space: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Fig. 19 .</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Fig. 19.-The histogram of exoplanets in the e space. There are four crosses indicating the centers of four clusters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Fig. 20 .</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Fig. 20.-The dendrogram of exoplanets in the lnP − e space: the single linkage algorithm's result is on the left and the SCM's is on the right. There are too many data points, so the data identity numbers below the horizontal axis are not clear.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Fig. 21 .</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Fig. 21.-The distribution of exoplanets in the lnP − e space. There are three crosses indicating the centers of three clusters. The triangles indicate the members of the Cluster P e 1 , the open squares indicate the members of the Cluster P e 2 , and the full circles indicate the members of the Cluster P e 3 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Various Bivariate Normal Mixture Distributions for the Three Tests</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Test 
α 1 
a 1 
Σ 1 
α 2 
a 2 
Σ 2 
α 3 
a 3 
Σ 3 

1 
0.2 
(1, 1) 

1.2 
0 
0 
1.2 

0.3 
(5.7, 5.7) 

1 0 
0 1 

0.5 
(9, 9) 

1.5 
0 
0 
1.5 


2 
0.2 
(1, 1) 

2 
1.5 
1.5 
2 

0.3 
(5, 5) 

3 
0.5 
0.5 
3 

0.5 
(10, 10) 

2 1 
1 2 


3 
0.2 
(1, 3) 

2 
1.5 
1.5 
4 

0.3 
(5, 7) 

3 
0.5 
0.5 
5 

0.5 
(9, 11) 

6 1 
1 4 


</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . The clustering results in the lnP space.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Cluster 
data point no. 
P 1 
1 
2 
3 
4 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
25 
26 
27 
28 
29 
30 
33 
34 
35 
37 
38 
P 2 
5 
6 
23 
24 
31 
32 
36 
39 
40 
41 
42 
43 
44 
45 
46 
47 
48 
49 
50 
51 
52 
53 
54 
55 
56 
57 
58 
59 
60 
61 
62 
63 
64 
65 
66 
67 
68 
69 
70 
71 
72 
73 
74 
75 
76 
77 
78 
79 
80 
81 
82 
83 
84 
85 
86 
87 
88 
89 
90 
91 
92 
93 
94 
95 
96 
97 
98 
99 
100 101 
102 103 104 105 106 107 108 109 110 111 
112 113 114 115 116 117 118 119 120 121 
122 123 124 125 126 127 128 129 130 131 
132 133 134 135 136 137 138 139 140 141 
142 143 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The clustering results in the lnP -lnM space.</figDesc><table>Cluster 
data point no. 
P M 1 
1 
2 
3 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
25 
26 
27 
28 
30 
33 
34 
P M 2 
4 
29 
35 
37 
39 
40 
41 
42 
43 
48 
P M 3 
5 
6 
23 
24 
31 
32 
36 
38 
44 
45 
46 
47 
49 
50 
51 
52 
53 
54 
55 
56 
57 
58 
59 
60 
61 
62 
63 
64 
65 
66 
67 
68 
69 
70 
71 
72 
73 
74 
75 
76 
77 
78 
79 
80 
81 
82 
83 
84 
85 
86 
87 
88 
89 
90 
91 
92 
93 
94 
95 
96 
97 
98 
99 
100 101 102 103 104 105 106 
107 108 109 110 111 112 113 114 115 116 
117 118 119 120 121 122 123 124 125 126 
127 128 129 130 131 132 133 134 135 136 
137 138 139 140 141 142 143 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 4 . The clustering result in the e space.</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Cluster 
data point no. 
e 1 
1 
2 
3 
4 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
25 
26 
27 
28 
30 
33 
37 
38 
39 
40 
42 
44 
45 
46 
48 
55 
56 
57 
66 
68 
71 
88 
96 
99 
102 111 113 118 119 
120 135 136 139 
e 2 
5 
23 
24 
29 
31 
34 
35 
36 
41 
43 
47 
50 
52 
53 
58 
59 
61 
62 
63 
64 
65 
67 
70 
72 
73 
74 
75 
76 
77 
78 
80 
81 
82 
83 
84 
85 
86 
87 
89 
90 
91 
92 
93 
94 
95 
97 
98 
100 101 103 
106 107 108 109 110 114 116 117 121 122 
123 125 126 127 128 129 130 131 132 133 
137 140 141 142 143 
e 3 
32 
49 
51 
54 
69 
79 
104 105 112 115 
124 134 138 
e 4 
60 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><head>Table 5 . The clustering results in the lnP − e space.</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Cluster 
data point no. 
P e 1 
1 
2 
3 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
25 
26 
27 
28 
29 
30 
33 
34 
P e 2 
4 
35 
37 
38 
39 
40 
41 
42 
45 
P e 3 
5 
6 
23 
24 
31 
32 
36 
43 
44 
46 
47 
48 
49 
50 
51 
52 
53 
54 
55 
56 
57 
58 
59 
60 
61 
62 
63 
64 
65 
66 
67 
68 
69 
70 
71 
72 
73 
74 
75 
76 
77 
78 
79 
80 
81 
82 
83 
84 
85 
86 
87 
88 
89 
90 
91 
92 
93 
94 
95 
96 
97 
98 
99 
100 101 102 103 104 105 106 
</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Livio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lubow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">248</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Baggaley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planetary and Space Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">865</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">893</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Galligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">899</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J S</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Stat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hartigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Stat. Ass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hartigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Clustering Algorithms</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kinoshita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">572</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1041</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I.-G</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-H</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">943</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I.-G</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-H</forename><surname>Ip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">582</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">449</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I.-G</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I.-G</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Bifurcation and Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Multivariate Statistical Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wichern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>PrenticeHall, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Macqueen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of the Fifth Berkeley Symposium on Mathematical Statistics and Probability</title>
		<meeting>eeding of the Fifth Berkeley Symposium on Mathematical Statistics and Probability<address><addrLine>Berkeley</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
			<biblScope unit="page">281</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pätzold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">568</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tabachnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">335</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Trilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Benz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">241</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Veras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">613</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. PAMI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">434</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I.-G</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">561</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">364</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zakamska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">869</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
