<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-11T12:26+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Target Selection for the SDSS-III MARVELS Survey</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-05-18">18 May 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Paegert</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Keivan</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>De Lee</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Scott</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thirupathi</forename><surname>Sivarani</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Suvrath</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Claude</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mack Iii</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Saurav</forename><surname>Dhital</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><surname>Hebb</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jian</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Target Selection for the SDSS-III MARVELS Survey</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-05-18">18 May 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Accepted by AJ</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present the target selection process for the Multi-object APO Radial Velocity Exoplanets Large-area Survey (MARVELS), which is part of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) III. MARVELS is a medium-resolution (R ∼ 11000) multi-fiber spectrograph capable of obtaining radial velocities for 60 objects at a time in order to find brown dwarfs and giant planets. The survey was configured to target dwarf stars with effective temperatures approximately between 4500 and 6250 K. For the first 2 years MARVELS relied on low-resolution spectroscopic pre-observations to estimate the effective temperature and log(g) for candidate stars and then selected suitable dwarf stars from this pool. Ultimately, the pre-observation spectra proved ineffective at filtering out giant stars; many giants were incorrectly classified as dwarfs, resulting in a giant contamination rate of ∼30% for the first phase of the MARVELS survey. Thereafter, the survey instead applied a reduced proper motion cut to eliminate giants and used the Infrared Flux Method to estimate effective temperatures, using only extant photometric and proper-motion catalog information. The target selection method introduced here may be useful for other surveys that need to rely on extant catalog data for selection of specific stellar populations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Target selection is a crucial step for most astronomical surveys, one that may have a significant impact on the result even before the first image is taken. This is especially true for exoplanet surveys. A common method is to pre-select stars according to brightness, then derive stellar parameters from reconnaissance observations and compile them into an Input Catalog from which the final set of targets is drawn. The NASA Kepler mission is one of the most prominent projects following this process. However, such pre-observations require telescope time and extensive effort to process and evaluate the reconnaisance data. Therefore, for MARVELS (Multi-Object APO Radial Velocity Exoplanet Large-area Survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ge et al. 2009</ref>) we opted to devise a technique to find the stellar populations suiting the scientific purposes of the survey using only existing catalog data, thus saving the time and effort that would otherwise go into pre-observations, and streamlining the target selection process significantly. We hope that our method will be useful for future surveys like the upcoming Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), or indeed any effort to select a particular population of stars from existing catalog data.</p><p>MARVELS is part of the SDSS-III program ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Eisenstein et al. 2011a</ref>) and uses a specially built 60-fiber spectrograph to obtain medium-resolution (R = 11000) spectra to derive the precision radial velocities needed to find exoplanets and brown dwarfs orbiting main sequence stars. The MARVELS instrument itself is described in <ref type="bibr">Ge et al. (2015a,b;</ref><ref type="bibr">in preparation)</ref>, the data reduction pipeline is described in <ref type="bibr">Thomas et al. (2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">in preparation)</ref>, and the final DR12 data release is described in <ref type="bibr">Alam et al. (2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">in preparation)</ref>. In this paper we focus on describing the MARVELS target selection process.</p><p>For each target field with a circular field of view of 7 square degrees, 56 stars are selected for observation and assigned to a fixed fiber which then is plugged to a hole in a metal plate placed in the focal plane of 2.5 m SDSS telescope ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Gunn et al. 2006</ref>). Four fibers are reserved for guide stars, which are chosen after the science targets are known. The plugs require a minimal distance of 75 arcsec and thus define the required minimal distance between target stars. Between October 2008 and July 2012, MARVELS made 1565 observations of 92 fields collecting multi-epoch data for 5520 stars, more than 90% of them with enough epochs to be processed through the pipeline and yield sufficient RV observations to search for companions, including stellar companions, brown dwarfs and giant planets.</p><p>Due to technical and administrative changes in January 2011-change of fibers, joint observation with the APOGEE SDSS-III survey (the APO Galactic Evolution Experiment, Allende <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Prieto et al. (2008)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Eisenstein et al. (2011b)</ref>)-the observation is divided into two different phases: before and after January 2011, hereafter referred to as "initial" (Years 1-2) and "final" (Years 3-4) phases.</p><p>Section 2 first describes the final target selection process used for fields observed after January 2011. It then describes the initial process that was used prior to January 2011 as well as the lessons learned and why the initial process was abandoned. Section 3 presents a summary of the properties of the targets observed. We conclude with a brief summary in Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Target Selection Methods</head><p>MARVELS observed 5520 stars over four years, observing 54 science targets per field at a time. MAR-VELS was designed to achieve a radial velocity precision of &lt; 30 m/s for stars as faint as V = 12 magnitudes in order to discover brown dwarfs and giant planets of a homogenous sample of targets with only few, wellunderstood biases. Prime targets for MARVELS are FGK dwarfs, limiting the effective temperatures (T eff ) to 3500 &lt; T eff ≤ 6250 K. Most giants-defined by log(g) &lt; 3.0 during the initial phase, log(g) &lt; 3.5 during the final phase-are excluded from the survey because many giant stars exhibit pulsation-driven radial velocity variations that dominate the radial velocity signals of orbiting giant planets or brown dwarfs. In addition, the photospheres of red giants can be very extended, up to ∼AU scales, precluding companions with orbits up to ∼1 yr. At the same time, for the brightest giants MARVELS could achieve a signal-to-noise ratio good enough for detecting intermediate-period (1 yr) giant planets and contribute knowledge about planets around evolved stars. For this reason, 6 fibers (or 10%) per field were reserved for the brightest giants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Final target selection process</head><p>This section describes the final process in effect between January 2011 and the end of observations in July 2012. During this time MARVELS shared the SDSS telescope with APOGEE. Both projects had to observe the same field and coordinate field and target selection, because the fibers for both spectrographs were plugged to the same metal plate. Therefore, each individual star could only be observed by one of the two surveys. The field names, center coordinates, and number of observations for the joint fields are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 6</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Basic input catalog construction</head><p>The basic catalog for the final MARVELS target selection is a modified Guide Star Catalog version 2.3 (GSC 2.3) ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lasker et al. 2008)</ref>. Although the GSC catalog includes most of the key information required for MARVELS target selection, the published catalog does not include proper motions. The GSC authors state that for the northern sky, proper motion errors are of the order of 6 − 8 mas/yr, while errors for the southern sky are much larger, and they prefer to release the catalog without any proper motions until the systematic behind this discrepancy is better understood. The proper motion errors in the northern sky are small enough for the purposes of MARVELS, and we obtained a version of GSC 2.3 that includes proper motions for the northern sky. This catalog has been cross-matched with 2MASS ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cutri et al. 2003)</ref> and is hereafter referred to as "modified GSC 2.3".</p><p>Some of the fields observed between January 2011 and July 2012 do not have proper motions in the modified GSC2.3. In this case we used Nomad ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Zacharias et al. 2004</ref>) or UCAC3 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Zacharias et al. 2010</ref>). While Nomad includes 2MASS JHK photometry from a previous match, it does not include a 2MASS designation or identifier, so we re-matched Nomad to 2MASS allowing for a positional error of 1.41 arcsec radius in J2000 coordinates and a rounding error for JHK of 0.002 mag in each band. Stars without a matching 2MASS entry were rejected.</p><p>We repeated the catalog matching for every target field and then applied a series of steps as given in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> to select optimal target stars. The final process includes a J-band reduced proper motion (RPM J ) cut to filter out giants and an estimate of the effective temperature using the infrared flux method <ref type="bibr">(IRFM, Casagrande et al. (2010)</ref>). These steps replaced pre-observations of 1000 stars per field, which measured log(g) and T eff from low-resolution spectra and subsequently selecting the 100 best suited target stars, as was done in the initial phase (see Section 2.2). The final process allowed us to select the 100 stars per field to be observed with the MARVELS spectrograph from existing catalog data only and thus greatly streamlined the process. The initial limit of 1000 candidate stars in step 8 of <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> was not strictly necessary but was a vestige from the initial target selection process (Section 2.2) and was retained for consistency.</p><p>The reason for selecting 100 stars for 56 fibers is that, during the initial phase, in many cases two fields were drilled on the same metal plate (double drilling), and as a result it was possible for stars from field A to collide with stars from field B. The final target selection for each field was done by the plate-drilling team, thus providing that team with a generous "reserve" of extra target stars took care of potential conflicts between fields on double drilled plates. During this process each star was assigned to a certain physical fiber, and once this assignment was made the same fiber was used for all future observations of the target.</p><p>Step Limit the total number to 100 per field 60 plugged, 40 as "reserve" in case of collisions 13</p><p>Check the 6 selected giants in Simbad Verify for T eff , exclude close binaries and known variables <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>: Target selection steps during the final phase. T eff from Casagrande relations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2.">Reduced Proper Motion Cut</head><p>To get an estimate of log(g), we first compute the reduced proper motion in J (RPM J ). With µ r , µ d as proper motion in right ascension and declination in arc-seconds per year and d as declination, we compute</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">µ = (cos d * µ r ) 2 + µ 2 d (1) RPM J = J + 5 log(µ)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>and then apply an empirical RPM J cut described in Collier <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cameron et al. (2007)</ref>: Stars with y ≥ RPM J are regarded as RPM J -dwarfs, stars with y &lt; RPM J as RPM J -giants.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">y = −58 + 313.42(J − H) − 583.6(J − H) 2 + 473.18(J − H) 3 − 141.25(J − H) 4<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Using proper motions from the modified GSC we first tested this cut by applying it to the 458 stars in the <ref type="bibr">Kepler Input Catalog (KIC;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kepler Mission Team 2009</ref>) that also have been observed by MARVELS. Note that the KIC was principally intended for broadly discriminating highly evolved giants from dwarfs, and thus the surface gravities in particular have relatively large uncertainties (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Casagrande et al. 2014</ref>). In the time since the MARVELS target selection strategy was implemented and tested, the NASA Exoplanet Archive has released updated stellar characteristics-namely log(g) and T eff -for stars observed by Kepler in quarters 1 to 16. While we used the original KIC values for target selection, for the comparisons shown in this paper we also re-ran the analysis with revised values from the NASA Exoplanet Archive. As we show below, the results using the updated KIC are not substantially different from that used in our actual target selection process.</p><p>We define giants as having log(g) ≤ 3.5, dwarfs having log(g) ≥ 4.1, and subgiants as those with log(g) between these values. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows the RPM J diagram for the MARVELS-Kepler overlap stars (using original KIC values in the left panel, revised values in the right panel). The solid black line marks the border between RPM J -dwarfs below and RPM J -giants above the line as defined by equation (3). Green symbols above the line are log(g)-dwarfs that are mis-identified as giants by the RPM J cut. Red symbols below the line are in turn log(g)-giants mis-identified as dwarfs. The MARVELS "region of interest" is 0.3 &lt; (J − H) &lt; 0.54 and below the RPM J cut, which translates to dwarfs or subgiants of spectral types F9 to K3.</p><p>A few stars on the left panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> are missing in the right panel-most notably those with J − H &gt; 0.7. These are evolved giant stars that were observed by Kepler in quarter 0 only then dropped and are thus not part of the revised values published in the NASA Exoplanet Archive for stars observed by Kepler in quarters 1 to 16. Nonetheless, the right panel with the revised values is more populated and confirms the ability of the RPM J cut to distinguish between dwarfs and giants-although again subgiants are not well discriminated.</p><p>Using the original KIC values we find that 6 stars (1.7%) are false negatives-log(g) dwarfs according to KIC, but giants according to the RPM J cut. Another 6 stars 1.7% are false positives-they are log(g) giants, falsely identified as dwarfs by the RPM J method. Most of the sub-giants are below the line and thus in the "dwarf"-region. Collier <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Cameron et al. (2007)</ref> included only stars with log(g) &lt; 3.0 or log(g) &gt; 4.0, thus excluding subgiants. In our analysis we included the missing log(g) interval and conclude that the RPM J cut does not seem able to distinguish sub-giants from dwarfs. For MARVELS this is not a problem, because sub-giants are valid target stars, but it should be considered for any future statistics derived from the MARVELS dataset, as subgiants will be included in the "dwarf" sample. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-In this HR diagram, log(g) from isochrones are plotted. The color of each bin is the median log(g) of all the isochrones that pass through that color-magnitude bin.</p><p>Note that the KIC stars span a magnitude range from V = 9 to 11.5, thus excluding the bright and faint end of the MARVELS magnitude range (7.6 to 13.0). Therefore, one concern is that the good performance of the RPM J cut for the KIC stars might not apply to the full range of MARVELS targets. In addition, when considering stars in other parts of the sky, one would necessarily need to use proper motions from heterogeneous catalog sources, thus potentially introducing systematic errors. Thus for the MARVELS target stars we checked how much of an influnce a change from the modified GSC to UCAC as source catalog for proper motions would have on our selection. Generally GSC and UCAC are in good agreement, with a mean difference in total proper motion of ∆µ = 0.37 ± 4.75 masec/yr. Thus on average we do not expect dramatic changes. We also checked the rate of stars switching from giant to dwarf classification according to the RPM J cut when changing from GSC to UCAC as the proper motion source catalog. We found this rate to be 1.75%, thus low enough to not cause concern.</p><p>Encouraged by these comparisons with the KIC we next tested the RPM J cut all-sky with the Hipparcos catalog <ref type="bibr">(ESA 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Perryman et al. 1997</ref>). We combined the Hipparcos catalog with isochrones to derive a log(g) determination based upon location within the HR diagram. We started with the Padova isochrones ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Marigo et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Girardi et al. 2010</ref>) from CMD 2.3 (http://stev.oapd.inaf.it/cmd). The isochrones were chosen to be solar metallicity (Z = 0.019) and range to in log 10 (Age) [yrs] from 6.60 to 10.10 (inclusive) in steps of 0.05. The intrinsic luminosities from the isochrones were transformed into the Johnson-Cousins filters using Maíz Apellániz (2006) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bessell (1990)</ref>. The HR diagram is a phase space of absolute V magnitude and B − V color. Each isochrone occupies a particular region of this phase space, but they fall in such a way that some regions have multiple isochrones overlapping and some regions have no isochrones. In order to quantify this, the phase space was separated into 40 bins in B − V and 80 bins in the M V . The minimum value, maximum value, and step size in B − V were −0.23, 3.12, and 0.0837, respectively. For M V the minimum value, maximum value, and step size were −6.14, 13.00, and 0.239, respectively. The isochrones are made up of a series of three coordinate data points (M V , B − V , and log(g)). Each isochrone data point is put into its appropratiate bin in color-magnitude phase space. Once this was done, the median log(g) of the data points in each color-magnitude bin was assigned as the log(g) of that bin as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The isochrones do not completely cover the HR diagram, so there are bins that do not have a log(g) value. The next step is to associate each Hipparcos star with a bin and throw out any stars that do not fall within 0.5 magnitudes (in both M V or B − V ) of a bin center that had a log(g) value. If a Hipparcos star has more than 1 bin within the 0.5 magnitude bin radius, then the star was associated with the closest bin center and was then assigned the log(g) of that bin. This results in a table of Hipparcos stars with log(g) that can then be used to test the RPM J method, see <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Note that our use here of 0.5-mag bins, and of a linear interpolation in log age, are simplified and arbitrary choices, however they suffice for the purposes of the check we seek to perform of the broad performance of the RPM J method to distinguish dwarfs from giants.</p><p>To compare the RPM J results with directly measured log(g) values, we chose the RAVE catalog, data release 2 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Zwitter et al. 2008</ref>) and <ref type="bibr">3 (Siebert et al. 2011</ref>). Both RAVE releases give comparable results, except that the fraction of log(g) giants which would be classified as RPM J -dwarfs is nearly three times higher with data release 2 (15% instead of 5.8%). We ascribe this to the improved RAVE pipeline used for data release 3.</p><p>The results for Hipparcos and RAVE DR3 are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. If the RPM J cut is the only information used, 92.5% of stars flagged as giants would be true giants according to the log(g) value derived for Hipparcos stars. 2.6% would be subgiants and 4.9% would be dwarfs. Furthermore 2.6% of the stars flagged as dwarfs would be giants, 39.9% subgiants and 57.5% dwarfs.</p><p>The results for all stars in RAVE DR3 are similar with a notable shift from sub-giants towards dwarfs and giants. While the ratio of correctly identified giants decreases by 9%, the ratio of correctly identified dwarfs improves by 17%. If we limit the RAVE stars to valid MARVELS targets-those matching the MARVELS magnitude and color cut (7.6 ≤ V &lt; 13, respectively (J − K S ≥ 0.29)-the results improve slightly, but not significantly, as shown in the bottom part of <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p><p>For MARVELS we conclude that using the RPM J cut as the only method for selecting dwarfs will result in a giant contamination rate of about 4%, which is much better than the rate we experienced from spectroscopic pre-observations (see Section 2.2). Importantly, however, subgiants comprise a large fraction of the "dwarf" sample. Therefore while the target selection procedure described above is highly effective at removing evolved red giants, subgiants are unavoidably mixed in with the dwarfs at the level of 20-40% (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>). <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>.-Reduced proper motion cut for Hipparcos stars as described in section 2.1.2: red points are giants; blue points are subgiants; green points are dwarfs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3.">Effective Temperature from Infrared Flux Method</head><p>We compute the effective temperature using color-metallicity-temperature relations based on the Infrared This error on T eff is larger than the 1-σ error derived from benchmark grade stars given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Casagrande et al. (2010)</ref>. One reason is the assumed solar metallicity of our target stars, as noted above. A second reason is the fact that the Casagrande relations are calibrated for dwarfs and subgiants, but not for giants. For MARVELS target selection this is not important because we exclude all but the 6 brightest giants which are vetted manually using Vizier (see above). While V − K S as a temperature estimator is more sensitive to reddening than, e.g., J − K S , it is less sensitive to metallicity errors. As reddening does not play a major role for the nearby dwarf stars that dominate the MARVELS targetsample, we consider V − K S to be a valid and optimal choice for our purposes (see Section 3.2 for an estimation of reddening and extinction). In cases where the limits of the Casagrande relations for J − K S and V − K S allow us to compute a T eff from both relations, we use the mean value.</p><p>We test the Casagrande relations with RAVE DR3, the result is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>. Running a leastsquares fit over all stars we find an offset of 100 ± 10 K between IRFM and RAVE temperatures. This offset matches the errors we estimate using KIC and the 85 ± 14 K the RAVE team reports when comparing their data to high-resolution external results and is comparable to the 72 ± 14 K RAVE reports for the general temperature offset in relation to external results. As reported by the RAVE team, the data show a wide spread of temperatures and a noticeable trend to yield higher temperatures especially for dwarf stars. However, the shift is about one MK-subclass-say G5 instead of G4-and not significant for the MARVELS target selection.</p><p>While the agreement between IRFM based temperatures and the RAVE spectroscopic temperatures is within the error margin for dwarfs with T eff ≤ 5000 K, it degrades quickly for hotter dwarfs. Notably the agreement between RAVE and IRFM-derived temperatures for giants and subgiants is not worse than the agreement for hot dwarfs. Thus we conclude that the choice to use the Casagrande relations for giants and subgiants, although they are calibrated for dwarfs, is reasonable.   Unlike in the final target selection, for the 1000 brightest stars matching the brightness and color cut of J − K S ≥ 0.29, a spectroscopic snapshot was taken by the SDSS double spectrograph, mainly used for SEGUE ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Yanny et al. 2009</ref>). The instrument has a resolution of R ∼ 2000 and is described in greater detail in Section 2 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Smee et al. (2013)</ref>. The double spectrograph saturates at V = 9, thus brighter stars needed special treatment during the initial phase. The stellar parameters T eff , log(g) and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref> were derived using a modified version of the SEGUE Stellar Parameter pipeline (SSPP <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lee et al. 2008</ref>). The target selection was a two-step process:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hipparcos</head><p>1. Select up to 1000 stars for stellar characterization with SDSS spectrograph 2. Using the characterization from step 1 select 100 stars for drilling, 60 of them will get observed with MARVELS For every star in a given field the steps in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> were applied. The distance parameter in step 6 of the selection process (62 ′′ ) is different from the 75 ′′ reported in step 5 of <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. The reason is that MARVELS switched to wider fibers in order to maximize the throughput in years 3 and 4. In addition the effective temperatures used here are derived from pre-observations using the modified SSPP pipeline instead of based on the Casagrande relations as in 1. In order to allow a consistent comparison, we computed T eff using the Casagrande relations for all stars tageted during the initial phase.</p><p>The observations took place during twilight at the Apache Point Observatory. The spectra were eval-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step Criterion</head><p>Reason Keep the 6 brightest giants Only 6 giants wanted 9</p><p>Keep stars with T eff &lt; 6250 K Exclude hot stars, T eff from SSPP pipeline 10</p><p>Limit F stars (those with 5800K ≤ T eff ≤ 6250K) to 40% of all MARVELS targets in the field Guarantee 50% GK stars, T eff from SSPP pipeline 11</p><p>If two stars are closer than 75 ′′ , keep the brighter star</p><p>Prefer bright stars for good SNR</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>12</head><p>Limit the total number to 100 per field 60 plugged, 40 as "reserve" in case of collision with guide stars <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>: Steps for pre-selecting targets for spectrographic snapshot observations with the SDSS spectrograph (steps 1-6) and for observation with MARVELS (steps 7-12). T eff from the modified SSPP pipeline.</p><p>uated for T eff , log(g) and [Fe/H] using the adapted SEGUE Stellar Parameter pipeline (SSPP). The stars were then split in a bright (7.6 ≤ V ≤ 9.0) and a faint (9.0 &lt; V &lt; 13.0) sample. Both samples were split between main sequence stars (log(g) &gt;= 3.0) and giants (log(g) &lt; 3.0). Although this split is different from the classification introduced with the final target selection (log(g) &lt; 3.5 for giants) it does not play a role in the large giant contamination of the initial phase. Only 10 stars from all stars observed in this phase have 3.0 ≤ log g ≤ 3.5 from the SSPP-pipeline and are flagged as RPM J -giants, thus this shift is not responsible for the high contamination by giants in the initial phase.</p><p>The bright stars were checked against SIMBAD and usually rejected-allowing for special targets-if any of the following conditions were met:</p><p>Bright stars passing these tests were combined with the faint star sample and steps 7 to 12 from <ref type="table">Table  3</ref> were applied. While it may appear that step 7-the first step after pre-selection-is redundant with step 3, several months may have elapsed between pre-selection and step 7. In this time the planned observations may have been delayed to a later date, thus necessitating a new check that the target stays on plate even with the new, later observation start date.</p><p>Although the spectrograph has only 64 fibers, we keep 100 stars in order to have a "reserve" if it turns out that a star can not be plugged because it is too close to a guiding star or for other technical reasons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Giant contamination in initial target selection</head><p>It was initially assumed that in this process 10% of the selected dwarfs would actually be giants due to errors in the log(g) determinations from the SSPP, yielding a final giant fraction of about 15% in the final sample. Instead, the contamination rate was about 35%, as determined later by the RPM J method. Some MARVELS fields overlapped with the Kepler field, and we compared the stellar characteristics obtained from SDSS spectra with those in the Kepler Input Catalog (KIC). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref> shows the log(g) values from SDSS spectra versus values in the KIC. At T eff &lt; 5000 K results diverge rapidly and there is no agreement at all for T eff &lt; 4500 K. Moreover, for all stars with KIC log(g) &lt; 3 the values disagree strongly. Given the fact that the original KIC values for log(g) are up to 1.0 dex too high <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Casagrande et al. 2014</ref>), the true contamination by giants in the SSPP selected sample is even higher than suggested by <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> shows the HR diagram (effective temperature and log(g)) for the same set of stars from KIC and the SSPPpipeline modified for MARVELS, again showing the strong discrepancies in the SSPP estimated log(g) values for cool giants. We conclude that cool giants are misidentified as dwarfs by the modified SSPP pipeline. We therefore abandoned the spectroscopic pre-observations in favor of the streamlined target selection process described in section 2.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Summary of selected stars</head><p>The initial phase was significantly longer than the final phase-26 versus 15 months. The number of stars selected for observation reflects this asymmetry: 4130 stars in the initial phase, and 2900 stars for the final phase-adding to 7030 stars designed for observation out of which 5520 actually got observed. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the distribution on the sky in galactic coordinates. The field centers along the galactic plane are from the final phase and located at galactic latitudes of −8, −4, 0, 4 and 8 degrees, and thus appear to blend into each other. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows the magnitude distribution in the V-band, for the initial phase at the left, for the final phase at the right. Aside from the different total numbers mentioned above, the most pronounced difference is a shift of the maximum by 0.5 mag-from around 11.25 mag for the initial to 11.55 mag for the final phase. The reason is that coordination with APOGEE placed the fields outside of the galactic plane. Since MARVELS and APOGEE could not observe the same stars in those sparse fields, the available stars were fainter. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> is a stacked histogram for effective temperatures of RPM J -dwarfs and RPM J -giants during the initial phase (left) and the final phase (right). For this comparison we computed effective temperatures for all stars from the initial phase using the Casagrande relations in order to allow a direct comparison to the temperatures estimated in the final phase. In the initial phase giants are overrepresented for T eff &lt; 5000 K, indicating again that the log(g) values from the modified SSPP-pipeline were unreliable for cooler stars. Out of the 4130 stars selected for observation during the initial phase, 1414 stars are flagged as giants by the RPM J method. This is 34% of the sample.</p><p>To estimate the fraction of giants in our sample we take the rates for MARVELS-selected RAVE stars from <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. About 14% of the RPM J -giants are false positives, and thus are either dwarfs or sub-giants. On the other hand 3% of the RPM J -dwarfs are false positives, and therefore giants. The estimated rate for the initial phase is then 34 − 0.14 × 34 + 0.03 × 66 = 31%. For the final phase we manually checked 6 giants per field (10%). To this we add the 4% error for RPM J -dwarfs and thus end with 14% giants in stars selected for the final phase. Given that we do want 10% of the stars to be giants, the difference between estimated and wanted giants gives the contamination rate. The results are summarized in   , so reddening and extinction might have to be taken into account. Using the RPM J cut to distinguish dwarfs and subgiants from giants, extinction moves stars down in the RPM J diagram, reddening moves them to the right. There are 3 possible effects:</p><p>• Giants are pushed downwards over the cut by extinction, contaminating our sample.</p><p>• Dwarfs are shifted out of the region of interest by reddening and are lost.</p><p>• Hot stars are moved downward and to the right into our region of interest, polluting the sample.</p><p>We estimate the effect on a typical field for the first 2 years of observation (Kepler field) and-as worst case scenario-when observing directly towards the galactic center (assuming that redenning and extinction both increase towards the galactic center).</p><p>Taking the absolute magnitudes for dwarfs and giants from Allen (2001) and extending to bluer colors using <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Schaifers et al. (1982)</ref>, we computed the spectroscopic distances for dwarfs and giants of different spectral types with apparent magnitudes of V = 10 and 13, representing the bright and faint end of our targets. We then computed the typical proper motions these stars would have according to the galactic model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dhital et al. (2010)</ref> and placed them into a RPM J diagram. showing the faint end of MARVELS magnitude range, we do not overplot the MARVELS-Kepler overlap stars, thus keeping the reddening/extiction vector more visible. The typical position of stars of a given spectral type and magnitude according to the galactic model from <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dhital et al. (2010)</ref> are marked as box and whiskers. Each box represents 50% of all stars, the whiskers the upper and lower 27% -leaving 3% outliers apart. The spectroscopic distances of dwarfs and giants are given at the bottom. For each of the boxes we computed a reddening-extinction vector. We multiplied an assumed mean density of N H = 1 atom/ccm with the spectroscopic distance, yielding a column density of n H = N H d. This column density we converted to A V and further to E(B − V ), adopting the relations</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A V = n H /2.30 × 10 21 , E(B − V ) = A V /3.1 (6)</formula><p>Taking A J /A V = 0.282 and A H /A V = 0.190 from <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cardelli et al. (1989)</ref> we converted E(B − V ) to E(J − H) which completes the vector (E(J − H), A J ). For dwarfs we plotted this vector at each box. For V = 10 there is no noticeable shift in and out of the region of interest. For V = 13 the brightest stars (A0) can be shifted in the region of interest. However, they are a very small fraction of the stellar population and thus will not significantly pollute the sample. We repeated the same analysis for observations towards the Galactic Center, with the results shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">figure 11</ref>. Compared to the Kepler field there is a slight but insignificant shift in the position of the boxes. For bright stars (V = 10, left panel) reddening and extinction do not play a significant role. For faint stars (V = 13, right panel) A0 stars get shifted into the region of interest. We might see pollution by late F-dwarfs; A5 to F5 are not reddened enough. As even in the worst case of observing towards the Galactic Center we only would see a light pollution by late F-dwarfs, we concluded that correcting for reddening and extinction is not necessary for the MARVELS target selection.</p><p>Reddening and extinction get stronger if we assume a higher density than average 1 atom per ccm. The spectroscopic distance of giants with an apparent magnitude of V = 13 is 4.8 kpc. As long as we do not hit a denser region within this distance, our estimation of reddening and extinction holds. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary</head><p>In this paper we have discussed the targe selection methodology for creating an input catalog for the MARVELS radial velocity survey. The MARVELS survey was interested in looking for radial velocity companions to stars of the FGK spectral type primarily focusing on dwarf stars. To achieve this goal, a target selection criteria of 10% giant stars 90% dwarf stars was set. Target selection for MARVELS is broken down into two distinct phases, the initial phase which found targets for the first half of the survey, and the final phase which found targets for the second half of the survey. The initial target selection method used low-resolution (R ∼ 2000) spectra from the SDSS spectrographs processed by a modified SSPP pipeline. This method ulitmately proved to be inadequate for removing giant star contamination primarly on the cool end (T eff &lt; 4500). This result was not entirely unexpected because the MARVELS stars are significantly brighter than what the SSPP was designed to work with. As a result, the giant contamination rate for the initial phase was 31%. Given the results of the initial phase, the final phase of target selection used a different method. Instead of low-resolution spectra, a reduced proper motion method (RPM J ) was employed. This method did a much better job meeting our criteria providing a giant contamination rate of just 13%.</p><p>This investigation also revealed two other notable results. First is that interstellar reddening is not a major factor in influencing the stars selected for MARVELS. This is due to primarily to the relatively short distances to the MARVELS stars and the way in which the reddening vector points in the RPM J diagram. Second is that the RPM J method, although being quite useful for separating dwarfs and giants, is not able to adequately separate dwarfs and subgiants (subgiant contamination of the dwarf sample is on order 30%). For the MARVELS scientific goals this was not important. However, future surveys or missions need to be aware of this fact when designing their respective input catalogs.</p><p>We acknowledge the generous support from the W.M. Keck Foundation for developing the MARVELS survey instruments. The MARVELS project was also supported from NSF with grant AST-0705139, NASA with grant NNX07AP14G and the University of Florida. Funding for SDSS-III has been provided by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the Participating Institutions, the National Science Foundation, and the U.S. Department of Energy Office of Science. The SDSS-III web site is http://www.sdss3.org/. <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 5</ref> provides fieldnames, coordinates and number of observations during the initial phase, <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 6</ref> provides the same information for the final phase.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Observed Fields</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Reduced proper motion for KIC stars with SDSS spectra using equations (2). Red crosses: giants, blue stars: subgiants, green x: dwarfs, solid line: cut according to Equation 3. Note that the y-axis is inverted. Left panel: log(g) values from original KIC, right panel: revised log(g) values from NASA Exoplanet Archive; stars with J − H &gt; 0.7 are evolved giants that were only observed by Kepler in Q0 and not observed in later quarters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Flux Method (IRFM) as described in Casagrande et al. (2010). For stars with 0.78 &lt;= V −K &lt;= 3.15 and −5.0 &lt;= [Fe/H] &lt;= 0.4, and defining x = V − K, and T eff = 5040.0/θ eff , Casagrande et al. (2010) gives the relation θ eff = 0.5057 + 0.2600x − 0.0146x 2 − 0.0131x[Fe/H] + 0.0288[Fe/H] + 0.0016[Fe/H] 2 (4) Using instead the J −K colors, for stars with 0.07 ≤ J −K S ≤ 0.80 and the same metallicity restrictions, and now defining x = J − K S : θ eff = 0.6393 + 0.6104x + 0.0920x 2 − 0.0330x[Fe/H] + 0.0291[Fe/H] + 0.0020[Fe/H] 2 (5) Without a measured value for [Fe/H], we assume solar metallicity for all our target stars. The additional error induced by this assumption does not exceed 80 K at the extreme ends of the color range and for [Fe/H] = ±0.4. Comparing T eff from the Casagrande relations with the original T eff values in KIC we estimated an error of 105 K for dwarfs and 165 K for giants. According to Table 8 and Figure 18 in Pinsonneault et al. (2012), the KIC T eff values are approximately 200K systematically too low for dwarfs and giants alike, so in reality the T eff errors for the MARVELS target selection is likely closer to this value of 200 K.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Effective temperature from RAVE and Infrared Flux Method. Solid black line: identity, dashed line: RAVE error (204 K), horizontal line: Marvels hot star cut-off at (T eff &gt; 6250 K). Panels are by log(g) from RAVE: Left-giants; Center-subgiants; Right-Dwarfs</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-log(g) from spectra taken with SDSS and from KIC; the diagonal line represents identity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-T eff vs. log(g) for the same stars from KIC and via a modified SSPP-pipeline for SDSS spectra. Both axis are inverted to resemble the display of an HR-diagram</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 10 Fig. 7 .</head><label>107</label><figDesc>Figure 10 shows the result for the Kepler field with stars with V = 10 in the left and stars with V = 13 in the right panel. The MARVELS region of interest is shaded. For illustration we plotted the overlap stars of Kepler and MARVELS with colored symbols in the left panel. In order not to overcrowd the right panel</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .Fig. 9 .</head><label>89</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-V magnitude distribution for the initial phase (left) and final phase (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10.-Reddening and extinction for the Kepler field. Left panel: stars with V = 10; Right panel: stars with V = 13. Grey shade: MARVELS region of interest. Box and whiskers: galactic model position of stars with given magnitude and spectral type. Numbers on the lower legend are the typical distances of dwarfs (top, green) and giants (bottom, red)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11.-Reddening and extinction for the Galactic Center. Left panel: stars with V = 10; Right panel: stars with V = 13. Grey shade: MARVELS region of interest. Box and whiskers: galactic model position of stars with given magnitude and spectral type. Numbers on the lower legend are the typical distances of dwarfs (top, green) and giants (bottom, red)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Classification of Hipparcos and RAVE stars 
by RPM J cut. The bottom category of RAVE (se-
lected) is restricted to stars in the MARVELS regime 
for V -mag and J − K color. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>phase 
initial final 
RPM J -giants 
34 % 10 % 
RPM J -dwarfs 
66 % 90 % 
est. giants 
31 % 14 % 
wanted 
10 % 10 % 
contamination 21 % 
4 % 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Giant comtamination rates for 
the initial and final phase. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="true"><head>Table 5 : Name, center coordinates and number of observations for fields from the initial phase</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Name 
RA 
Dec 
l 
b 
Obs 
47UMA 
164·86 
40·43 175·787 
63·3645 
29 
51PEG 
344·37 
20·77 
90·06669 −34·72791 
36 
FIELD1068 
264·3 
30 
54·18431 
28·24962 
23 
FIELD1110 
100·8 
33 
182·19045 
12·7985 
23 
FIELD1348 
262·86 
42 
67·41378 
32·0944 
23 
FIELD1349 
268·57 
42 
68·33689 
27·92775 
25 
FIELD1572 
321·7 
54 
95·6606 
2·33948 
31 
FIELD1631 
101·54 
60 
155·71982 
22·6218 
34 
GJ176 
70·73 
18·96 180·01238 −17·42718 
30 
GJ436 
175·55 
26·71 210·53025 
74·57257 
29 
GL273 
111·85 
5·23 212·33978 
10·37355 
28 
HAT-P-1 
344·45 
38·67 
99·7928 
−19·04242 
36 
HAT-P-3 
206·09 
47·97 100·09623 
66·74412 
24 
HAT-P-4 
229·99 
36·13 
58·29627 
57·34666 
6 
HD118203 
203·51 
53·73 109·3461 
62·26017 
26 
HD17092 
41·59 
49·65 141·3032 
−9·07813 
30 
HD17156 
42·44 
71·75 131·99263 
10·99141 
38 
HD219828 
349·69 
18·65 
94·26312 −39·00768 
36 
HD37605 
85·01 
6·06 199·10635 −12·89319 
28 
HD4203 
11·17 
20·45 120·78828 −42·39362 
36 
HD43691 
94·89 
41·09 172·65004 
11·92868 
31 
HD46375 
98·3 
5·4 
206·04629 
−1·57714 
25 
HD49674 
102·88 
40·87 175·33733 
17·37424 
26 
HD68988 
124·59 
61·46 155·26411 
33·91797 
40 
HD80606 
140·66 
50·54 167·51619 
44·3251 
29 
HD88133 
152·53 
18·12 217·91036 
51·87233 
25 
HD89307 
154·59 
12·56 227·39155 
51·36809 
29 
HD89744 
155·54 
41·17 178·49592 
56·40393 
35 
HD9407 
23·64 
68·95 126·80841 
6·40343 
29 
HIP14810 
47·81 
21·1 
161·54971 −31·09206 
31 
K10 
294·12 
46·01 
78·80125 
11·96774 
23 
K14 
299·64 
44·87 
79·67739 
8·02455 
23 
K15 
296·12 
43·53 
77·23814 
9·55789 
20 
K20 
294·71 
39·63 
73·25579 
8·6313 
23 
K21 
291·58 
38·15 
70·78675 
10·11117 
19 
K4 
295·69 
49·9 
82·83844 
12·79648 
19 
K5 
291·93 
48·45 
80·38966 
14·37021 
20 
K7 
285·05 
45·2 
75·36922 
17·43255 
20 
K8 
281·91 
43·44 
72·80583 
18·91956 
26 
KEPLER3-TRES2 285·9 
49·2 
79·51202 
18·32046 
21 
KEPLER4 
282·52 
47·46 
76·97688 
19·84864 
23 
WASP-1 
5·17 
31·99 115·36902 −30·42966 
36 
XO-1 
240·55 
28·09 
45·73607 
48·00637 
20 
XO-2 
117·03 
50·16 168·36412 
29·32105 
31 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="true"><head>Table 6 : Name, center coordinates and number of observations for fields from the final phase</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Name 
RA 
Dec 
l 
b 
Obs 
APG 030-04 
285·09054 
−4·42875 
30 
−4 
2 
APG 030-08 
288·67708 
−6·23117 
30 
−8 
6 
APG 030+00 
281·5215 
−2·60914 
30 
0 
2 
APG 030+04 
277·96279 
−0·77944 
30 
4 
1 
APG 060-04 
299·71129 
21·85097 
60 
−4 
3 
APG 060+00 
295·97625 
23·89036 
60 
0 
2 
APG 060+04 
292·12433 
25·83681 
60 
4 
3 
APG 060+08 
288·14717 
27·67833 
60 
8 
1 
APG 090-04 
322·15829 
45·5085 
90 
−4 
3 
APG 090-08 
325·90667 
42·55142 
90 
−8 
1 
APG 090+04 
313·379 
50·984 
90 
4 
2 
APG 090+08 
308·21592 
53·43419 
90 
8 
1 
APG 120-08 
7·82354 
54·757 
120 
−8 
3 
APG 120+04 
5·44675 
66·70278 120 
4</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Allen&apos;s Astrophysical Quantities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Allende</forename><surname>Prieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Majewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schiavon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomische Nachrichten</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1018</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bessell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1181</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cardelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Clayton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">345</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">245</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ramírez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meléndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bessell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Asplund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Silva Aguirre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">787</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Collier Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">380</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1230</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cutri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Skrutskie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Dyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">2MASS All Sky Catalog of point sources</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dhital</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bochanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eisenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Weinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>AJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Astrometric and photometric star catalogues derived from the ESA HIPPARCOS Space Astrometry Mission</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ESA Special Publication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1200</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The HIPPARCOS and TYCHO catalogues</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>De Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7440</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Girardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">724</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1030</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Siegmund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2332</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">VizieR Online Data Catalog</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Kepler Mission Team</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lasker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lattanzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">735</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Beers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sivarani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2022</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maíz Apellániz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1184</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Girardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bressan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">482</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">883</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A C</forename><surname>Perryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lindegren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kovalevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pinsonneault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">-˙</forename><surname>Molenda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zakowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schaifers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Voigt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Landolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Boernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hellwege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomy and Astrophysics. B: Stars and Star Clusters</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Siebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E K</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Siviero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">187</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Smee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uomoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yanny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rockosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Newberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4377</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zacharias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Monet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1418</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zacharias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Finch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Girard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2184</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zwitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Siebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Munari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">421</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
