<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:21+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Solar Neighborhood XXXVI. The Long-Term Photometric Variability of Nearby Red Dwarfs in the V RI Optical Bands</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-03-06">6 Mar 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Altonio</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hosey</surname></persName>
							<email>altoniohosey@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Todd</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
							<email>toddhenry28@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wei-Chun</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
							<email>jao@astro.gsu.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sergio</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dieterich</surname></persName>
							<email>dieterich@astro.gsu.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Winters</surname></persName>
							<email>winters@astro.gsu.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lurie</surname></persName>
							<email>lurie@uw.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adric</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
							<email>adric.riedel@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">RECONS Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>17201</postCode>
									<settlement>Chambersburg</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30302-4106</postCode>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysics, American Museum of Natural History</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>98195, 10034</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle, New York</settlement>
									<region>WA, NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Solar Neighborhood XXXVI. The Long-Term Photometric Variability of Nearby Red Dwarfs in the V RI Optical Bands</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-03-06">6 Mar 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">submitted to The Astronomical Journal 03 SEP 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>United States Naval Observatory</term>
					<term>Flagstaff</term>
					<term>AZ</term>
					<term>86001 jsubasavage@nofsnavymil -2 - Subject headings: stars: low mass -stars: planetary systems -stars: statistics -stars: variables -techniques: photometric</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present an analysis of long-term photometric variability for nearby red dwarf stars at optical wavelengths. The sample consists of 264 M dwarfs south of Dec. = +30 with V − K = 3.96-9.16 and M V ≈ 10-20, corresponding to spectral types M2V-M8V, most of which are within 25 pc. The stars have been observed in the V RI filters for ∼4-14 years at the CTIO/SMARTS 0.9m telescope. Of the 238 red dwarfs within 25 pc, we find that only ∼8% are photometrically variable by at least 20 mmag (∼2%) in the V RI bands. Only four stars have been found to vary by more than 50 mmag, including GJ 1207 at 8.6 pc that experienced a single extraordinary flare, and GJ 2006A, TWA 8A, and TWA 8B, which are all young stars beyond 25 pc linked to moving groups. We find that high variability at optical wavelengths over the long-term can in fact be used to identify young stars. Overall, however, the fluxes of most red dwarfs at optical wavelengths are steady to a few percent over the long term. The low overall rate of photometric variability for red dwarfs is consistent with results found in previous work on similar stars on shorter timescales, with the body of work indicating that most red dwarfs are only mildly variable. As expected, we find that the degree of photometric variability is greater in the V band than in the R or I bands, but we do not find any obvious trends in variability over the long term with red dwarf luminosity or temperature. We highlight 17 stars that show long-term changes in brightness, sometimes because of flaring activity or spots, and sometimes because of stellar cycles similar to our Sun&apos;s solar cycle. Remarkably, two targets show brightnesses that monotonically increase (G 169-029) or decrease (WT 460AB) by several percent over a decade. We also provide long-term variability measurements for seven M dwarfs within 25 pc that host exoplanets, none of which vary by more than 20 mmag. Both as a population, and for the specific red dwarfs with exoplanets observed here, pho-tometric variability is therefore often not a concern for planetary environments, at least at the optical wavelengths where they emit much of their light.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Red dwarfs comprise the majority of stars in the Galaxy, accounting for roughly threequarters of all stars in the solar neighborhood <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Henry et al. 2006</ref>). As the lowest luminosity hydrogen-burning stars, red dwarfs are long-lasting, stable energy producers, making them ideal candidates for planetary environments. One aspect of red dwarfs that may prove crucial to the potential of life on any orbiting planets is the consistency in the flux provided by the stars, i.e., the stellar variability. In this paper we investigate the long-term photometric variability at optical wavelengths of a large sample of red dwarfs.</p><p>The RECONS 1 (REsearch Consortium On Nearby Stars) team has gathered photometry in the V RI optical bands for more than 1000 nearby red dwarfs since 1999 ( <ref type="bibr">Winters et al. 2011;</ref>. In this paper we focus on the long-term variability of 264 red dwarfs (generally within 25 pc) for which we are determining trigonometric parallaxes and searching for low mass companions as part of our astrometry/photometry effort carried out at the CTIO/SMARTS 0.9m. These stars typically have been observed on 10-30 nights each, at ∼5 frames/night, spread over 4-14 years. This provides a rich dataset of more than 24,000 observations for the 264 stars, or nearly 100 individual frames/star. Our goals in this paper are to determine the fraction of red dwarfs photometrically variable at optical wavelengths over long time periods, to explore the dependence of variability on their luminosities and temperatures, and to identify individual stars exhibiting long-term stellar cycles. We also briefly address the effects of variability on the fluxes received by exoplanets, given recent discoveries of both gas giant and super-terrestrial exoplanets orbiting nearby red dwarfs.</p><p>Previous efforts have examined samples of M dwarfs at optical wavelengths, often in smaller numbers or over shorter time periods. In his classic study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Weis (1994)</ref> reported photometric measurements of 43 stars over an 11 year period. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jao et al. (2011)</ref> reported the first study of variability in red subdwarfs, including 130 stars from the RECONS program discussed here, observed for ∼3-9 years. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koen et al. (2010)</ref> provided photometry for over 700 stars, including many M dwarfs observed at multiple epochs. Transit searches have yielded rotation periods for field K and M dwarfs via HATNet ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hartman et al. 2011</ref>) and MEarth ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Irwin et al. 2011</ref>) in datasets up to a few years in length that also provide guidance on overall variability rates. Gomes da <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Silva et al. (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref> examined spectroscopic data for 27 stars using the NaI feature and for 93 stars using the Hα feature, respectively, to reveal long-term changes. Space-based efforts using Kepler data over a few months provide results for the variability of M dwarfs in the Kepler bandpass ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ciardi et al. 2011</ref>), and investigate their flare rates and intensities ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Walkowicz et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hawley et al.</ref> be closer than 25 pc. However, there are two groups of red dwarfs on the program that were eventually found to be at significantly different distances than anticipated. Cool subdwarfs ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jao et al. 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jao et al. , 2011</ref>) fall below the main sequence in the H-R diagram, and are closer than their photometric distance estimates imply. Young red dwarfs ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Riedel et al. 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Riedel et al. , 2014</ref>) lie above the main sequence and are consequently further than their photometric distance estimates. Thus, the best assessment of variability rates in a census of stars includes a detailed analysis of their distances, to prevent over or underrepresentation of subsamples of stars that may bias the statistics. Of the 264 stars in the sample discussed here, 238 are known to be within 25 pc based on our trigonometric parallaxes. Below, we analyze both the entire list of stars observed and the restricted sample of only those within 25 pc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Observations and Data Reduction</head><p>RECONS has been using the CTIO/SMARTS 0.9m telescope for astrometric and photometric observations since 1999, first as an NOAO Surveys Program, and since 2003 under the auspices of the SMARTS Consortium. The telescope is equipped with a 2048 x 2048 Tektronix CCD camera that is rarely moved, which provides the long-term astrometric stability needed for parallax work ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dieterich et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Henry et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jao et al. 2005</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jao et al. , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jao et al. , 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Riedel et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Riedel et al. , 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Riedel et al. , 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Subasavage et al. 2009</ref>) as well as a stable photometric platform. Images taken during the program are used here to investigate the photometric variability of the nearby M dwarfs that have been targeted for parallax and proper motion measurements. Observations are made using the central quarter of the chip, which provides a 6. ′ 8 square field of view and pixels 401 milliarcseconds in size. Parallax frames are taken in the V , R, and I filters 2 with magnitudes ranging from 9 to 20.</p><p>For astrometry, five images of each star are typically taken per night, usually within 30 minutes of transit. The target star is positioned in the field so that 5-10 reference stars, normally fainter by 1-4 magnitudes, surround the target. These stars constitute a reference grid for the astrometric reductions, and are also used for the photometric variability study described here. Additional details of the observations can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jao et al. (2005)</ref>. Exposure times usually range from 10-300 sec, with a few of the faintest stars requiring 600-900 sec integrations.</p><p>Data reduction includes calibration using flatfield and bias frames that are taken nightly. Each science frame is then manually checked for saturation of the target star or any reference stars. A frame with a saturated target star is discarded; individual reference stars are discarded if saturated, but the frame is used if sufficient reference stars remain available for reliable relative photometry.</p><p>V RI photometry from our program is given for the sample stars in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Details of the photometry observations and reductions can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Jao et al. (2005)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Winters et al. (2011)</ref>. Briefly, calibration frames are taken nightly, and standard stars selected from <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bessel (1990)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Graham (1982)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Landolt (1992</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Landolt ( , 2007</ref> are observed multiple times each night in order to derive transformation equations and extinction curves. Apertures 14 ′′ in diameter were used to determine the stellar fluxes, except in cases where close contaminating sources needed to be deblended, in which case smaller apertures were used and aperture corrections were applied. Photometric errors for the V RI magnitudes are typically 0.03 mag, measured using (usually) multiple nights of data and taking into account extinction corrections for each night via standard star observations. These errors are much larger than the relative photometry for the variability measurements discussed below, which instead use stars in the target fields at virtually identical airmasses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Variability Measurements</head><p>Here we define photometric variability to be the standard deviation of a star's flux, measured in milli-magnitudes (mmag), when compared to a set of reference stars. Once a setup frame that positions a target star within an ensemble of reference stars has been established, the target star's magnitude in each frame is compared to the reference stars using the methodology outlined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jao et al. (2011)</ref>. As an amendment to that methodology, we incorrectly stated in that paper that our instrumental magnitudes were based on counts within a defined aperture, whereas in fact they are based on Gaussian fits to the light distribution of each source. Briefly, we calculate instrumental magnitudes via SExtractor by integrating an object's pixel values within a circular Gaussian profile that is scaled to an object's image size and shape in a frame. The FWHM of this circle will be the radius of the disk that contains half of the object's flux. We control for changes in seeing, airmass, and atmospheric transparency in a series of exposures for an object by utilizing the prescription discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Honeycutt (1992)</ref>.</p><p>True stellar variability may be due to short-term flaring activity, mid-term rotation with spots, or long-term changes in spot numbers, i.e., a stellar cycle. Variability in frames due to other causes is identified and removed from the dataset. Such false variability may be caused by frames compromised by high background because they were taken in twilight or moonlight, or by contamination by a nearby source as the proper motion of the target star causes its position to slide across the field. One of the advantages to this long-term program and its fairly high resolution images (401 milliarcsecond pixels) is that the positions of background sources can be identified and monitored over time relative to target stars, thereby eliminating contaminating sources. Finally, reference stars that do not fit the trend of instrumental magnitude standard deviation with brightness (see Jao et al. 2011, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3)</ref> are removed from the analysis, and the target star's brightness is compared to the remaining "quiet" reference stars.</p><p>For the stars discussed here, we find standard deviations in the photometric series as low as 6.4 mmag, although only a half dozen stars have standard deviations below 7 mmag, which we adopt as the one-sigma minimum deviation threshold. This matches the 7-8 mmag variability measured for three stars in Jao et al. (2011) with long time-series of images using two different V filters. Thus, mixing the two V filters is not a serious concern because the filters appear to be so similar that any offsets are much smaller than the 7 mmag minimum variability threshold we can measure. This level, which we refer to henceforth as the detectable "variability floor", is represented with horizontal solid lines at 7 mmag in Figures 2-4. As a conservative measure of variability, we define significantly variable stars as those with standard deviations of 20 mmag or more relative to the chosen reference star set, but note that some stars in the 15-20 mmag range are variable at a lower level. This value is measured on an absolute scale, so that −20 mmag and +20 mmag differences would both be regarded as variability by 20 mmag.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 2-4</ref> we show photometric variability as functions of apparent V RI magnitude, V − K s color, and M V . There are 114 stars observed in the V filter, 81 in the R filter, and 69 in the I filter.</p><p>In the three panels of <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, there are no obvious trends in variability with apparent magnitude, but there are more stars variable by at least 20 mmag in V than in R or I. The intrinsically faintest, reddest, stars are typically observed in the I filter to boost S/N, and as discussed in §6, among the three filters this is where we find the least variability, as expected. Our variability floor of 7 mmag is the same in all three filters and at all brightnesses because we integrate for longer times on fainter targets to boost S/N for the astrometry studies, with the consequence that our photometric errors are not a strong function of brightness ( <ref type="bibr">Winters et al. 2011</ref>). We therefore conclude that systematic errors concerning our lower limit of variability detection have been ameliorated, and that the overall observational thresholds for variability detection are consistent among the three filters and at various target brightnesses.</p><p>The three panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> show perhaps a subtle trend of long-term variability with V − K color, which corresponds to temperature, with redder M dwarfs perhaps a bit more variable in V and R, but not in I, than early-type M dwarfs. However, this trend is weak, if present at all, and only with a much larger sample might the trend be confirmed. The three panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> are similar to those in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>, now using absolute magnitudes to explore trends in luminosity rather than temperature. The results are predictably similar to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> because luminosity is linked to temperature for main sequence stars.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Discussion</head><p>Inspection of Figures 2-4 reveals a distribution of long-term variability in red dwarfs that we divide into two populations: (1) clearly variable stars that change brightness by more than 20 mmag, with a few stars highly variable at more than 50 mmag, and (2) those that are relatively quiescent with variability less than 20 mmag. The division at 20 mmag is used to compute the fractions of variable stars, illustrated using a restricted sample of stars in the histogram of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> (discussed below). As illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figures 6-8</ref>, there are some likely variable stars in the relatively quiescent group with variability measurements of 15-20 mmag, but our goal here is to understand what fraction of red dwarfs vary by a significant amount, here chosen to be a threshold of 20 mmag, or ∼2% in flux in the observed bands. In the full sample, only 24 (9%) of the 264 stars vary photometrically by at least 20 mmag over long timescales; thus, ∼90% of red dwarfs change in optical brightness by less than 2%. For the full sample, the fractions of stars that fall into the variable/quiescent groups are 18%/82% in the V band (114 stars), 4%/96% in the R band (81 stars), and 3%/97% in the I band (69 stars).</p><p>These fractions are subject to the biases of the observational program, which targets red dwarfs possibly within 25 pc. The primary bias of concern is the sample of young stars that are larger and intrinsically brighter than main sequence dwarfs, resulting in distance estimates placing them much closer than their true distances. There are 15 young stars, as determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Riedel et al. (2014)</ref>, in our sample, denoted with "Y" in Column (2) of <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table  1</ref>, and with encircled points in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 2-4</ref>. Seven of these stars were observed in the V filter and eight in the R filter. Seven of the stars vary by more than 20 mmag (six in V and one in R), implying that 47% are variable stars by our criterion, a much higher fraction than in the sample as a whole.</p><p>Ideally, we would use a complete, volume-limited, sample to measure the fractions of red dwarfs photometrically variable over long timescales. Our best possible assessment with the current dataset is to restrict the sample to the 238 stars known to be within 25 pc via our trigonometric parallaxes, which is at least more representative of the red dwarf population than the full sample. Among these, the fractions of variable/quiescent red dwarfs are 13%/87% in the V band (106 stars), 4%/96% in the R band (70 stars), and 3%/97% in the I band (62 stars). Overall, only 19 of the 238 stars (8%) are variable by 20 mmag or more. We retain six young stars in the 25 pc sample (two observed at V and four at R) that vary by 17-25 mmag. All six stars vary by more than the median variability values in the V (14 mmag), R (13 mmag), and I filters (11 mmag).</p><p>Somewhat to our surprise, we do not see any strong trends in long-term variability with color ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>) or luminosity ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>) through the full range of red dwarfs in our sample. From the earliest types that have V − K = 4.0, M V ∼ 10, spectral type M2V, and T = 3600K, to those with V − K = 9.2, M V ∼ 20, spectral type M8V, and T = 2200K, (for empirical definitions of M dwarfs, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Henry et al. (1994)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baraffe &amp; Chabrier (1996)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Henry et al. (2006)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dieterich et al. (2014)</ref>), there are no obvious trends in activity with stellar type seen in any of the V RI bands. This is a particularly revealing result -stars that differ by a factor of ∼10 4 in visual flux (using M V ) and ∼160 in total luminosity do not exhibit any trends in their photometric variability over long time periods in the bands where they exhibit a sizeable amount of flux. For example, M0V stars emit 46% of their flux in the V RI bands, in contrast to M5V stars that emit 17% in the same bands. Furthermore, because red dwarfs lose their radiative zones and become fully convective around V − K ≈ 4.5, M V ≈ 11.0 (Chabrier &amp; Baraffe 1997), we might also expect to see an abrupt change in long-term photometric variability character at that color and absolute magnitude. We do not see such a change in the current sample, but we have not observed many stars bluer than V − K = 4.5.</p><p>To evaluate the relative variability in the three bands, we restrict the 25 pc sample further to include only stars with V − K = 4.5-6.5, in order to limit the effects of fainter, redder, stars in the sample that are typically observed in the I filter. This subsample contains a total of 180 stars, with median variability values of 14 mmag at V (94 stars), 13 mmag at R (66 stars), and 11 mmag at I (20 stars). These values are unchanged from the analysis including stars of all colors within 25 pc, and we conclude that red dwarfs vary slightly more in the V and R bands than in the I band over multi-year timescales, confirming what we reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jao et al. (2011)</ref>.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> we show the fractions of stars within 25 pc observed in V that are variable by more than 20 mmag, as a function of M V . The range is restricted to only those bins that have at least 10 stars, thereby including 97 of the 106 stars meeting the selection criteria. The error bars represent counting statistics and illustrate that more stars are needed to discern if there are any trends with luminosity -the total of 13 stars meeting our variability threshold is too small a sample to identify any trend.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Systems Worthy of Note</head><p>Here we provide details on several stars observed during the survey, grouped by type of variability and listed alphabetically within each group. Example plots of variability in the various categories are presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figures 6-8</ref>. We break the stars into those showing stellar cycles, trends, and erratic brightness changes likely due to spots and/or flares. We note that some of these stars do not formally exceed our conservative 20 mmag threshold for obvious variability, but they are highlighted here primarily because we see compelling trends in their data sets.</p><p>In the upper left panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>, we first show a baseline non-variable target, SCR 1845-6357AB, which is composed of an M8.5V dwarf and a brown dwarf companion separated by ∼1 ′′ that does not affect the photometry. In fact, this target has such a low level of variability that we have adopted it as a red photometric standard.</p><p>Stellar Cycles in GJ 831AB, GJ 1061, LHS 2397aAB, LP 467-016AB, and SCR 0613-2742AB: These five targets exhibit cyclic variations in their photometry, illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>. GJ 831AB is a fast-orbiting binary with an orbital period of 1.93 years and ∆V =2.1 between the two components ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Franz et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Henry et al. 1999</ref>). <ref type="bibr">3</ref> We see a pattern in our current dataset with a period of ∼8 yr, although there are deviations from a clear sinusoidal cycle in 2005. Given ∆V =2.1, presumably the observed variability is in the primary component. The variation in GJ 1061 is muted, with a tentative cycle lasting about 8 years. The variations in LHS 2397aAB and LP 467-016AB appear to be robust, with periods of ∼4 years and ∼5 years, respectively. The most obvious cycle is that of SCR 0613-2742AB, for which we derive a period of ∼0.4 years. Because of the short period for the cyclic behavior noted for SCR 0613-2742AB, we are likely seeing evidence of the rotation period, while the longer term upward trend may reflect a portion of a long-term cycle.</p><p>Photometric Trends in G 169-029, GJ 876, L 449-001AB, LHS 1610AB, LHS 2021, and WT 460AB: These six targets show long-term trends in their photometry, illus-trated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 7</ref>, but have not yet clearly completed a cycle in our coverage. Remarkably, G 169-029 (10 years) and WT 460AB (13 years), show extraordinarily long-term trends that have yet to invert, with overall flux changes of ∼5% in R and I, respectively. To our knowledge, these are the first discoveries of changes in red dwarf fluxes lasting a decade or more. WT 460AB is a binary composed of two red dwarfs with spectral types M5.5V and ∼L1V separated by 0. ′′ 5 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Montagnier et al. 2006</ref>). The large ∆H=2.5 mag difference implies an even larger ∆I, so presumably the change in brightness is due to the M dwarf. The data series on L 449-001AB similarly shows a long-term trend throughout the 5-year time series in-hand. Additional trends are seen in the data for G 161-071, LHS 547, and SCR 2036-3607 (not shown here).</p><p>Spots in GJ 2006A, LP 932-083, and TWA 8A: These targets show distinctive variability illustrated in the left three panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref>, at levels of 77 mmag, 46 mmag, and 79 mmag, respectively. The data indicate that these stars change their broadband fluxes frequently, likely because much of the stellar surface is active with flares and/or spots. Flares and spots are both modulated by stellar rotation, as the active regions rotate in/out of our view, and as the spots change over long time periods. We do not see obvious cyclic patterns in the brightnesses of these three stars. The case of TWA 8AB is particularly intriguing. This is a binary member of the TW Hydra Association separated by 13 arcseconds, in which the A component shows clear spot activity and for which we have observed a flare in the B component (see below). Additional evidence for spots is seen in the data for G 007-034, G 131-026, GJ 1123, GJ 1284AB, GJ 2006B, LHS 2206, LHS 5094, LP 834-032, and Proxima Centauri (not shown here). Overall, there are only four red dwarfs in the sample that vary by more than 50 mmag: GJ 1207, GJ 2006A, TWA 8A, and TWA 8B, all observed in the V filter. The GJ 2006 (the B component varies by 36 mmag in V ) and TWA 8 systems are young stars, as discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Riedel et al. (2014)</ref>. GJ 1207 is not known to be a young system, and without the single extreme flare event mentioned above, it would fall in our quiescent group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Comparison to Previous Studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1.">Long-Term Results from Ground-Based Studies</head><p>In his classic study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Weis (1994)</ref> used a GaAs photomultiplier tube and a similar V RI filter set to that used in our study. Although Weis was not able to guarantee the same tube and filter set for every run (typically seven to eight nights, which he referred to as a season of observation), he provided valuable results on the variability of nearby M dwarfs. He observed 43 stars for up to 11 years in all three of the V RI filters, and determined a variability detection limit of 5 mmag for his observational technique. Weis used σ a to denote the average mean error of a seasonal mean magnitude and σ b to denote the dispersion of the seasonal mean magnitudes about the overall mean. These two quantities correspond to short-term (over a ∼week) and long-term (over years) variability measurements. He concluded that 21 of the stars exhibited long-term variability at the 95% confidence level. However, most of the variability was in the range 10-20 mmag; only 8 (19%), 4 (9%), and 0 (0%) stars were variable at the 20 mmag level over long time periods in the V , R, and I bands, respectively. Our variability measurements are similar to Weis' σ b measurement, and we find similar fractions of variability, albeit for ∼six times the number of stars: 18%, 4%, and 3% of our stars vary by more 20 mmag or more at V , R, and I, respectively. To our knowledge, Weis' work is the first significant study of the long-term variability of red dwarfs. Jao et al. (2011) studied a set of 22 cool subdwarfs, and compared them to 108 main sequence red dwarfs. Those results are based on the same long-term astrometry/photometry taken during the RECONS program at the 0.9m outlined above, but over a somewhat shorter time period. For the first time, that study revealed that red subdwarfs are less photometrically variable in the V RI bands than their main sequence counterparts, with average variabilities for the 22 cool subdwarfs at levels of only 7 mmag at V (3 stars), 8 mmag at R (13 stars), and 7 mmag at I (6 stars). This is effectively the variability floor level of our observations, and in fact, cool subdwarfs are likely even less variable than indicated by those values.</p><p>Spectroscopic variability studies of M dwarfs spanning years have been carried out by Gomes da <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Silva et al. (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref>. Both studies focused primarily on stars with spectral types M0V-M4V, a bluer set of stars than our M2V-M8V sample. Gomes da Silva et al. (2012) investigated 27 M dwarfs in the HARPS radial velocity program with a median observational timespan of 5.9 years to detect correlations between long-term activity variations and the measured radial velocities. By using the NaI D doublet as an activity index, they found that 14 of the stars had activity indicative of long-term variations, although in truth, only a few of the NaI vs. time plots show convincing cycles. Assuming their selection of the five stars deemed to have reliable sinusoidal signals in their NaI indices, their variable activity rate is 19%.</p><p>In a comparable spectroscopic study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref> used ∼11 years of spectra from the McDonald Observatory M Dwarf Planet Search to reveal cyclic variations in M dwarfs that could be measured using the Hα line. Among their 93 stars they identified five exhibiting periodic signals ranging from 0.8-7.4 years, and found eight additional stars showing long-term trends, or at least offsets in Hα index over time. Their fraction of stars with detected changes in Hα, 14%, is similar to our fraction of stars varying by more than 20 mmag in the V band, 18%, implying that changes in Hα may correlate quite well to changes in V band flux.</p><p>The single star included in Gomes da <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Silva et al. (2012)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref>, and our study is the multi-planet system GJ 581. The spectroscopic studies report periodic signals in NaI lasting 3.9 years in a 6-year dataset and in Hα lasting 4.5 years in a 9-year dataset, respectively. GJ 581 falls in the quiescent set of our stars, varying by only 13 mmag in V over 12.8 years. We note that GJ 581 has the largest false alarm probability (0.12) of the five stars with periodic signals in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref>, and although Gomes da <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Silva et al. (2012)</ref> state that this is the star with the highest probability that its activity data can be fitted with a sinusoidal signal, the amplitude is only twice the average error. We conclude that this particular cycle may not be real. Nonetheless, long-term photometric monitoring of GJ 581 and the other NaI and Hα variable stars would certainly be a worthy project, particularly at the ∼1 mmag level possible with ground-based telescopes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2.">Shorter-Term Results from Ground-Based Studies</head><p>Hartman et al. (2011) explored the optical variability of a sample of 27560 field K and M dwarfs using data from the HATNet transit-search survey. Their observational series range from 45 days to 2.5 years, with a median time span of half a year. Thus, they are sampling time periods suited for exploring rotation periods, rather than the stellar cycles we are investigating. After carefully deleting blended sources, a concern because of HATNet's 9-14 ′′ /pixel scales, they find 1490 stars (excluding eclipsing binaries) that vary at the 10 mmag level in the RI bands, indicating that at least ∼5% vary at this level. In their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure  14</ref>, they show an increasing fraction of variable stars with V − K color. For stars having V − K = 4.5-6.5, like most of those in our study, they find 10 mmag variability rates rising from 7% to more than 40%, although the error bars are significant, particularly beyond V − K = 5.25 because there are 20 or fewer stars in each of those three bins. Regardless, this large survey indicates that most M dwarfs do not vary by more than 1% over many months, similar to our conclusion for similar stars over many years. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Irwin et al. (2011)</ref> reported rotation periods, based upon photometric variability, in the range of a few hours up to about 5 months for 41 red dwarfs from the MEarth project. Their study differs from that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hartman et al. (2011)</ref> in that they were specifically targeting nearby stars, and using much higher resolution images, with pixels 0.76 ′′ in size so blending is rarely an issue. As with the HATnet survey, their observations are higher cadence than ours, with typically several hundred to several thousand observations per star over time periods of 3 months to 3 years, with an upper sensitivity limit to periodicities at 5 months.</p><p>The observations were made through a long pass filter at 715 nm, and periodic variations were reported with amplitudes of 2.7 to 23.9 mmag in their <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Their study does not examine the long-term variability discussed here, but as with <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hartman et al. (2011)</ref>, provides important complementary information. The 41 stars with rotation periods were extracted from an overall sample of 273 stars, of which ∼80% had at least 100 observations on 10 or more nights, indicating that ∼20% of the well-sampled stars had determinable rotation periods. Among these, 10 have semi-amplitudes of at least 10 mmag, or roughly 5%, similar to that found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hartman et al. (2011)</ref>, although no information was provided about the variability rate for stars not found to have rotation periods.</p><p>Finally, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koen et al. (2010)</ref> reported UBV RI photometry for over 700 nearby stars, primarily of spectral types K and M. Their study is rather different than ours, as it was an effort to provide photometry, with typically a handful of observations per star rather than long time series over many years. Nonetheless, as outlined in their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> (based on apparent V magnitude), they find that most of their sample stars vary by less than 20 mmag, similar to our result.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.">Results from the Kepler Mission</head><p>To date, the Kepler mission has provided an opportunity to study a few thousand M dwarfs in the northern hemisphere photometrically, although most are not in the immediate solar neighborhood, and none are in common with the stars studied here. Kepler samples the light curves of stars in a bandpass that spans 400-850 nm, every 30 minutes for the datasets discussed here. This single bandpass roughly corresponds to the combined light of the V RI bands we have used.</p><p>In a study of the first month of Q1 Kepler science data, Ciardi et al. (2011) extracted variability rates for periods up to 33 days for 129,000 dwarfs, including more than 2000 identified as M dwarfs. There are two apparent magnitude samples examined that provide useful statistics, but there are several caveats: the stars are at various distances, sources are defocused so may be unresolved multiple systems or blends with background stars, and while significant efforts were made to separate the dwarfs and giants, no color information for individual stars is given, so various types of M dwarfs (and possibly other red objects) were mixed in the samples. Using data in their <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, for M dwarfs having M Kepler = 12-14, 14 of 154 stars (9%) had magnitude dispersions greater than 10 mmag over the 33 day period. For M Kepler = 14-16, 150 of 2182 stars (7%) varied by 10 mmag. In addition, they find that the overall variability fraction at the 30-minute sampling rate increases for the M dwarfs as baselines increase from 1 to 33 days, and therefore conclude that M dwarfs vary primarily on timescales of weeks or longer. Because our variability floor is 7 mmag, a direct comparison to the results from Kepler, which measures photometry to tens of parts per million, is problematic -we find that 193 (73%) of the 264 stars in our sample vary by at least 10 mmag in one of the three V RI filters, but this large fraction is simply because 10 mmag is very close to our variability floor.</p><p>In a second Kepler study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Walkowicz et al. (2011)</ref> examined ∼ 23,000 K and M dwarfs in the same Q1 dataset as <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Ciardi et al. (2011)</ref>, again using the 30-minute cadence results over a 33 day time period, with the goal of identifying flare stars. They found 373 stars that exhibited flare activity via their EW phot parameter. They derive three characteristics of the stars in their flare sample: (1) M dwarfs flare more frequently than K dwarfs, but for shorter durations, (2) there is no dependence on the flare peaks with stellar effective temperature, and (3) stars that have larger quiescent variability have intrinsically larger flares. Overall, the fraction of stars exhibiting flares in the Kepler dataset is very low, less than 2%. This is consistent with our data, given that we have identified only three stars that clearly flare among 264.</p><p>More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hawley et al. (2014)</ref> report flare occurrence rates for five M dwarf systems (four singles and one close double) monitored by Kepler in short cadence mode. Three of the M dwarfs had no Hα emission and were labeled "inactive", yet still produced a few energetic flares, but at much lower rates than their active counterparts. These three inactive M dwarfs were in flaring states for 0.1%, 0.6%, and 1.5% of the time observed, while the two active M dwarf systems spent 27% and 36% of the time in a flaring state. Thus, chromospherically inactive M dwarfs do exhibit energetic flares, but only rarely, which is consistent with the very few flares we have seen in more than a decade of monitoring nearby red dwarfs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.">Summary of Results</head><p>The long term efforts of <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Weis (1994)</ref>, Jao et al. (2011), Gomes da <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Silva et al. (2012)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Robertson et al. (2013)</ref>, as well as our study presented here, all indicate that only ∼10-20% of red dwarfs vary by at least 2% in the V band, or when using proxy spectral features. At R and I, the variability rate is much lower. In sum, these studies clearly indicate that M dwarfs do exhibit long-term cycles like our Sun, but that most M dwarfs do not vary by more than a few percent over long timespans.</p><p>The remaining optical wavelength studies discussed here focus on timespans suited to determining rotation periods, rather than stellar cycles. Those results explore timescales up to a few months in duration, whereas our measurements are over years, yet in sum also indicate that only a small fraction of M dwarfs exhibit flux variability exceeding a few percent. Although the V RI bands in which we have observed the stars in this survey may not be those in which variability is greatest, such as at x-ray wavelengths, red dwarfs emit much of their flux in these bands, in particular for the earlier types. Most of the rest of red dwarfs' flux is emitted in the near-infrared, and the study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Goulding et al. (2012)</ref> of ∼9600 M dwarfs yielded only 68 stars (less than 1%) that were periodically variable by more than 10 mmag (their <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table A1</ref>) in the J band. This is a much smaller fraction than we found at V RI, and confirms the trend of less variability with increasing wavelength.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">M Dwarf Variability and Exoplanets</head><p>One of the motivations for this study was to evaluate the variability of the ubiquitous red dwarfs because such variations will affect the environments, and perhaps the habitability, of any orbiting planets. In particular, long-term variations in the flux emitted could affect planetary atmospheres in ways similar to how our Sun affects the Earth's atmosphere, e.g., the cyclic influx of charged particles that cause aurorae and expansion/contraction of the atmosphere. Here we discuss some of the nearest red dwarfs with detected exoplanets to provide context for effects on planetary environments that stretch over years.</p><p>In <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>, we list M dwarfs within 25 pc currently reported to have orbiting exoplanets. This sample has been created using the intersection of the exoplanets.org and exoplanet.eu websites as of 01 July 2014 -stars are only included if the detected exoplanets have been vetted and listed by both groups. The sample is heavily skewed to the closest M dwarfs; presumably many more planets await discovery within 25 pc. We list the number of reported planets and photometry for the 17 stars, as well as our own monitoring results for seven stars, including V RI photometry, filters used for the long-term observations, the variability levels, and the duration and number of observations (nights, frames). The unobserved stars in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> are not being followed because they are either too bright for our astrometric program, requiring short exposures and consequently poor centroids for astrometry, or are in the northern sky.</p><p>None of the seven exoplanet host stars we have observed has been found to be variable by more than 20 mmag in the available datasets. The only star of note among the seven is GJ 876, which displays a possible stellar cycle <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">(Figure 7)</ref>, growing brighter from <ref type="bibr">[2004]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2005]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2006]</ref>, and rather fainter in the most recent epoch available in 2013. We conclude that photometric variability, at least at optical wavelengths, is not a concern for the environments of exoplanets orbiting most red dwarfs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">Conclusions</head><p>We have collected photometric observations for 264 red dwarfs over the past 14 years, with a median duration in the coverage of 7.9 years. We have used these images to determine long-term photometric variability in the V RI bands, and reach the following conclusions:</p><p>• Only ∼10% of red dwarfs are variable at the 20 mmag level over multi-year timescales in the V RI photometric bands. Thus, the impression that red dwarfs are highly active with large changes in brightness is likely due to the notoriety of a small number of highly variable stars, e.g. EV Lac. Instead, most red dwarfs are relatively quiet, at least at optical wavelengths.</p><p>• As expected, we find that the measured variability is lower in the I band than in the V or R bands. Of the 25 stars varying by more than 20 mmag, 20 were observed in the V band. Given that most red dwarfs emit the majority of their flux in the I band, or at even longer wavelengths in the near-infrared where the variability is even lower, the overall fluxes of most red dwarfs change very little.</p><p>• To our surprise, we find no clear trends in variability at the 20 mmag level for M dwarfs as functions of luminosity or temperature, at least in the current sample. However, identifying relatively young stars can be accomplished via long-term photometric monitoring.</p><p>• We have identified several red dwarfs exhibiting long-term photometric changes, including five stars with cyclic periods lasting up to 8 years and nine stars with long-term trends, two of which have been continuing for a decade. At least 12 additional stars show evidence of spots.</p><p>These results have a particular application to the study of habitable environments around M dwarfs. To first-order, planetary surface temperatures are estimated based on the stellar flux and the distance of a planet from its host star. Here we investigate a secondorder effect over ∼decade timescales: the change in insolation as an M dwarf varies may be crucial for planetary environmental impact. We find that ∼90% of M dwarfs vary by less than 2% at wavelengths where they emit much of their light, implying that long-term flux levels do not change appreciably on most planets orbiting red dwarfs.</p><p>To further refine the fractions of variables in the red dwarf population, future studies should target larger, volume-limited samples. This would reduce concerns related to biases in the current sample, including the overabundance of active young stars and unresolved multiples that have been treated as single stars. In addition, more refined studies could probe to higher precision. For example, the CTIO/SMARTS 0.9m telescope used to make the observations discussed here is able to reach photometric precisions of ∼1 mmag when target stars are defocused to boost the total stellar signals, compared to the 7 mmag variability floor achieved here using the tightly focused images required for astrometry. Nonetheless, we now know that most red dwarfs, which comprise three-quarters of all stars in the solar neighborhood, are photometrically stable on decade timescales at a level of 2% at optical wavelengths. This bodes well for the stability of environments on any planets that might be orbiting them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">Acknowledgments</head><p>ADH thanks the McNair Fellowship program under the support of TRIO for providing funding for this research. The RECONS effort has been supported by the National Science Foundation through grants AST 05-07711, AST 09-08402, and AST 14-12026. We also thank the members of the SMARTS Consortium and the CTIO staff, who enable the operations of the small telescopes at CTIO. This research has made use of results from the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System Bibliographic Services, as well as the SIMBAD and VizieR databases operated at CDS, Strasbourg, France, and the Two Micron All Sky Survey, which is a joint project of the University of Massachusetts and the Infrared Processing and Analysis Center, funded by NASA and NSF.</p><p>Winters, J. G., Henry, T. J., Jao, W.-C., Subasavage, J. P., <ref type="bibr">Finch</ref>  s: "Y" in Column 2 indicates stars confirmed to be young in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Riedel et al. (2014)</ref>. V RI photometry is from this paper = *,   For seven stars, the filter listed is used to observe the star for parallax and photometric variability. The two stars indicated with a are being observed but not included in the larger study discussed here because they do not yet have four years of observations. Stars not observed in this program are listed for completeness, with the filter, variability, and coverage metrics left blank.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The median time coverage is 7.9 years. Some stars were not observed uniformly throughout the time period, i.e. they had fewer than three nights of observations in some years. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-The photometric variability defined as the standard deviation of a target star's brightness relative to reference stars in the field, is shown in each of the three filters used for long-term astrometric measurements, V RI, as a function of target brightness. Circled points represent stars denoted as young, with "Y" beside their names in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. Four stars discussed in the text vary by more than 50 mmag at V and are represented by arrowed points in the V panel. There are no obvious trends in photometric variability with apparent magnitude, with a variability floor represented by solid lines at 7 mmag in all three filters. Dotted lines at 20 mmag indicate our selected threshold between active (above) and quiescent (below) stars.       <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> caption for plot layout details. The three left panels show data for stars that appear to show evidence of spots, whereas the three right panels show stars with obvious flare events.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Flares in GJ 1207, LHS 6167AB, and TWA 8B: These three stars show clear flare events, illustrated in the right panels of Figure 8. GJ 1207 has the largest variability measurement, 196 mmag, in the sample, caused entirely by our observation of a flare that brightened the star by 1.7 mag in V on UT 2002 June 17 (Henry et al. 2006). Omitting the flare event reduces its variability to 18 mmag. LHS 6167AB shows a flare with amplitude 0.2 mag on UT 2013 April 2. TWA 8B is the second most variable star in our sample, at 124 mmag, again caused by single 0.7 mag flare in V observed on UT 2000 March 27.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Dieterich et al. (2014) = Die14, et al. (2004) = Hen04, Henry et al. (2006) = Hen06, Jao et al. (2005) = Jao05, Jao et al. (2011) = Jao11, Jao et al. (2014) = Jao14, Mamajek et al. (2013) m13, Riedel et al. (2010) = Rie10, Riedel et al. (2014) = Rie14, Subasavage et al. (2009) = Sub09, Winters et al. (2011) = Win11, and Winters et al. (2015) = Win15.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Notes: V RI photometry is from this paper = *, Bessel (1990) = Bes90, Koen et al. (2010) = Koe10, Weis (1996) = Wei96, and our program, Riedel et al. (2010) = Rie10, Winters et al. (2015) = Win15. V − Ks uses Ks from 2MASS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-This histogram outlines the photometric variability time coverage for the sample stars, listed individually in Table 1. The median time coverage is 7.9 years. Some stars were not observed uniformly throughout the time period, i.e. they had fewer than three nights of observations in some years.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-The photometric variability is shown in each of the three filters used for long-term astrometric measurements, V RI, as a function of target V − K color. There are no obvious trends in photometric variability with temperature. See the caption of Figure 2 for additional details of the plot format.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-The photometric variability is shown in each of the three filters used for long-term astrometric measurements, V RI, as a function of absolute magnitude. There are no obvious trends in photometric variability with luminosity. See the caption of Figure 2 for additional details of the plot format.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-The fractions of variable stars within 25 pc observed in the V filter are shown, setting the variability threshold at 20 mmag. In total, there are 106 stars in the sample, of which 14 (13%) vary by more than 20 mmag. Nine stars are not shown because they fall in one brighter bin and two fainter bins with too few stars to be statistically useful. Large error bars represent counting statistics, illustrating that the sample suffers from small numbers of detected variable stars. This precludes detecting any clear trends in variability in the current dataset.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-Each panel illustrates the brightness for one target measured relative to a set of observed background reference stars, where each point represents an individual image. The filter for the observations is given in the upper left of each panel after the target name. The relative brightnesses are given as magnitude differences, measured in milli-magnitudes, with the average deviation from zero listed at the top right. The star is brighter when points are plotted toward the top, i.e. at negative offsets. Dotted lines represent offsets twice that of the average deviation. The upper left panel for SCR 1845-6357AB shows a non-variable star. The other five panels show stars with periodic variations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-See Figure 6 caption for plot layout details. Each of the six stars shown exhibits a long-term trend that does not appear to have yet completed a full cycle in the available datasets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-See Figure 6 caption for plot layout details. The three left panels show data for stars that appear to show evidence of spots, whereas the three right panels show stars with obvious flare events.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Red Dwarfs Studied for Long-Term Variability</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Name 
Young 
R.A. 
Dec. 
V 
R 
I 
Ref. 
Ks 
V − Ks 
Filter 
Variability 
Timespan 
Duration 
#Nights 
#Frames 
π trig ± σ 
Ref. 
J2000.0 
J2000.0 
(mmag) 
(yr) 
(mas) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) 
(9) 
(10) 
(11) 
(12) 
(13) 
(14) 
(15) 
(16) 
(17) 
(18) 

. 
GJ 1001A 
... 
00 04 36 
−40 44 02 
12.83 
11.62 
11.08 
Win15 
7.74 
5.09 
R 
13.7 
1999.64-2011.74 
12.10 
21 
112 
77.02 2.07 
Die14 
GJ 1002 
... 
00 06 43 
−07 32 17 
13.84 
12.21 
10.21 
Win15 
7.44 
6.40 
R 
13.9 
2003.77-2012.87 
9.10 
14 
64 
207.18 3.09 
Dav14 
L 217-028 
... 
00 08 17 
−57 05 52 
12.13 
11.00 
9.57 
Win15 
7.40 
4.73 
V 
9.8 
2000.50-2008.00 
7.25 
15 
68 
... 
... 
G 131-026 
... 
00 08 53 
+20 50 25 
13.52 
12.19 
10.50 
Rie14 
8.01 
5.51 
V 
18.9 
1999.71-2011.89 
12.18 
21 
97 
54.13 1.35 
Rie14 
GJ 1005AB 
... 
00 15 28 
−16 08 01 
11.48 
10.27 
8.70 
Win15 
6.39 
5.09 
V 
8.2 
2003.75-2011.90 
7.96 
22 
95 
... 
... 
GJ 2006A 
Y 
00 27 50 
−32 33 06 
12.95 
11.79 
10.29 
Rie14 
8.01 
4.94 
V 
76.8 
2000.57-2010.82 
10.25 
17 
69 
30.14 2.50 
Rie14 
GJ 2006B 
Y 
00 27 50 
−32 33 23 
13.25 
12.04 
10.48 
Rie14 
8.12 
5.13 
V 
36.2 
2000.57-2010.82 
10.25 
17 
69 
31.78 2.47 
Rie14 
GR 50 
... 
00 32 53 
−04 34 07 
13.97 
12.68 
11.00 
Win15 
8.35 
5.62 
R 
13.0 
2007.82-2012.95 
5.13 
11 
59 
... 
... 
LHS 1140 
... 
00 44 59 
−15 16 17 
14.18 
12.88 
11.19 
Win15 
8.82 
5.36 
V 
12.2 
2003.95-2011.88 
7.93 
12 
52 
... 
... 
L 087-002 
... 
00 57 12 
−64 15 24 
12.40 
11.28 
9.81 
Win15 
7.60 
4.80 
V 
8.9 
2008.86-2012.87 
4.01 
14 
70 
... 
... 
GJ 1025 
... 
01 00 56 
−04 26 56 
13.35 
12.08 
10.52 
Win15 
8.22 
5.13 
V 
19.8 
2000.57-2012.75 
12.17 
13 
66 
87.70 2.38 
Jao05 
SCR 0103-5515ABC 
Y 
01 03 35 
−55 15 56 
15.48 
14.00 
12.07 
Rie14 
9.24 
6.24 
R 
15.4 
2007.82-2012.87 
5.05 
11 
49 
21.18 1.37 
Rie14 
L 087-010 
... 
01 04 06 
−65 22 27 
13.98 
12.63 
10.95 
Win15 
8.53 
5.45 
V 
13.9 
2008.64-2012.88 
4.24 
10 
44 
... 
... 
GJ 54AB 
... 
01 10 22 
−67 26 41 
9.82 
8.70 
7.32 
Win15 
5.13 
4.69 
V 
16.4 
2000.75-2012.00 
11.20 
40 
197 
141.20 3.38 
Hen06 
LP 467-016AB 
Y 
01 11 25 
+15 26 21 
14.46 
12.95 
11.03 
Rie14 
8.21 
6.25 
R 
19.2 
1999.71-2009.57 
9.86 
15 
79 
45.79 1.78 
Rie14 
LEHPM 1-1343 
... 
01 13 16 
−54 29 13 
14.16 
12.85 
11.17 
Win15 
8.68 
5.48 
R 
21.3 
1999.91-2004.98 
5.06 
14 
64 
... 
... 
GJ 2022B 
Y 
01 24 30 
−33 55 01 
15.50 
14.09 
12.33 
Rie14 
9.68 
5.82 
R 
14.4 
1999.62-2011.53 
11.91 
16 
66 
38.80 2.13 
Rie14 
L 002-060 
... 
01 29 20 
−85 56 11 
13.49 
12.21 
10.58 
Win15 
8.08 
5.41 
I 
6.7 
2003.95-2008.70 
4.75 
10 
55 
... 
... 
LP 991-084 
... 
01 39 21 
−39 36 09 
14.48 
12.97 
11.06 
Win15 
8.27 
6.21 
V 
14.2 
2003.94-2012.96 
9.02 
14 
66 
... 
... 
L 294-092 
... 
01 47 42 
−48 36 05 
12.42 
11.23 
9.72 
Win15 
7.45 
4.97 
R 
9.2 
2004.75-2012.00 
6.99 
23 
63 
... 
... 
LHS 1302 
... 
01 51 04 
−06 07 05 
14.49 
13.00 
11.17 
Win15 
8.55 
5.94 
R 
11.8 
1999.71-2011.78 
12.06 
31 
178 
100.78 1.89 
Hen06 
LHS 5045 
... 
01 52 51 
−48 05 41 
13.79 
12.48 
10.80 
Win15 
8.24 
5.55 
R 
9.4 
2004.00-2008.80 
5.67 
20 
44 
... 
... 
SIP 0152-6329 
... 
01 52 55 
−63 29 30 
15.41 
13.93 
12.01 
* 
9.26 
6.15 
R 
16.4 
2007.82-2012.94 
5.12 
8 
41 
... 
... 
L 088-043 
... 
01 53 37 
−66 53 34 
11.68 
10.60 
9.24 
Win15 
6.99 
4.69 
R 
8.1 
2005.71-2011.89 
6.18 
15 
79 
... 
... 
L 173-019 
... 
02 00 38 
−55 58 04 
11.90 
10.70 
9.15 
* 
6.77 
5.13 
V 
19.8 
2007.81-2011.96 
4.15 
11 
57 
... 
... 
LHS 1339 
... 
02 05 48 
−30 10 36 
12.18 
11.07 
9.69 
Win15 
7.56 
4.62 
V 
9.1 
2004.00-2008.90 
4.93 
25 
36 
... 
... 
GJ 85 
... 
02 07 23 
−66 34 11 
11.49 
10.49 
9.31 
Win15 
7.36 
4.13 
V 
9.2 
2003.95-2012.70 
8.75 
14 
69 
... 
... 
LHS 1351 
... 
02 11 18 
−63 13 41 
12.23 
11.15 
9.82 
Rie10 
7.73 
4.50 
V 
8.7 
2000.58-2004.98 
4.40 
12 
68 
71.53 1.64 
Rie10 
LHS 1358 
... 
02 12 54 
+00 00 16 
13.58 
12.31 
10.66 
Rie10 
8.17 
5.41 
R 
15.1 
1999.71-2003.86 
4.15 
11 
58 
65.27 2.07 
Rie10 
LHS 1363 
... 
02 14 12 
−03 57 43 
16.44 
14.71 
12.62 
Win15 
9.49 
6.95 
I 
11.1 
2003.94-2012.95 
9.01 
17 
64 
... 
... 
G 075-035 
... 
02 41 15 
−04 32 17 
13.79 
12.48 
10.77 
Win15 
8.25 
5.54 
R 
10.1 
2003.95-2012.94 
8.99 
16 
73 
... 
... 
LP 993-115A 
... 
02 45 10 
−43 44 32 
12.38 
11.17 
9.61 
Rie14 
7.20 
5.18 
V 
21.0 
1999.62-2012.95 
13.32 
15 
71 
89.62 1.73 
Rie14 
LP 993-115BC 
... 
02 45 14 
−43 44 10 
12.69 
11.37 
9.67 
* 
7.27 
5.42 
V 
14.5 
1999.62-2012.95 
13.32 
15 
71 
84.12 2.08 
Rie14 
SCR 0246-7024 
... 
02 46 02 
−70 24 06 
14.86 
13.44 
11.61 
Win11 
9.02 
5.84 
R 
12.6 
2006.87-2012.94 
6.07 
12 
51 
... 
... 
SO 0253+1652 
... 
02 53 00 
+16 52 52 
15.14 
13.03 
10.65 
Hen06 
7.59 
7.55 
I 
7.7 
2003.53-2009.04 
5.50 
19 
118 
260.63 2.69 
Hen06 
LHS 1491 
... 
03 04 04 
−20 22 43 
12.84 
11.65 
10.13 
Rie10 
7.75 
5.09 
V 
17.9 
1999.71-2005.00 
5.29 
15 
70 
67.28 1.25 
Rie10 
LEHPM 1-3070 
... 
03 06 11 
−36 47 52 
19.38 
16.98 
14.49 
Die14 
10.63 
8.75 
I 
8.5 
2009.75-2013.80 
4.06 
11 
54 
76.46 1.42 
Die14 
LP 831-045 
... 
03 14 18 
−23 09 29 
12.58 
11.42 
9.93 
Win15 
7.63 
4.95 
V 
16.6 
2003.95-2011.77 
7.82 
20 
60 
... 
... 
LHS 1550 
... 
03 28 48 
−27 19 04 
13.75 
12.58 
11.07 
* 
8.77 
4.98 
R 
13.9 
2008.86-2012.94 
4.08 
11 
57 
... 
... 
LP 888-018 
... 
03 31 30 
−30 42 38 
18.81 
16.55 
14.10 
Win15 
10.26 
8.55 
I 
9.0 
2003.95-2012.88 
8.93 
15 
69 
... 
... 
LEHPM 1-3396 
... 
03 34 12 
−49 53 32 
19.38 
16.85 
14.39 
Win15 
10.39 
8.99 
I 
8.4 
2004.75-2012.93 
8.18 
20 
95 
... 
... 
LHS 1561 
... 
03 34 39 
−04 50 33 
13.07 
11.84 
10.30 
Rie10 
7.93 
5.14 
V 
7.8 
2000.07-2010.97 
10.91 
14 
72 
34.20 1.72 
Rie10 
LHS 176 
... 
03 35 38 
−08 29 22 
15.92 
14.30 
12.31 
Jao11 
9.46 
6.46 
I 
9.7 
2004.00-2009.10 
5.17 
17 
47 
77.77 1.30 
Jao11 
GJ 1061 
... 
03 36 00 
−44 30 46 
13.09 
11.45 
9.46 
Hen06 
6.61 
6.48 
R 
15.2 
1999.62-2012.95 
13.32 
31 
194 
271.92 1.34 
Hen06 
SCR 0336-2619 
... 
03 36 31 
−26 19 57 
16.33 
14.76 
12.72 
* 
9.76 
6.57 
I 
10.8 
2008.70-2012.94 
4.23 
7 
39 
... 
... 
LP 944-020 
... 
03 39 35 
−35 25 43 
18.70 
16.39 
14.01 
Die14 
9.55 
9.15 
I 
8.8 
2003.95-2012.94 
8.99 
14 
59 
155.89 1.03 
Die14 
SCR 0342-6407 
... 
03 42 57 
−64 07 56 
16.01 
14.65 
12.89 
Jao11 
10.58 
5.43 
I 
7.0 
2003.94-2007.89 
3.95 
12 
66 
41.56 2.01 
Jao11 
LHS 1582AB 
... 
03 43 22 
−09 33 50 
14.69 
13.33 
11.60 
Rie10 
8.85 
5.84 
R 
14.6 
2000.87-2012.70 
11.82 
22 
92 
50.84 1.21 
Lur14 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 2 . M Dwarfs Nearer than 25 Parsecs with Exoplanets</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Name 
# Planets 
V 
R 
I 
Ref. 
V − Ks 
Filter 
Variability 
Duration 
# Nights 
# Frames 
(mmag) 
(yr) </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> Visiting Astronomer, Cerro Tololo Inter-american Observatory. CTIO is operated by AURA, Inc. under contract to the National Science Foundation.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> www.recons.org</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> The central wavelengths for the V J , R KC , and I KC filters used in this study are 5438/5475, 6425, and 8075Å8075Å, respectively. The two V filters used during this study have been found to be photometrically identical at a level better than the 7 mmag minimum level of our variability sensitivity, as there are no offsets observed in the more than 100 stars observed in the V band (Jao et al. 2011). The subscript &quot;J&quot; indicates Johnson, &quot;KC&quot; indicates Kron-Cousins (usually known as Cousins), and are hereafter omitted.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> A possible third component mentioned in those papers has not been confirmed through continued work on the dataset, so the system is a binary, not a triple.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baraffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">357</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Winters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baraffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1039</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Von Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bryden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Davison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dieterich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Finch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2898</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1361</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gomes Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">541</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Goulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pinfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">427</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3358</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">244</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">´ A</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">166</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hawley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">797</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">864</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Beaulieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ianna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mendez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2360</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Beaulieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2460</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Honeycutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">435</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">727</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ianna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bartlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Méndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1954</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kilkenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Van Wyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1949</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Landolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">372</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Landolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2502</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lurie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mamajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bartlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seifahrt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">154</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Montagnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ségransan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Beuzit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Finch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Finch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">897</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Endl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dodson-Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">764</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">413</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hambly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1658</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4547</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Walkowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1135</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weis</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">.. ... ... ... ...</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>34 Bes90 4.71 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">.. ... ... ... ...</orgName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>98 8.95 7.72 Wei96 4.37 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">33 Bes90 5.04 ... ... ... ... ...</orgName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">.. ... ... ... ...</orgName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">436</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>58 8.25 Wei96 4.58 .</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">581</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">667</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">GJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">849</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
