<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:21+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">High-precision multi-band time-series photometry of exoplanets Qatar-1 b and TrES-5 b</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>1⋆</roleName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mislis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Qatar Environment and Energy Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Qatar Foundation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tornado Tower</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Floor 19</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 5825</postBox>
									<settlement>Doha</settlement>
									<country key="QA">Qatar</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mancini</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Königstuhl 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tregloan-Reed</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">NASA Ames Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94035</postCode>
									<settlement>Moffett Field</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ciceri</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Königstuhl 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Astrophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Keele University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ST5 5BG</postCode>
									<settlement>Staffordshire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>D&amp;apos;ago</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Salerno</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Giovanni Paolo II</addrLine>
									<postCode>84084</postCode>
									<settlement>Fisciano</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bruni</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">INAF â ˘ A¸SA¸S Osservatorio Astronomico di Bologna</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Ranzani 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>I-40127</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ö</forename><surname>Ba¸stürkba¸stürk</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dept. of Astronomy and Space Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ankara University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tando˘ gan</addrLine>
									<postCode>TR-06100</postCode>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alsubai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Qatar Environment and Energy Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Qatar Foundation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tornado Tower</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Floor 19</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 5825</postBox>
									<settlement>Doha</settlement>
									<country key="QA">Qatar</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bachelet</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Qatar Environment and Energy Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Qatar Foundation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tornado Tower</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Floor 19</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 5825</postBox>
									<settlement>Doha</settlement>
									<country key="QA">Qatar</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bramich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Qatar Environment and Energy Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Qatar Foundation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tornado Tower</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Floor 19</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 5825</postBox>
									<settlement>Doha</settlement>
									<country key="QA">Qatar</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Th</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Königstuhl 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hinse</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Korea Astronomy and Space Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>776 Daedukdae-ro, Yuseong-gu</addrLine>
									<postCode>305-348</postCode>
									<settlement>Daejeon</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Iannella</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Salerno</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Giovanni Paolo II</addrLine>
									<postCode>84084</postCode>
									<settlement>Fisciano</settlement>
									<region>SA</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Parley</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Qatar Environment and Energy Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Qatar Foundation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tornado Tower</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Floor 19</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 5825</postBox>
									<settlement>Doha</settlement>
									<country key="QA">Qatar</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Königstuhl 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-69117</postCode>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">High-precision multi-band time-series photometry of exoplanets Qatar-1 b and TrES-5 b</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7"/>
							<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Printed 15 September 2018</note>
					<note>(MN L A T E X style file v2.2)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>stars: planetary systems -planets and satellites: fundamental parameters, de- tection -techniques: photometric</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present an analysis of the Qatar-1 and TrES-5 transiting exoplanetary systems, which contain Jupiter-like planets on short-period orbits around K-dwarf stars. Our data comprise a total of 20 transit light curves obtained using five medium-class telescopes, operated using the defocussing technique. The average precision we reach in all our data is RMS Q = 1.1 mmag for Qatar-1 (V = 12.8) and RMS T = 1.0 mmag for TrES-5 (V = 13.7). We use these data to refine the orbital ephemeris, photometric parameters, and measured physical properties of the two systems. One transit event for each object was observed simultaneously in three passbands (gri) using the BUSCA imager. The QES survey light curve of Qatar-1 has a clear sinusoidal variation on a period of P ⋆ = 23.697 ± 0.123 d, implying significant starspot activity. We searched for starspot crossing events in our light curves, but did not find clear evidence in any of the new datasets. The planet in the Qatar-1 system did not transit the active latitudes on the surfaces of its host star. Under the assumption that P ⋆ corresponds to the rotation period of Qatar-1 A, the rotational velocity of this star is very close to the v sin i ⋆ value found from observations of the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect. The low projected orbital obliquity found in this system thus implies a low absolute orbital obliquity, which is also a necessary condition for the transit chord of the planet to avoid active latitudes on the stellar surface.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Ground-based photometric surveys have found a large number of transiting planets, possessing a huge diversity in their physical and orbital properties. The precise characterisation of these objects is a challenge as it requires high-quality data, both photometric and spectroscopic. The main limitation to our understanding of most transiting planets is due to the quality of the transit light curve, which is critical in determining the properties of both the planets and their host stars <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Southworth 2008</ref>. In this work we present follow-up photometry of two transiting ⋆ E-mail: dmislis@qf.org.qa planets orbiting cool stars -Qatar-1 b and TrES-5 b -aimed at improving measurements of their physical properties but also investigating the spot activity of their host stars. Our new data allow a significant improvement in our understanding of both systems, and, in the case of TrES-5, form the basis of the first study of the system since the discovery paper. Qatar-1 b was discovered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Alsubai et al. (2011)</ref>, and was the first planet found by the Qatar Exoplanet Survey (QES), an exoplanet transit survey focused on hot Jupiters and hot Neptunes via the transit method <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Alsubai et al. 2013</ref>). The transiting planet TrES-5 b was discovered shortly afterwards ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Mandushev et al. 2011</ref>) using observations by the TrES survey ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alonso et al. 2004</ref>). The Qatar-1 and TrES-5 systems are notably similar in terms of orbital period (1.4- , and the planetary radius (∼1.2 R Jup ) and equilibrium temperature (1400-1500 K). Qatar-1 has subsequently been studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref>, who found a sky-propjected orbital obliquity consistent with axial alignment, and by von <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Essen et al. (2013)</ref>, who found indications of transit timing variations (TTVs) in this system. No studies of TrES-5 have been published since its discovery paper ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Mandushev et al. 2011</ref>). The possibility to observe occulted starspots during planetarytransit events opens new opportunities in the understanding of stars in general and planetary systems in particular. Those spots which are occulted by the planet manifest themselves as a small increase in flux during transit, which can be modelled to obtain the spot size, position and temperature (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Mancini et al. 2014</ref>). Multiple observations of the same spot during different transits can yield the orbital obliquity of the system ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Nutzman et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Sanchis-Ojeda et al. 2011</ref>) to a significantly higher precision than achievable via the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Tregloan-Reed et al. 2013</ref>). The wavelength dependence of the amplitude of the unocculted starspots can mimic changes in the apparent radius of transiting planets as a function of wavelength ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pont et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Oshagh et al. 2014</ref>). In this work we present high-precision photometric observations of Qatar-1 and TrES-5, and use them to get more accurate measurements of the physical parameters of the systems. Some of our data were obtained in multiple passbands simultaneously, but we find no evidence for spot crossings in these data. We do, however, find strong evidence that the Qatar-1 A is a spotted star from the longterm light curve of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">OBSERVATIONS AND DATA REDUCTION</head><p>Our observations were obtained using five medium-size telescopes equipped with imaging instruments, and operated out of focus (see . A summary of the observations is given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The data were reduced using the DEFOT pipeline from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Southworth et al. ( , 2014</ref>. This pipeline was used to debias and flat-field the data, then perform aperture photometry on the target and all possible comparison stars. The radii of the software apertures (target, inner sky, outer sky) for each dataset were chosen to give the lowest scatter in the final light curve. The final light curve was constructed by calculating differential magnitudes versus a weighted set of comparison stars. The weights were optimised simultaneously with the coefficients of a low-order polynomial of magnitude versus time, in order to rectify the light curve to zero differential magnitude and minimise the scatter of the data obtained outside transit.</p><p>The data were reduced using the method and the DEFOT pipeline from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Southworth et al. ( , 2014</ref>.</p><p>A total of 11 transits were observed using the 1.23 m telescope at Centro Astronómico Hispano-Alemán (CAHA). This uses a 2048 × 2048 pixel CCD camera with a plate scale of 0.32 ′′ px −1 and has a 21.5 ′ × 21.5 ′ field of view with the default BVRI filters. Ten of the transits were obtained through a Cousins R filter and the last through a Cousins I filter. The first three transits were already presented in the study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref> but were re-reduced for the current work.</p><p>One transit each of Qatar-1 and TrES-5 was observed using the CAHA 2.2 m telescope equipped with the BUSCA instrument. This obtains CCD images of a 5.8 ′ diameter field of view simultaneously in four optical passbands, split by dichroic elements. Each of the four CCDs has 4096 × 4096 pixels and is operated using 2×2 binning. For both transits we obtained useful data in the ThuanGunn g, r and i passbands. The data taken through the Strömgren u filter were discarded due to high scatter: both objects are comparatively faint (V = 12.8 for Qatar-1 and V = 13.7 for TrES-5) and cool so have very low flux levels in this passband.</p><p>One transit of Qatar-1 was monitored with the 1.0 m telescope (T100) at TÜB ˙ ITAK National Observatory (TUG) in Turkey, equipped with a 4096 × 4096 pixel CCD with a field of view of 21.5 ′ × 21.5 ′ . The transit was observed through a Cousins R filter. One transit of TrES-5 was obtained using the 2.5 m Isaac Newton Telescope (INT) at La Palma, Spain, and the Wide Field Camera (WFC). This is a mosaic of four CCDs of which we used only CCD4, to avoid possible systematic errors and calibration issues resulting from the use of multiple CCDs in the mosaic. This CCD has 2048 × 4096 pixels, giving a field of view of 11.3 ′ × 22.5 ′ , and a Cousins I filter was selected.</p><p>Finally, a transit of TrES-5 was observed using the Cassini 1.52 m telescope at Bologna Astronomical Observatory, Loiano, Italy. The BFOSC instrument was used in imaging mode, with a Thuan-Gunn r filter. The 1024 × 1024 pixels CCD provided a field of view of 13 ′ × 12.6 ′ at 0.58 ′′ per pixel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">TRANSIT ANALYSIS</head><p>Each transit light curve was modelled with the JKTEBOP code to extract measurements of its photometric parameters. The object size parameters in JKTEBOP are the fractional radii of the star and the planet (r A and r b ), which are the ratios between the true radii and the semimajor axis (r A,b = R A,b a</p><p>). The fitted parameters were the sum of the fractional radii (r A + r b ), the ratio of the radii</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(k = r b r A = R b R A</formula><p>), the orbital inclination (i), and a reference time of mid-transit. We assumed an orbital eccentricity of zero for both objects based on previous studies ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Mandushev et al. 2011</ref>).</p><p>Limb darkening was applied using the quadratic law, with coeffi-  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Qatar-1</head><p>For Qatar-1, we collected 12 light curves in total (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). We fit each of the datasets individually, obtaining the parameter values given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>. The parameter values in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> were combined into weighted means for the determination of the physical properties of the system (see below). We then fitted the T 0 values with a straight line versus cycle number to determine the orbital ephemeris. The uncertainties were obtained using 1000 Monte Carlo simulations. The resulting ephemeris is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">T 0 = 2455799.57954(4) + 1.42002586(275) · E<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where T 0 is the transit mid-time, E is the cycle number and the bracketed quantities give the uncertainty in the final digit of the preceding number. All times in our analysis were converted to Barycentric Julian Day (BJD/TDB). We supplemented our T 0 values with data from the literature and searched for TTVs. We included timings from the ETD amateur database 1 with quality higher than 3. We fit a linear function to T 0 and then removed the linear trend. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>   <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2013)</ref> found evidence for TTVs in Qatar-1 but we need further and more precise data in order to analyse this scenario in detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Multi-band photometry of Qatar-1</head><p>The BUSCA light curves were obtained simultaneously in three filters using the same telescope and instrument, so are useful for investigating the possible presence of starspots. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> shows the three light curves overplotted. Whilst there are suggestions of starspots in the g and r data, these are close to the level of the noise so their existence is not proven. This transit was also monitored using the CAHA 1.23 m telescope (first dataset in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>), and these data do not confirm the presence of any starspots.</p><p>Whilst we have no clear detection of starspots via occultation during transit, spots are a common phenomenon on the surfaces of K-type dwarfs. They can cause brightness modulation at the rotational period (and/or its submultiples) of the star. We used the discovery light curves from QES ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Alsubai et al. 2011</ref>), which span 380 days, to search for stellar variability. A Lomb-Scargle periodogram of the data shows a clear detection of sinusoidal modulation at a period of P ⋆ = 23.697 ± 0.123 d <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 4)</ref>, which we take to be the rotational period of the star. The implied stellar rotation velocity of v = 1.76 km s −1 is fully consistent with the value of v sin i ⋆ = 1.7 ± 0.3 km s −1 found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref> from the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect. This in turn indicates that the inclination of the stellar rotation axis, i ⋆ , is close to 90 • , so the true orbital obliquity of the system is close to the measured value of the projected orbital obliquity found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">TrES-5b</head><p>The analysis of our eight light curves of TrES-5 followed the same steps as for Qatar-1 above. The best-fitting photometric parameters are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 3</ref> and the best fits are plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>. The parameter values in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 3</ref> were combined into weighted means for the determination of the physical properties of the system (see  Date</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">r A + r b k r A r b Inclination ( • ) T 0 (BJD/TDB)</formula><p>below). The resulting orbital ephemeris is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">T 0 = 2456458.59219(9) + 1.48224686(614) · E<label>(2)</label></formula><p>As with Qatar-1, we added T 0 measurements from the ETD database (again using only those with qualities higher than 3) and formed the O − C diagram <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">(Fig. 6)</ref>. The best-fitting ephemeris has χ 2 red = 7.15, which a factor of ten lower than that for Qatar-1. This χ 2 red indicates either that the linear ephemeris is a poor representation of the data or that the errorbars of many of the T 0 values are underestimated. As with Qatar-1, further data are needed to investigate this situation and to provide clear evidence (or otherwise) of the presence of TTVs in this system.</p><p>The multi-band data from BUSCA are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7</ref>, and contain no clear evidence of starspot occultations. The data during totality (between 2nd and 3rd contact) are rather noisy so are not good indicators of the presence of starspots. This is at least partly    <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. Spectroscopic properties of the host stars in the Qatar-1 and TrES-5 systems adopted from the literature. References: (1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(2)</ref>  due to the relative faintness of TrES-5 (V = 13.7), at least for a 2-m class telescope equipped with an instrument containing many optical elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">PHYSICAL PROPERTIES</head><p>We determined the physical properties of the two systems from the light curve fits (the weighted means in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Tables 2 and 3</ref>), from the spectroscopic measurements of host star's atmospheric properties, and from the tabulated predictions of five different sets of theoretical stellar evolutionary models. The values of r A , r b and i in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Tables  2 and 3</ref> were combined according to their weighted mean, inflating the resulting errorbars to enforce χ 2 ν = 1.0 for each quantity. The spectroscopic measurements of the stellar effective temperature (T eff ), metallicity Fe H and orbital velocity amplitude (K A ) were taken from published studies and are summarised in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. Tabulated predictions were obtained from the Claret (2004a), Y 2 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Demarque et al. 2004</ref>), Teramo ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Pietrinferni et al. 2004</ref>), VRSS ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">VandenBerg et al. 2006</ref>) and DSEP ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Dotter et al. 2008</ref>) stellar models.</p><p>For each target we began by estimating a value for the velocity amplitude of the planet, K b , allowing us to calculate a set of physical properties for the system using standard formulae. The value of K b was then iteratively refined to maximise the agreement between the observed and predicted T eff , and the measured r A and predicted R A a . Finally, the full procedure was undertaken using each of the five sets of stellar model predictions. For both objects we assumed a circular orbit, based on the conclusions of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. (2013)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Mandushev et al. (2011)</ref>. We used the set of physical constants given by Southworth (2011).</p><p>The uncertainties on the input parameters were propagated through the analysis using a perturbation approach, and added in quadrature to give the final random error. A systematic errorbar was also estimated based on the interagreement between the results obtained using each of the five different model sets. <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 5</ref> gives our final physical properties, random errorbars for all quantities, and systematic errorbars for those results which depend on stellar theory.</p><p>Also, only for Qatar-1A, we were able to calculate the stellar rotation period. Thus, we can use gyrochronology model to estimate stellar the age of Qatar-1b host star. Using the model from <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barnes (2007)</ref> and stellar rotation period 23.697 days and B-V=1.06, we estimate the age of Qatar-1A τ g = 1.1865 ± 0.47 Gyr.</p><p>Our final results for Qatar-1 are in good agreement with published studies ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Alsubai et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Covino et al. 2013</ref>), and yield a significant improvement in precision. In the case of TrES-5 we agree with the findings of Mandushev et al. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2011)</ref>   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">RESULTS AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We present extensive optical photometry of transit events in two extrasolar planetary systems with K-dwarf host stars. Our data comprise 12 light curves of Qatar-1 and eight light curves of TrES-5. These data include simultaneous observations in three passbands of one transit for each object. We use thse data to search for starspot crossing events during transit, with a negative result. We do, however, measure the rotational period of P ⋆ = 23.697 ± 0.123 d for Qatar-1 A from the survey photometry in its discovery paper, showing that this does display spot activity. The corresponding rotational velocity is close to the v sin i ⋆ value measured from an observation of the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect in this system, so its low projected orbital obliquity also implies a low true orbital obliquity. The lack of observed spot crossings may be due to the planets crossing latitudes of the stars which show low spot activity, i.e. the planetary chords miss the active latitudes of the stellar surfaces. We use our data to measure the photometric parameters of both systems. When combined with published spectroscopic quantities, these yield precise measurements of the full physical properties of the systems. Qatar-1 and TrES-5 have notable similarities in their respective stellar properties, and planetary equilibrium temperature, radius and density. Our results also yield refined measurements of the orbital ephemerides of the systems. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Left: our light curves of Qatar-1 (blue points) with the JKTEBOP best fits (red lines) overplotted. The telescope and filter used for each dataset are labelled. Right: the residuals of each fit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. O − C diagram for the transit times of Qatar-1. Our own data are shown using blue dots, 26 data points from von Essen et al. (2013) (green dots), and the 69 additional light curves from ETD database (red dots).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>shows the re- sults (O − C diagram) overplotted with the best linear fit. The χ 2 red value is 31.4, which is very high. This implies that the O − C data cannot be explained by a simple linear fit, but still the amplitude of our O-C residuals are smaller (RMS O−C = 1.50 minutes) than von Essen et al. (2013) (RMS O−C = 1.67 minutes), Covino et al. (2013) (RMS O−C = 2.45 minutes) or ETD (RMS O−C = 3.85 min- utes). von Essen et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. The BUSCA light curves of Qatar-1. Green, red and black points show the g, r and i data, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Left: our light curves of TrES-5 (blue points) with the JKTEBOP best fits (red lines) overplotted. The telescope and filter used for each dataset are labelled. Right: the residuals of each fit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Long-term light curve of Qatar-1 from QES, phase-folded on a period of 23.697 d. The best fit is shown by a red line.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. O − C diagram for the transit times of TrES-5. Our own data are shown using blue dots and the eight additional light curves from ETD database are shown with red dots.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. The BUSCA light curves of TrES-5. Green, red and black points show the g, r and i data, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>but do not ob- tain significantly smaller errorbars. This is because we account for systematic errors whereas Mandushev et al. (2011) do not, and also because the errors estimated by Mandushev et al. (2011) ap- pear to be too small (for example they claim that the orbital in-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Summary of observations of Qatar-1 and TrES-5.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Telescope 
Date 
Start (UT) End (UT) Frames (No) 
Exp (sec) 
Filter 
Airmass 
Moon (%) 
Apertures (px) 
RMS (10 −4 ) 

Qatar-1: 
CAHA 1.23m 
2011.08.25 
23:55 
03:36 
158 
60 
Cousins R 1.20→1.76 
12.8 
9,25,35 
12.6 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.25 
23:46 
04:39 
115 
60 
Gunn g 1.19→2.20 
12.8 
16.5,64.9,78.3 
10.5 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.25 
23:46 
04:39 
117 
60 
Gunn r 1.19→2.20 
12.8 
17,36.1,70 
7.4 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.25 
23:46 
04:39 
118 
60 
Gunn i 1.19→2.20 
12.8 
13.2,38.9,61.9 
9.6 
CAHA 1.23m 
2012.07.21 
20:32 
00:34 
112 
120 
Cousins R 1.33→1.13 
8.0 
7.9,31.9,45 
7.1 
CAHA 1.23m 
2012.09.11 
00:27 
03:48 
78 
120 
Cousins R 1.36→2.20 
27.1 
19.9,38.9,53 
7.5 
CAHA 1.23m 
2013.06.14 
20:48 
00:30 
95 
120 
Cousins R 1.73→1.19 
19.3 
12.2,41,50.2 
8.8 
CAHA 1.23m 
2013.07.28 
20:17 
01:05 
156 
120 
Cousins R 1.31→1.16 
59.1 
25.8,39,61 
7.3 
CAHA 1.23m 
2014.04.19 
01:40 
04:38 
109 
160 
Cousins R 1.61→1.17 
80.1 
19,29,50 
25.6 
CAHA 1.23m 
2014.06.04 
20:42 
02:57 
138 
150 
Cousins R 1.97→1.13 
12.9 
20,30,50 
7.7 
TUG100 
2014.06.04 
21:39 
01:42 
98 
120 
Cousins R 1.69→1.16 
12.9 
20,30,35 
14.0 
CAHA 1.23m 
2014.09.07 
23:57 
04:37 
135 
96-135 
Cousins R 1.25→2.32 
98.2 
22,40,60 
11.8 

TrES-5: 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.26 
20:55 
00:55 
95 
60 
Gunn-g 
1.02→1.57 
7.0 
10.2,45.4,56.5 
12.3 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.26 
20:55 
00:55 
88 
60 
Gunn-r 
1.02→1.57 
7.0 
17.3,42.1, 55.6 
8.5 
CAHA 2.2m 
2011.08.26 
20:55 
00:55 
91 
60 
Gunn-i 1.02→1.57 
7.0 
10,28,39.1 
12.1 
CAHA 1.23m 
2012.09.10 
19:21 
23:36 
77 
170 
Cousins R 1.11→1.21 
29.0 
16,40.1,54.8 
8.5 
CAHA 1.23m 
2013.06.15 
00:42 
03:50 
65 
125 
Cousins R 1.14→1.11 
44.9 
12,38,55.3 
9.0 
CAHA 1.23m 
2013.07.30 
23:10 
04:03 
128 
120 
Cousins I 1.08→1.47 
38.2 
13.7,27.8,46 
11.3 
Cassini 1.52m 2013.09.14 
21:19 
02:59 
139 
180 
Gunn r 1.08→2.09 
78.2 
9.8,22.6,38.7 
13.0 
INT 2.5m 
2013.09.14 
21:04 
22:22 
37 
120 
Cousins I 1.05→1.17 
72.4 
18,28,50 
4.1 

1.5 d), host star effective temperature (4800-5200 K) and metallic-
ity ( 


Fe 
H 


= 0.20)</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . Fitted parameter values for each light curve of Qatar-1. Date r A + r b k r A r b Inclination ( • ) T 0 (BJD/TDB)</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>2011.08.25 
0.178 ± 0.011 
0.1455 ± 0.0039 
0.155 ± 0.009 
0.0226 ± 0.0018 
84.64 ± 0.84 
55799.5759 ± 0.0002 
2011.08.25 
0.179 ± 0.009 
0.1469 ± 0.0039 
0.156 ± 0.007 
0.0229 ± 0.0016 
84.62 ± 0.66 
55799.5755 ± 0.0001 
2011.08.25 
0.184 ± 0.009 
0.1467 ± 0.0041 
0.160 ± 0.007 
0.0235 ± 0.0016 
84.02 ± 0.73 
55799.5758 ± 0.0002 
2011.08.25 
0.172 ± 0.011 
0.1428 ± 0.0031 
0.150 ± 0.009 
0.0215 ± 0.0018 
85.18 ± 0.89 
55799.5756 ± 0.0001 
2012.07.21 
0.185 ± 0.004 
0.1500 ± 0.0022 
0.161 ± 0.004 
0.0241 ± 0.0008 
83.95 ± 0.32 
56130.4430 ± 0.0001 
2012.09.11 
0.178 ± 0.007 
0.1461 ± 0.0028 
0.155 ± 0.006 
0.0226 ± 0.0010 
84.50 ± 0.52 
56181.5668 ± 0.0001 
2013.06.14 
0.197 ± 0.006 
0.1524 ± 0.0024 
0.171 ± 0.004 
0.0260 ± 0.0010 
83.33 ± 0.34 
56458.4665 ± 0.0002 
2013.07.28 
0.183 ± 0.006 
0.1480 ± 0.0020 
0.159 ± 0.004 
0.0235 ± 0.0010 
84.10 ± 0.42 
56502.4905 ± 0.0002 
2014.04.19 
0.176 ± 0.018 
0.1471 ± 0.0083 
0.153 ± 0.015 
0.0226 ± 0.0030 
84.91 ± 1.50 
56766.6120 ± 0.0004 
2014.06.04 
0.181 ± 0.009 
0.1458 ± 0.0028 
0.158 ± 0.007 
0.0231 ± 0.0014 
84.41 ± 0.66 
56813.4731 ± 0.0002 
2014.06.04 
0.182 ± 0.020 
0.1446 ± 0.0076 
0.159 ± 0.016 
0.0230 ± 0.0032 
84.10 ± 1.50 
56813.4720 ± 0.0003 
2014.09.07 
0.173 ± 0.011 
0.1427 ± 0.0035 
0.151 ± 0.009 
0.0216 ± 0.0018 
83.86 ± 0.80 
56908.6149 ± 0.0002 

Weighted mean 
0.184 ± 0.002 
0.1475 ± 0.0009 
0.160 ± 0.002 
0.0236 ± 0.0004 
84.03 ± 0.16 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fitted parameter values for each light curve of TrES-5.</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Mandushev et al. (2011).</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Source 
Qatar-1 
Ref 
TrES-5 
Ref 

T eff (K) 
4910 ± 100 
1 
5171 ± 36 
2 


Fe 
H 


(dex) 
0.20 ± 0.10 
1 
0.20 ± 0.10 
2 
K A ( m s −1 ) 
265.7 ± 3.5 
1 
339.8 ± 10.4 
2 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 5 . Derived physical properties of the two systems. Where two sets of errorbars are given, the first is the statistical uncertainty and the second is the systematic uncertainty.</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Quantity 
Symbol Unit 
Qatar-1 
TrES-5 

Stellar mass 
M A 
M ⊙ 
0.818 ± 0.047 ± 0.050 
0.901 ± 0.029 ± 0.008 
Stellar radius 
R A 
R ⊙ 
0.796 ± 0.016 ± 0.017 
0.868 ± 0.013 ± 0.002 
Stellar surface gravity 
log g A 
c.g.s. 
4.549 ± 0.011 ± 0.009 
4.517 ± 0.012 ± 0.001 
Stellar density 
ρ A 
ρ ⊙ 
1.621 ± 0.046 
1.381 ± 0.051 

Planet mass 
M b 
M Jup 
1.293 ± 0.052 ± 0.054 
1.790 ± 0.067 ± 0.010 
Planet radius 
R b 
R Jup 
1.142 ± 0.026 ± 0.024 
1.194 ± 0.015 ± 0.003 
Planet surface gravity 
g b 
m s −2 
24.56 ± 0.70 
31.1 ± 1.0 
Planet density 
ρ b 
ρ Jup 
0.811 ± 0.036 ± 0.017 
0.983 ± 0.039 ± 0.003 
Equilibrium temperature 
T ′ 

eq 

K 
1388 ± 29 
1480 ± 13 
Safronov number 
Θ 
0.0640 ± 0.0017 ± 0.0014 
0.0817 ± 0.0028 ± 0.002 
Orbital semimajor axis 
a 
au 
0.02313 ± 0.00044 ± 0.00048 
0.02459 ± 0.00026 ± 0.0007 
Age (gyrochronology) 
τ g 
Gyr 
1.19 ± 0.47 

clination is i = 84.529 ± 0.005 degrees, a level of precision not 
normally achieved even with Kepler or Hubble Space Telescope 
light curves). Our results are therefore to be preferred to those of 
Mandushev et al. (2011) because they are based on a larger and 
more precise dataset, and because our errorbars have been more 
robustly calculated. 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This publication is supported by NPRP grant ♯ X-019-1-006 from the Qatar National Research Fund (a member of Qatar Foundation). The statements made herein are solely the responsibility of the authors. Based on observations obtained with the 1.52-m Cassini telescope at the OAB Observatory in Loiano (Italy), and with the 1.23-m and 2.2m telescopes at the Centro Astronòmico Hispano Alemàn (CAHA) at Calar Alto (Spain), jointly operated by the Max-Planck Institut for Astronomy and the Instituto de Astrofìsica de Andalucìa (CSIC). We thank to TÜB ˙ ITAK for the partial support in using T100 telescope with project number 12CT100-378. OB acknowledges the support by the research fund of Ankara University (BAP) through the project 13B4240006.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>References Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">613</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alonso</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">487</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alsubai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">709</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alsubai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AcA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">465</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">669</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Claret</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">424</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">919</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Claret</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Covino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">554</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Demarque</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">667</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mancini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">443</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2391</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mandushev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">741</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mislis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">510</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nutzman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fortney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">740</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oshagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">568</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pietrinferni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">612</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">168</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2917</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanchis-Ojeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">733</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">386</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1644</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">272</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1689</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2166</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">776</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tregloan-Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Southworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tappert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">428</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3671</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vandenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bergbusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dowler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Von Essen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schröter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H M M</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">555</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
