<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:11+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">IMPROVED VARIABLE STAR SEARCH IN LARGE PHOTOMETRIC DATA SETS - NEW VARIABLES IN CoRoT FIELD LRa02 DETECTED BY BEST II</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-05-10">10 May 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fruth</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chini</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sz</forename><surname>Csizmadia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eigmüller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kirste</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lemke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pasternacki</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Titz-Weider</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">IMPROVED VARIABLE STAR SEARCH IN LARGE PHOTOMETRIC DATA SETS - NEW VARIABLES IN CoRoT FIELD LRa02 DETECTED BY BEST II</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-05-10">10 May 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Subject headings: binaries: eclipsing -methods: data analysis -stars: variables: general Online-only material: color figures</term>
					<term>figure set</term>
					<term>machine-readable and VO tables</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The CoRoT field LRa02 has been observed with the Berlin Exoplanet Search Telescope II (BEST II) during the southern summer 2007/2008. A first analysis of stellar variability led to the publication of 345 newly discovered variable stars. Now, a deeper analysis of this data set was used to optimize the variability search procedure. Several methods and parameters have been tested in order to improve the selection process compared to the widely used J index for variability ranking. This paper describes an empirical approach to treat systematic trends in photometric data based upon the analysis of variance statistics that can significantly decrease the rate of false detections. Finally, the process of reanalysis and method improvement has virtually doubled the number of variable stars compared to the first analysis by Kabath et al. A supplementary catalog of 272 previously unknown periodic variables plus 52 stars with suspected variability is presented. Improved ephemerides are given for 19 known variables in the field. In addition, the BEST II results are compared with CoRoT data and its automatic variability classification.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>During the last decade, ground-and spacebased surveys have been very successful in detecting transiting exoplanets. In addition to their primary science goal, the large photometric data sets acquired by them allow studying millions of stars for variability. Numerous projects thus provide an exceedingly increasing number of detec-  <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Samus et al. 2009</ref>) or the Variable Star Index 1 (VSX). Such catalogs not only broaden the statistical sample of variable stars, but are also important to gain further knowledge about the different processes that cause stellar variability.</p><p>Several methods have been proposed to search for periodic signals in astronomical time series (for a good overview, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1999)</ref>. One of the most widely applied algorithms is the analysis of variance (AoV) statistic ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1996)</ref>, which provides an optimal period search in uneven sampled observations. It has been used very successfully by projects like HAT ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bakos et al. 2004</ref>), WASP (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Maciejewski et al. 2011</ref>), or OGLE (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Soszynski et al. 2008</ref>). In addition, the J index <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Stetson 1996</ref>) is frequently used to quantify variability in general and/or for selecting candidate stars prior to a period search in order to minimize computation time (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Zhang et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pepper &amp; Burke 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Pasternacki et al. 2011</ref>).</p><p>However, both methods -the AoV period search and Stetson's variability index -are strongly affected by systematic trends present in ground-based data sets (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Pepper &amp; Burke 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Karoff et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kabath et al. 2009a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hartman et al. 2011</ref>). Most dominant are diurnal systematics, introducing artificial variability with periods of one day or multiples thereof. Such trends generally yield a higher ranking of nonvariable stars, thus increasing the false alarm rate. A common approach to account for candidates with systematic variability is to set limits, e.g., to exclude detections within certain period ranges. However, any such manual mechanism is usually not well applicable to other data sets or projects, and the number of missed detections (false negatives) is often unknown. Therefore, a more sophisticated treatment of systematic variability in combination with period search and ranking is needed.</p><p>The Berlin Exoplanet Search Telescope (BEST; <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Rauer et al. 2004</ref>) and BEST II ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rauer et al. 2010</ref>) are used to perform ground-based support of the CoRoT space mission ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baglin et al. 2006</ref>). By obtaining high-precision and long-time series photometry of the CoRoT target fields prior to the satellite's observations, planetary candidates can quickly be checked in the BEST data archive (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Deeg et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rauer et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alonso et al. 2012</ref>). In addition, the obtained light curves can be used to identify variable stars. The BEST project has already yielded the detection of several hundreds of new periodic variable stars ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Karoff et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kabath et al. 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kabath et al. , 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kabath et al. , 2009b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Pasternacki et al. 2011)</ref>.</p><p>A first characterization of periodic stellar variability in the CoRoT field LRa02 has been published by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kabath et al. (2009a)</ref>. Following the detections from this first publication (denoted as Paper I hereafter), it was possible to optimize the BEST II reduction pipeline. The large, wellcharacterized data set LRa02 was used as a proxy to analyze and automatically include systematic biases in the variable star candidate selection and period search, yielding a significantly reduced false alarm rate.</p><p>The optimized procedure to rank periodic variable stars is described in this paper. In addition, we present a large catalog extension to the variable star classification in LRa02 that was obtained through the reanalysis and compare our results to publicly available CoRoT data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">TELESCOPE AND OBSERVATIONS</head><p>BEST II is located at the Observatorio Cerro Armazones, Chile. It is operated by the Institut für Planetenforschung of the Deutsches Zentrum für Luft-und Raumfahrt in robotic mode from Berlin since summer 2007.</p><p>The system consists of a 25 cm Baker-RitcheyChrétien telescope with a focal ratio of f /5.0, yielding a wide field of view (FOV) of 1 • .7 × 1 • .7. It is equipped with a 4k × 4k, 16 bit Finger Lakes Imager CCD (KAF-16801E1) with a pixel size of 9 µm, and an angular resolution of 1 ′′ . 5 pixel −1 . BEST II observes without any filter to maximize the photon yield -the CCD sensitivity peaks at 650 nm and is roughly comparable to the Johnson R band.</p><p>The CoRoT long-run field LRa02 was observed by BEST II for 41 nights from 2007 November to 2008 February prior to the satellite observations. As the FOV of CoRoT is slightly larger than BEST II, we split the field into two subfields (called LRa02a and LRa02b, respectively) and pointed at them alternating. Paper I indicates their corresponding center coordinates and shows the orientation with respect to the CoRoT FOV ( <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> in Paper I).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">DATA SET AND VARIABILITY CRI-TERIA</head><p>The acquired data set was calibrated and reduced using the BEST automated photometric data pipeline as outlined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rauer et al. (2010)</ref>. The actual reduction procedure for the field LRa02 has already been described in detail in Paper I and below only those steps relevant to the new results are discussed.</p><p>In Paper I, Kabath et al. reported the detection of 350 periodic variable stars (of which five were previously known). Their selection was based upon the variability index J (Stetson 1996), calculated for each star by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">J = n−1 k=1 w k sgn(P k ) |P k | n−1 k=1 w k ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where k is indexing individual data points. P k is calculated from each pair of subsequent magnitudes m k and m k+1 using the corresponding normalized residuals δ k and δ k+1 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">P k = δ k δ k+1 with δ k = n n − 1 m k − m σ k ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where σ k denotes the uncertainty of measurement k, m the mean magnitude, and n the number of measurements for the selected star. The weights w k in Equation (1) were calculated following the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Zhang et al. (2003)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">w k = exp − t k+1 − t k ∆t ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where t k is the time of observation k and ∆t is the median of all pair time spans (t k+1 − t k ). In Paper I, the limit of J ≥ 0.5 was applied in order to distinguish variable from constant field stars. This preselection yielded 1,858 stars in LRa02a and 1,868 stars in LRa02b, respectively. For each star, the AoV statistic Θ (Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1996) was calculated for a period range of 0.1-35 days. The light curves were folded with the frequency ω max corresponding to the maximum AoV value,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Θ(ω max ) = max (Θ(ω)) ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and then inspected visually. Most folded light curves showed no clear periodic variability or an artificial period of one day or multiples thereof, which can be caused by systematic effects due to the observational cycle. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kabath et al. (2009a)</ref> finally identified 173 periodic variables in LRa02a and 177 in LRa02b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">REANALYSIS</head><p>In the BEST archive, some stars are marked as clear variables with large J indices (up to 10 and higher). <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows the count of all stars in subfield LRa02b and the corresponding number of variable star detections in Paper I as a function of the J index. Altogether, the large number of false positives shows that the J index alone is not an effective criterion for selecting variable stars. Furthermore, a number of clear detections with low J values indicates that several variables must have been missed in Paper I due to the cutoff.</p><p>In order to improve the quality of our preselection process and to maximize the detection yield, we performed a deeper analysis of our data set LRa02. Field LRa02 was chosen for this purpose because it was observed with longest duration within the BEST project so far.</p><p>The performed reanalysis consisted of three main steps.</p><p>First, the best period was searched in all light curves from the initial data set without any preselection criterion, i.e., directly using the AoV multiharmonic algorithm for all stars in both subsets. Each of the resulting 37,361 folded light curves in LRa02a and 66,974 in LRa02b was then examined visually for periodic stellar variability. In addition to the variable stars from Paper I, this first step already revealed 189 additional variable stars that were not detected in our first publication. During this step, we also discovered a bug in our implementation of the J index that yielded systematically lower values especially for short periods, which is why many of these detections show periods of less than a day.</p><p>Second, the combined data set of variable stars from Paper I and the additional manual detections were used to optimize the BEST II selection process (see next Section 5). With a very good knowledge of this data set, it was possible to compare different selection methods and to adjust their corresponding parameters.</p><p>Third, the new search algorithm was applied to the data set with optimized parameters. The improvements to the pipeline finally lead to an increase of detections by another 135 variable stars that were not found during all previous steps (see Section 6.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">IMPROVEMENTS ON VARIABIL-ITY SEARCH</head><p>The deep analysis of the BEST II data set LRa02 gives us the opportunity to study the performance of variability search algorithms in detail. The aim is to recover all variable stars in the data set automatically and to minimize the number of false alarms (and manpower) at the same time.</p><p>In this section, we show the limitations of the J index with regard to systematic trends (Section 5.1), describe how to quantify the performance of a variability search (Section 5.2), present the algorithms tested (Sections 5.3 and 5.4), and finally compare the performance of different approaches and parameters (Section 5.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Limitations of the Variability Index J</head><p>After the first step of the reanalysis, the visual inspection, the majority of new detections showed J indices below the limit of 0.5 applied before, which is why they were not detected in Paper I. The relation between periods and variability is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. A clear bulk of stars can be found at about 0.01 ≤ J ≤ 0.1, with the limits being widely period independent and populated by stars showing noise only. Most new variable star detections are found in the region between J = 0.1 and the cutoff limit of J = 0.5 from Paper I. A small number of new variables with J &gt; 0.5 were not detected in Paper I because their J indices have been initially underestimated (see Section 4).</p><p>The dominant variation in many light curves is due to diurnal systematics, aliasing, or a combi- <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>.-J index histogram for subfield LRa02b (qualitatively equal to LRa02a). The solid line shows the total star count in bins of 0.1 (J &lt; 2) and 1 (J ≥ 2), whereas the dotted line shows the number of variable star detections from Paper I. The red dashed line denotes the cutoff limit of J = 0.5 as applied in Paper I. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-Variability J index plotted vs. determined period without treatment of systematic effects for all stars in the BEST II field LRa02a (top) and <ref type="bibr">LRa02b (bottom)</ref>. Variable stars identified in Paper I are marked with blue dots, whereas variable stars from the manual reanalysis appear red. The dashed line shows the selection limit of J = 0.5 as applied in Paper I. nation of both. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows a large accumulation of stars having periods of one day or integral fractions/multiples thereof, often in combination with large J indices. Consequently, this leads to a very high number of false alarms when using the Stetson index as the only criterion for variability selection. In the example of the data set LRa02, a cutoff limit of J = 0.1 would be sufficient to include all variable stars in the selection sample, but only 74% of all light curves would be sorted out. The remaining large sample of 31,000 stars is mainly affected by systematic effects and contains only 681 stars with real physical variability (see Section 6). The corresponding false alarm rate of about 98% shows the need for an automated treatment of systematic variability, which is not part of the J index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Quantitative Assessment of Period Search Algorithms</head><p>Two fundamental criteria are used to assess the quality of period search algorithms: the significance of the detection itself and the correct determination of the frequency of variability.</p><p>First, a quantity ξ is introduced to evaluate the detection efficiency of any given search algorithm. Detection methods are usually based upon a single numerical value q (e.g., the Stetson index, q ≡ J) that can be used to prioritize a candidate list. frequencies. The set Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ) of non-systematic frequencies is obtained by excluding the subsets Ω sys 1 (master power spectrum cut) and Ω sys 2 (empty phases). The size of both can be adjusted with the parameters n 1 and n 2 . Maxima of Θ(ω) and δΘ(ω) are searched within Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ) to obtain the frequencies ω viously identified variable stars listed first) to 1 (listed last). For details on the calculation of ξ see the Appendix.</p><p>The second criterion is tested by comparing the frequency ω correct that was verified manually with the frequency of a tested algorithm. We consider a tolerance range of 2% around ω correct for a correct determination. Also included are 2% deviation around half or twice that value, because the distinction between these is often ambiguous from the light curve itself. The fraction n ω of correctly identified frequencies can then be used for a quantitative comparison between tested algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Frequency Determination and Exclusion of Systematics</head><p>Because systematics and their aliases are usually limited to a set of few well-defined frequencies {ω sys }, they can be excluded by searching the best frequency ω max only on a subset Ω * = {ω * } = {ω}\{ω sys } <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 3)</ref>. We tested three different methods to account for systematic frequencies, both independent of each other as well as in combination.</p><p>1. Master power spectrum. Systematic periodic signals affect many light curves in a data set and can thus be distinguished from real stellar variability by analyzing many power spectra Θ i (ω) of individual stars i statistically. We use the mean of all N * spectra to build a master spectrum</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Θ M (ω) = 1 N * i=1...N * Θ i (ω).<label>(5)</label></formula><p>In order to identify significant peaks in the master spectrum, a baseline fit is determined. Among several investigated functions, a polynomial loglog fit,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ln(Θ base M (ω)) = 4 i=0 c i · (ln ω) i ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>with coefficients c i maps the baseline best and most reliable for various tested data sets. The baseline-subtracted spectrum can then be searched for systematics. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> shows how Θ M − Θ base M peaks clearly at the diurnal frequencies that we aim to identify. Finally, a simple cutoff using the standard deviation σ base</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">M of the subtracted spec- trum Θ M − Θ base M</formula><p>is applied to filter systematics automatically. The corresponding set of frequencies having peaks at least n 1 · σ base M above the average power spectrum is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Ω sys 1 (n 1 ) = {ω | Θ M (ω) &gt; Θ base M (ω) + n 1 · σ base M },<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where the parameter n 1 can be adjusted to quantify the degree of exclusion.</p><p>2. Frequencies with empty phases. Groundbased observations are strongly affected by periodic gaps in the data, most commonly due to the diurnal cycle. The incomplete phase coverage leads to aliasing and can often cause false positive detections. We use a simple model to exclude frequencies with poor phase coverage: first, the folded light curve is split into N boxes = 100 intervals of the same length. The number of empty intervals N empty boxes (ω) is then counted for each sampled frequency. A frequency is considered systematic by this criterion if the fraction of empty intervals is larger than a relative threshold parameter n 2 , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Ω sys 2 (n 2 ) = {ω | N empty boxes (ω) &gt; n 2 · N boxes }. (8)</formula><p>Both criteria 7 and 8 are merged to exclude systematic frequencies determined in either way, i.e., the overall set of non-systematic frequencies ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 3</ref>) is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ) = {ω} \ (Ω sys 1 (n 1 ) ∩ Ω sys 2 (n 2 )) (9)</formula><p>and the search for ω max is restricted from the whole frequency range (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(4)</ref>) to the subset Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">∀ω ∈ Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ) : Θ(ω) ≤ Θ(ω (1) max ).<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Note that the function N empty boxes (ω) is similar but not equivalent to the window function γ N (ω) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Deeming 1975)</ref>. Limiting the latter was tested as an alternative criterion; it shows a very similar ranking performance, but slightly less correctly determined frequencies. Being more simple, the empty phase criterion was chosen for the final test setup.</p><p>3. Power spectrum scaling. In addition to the exclusion of systematic frequencies, we also investigated a method to include the information about systematics into the AoV results directly. Instead of searching for the maximum of Θ(ω), an artificial spectrum</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">δΘ(ω) = Θ(ω)/Θ M (ω) (11)</formula><p>is created by dividing the AoV spectrum Θ of every star by the master power spectrum Θ M . Its maximum is found at the frequency ω</p><p>max in analogy to Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(10)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">∀ω ∈ Ω * (n 1 , n 2 ) : δΘ(ω) ≤ δΘ(ω (2) max ) .<label>(12)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Variable Star Ranking</head><p>In addition to the J index, two methods to prioritize variable star candidates were tested.</p><p>The first method takes the AoV result directly, i.e., q</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">(1) 1 = Θ(ω (1) max ).<label>(13)</label></formula><p>In its special case of no excluded systematic frequencies (n 1 → ∞, n 2 = 1), this is a widespread method for prioritizing variable star candidates. Likewise, the maximum of the divided power spectrum δΘ could serve as a variability indicator:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">q (2) 1 = δΘ(ω (2) max ).<label>(14)</label></formula><p>The AoV statistic Θ ≡</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">(n−n )x 2 n x−x 2</formula><p>compares the quadratic norm of a model x (with n free parameters) with the residuals that remain after subtraction of the model from n observations x (Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1999). Because it has optimum period detection properties (Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1996), we expect q 1 to yield the best ranking. However, as an empirical alternative we also tested the light curve's standard deviation with and without the periodic signal obtained by the AoV multiharmonic fit:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">q (1) 2 = σ σ ′ (ω (1) max ) and q (2) 2 = σ σ ′ (ω (2) max ) (15)</formula><p>It is dependent upon the frequency ω max determined in the previous section, which is why different choices of ω max lead to different rankings. The quoted σ ′ refers to the standard variation after subtraction of the corresponding fit (for calculation of coefficients, see Schwarzenberg-Czerny &amp; Kaluzny 1998).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.">Comparison of Variability Search Performance</head><p>The quantities ξ and n ω have been calculated for both frequencies ω 1,2 . For each run, the parameters n 1 and n 2 were varied independently <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> Results of the tested variable star ranking methods and parameters.</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">ω (1) max ω (2) max J q (1) 1 q (1) 2 q (2) 1 q (2) 2 Index (n 1 ,n 2 ) ξ LRa02a (0, 0) 0.0051 (0, 0) 0.010 (0.2, 10%)</formula><p>0.0035</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(0.2, ≥70%)</formula><p>0.010 0.032</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">LRa02b (0, 0) 0.0035 (0, 0) 0.0056 (0, 0)</formula><p>0.0027</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">(0, 0)</formula><p>0.0062 0.034</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">(n 1 ,n 2 )</formula><p>nω LRa02a</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">(5−10, 10%) 65% (≥5, 10%) 84% LRa02b (≥10, 0) 63% (≥5, 10%) 81%</formula><p>Note.-The quantities ξ and nω are shown for each tested ranking parameter q, both methods of determining the best frequency ω (k) max and both analyzed data sets. For clarity, only the best value achievable by variation of the parameters n 1 (master power spectrum cut) and n 2 (empty phases) is shown for each method. The corresponding values/ranges of n 1 and n 2 are shown in small brackets above each value.</p><p>on the following values: n 1 = {0, 0.01, 0.05, 0.1, 0.2, 0.5, 1, 2, 5, 10, 1000} n 2 = {0%, 10%, 20%, 30%, 40%, 50%, 60%, 70%, 80%, 90%, 100%}</p><p>The results of the comparison are summarized in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>, which shows the best value for ξ and n ω achievable with each tested method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.1.">Number of Harmonics</head><p>Paper I and the first step of the reanalysis (Section 4) determined the stellar variability using AoV periodograms with two harmonics, which was also used for this comparison. Furthermore, the number of harmonics was set to N = 7 in a second test in order to increase the sensitivity on sharp signals that are, e.g., caused by eclipsing binaries (for the sensitivity dependence on the number of harmonics, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Schwarzenberg-Czerny 1999)</ref>. Both results show very similar ranking performances (for the best ranking method q 1 , we find ξ 7 ≈ ξ 2 ± 0.001 in both data sets), but the N = 2 test naturally yields a slightly better (12%-15%) frequency match with the initial run that was obtained using the same number of harmonics. However, the test with seven harmonics revealed a number of additional interesting eclipsing binaries that could not be detected using the smaller number of model parameters (see Sections 6.1 and 6.3). Therefore, we prefer the latter for our improved variability search (Section 5.6) and focus in the following on the details of the search performance with N = 7 harmonics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.2.">Ranking</head><p>The performance of the ranking differs only slightly between the tested methods. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> shows how the quantities q 1 (AoV) and q 2 (σ-ratio) both provide a sorting that lists stars with real variability first. The numerical quantity ξ yields with ≈ 0.003 for q (2) 1 a minimum close to the optimal ranking (ξ = 0). It is an order of magnitude lower than the previously used J index (ξ ≈ 0.03) and significantly lower than ranking the AoV power without exclusion of systematics (ξ ≈ 0.022 for q with n 1 = 1000 and n 2 = 100%). In particular, this corresponds to a drastically decreased false alarm rate. <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> shows the dependence of the ranking performance on the parameters n 1 and n 2 for the two best methods q (1) 1 and q <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref> 1 . In both cases, the most restrictive exclusion of systematic frequencies yields the best sorting. Thereby, the cut in the master power spectrum (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>) has a slightly larger impact than the exclusion of empty phases (Equation <ref type="formula">(8)</ref>). The minimum of ξ is reached for n 1 = n 2 = 0, but is almost independent of n 2 , because the first criterion is more restrictive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.3.">Frequency Determination</head><p>The frequencies found in Paper I and by manual reanalysis of the data set are in good agreement with the values of ω (k) max (see <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> and <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>). Without master spectrum division (k = 1), about two-thirds of the frequencies are recovered. However, the yield increases to about 80% if the procedure is applied (k = 2).</p><p>Interestingly, the frequency exclusion from the first criterion (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>) now has the reverse effect -the maximal agreement is reached if it is almost switched off by setting n 1 ≥ 5. Smaller values of n 1 are too restrictive and can increase the number of wrong periods by up to about 10%. On 2 , and the Stetson J index (left to right). Solid lines represent the unweighted case (k = 1), whereas dotted lines include the effect of master power spectrum division (k = 2). Only the parameters n 1 and n 2 of the most successful sorting are used for each method (compare <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). The black dashed line shows the optimal ranking for comparison. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>.-Influence of systematic frequency exclusion method on variable star ranking efficiency for the data set LRa02b. The quantity ξ is shown on the y-axis as a function of the model parameters n 1 (lines) and n 2 (x-axis) for the best tested ranking method using q 1 . The left plot shows the results with ω (1) max as the maximum frequency, whereas the effect of division by the master power spectrum (ω <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref> max ) can be seen on the right. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>.-Fraction nω of correctly identified frequencies ω <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref> max as a function of model parameters n 1 (lines) and n 2 (x-axis) for variable stars in data set LRa02a (left) and LRa02b (right), respectively. the other hand, the exclusion of empty phases has again a small influence, although a value of n 2 = 10% yields a slight improvement for the majority of tested scenarios <ref type="figure">(Figure 7)</ref>.</p><p>The remaining small group of variable stars detected with a different period has been analyzed carefully. The majority of them shows multiperiod variation and was identified with a rational multiple (e.g., 1/7, 2/5) of the original frequency. For some stars, the original period had to be revised during the reanalysis (see also Section 6). A small rest shows amplitudes close to the noise level, such that the period could not be determined unambiguously.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6.">New Selection Method</head><p>Based upon the results from the comparison, a new procedure was set up to search for variable stars within the BEST project.</p><p>1. The J index is used to exclude non-variable stars in order to save computation time.</p><p>High values of J can originate from either real variability or systematic trends, leading to a very high false alarm rate when being used as the only ranking criterion. However, low J indices give a reliable criterion for non-variability, i.e., neither physical nor systematic variations. In the studied data set LRa02, no star shows clear variability below J = 0.1. This limit is therefore used for analyses of BEST II data sets, for which it typically excludes 50%-75% of all stars.</p><p>2. The AoV algorithm is applied with N = 7 harmonics to the selected subset (J ≥ 0.1) in order to obtain power spectra.</p><p>3. The improved selection method is applied to rank all investigated stars. Following the results from Section 5.5, a master power spectrum is calculated, the number of empty boxes is counted for each test period, and each individual power spectrum is divided by the master power spectrum (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(11)</ref>). For the ranking, the frequency ω</p><p>max is determined from the subset of non-systematic frequencies in the divided spectrum δΘ(ω) by following Equations (7)-(9) and (12) with the parameters n 1 = 0 and n 2 = 10%. The corresponding maximum δΘ(ω <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref> max ) (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref>) serves as the quantity q for priorization (see example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 8</ref>). However, in order to improve the final period ω f , ω</p><p>max is recalculated without exclusion of systematic frequencies from the master power spectrum, i.e., by setting n 1 → ∞, n 2 = 10% and applying Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>- <ref type="formula">(9)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref> again.</p><p>4. All light curves are folded with their respective final periods ω f and analyzed visually in descending order of q = δΘ(ω</p><p>max ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">RESULTS</head><p>In addition to the 350 variables already published in Paper I, 279 stars in LRa02 were identified with clear periodic variability (114 in LRa02a and 165 in LRa02b). Furthermore, we identified 52 suspected periodic variable stars (17 in LRa02a and 35 in LRa02b). For the latter, the quality of the light curves is not sufficient to fully exclude systematic errors as sources of variability, the folded light curves are partly incomplete or the point-spread functions of two neighboring stars overlap each other such that the signal cannot be well separated. The number of detections in this work is compared with Paper I in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>. Note. The number of previously known variables in the field confirmed by BEST II is given in brackets (included in first number).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Application of the New Method to LRa02</head><p>A large number of 189 new variable stars was already identified in the BEST II data set LRa02 by the first step of the reanalysis, the manual screening (see Section 4). After the search procedure was tested and optimized using the results from Paper I and this additional sample of detections, the most successful sorting method (see description in Section 5) was finally applied to search the data set LRa02 once more.</p><p>In addition to the 350 variable stars published in Paper I and the 189 found by the manual reanalysis, this improved search yielded another 135 previously unknown variable stars. Reasons why these went undetected by previous searches are as follows.</p><p>• Systematic trends or aliases were found instead of the real periodicity. (left plots) is strongly affected by systematic noise, while LRa02b2 17835 (right plots) shows both physical and systematic variability. In each plain AoV spectrum Θ(ω) (upper plots), the position of the overall maximum is marked -it is found at systematic frequencies for both cases. Furthermore, the maximum of Θ(ω) and the J index are both much larger for the first star, leading to a false alarm when using these quantities to rank the variability. The functionality of the new variable star search algorithm is shown in the lower plots. In addition to the division by the master power spectrum, systematic frequencies are filtered out (Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>- <ref type="formula">(9)</ref> with parameters n 1 = 0 and n 2 = 10%, marked red in the spectrum), and the maximum ω</p><p>max is determined on the non-systematic subset of frequencies (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(12)</ref>). To use the corresponding maximum q</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">(2) 1 = δΘ(ω (2) max )</formula><p>for ranking is much more sensitive to real variability. The second star LRa02b2 17835 is a new detection of this paper <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 3</ref> and <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>). <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>.-Photometric quality of the BEST II data set LRa02a (in line with LRa02b). The standard deviation σ of each light curve is plotted vs. the BEST II instrumental magnitude R B for each star. The red fit line indicates the lower noise limit σ min B (R B ) for this data set.</p><p>• The AoV algorithm was run with N = 2 harmonics for Paper I and the manual reanalysis, but with N = 7 for the latest search. This leads to a higher sensitivity for nonsinusoidal variations, which is particularly important for the detection of Algol type eclipsing binaries (at least 27 additional EA variables with long periods (P &gt; 2 days) can be attributed to the increase of N , some of them being very eccentric).</p><p>• A total of 21 variable stars on the edge of the BEST II FOV with few datapoints were excluded by earlier reductions of the data set.</p><p>Due to an improved data quality <ref type="figure">(Figure 9</ref>) and increased sensitivity for non-sinusoidal events, we could also refine the periods for 17 of the variable stars published in Paper I (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Classification of Variability</head><p>The newly discovered periodic variable stars are classified by the shape, amplitude, and period of their folded light curves according to the scheme used by the GCVS. We identified pulsating stars of the Delta Scuti type (DSCT), RR Lyrae type (RR), and Cepheid variables (CEP). Eclipsing binary star systems were classified as Algol type (EA), Beta Lyrae type (EB), or W Ursae Majoris type (EW). Stars having sinusoidal-like light curves and showing eclipses are marked as rotating ellipsoidal variables (ELL), whereas some light curves exhibit characteristic features of spotted stars (SP). In case the type of variability could not be determined from the light curve alone, we classified a star as VAR, meaning that further observations are needed to constrain the proper physical origin of stellar variability. Stars that are variable on time scales longer than the observational baseline are classified as long periodic (LP). This class can also include non-periodic variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3.">Catalog of New Variables in LRa02</head><p>The newly identified periodic variable stars of the BEST II data set LRa02 are listed in Table 3. A set of stars from Paper I with revised ephemerides is presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 4</ref>. Due to the reanalysis, the internal numbering is not consistent with Paper I, which is why IDs were given different prefixes (i.e., LRa02a2 and LRa02b2, respectively). Corresponding IDs of the nearest Two Micron All Sky Survey (2MASS) object are given if the catalog coordinates do not differ from our astrometry by more than 2 arcsec. In some cases, two neighboring stars could be spatially resolved, but their photometric apertures overlap so that the actual source of variation is ambiguous. Such objects have been marked with a "c" (crowded), whereas suspected variables are indicated with an "s" flag. All instrumental magnitudes given are obtained without any filter so that their absolute value should only be considered as a rough estimation. <ref type="bibr">2</ref> Amplitudes and ephemerides (T 0 in rHJD=HJD-2,454,400) are the results of the AoV algorithm. However, after visual inspection, several periods have been refined manually (usually to rational multiples of the initial result).</p><p>The corresponding phase-folded light curves can be found in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figures 10 and 11</ref>. For stars classified as LP, light curves are shown unfolded and no ephemerides are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Tables 3 and 4</ref>. Light curves in a machine-readable format as well as finding charts are available upon request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4.">Comparison with Known Variables</head><p>We searched the VSX and the GCVS for previously known variable stars within a radius of 10 arcsec around each of our new detections. A total number of seven variables was found in these catalogs. For comparison, the new BEST II results for these are included in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 3</ref> and marked with "k" as known variables.</p><p>The three stars CoRoT 110742676, NSVS 12579155, and NSVS 12585233 have periods longer than 50 days. BEST II confirms their long-time periodicity, but the phase coverage of their cycles is insufficient to confirm the periods quantitatively. For the four eclipsing binaries ASAS J064835-0534.3, DY Mon, <ref type="bibr">[KEE2007]</ref> 1318, and <ref type="bibr">[KEE2007]</ref> 1334, both the classifications and periods are completely confirmed.</p><p>The latter two have first been detected by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kabath et al. (2007)</ref> in the CoRoT IR01 field with BEST, for which the chosen FOV shows a small overlap with the BEST II field LRa02a. However, the precision in the periods of these two binaries could be significantly improved because the LRa02 data set covers a much larger time period (41 compared to 12 nights) and the photometric quality of BEST II is better.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.">Comparison with CoRoT</head><p>The LRa02 data sets of BEST II and CoRoT are, except for the fact that they point to the same field, completely independent of each other and thus provide a great opportunity to compare the scientific results of the two surveys. Notes. Stars have been matched with the closest 2MASS object within a radius of 2 arcsec. Coordinates are given for epoch J2000.0 and were derived by an astrometric match of CCD to USNO-A2 coordinates. Given magnitudes are instrumental and reflect the CCD sensitivity as observations have been obtained without filter. Overlapping apertures of neighboring stars can lead to contaminated light curves -such cases are marked with a "c" flag. Suspected variables are marked by "s". Amplitudes A and ephemerides (variability period P and times of minimum brightness T0, given in rHJD=HJD-2454400) are the results of the AoV algorithm. <ref type="table">(This Table is</ref> available in its entirety in machine-readable and Virtual Observatory (VO) forms in the online journal. A portion is shown here for guidance regarding its form and content.)  <ref type="figure">Fig. 10</ref>.-Phase-folded light curves of variable stars detected in field LRa02 after reanalysis of the data set.</p><p>(The complete figure set (331 images) is available in the electronic edition of the Astronomical Journal)</p><p>A step in the scientific analysis of CoRoT data consists of an automatic stellar variability classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Debosscher et al. 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Debosscher et al. , 2009</ref>. This method was also applied to the CoRoT observations of field LRa02, and the results are meanwhile -together with the full light curves -publicly available through the CoRoT archive. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> The CoRoT LRa02 data set contains 11,448 targets, from which 10,392 (91%) are matching a BEST II target within a maximum angular distance of 1 ′′ . Because LRa02 was not covered completely by BEST II <ref type="figure">(Figure 1</ref> in Paper I), 454 CoRoT targets are located outside of the BEST II FOV. Furthermore, the magnitude ranges do not overlap completely, so that 425 bright CoRoT stars are saturated on the BEST II CCD. The remaining 177 CoRoT targets are within the FOV and right magnitude range, but have no BEST II counterpart due to technical issues such as blooming. In the same way, BEST II observed a total of 93,943 stars in both pointings that have not been given a CoRoT mask or are located outside the CoRoT FOV.</p><p>From the 681 variable stars presented together in Paper I and this work, 262 variables (190 from Paper I, 72 from this work) match a CoRoT target. The corresponding CoRoT IDs are shown for the new detections in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Tables 3 and 4</ref>.</p><p>CoRoT observed the LRa02 field about 1 year after BEST II, and the observing times do not overlap. Because this work focuses on the im- provement of variable star detection for groundbased telescopes, CoRoT and BEST II light curves have not been combined. However, we note that such a combination might yield improved ephemerides. BEST II light curves of interesting objects will be provided on request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.1.">Detection Efficiency of BEST II and the New Search Algorithm</head><p>For stars both observed with CoRoT and BEST II, it is possible to investigate the performance of BEST II more in detail. The automatic classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Debosscher et al. 2007</ref>) provides information about the amplitude of variation for CoRoT targets. Because the satellite has a much higher photometric precision, most of these amplitudes are well below the detection limit of BEST II. However, the knowledge of stellar variability with higher precision can be used to evaluate the detection efficiency of BEST II. Of particular interest are two questions: first, how many stars with sufficiently high variation in the CoRoT data set have been detected as variables from BEST II data. Second, if these are clearly distinguished by the new detection algorithm from the rest of stars having variabilities below the threshold of BEST II.</p><p>The full amplitude A C of variation was derived from the fit coefficients given in the CoRoT classification. As this contains each a low-and highfrequency entry for every CoRoT target, the amplitude was calculated as the maximum of both. The value A C itself contains no information on whether the signal can be detected by BEST II or   <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(16)</ref>). On the y-axis, the left plot shows the suggested new quantity for variability ranking q = δΘ(ω <ref type="bibr">(2)</ref> max ) (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref>) and the right plot the Stetson J index for comparison. Variable stars detected in Paper I or this work are marked red. The area of possible BEST II detections is indicated in gray.</p><p>not, which strongly depends on the magnitude of a given star. Therefore, the quantity</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">S/N = A C /σ min B (R B ) (16)</formula><p>is used to estimate the variability signal to noise (S/N). The noise σ min B (R B ) gives the photometric precision achievable with BEST II in the given data set for a star of magnitude R B . It was determined by a fit to the σ-magnitude plot of the field <ref type="figure">(Figure 9</ref>). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 12</ref> shows the expected S/N for all stars that are contained in both data sets. From 680 stars with CoRoT amplitudes that should be visible in the BEST II data (S/N &gt; 3), 162 were detected as variable stars in Paper I and this work. 448 stars are expected to have a large S/N &gt; 3, but show no significant variability in the BEST II data set (q &lt; 9). 70 stars with both expected and measured variability (S/N &gt; 3, q &gt; 9) were not detected by BEST II.</p><p>We have checked CoRoT light curves with significant variability in the CoRoT classification, but that are not variable in the BEST II data. Many of them show strong instrumental effects (hot pixels; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Auvergne et al. 2009</ref>) which obviously mislead the automatic classification algorithm. However, from the 448 stars in this region, only 88 show a probability larger than 95% to belong to any class so that most can be considered false alarms.</p><p>Stars that are expected to be variable (S/N &gt; 3) and show variation in the BEST II light curve (q &gt; 9), but were not detected as variable stars after visual inspection have been re-inspected. Such targets have been missed due to the smaller phase coverage of BEST II, or because the real noise of individual light curves is underestimated using σ min B (e.g., due to higher order extinction effects for very red stars).</p><p>The distinction between variable and nonvariable stars works very well using the new ranking quantity q = δΘ(ω (2) max ) (see Section 5). If the limit q = 9 is chosen to separate variables from the bulk of non-variable stars, 92% of all matched stars are found below the limit. Only seven variables have q &lt; 9, but their light curves and low S/N indicate rather false detections than too low variability values. From all 780 stars with q &gt; 9, one third belongs to the set of variable star detections. For comparison, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 12</ref> also shows the J index vs. the expected S/N. The plot shows clearly that the separation between real and artifical variability is much weaker. The strength of the new ranking is particularly clear in the regime of 1 &lt; S/N &lt; 3, i.e., close to the detection limit of BEST II.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.2.">Comparison of Classifications</head><p>The variable star detections of BEST II were compared in detail with the automatic CoRoT classification for the 262 matched variables. The overall agreement between both methods is very good; details regarding the period and magnitude determination as well as the classifications obtained by BEST II and CoRoT are given in the remainder of this section. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> shows some instructive examples of variable stars in agreement (a) and with differences in the determined periods and/or classifications ((b)-(f)).</p><p>The mean magnitudes of matched stars are in  reasonably good agreement ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 14)</ref>. Only a few very long-term variables -like the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>(d) -show differences in the order of 1 mag and above because BEST II and CoRoT observed during different phases; the remaining majority differs by only (0.059 ± 0.158) mag. Periods determined by BEST II have been compared with the main frequency from the automatic CoRoT characterization. For 72.5% of the matched stars, the periods are equal or integral (n = 1, . . . , 5) multiples of each other to a precision of at least 1%. The histogram of period ratios in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 15</ref> shows that most detections have been identified in the CoRoT data with half the period compared to BEST II. This is because many periods are doubled during the visual inspection of BEST II light curves in order to show full cycles (e.g., Figures 13(c) and 13(e)), in particular for W Ursae Majoris eclipsing binaries (EW).</p><p>The classes from visual inspection of BEST II light curves match the automatic classification of the CoRoT data set well. From the 262 variables present in both data sets, 196 stars have BEST II variability classes that are consistent with either the short-or long-periodic classification in the CoRoT data set. Note that the variability classes used by BEST II and CoRoT are slightly different: for example, BEST II distinguishes within the CoRoT class ECL between the eclipsing binary types EA, EB, and EW, while the CoRoT scheme includes, e.g., slowly pulsating B-stars, which are simply identified as VAR within the BEST II study. All such consistent refinements are considered a classification match.</p><p>The 64 stars with a clear disagreement in the variability classifications were checked carefully by reviewing the light curves from both BEST II and CoRoT. For 26 stars, the variability classes ob- tained by BEST II appear more realistic. Most of such cases are LP variable stars (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Fig- ure 13(d)</ref>) that have been identified as such in the BEST II data set by visual inspection. For these cases, even the longer CoRoT baseline does not cover a full cycle, so that the period and classification obtained from the CoRoT pipeline are not conclusive. Furthermore, some eclipsing binaries are clearly misclassified by the automatic CoRoT procedure. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13(e)</ref> shows an example of a W Ursae Majoris type eclipsing binary that was identified as an RR Lyrae pulsator -most likely because it was detected with half of its physical period from the CoRoT data set. For three stars similar to the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13(b)</ref>, narrow eclipse events were not detected by the CoRoT analysis. Most of the stars with implausible variability types were classified as BE by the automatic classification, which was described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Debosscher et al. (2009)</ref> as a "trash" class regarding its wide parameter spread. For 16 stars like the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>(f), the CoRoT classifications are in better agreement with the measurements. For most of these cases, this clearly results from the better photometric quality of the satellite data. For 22 cases, the photometric data itself are insufficient to choose between the CoRoT and BEST II classifications (e.g., EW/ELL). No automatic classification data were available for the two CoRoT targets 110833621 and 300001413.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">SUMMARY AND DISCUSSION</head><p>The CoRoT target field LRa02 was observed with BEST II during 41 nights from 2007 November to 2008 February (see Paper I). We reanalyzed the data set in order to improve the detection method and to maximize the number of detections. In addition to the 350 periodic variable stars already published earlier (Paper I), we present a catalog of 272 new variables and 52 stars with suspected variability. For seven known variables both the classifications and periods are confirmed, and the periods could significantly be improved for two of them. Revised ephemerides are presented for 17 variable stars from Paper I.</p><p>From a manual inspection of all light curves without any preselection criterion, it turned out that most of the new periodic variable stars went undetected in Paper I because the applied variability criterion using the Stetson J index was too restrictive. But because the J index is heavily biased by systematic effects, a smaller cutoff limit leads to very high false alarm rates (≈ 98%) and is therefore not a practical alternative. However, although the J index is not capable to distinguish between systematic and stellar variability, it can still be used to exclude non-variable stars from the analysis: no variable star is falsely rejected if light curves with low variability indices J &lt; 0.1 are sorted out in both data sets of this study. This separation can be particularly useful if the full AoV process is too time consuming for a whole data set.</p><p>The deep characterization of the data set enabled us to compare and train different automatic methods for an improved variability ranking. In particular, a master power spectrum was calculated as the mean of all individual AoV spectra. This method proved a valuable tool for exclusion of systematic frequencies and hence the ranking of real variability. The best algorithm found separates variable stars very effectively from the nonvariable background population and in parallel recovers their frequencies well. The new ranking method is particularly superior to the J index in regimes where the amplitude of variation becomes comparable to the noise level, i.e., close to the detection limit of the photometric system. It shows an almost equal performance for both independent subsets LRa02a and LRa02b, so that it should be easily applicable to other data sets.</p><p>Finally, the results from both Paper I and this work have been compared with the publicly available CoRoT data set. BEST II obtained light curves for 91% of all CoRoT targets in LRa02. From all 681 variable stars observed with BEST II in the field, 262 are matched with CoRoT targets. Stellar amplitudes measured by CoRoT show that BEST II detects variability efficiently in its parameter range. The results of period determination and variability classification are found to be in very good overall agreement, confirming the validity of the measurements, data reduction, and scientific analysis of both projects. 196 stars show consistent classifications. CoRoT yields a better classification in case of small variability for 16 targets, e.g., Be stars. On the other hand, the final visual screening of folded BEST II light curves proves to be an important step in the analysis. For 26 stars it was found to yield a more realistic classification, in particular for eclipsing binaries and stars with variability on time scales comparable to the observational baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Calculation of sorting parameter</head><p>Let X * = {x i } with i ∈ {1, . . . , N * } be the group of all stars in a data set. The selection of variable stars -e.g., by sorting all stars by a ranking quantity q -can then be considered a permutation p v : X * → X * that splits X * into a part X v ⊂ X * containing all N v variable stars and another part with the rest:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">p v (x i ) ∈ X v for i ≤ N v p v (x i ) / ∈ X v for i &gt; N v .</formula><p>A check of the first N v within { p v (x i )} would thus reveal all variable stars in the data set. Unfortunately, such an optimal sorting p v is usually unknown. In practice, a given permutation p v aims at a similar splitting of variable and non-variable stars, but contaminates both groups with false positives. The number of identified variable stars N ′ v ≤ N v thus depends on the number of stars N c * ≤ N * that are actually checked:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">N ′ v (p v , N c * ) = Nc * i=1 δ v (p v (x i ))</formula><p>with δ v (x i ) := 1 x i ∈ X v 0 otherwise .</p><p>A given variable star selection p v can be compared directly with the optimal procedure p v . The number of missed variable stars is</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">N ′ v (p v , N c * ) = N ′ v ( p v , N c * ) − N ′ v (p v , N c * ) , whereby N ′ v ( p v , N c * ) = min(N c * , N v ).</formula><p>For a comparison between different approaches, it is useful to evaluate the performance of p v as a whole. For that, one can define the quality parameter</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">ξ = N * Nc * =1 N ′ v (p v , N c * ) N v (N * − N v ) .</formula><p>The parameter ξ sums missed variable stars for all values of N c * . The denominator accounts for normalization such that ξ = 0 for p v (best selection) and ξ = 1 for its counterpart (worst selection).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-Schematic view on the rejection of systematic</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Master power spectrum for data sets LRa02a (top) and LRa02b (bottom).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Number of variable stars N ′ v as a function of the number of inspected stars Nc * for LRa02a (left) and LRa02b (right). The different lines represent tested ranking methods: q (k) 1 , q (k)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8.-Example for power spectra Θ(ω) (upper plots) and δΘ(ω) (lower plots, see Equation (11)) -the star LRa02b2 01822</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>3</head><label></label><figDesc>CoRoT data are available to the community from the CoRoT archive: http://idoc-corot.ias.u-psud.fr/.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11.-Phase-folded light curves of known variable stars with revised parameters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12.-Detection efficiency of BEST II for the field LRa02. Shown are 10,392 stars that are measured by both BEST II and CoRoT. The expected BEST II S/N of CoRoT amplitudes is plotted on the x-axis (Equation (16)). On the y-axis, the left plot shows the suggested new quantity for variability ranking q = δΘ(ω</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13.-Examples for variable stars identified both by BEST II and CoRoT. Each row shows light curves of the same star: in the first column, the BEST II light curve is folded with the period from BEST II; in the second column, the CoRoT light curve folded with the BEST II period; and in the third column, the CoRoT light curve folded with the CoRoT period. Unfolded light curves are shown for long periodic variables.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14.-Histogram of differences between CoRoT and BEST II magnitudes (for matched detections, without very long periodic variables).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15.-Histogram of CoRoT and BEST II period ratio for matched variable star detections. The insets show the two main peaks enlarged (normalized).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Variable Star Detections in BEST II 
Data Set LRa02 -Summarized Counts for Paper I 
(Kabath et al. 2009a) and This Work. 

LRa02a 
LRa02b 
Total 
Paper I 
173 (4) 
177 (1) 
350 (5) 
This paper 
114 (2) 
165 (5) 
279 (7) 
This paper (suspected) 
17 (0) 
35 (0) 
52 (0) 
Total 
304 (6) 
377 (6) 
681 (12) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 3 : Catalog of Variable Stars Detected in CoRoT Field LRa02 after Reanalysis of the Data Set, Sorted by Internal BEST II Identifiers.</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>BEST ID 
Flag 
2MASS ID 
α(J2000.0) 
δ(J2000.0) 
RB (mag) 
T0 [rHJD] 
P (d) 
A (mag) 
J Index 
Type 
Other Names 
LRa02a 
LRa02a2 00759 
06473611-0352264 
06 h 47 m 36.1 s 
−03 • 52 ′ 26 ′′ . 6 
18.11 
34.638 
0.828 ± 0.002 
0.4 ± 0.2 
0.306 
EA 
LRa02a2 01976 
06483833-0312255 
06 h 48 m 38.3 s 
−03 • 12 ′ 25 ′′ . 6 
16.34 
35.163 
0.8348 ± 0.0006 
0.30 ± 0.05 
1.37 
EA/SP 
LRa02a2 03383 
06481122-0346301 
06 h 48 m 11.2 s 
−03 • 46 ′ 30 ′′ . 4 
17.13 
35.097 
1.294 ± 0.005 
0.12 ± 0.07 
0.323 
CEP 
LRa02a2 04701 
06472903-0432171 
06 h 47 m 29.0 s 
−04 • 32 ′ 17 ′′ . 2 
15.25 
38.772 
8.6 ± 0.2 
0.04 ± 0.02 
0.445 
ELL/SP 
LRa02a2 05225 
06483988-0339178 
06 h 48 m 39.9 s 
−03 • 39 ′ 17 ′′ . 9 
16.51 
34.937 
0.4350 ± 0.0004 
0.12 ± 0.07 
0.812 
ELL/SP 
LRa02a2 05867 
06475987-0416581 
06 h 47 m 59.9 s 
−04 • 16 ′ 58 ′′ . 3 
17.72 
34.841 
0.5255 ± 0.0005 
0.4 ± 0.2 
0.457 
EB 
LRa02a2 06108 
06475271-0424518 
06 h 47 m 52.7 s 
−04 • 24 ′ 51 ′′ . 9 
17.00 
34.601 
2.747 ± 0.008 
0.22 ± 0.07 
0.469 
EA 
LRa02a2 06147 
06492768-0308050 
06 h 49 m 27.7 s 
−03 • 08 ′ 05 ′′ . 2 
13.87 
34.711 
0.40998 ± 0.00006 
0.73 ± 0.03 
23.6 
EB 
LRa02a2 06168 
06483769-0348472 
06 h 48 m 37.7 s 
−03 • 48 ′ 47 ′′ . 3 
16.15 
35.256 
0.8230 ± 0.0006 
0.16 ± 0.03 
0.807 
EA 
LRa02a2 06363 
s 
06482994-0356402 
06 h 48 m 29.9 s 
−03 • 56 ′ 40 ′′ . 3 
15.80 
35.944 
1.646 ± 0.007 
0.04 ± 0.03 
0.548 
ELL 
LRa02a2 06993 
06482849-0403248 
06 h 48 m 28.5 s 
−04 • 03 ′ 24 ′′ . 8 
13.82 
34.705 
0.4248 ± 0.0002 
0.106 ± 0.008 
5.75 
EW/ELL 
CoRoT 300002950 
LRa02a2 07010 
06481669-0413092 
06 h 48 m 16.7 s 
−04 • 13 ′ 09 ′′ . 3 
14.56 
35.923 
2.309 ± 0.006 
0.04 ± 0.02 
0.658 
EA 
CoRoT 300002493 
LRa02a2 07056 
06484660-0349153 
06 h 48 m 46.6 s 
−03 • 49 ′ 15 ′′ . 5 
17.20 
34.934 
0.5425 ± 0.0005 
0.22 ± 0.06 
0.838 
EW 
LRa02a2 07090 
06493379-0311214 
06 h 49 m 33.8 s 
−03 • 11 ′ 21 ′′ . 3 
17.24 
34.925 
0.5427 ± 0.0007 
0.15 ± 0.07 
0.374 
EW 
LRa02a2 07148 
06480066-0427255 
06 h 48 m 00.7 s 
−04 • 27 ′ 25 ′′ . 5 
16.74 
34.676 
0.35786 ± 0.00008 
0.60 ± 0.05 
1.62 
EW 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Catalog of Periodic Variable Stars with Revised Parameters Compared to Paper I (Kabath et al. 2009a). 

BEST ID 
Flag 
2MASS ID 
α(J2000.0) 
δ(J2000.0) 
RB (mag) 
T0 [rHJD] 
P (d) 
A (mag) 
J Index 
Type 
Other Names 
LRa02a2 04976 
k 
06473121-0432567 
06 h 47 m 31.2 s 
−04 • 32 ′ 56 ′′ . 9 
15.05 
· · · 
· · · 
· · · 
0.964 
EA 
lra2a 00269 
LRa02a2 07847 
k 
06483188-0407577 
06 h 48 m 31.9 s 
−04 • 07 ′ 57 ′′ . 9 
16.45 
39.649 
1.5015 ± 0.0001 
1.3 ± 0.1 
4.04 
EA 
lra2a 00416 
LRa02a2 08694 
k 
06491193-0342336 
06 h 49 m 11.9 s 
−03 • 42 ′ 33 ′′ . 8 
16.14 
34.694 
0.31415 ± 0.00005 
0.46 ± 0.03 
4.50 
EW 
lra2a 00450 
LRa02a2 10471 
k 
06500331-0315474 
06 h 50 m 03.3 s 
−03 • 15 ′ 47 ′′ . 4 
16.44 
35.159 
2.695 ± 0.001 
0.8 ± 0.1 
0.943 
EA 
lra2a 00531 
LRa02a2 12019 
k 
06485506-0423379 
06 h 48 m 55.1 s 
−04 • 23 ′ 38 ′′ . 1 
15.33 
· · · 
· · · 
· · · 
6.12 
CEP 
lra2a 00601, CoRoT 110826631 
LRa02a2 24433 
ck 
06520050-0326327 
06 h 52 m 00.5 s 
−03 • 26 ′ 32 ′′ . 8 
13.66 
98.695 
6.785 ± 0.001 
0.6 ± 0.1 
6.82 
EA 
lra2a 01126, CoRoT 110677259 
LRa02a2 24442 
ck 
06520077-0326255 
06 h 52 m 00.8 s 
−03 • 26 ′ 25 ′′ . 7 
14.32 
98.695 
6.785 ± 0.001 
0.26 ± 0.01 
1.69 
EA 
lra2a 01127 
LRa02b2 03306 
k 
06474385-0541125 
06 h 47 m 43.8 s 
−05 • 41 ′ 12 ′′ . 7 
12.57 
· · · 
· · · 
· · · 
7.77 
LP 
lra2b 01648 
LRa02b2 05167 
k 
06484535-0458261 
06 h 48 m 45.4 s 
−04 • 58 ′ 26 ′′ . 2 
15.69 
34.740 
0.7749 ± 0.0004 
0.43 ± 0.04 
3.92 
EA 
lra2b 01600, CoRoT 300003628 
LRa02b2 13901 
k 
06484069-0537534 
06 h 48 m 40.7 s 
−05 • 37 ′ 53 ′′ . 6 
14.33 
35.085 
0.52869 ± 0.00009 
0.39 ± 0.02 
14.9 
EW 
lra2b 01437, CoRoT 300003441 
LRa02b2 23935 
k 
06491567-0550387 
06 h 49 m 15.7 s 
−05 • 50 ′ 38 ′′ . 9 
14.06 
35.241 
2.966 ± 0.009 
0.16 ± 0.02 
2.53 
EA 
lra2b 01257, CoRoT 110657689 
LRa02b2 31945 
k 
06 h 50 m 23.9 s 
−05 • 26 ′ 29 ′′ . 5 
15.60 
34.697 
2.239 ± 0.004 
0.24 ± 0.04 
1.42 
EA 
lra2b 01080 
LRa02b2 38262 
k 
06505364-0527405 
06 h 50 m 53.6 s 
−05 • 27 ′ 40 ′′ . 8 
12.43 
41.500 
41 ± 1 
0.18 ± 0.01 
28.1 
SR 
lra2b 00968, CoRoT 110839568 
LRa02b2 48861 
k 
06512387-0549233 
06 h 51 m 23.9 s 
−05 • 49 ′ 23 ′′ . 6 
13.58 
· · · 
· · · 
· · · 
5.93 
LP 
lra2b 00738 
LRa02b2 51632 
k 
06511964-0605018 
06 h 51 m 19.7 s 
−06 • 05 ′ 02 ′′ . 2 
15.92 
35.282 
1.388 ± 0.005 
0.08 ± 0.05 
0.879 
ELL/SP 
lra2b 00687 
LRa02b2 59423 
k 
06522734-0545516 
06 h 52 m 27.3 s 
−05 • 45 ′ 51 ′′ . 8 
13.41 
34.730 
1.8214 ± 0.0001 
0.62 ± 0.01 
14.4 
EA 
lra2b 00469 
LRa02b2 66851 
k 
06531961-0540496 
06 h 53 m 19.6 s 
−05 • 40 ′ 49 ′′ . 6 
15.29 
34.760 
0.45935 ± 0.00009 
0.57 ± 0.03 
6.44 
EW 
lra2b 00323 </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> http://www.aavso.org/vsx/</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> The zero point was shifted to minimize the residuals with the R magnitude of USNO-A2, yielding an rms deviation with the catalog of about 0.5 mag for all matched stars.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Almenara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Auvergne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Boisnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">411</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baglin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Auvergne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Boisnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">36th COSPAR Scientific Assembly</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">3749</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kovács</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">266</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Debosscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">475</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1159</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Debosscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>López</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">519</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deeg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Shporer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">343</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deeming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap&amp;SS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">´ A</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">166</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eigmüller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1560</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eigmüller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">654</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">569</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper I</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fruth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3911</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Karoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">766</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dimitrov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Neuhäuser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pasternacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Csizmadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Sz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1177</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eislöffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Erikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kabath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">53</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">VizieR Online Data Catalog</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Samus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Durlevich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<pubPlace>B/GCVS</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schwarzenberg-Czerny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schwarzenberg-Czerny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">516</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">315</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schwarzenberg-Czerny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kaluzny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">251</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Soszynski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Poleski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Udalski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stetson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">851</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X.-B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. J. Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
