<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:09+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Tidal interactions in multi-planet systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Tidal interactions in multi-planet systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received: date / Accepted: date</note>
					<note>Noname manuscript No. (will be inserted by the editor)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Planet formation · Planetary systems · Resonances · Tidal interactions</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We study systems of close orbiting planets evolving under the influence of tidal circularization. It is supposed that a commensurability forms through the action of disk induced migration and orbital circularization. After the system enters an inner cavity or the disk disperses the evolution continues under the influence of tides due to the central star which induce orbital circularization. We derive approximate analytic models that describe the evolution away from a general first order resonance that results from tidal circularization in a two planet system and which can be shown to be a direct consequence of the conservation of energy and angular momentum. We consider the situation when the system is initially very close to resonance and also when the system is between resonances. We also perform numerical simulations which confirm these models and then apply them to two and four planet systems chosen to have parameters related to the GJ581 and HD10180 systems. We also estimate the tidal dissipation rates through effective quality factors that could result in evolution to observed period ratios within the lifetimes of the systems. Thus the survival of, or degree of departure from, close commensurabilities in observed systems may be indicative of the effectiveness of tidal disipation, a feature which in turn may be related to the internal structure of the planets involved.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Commensurabilities and tidal circularization in planetary systems</head><p>We begin by considering the evolution of planetary systems undergoing tidal circularization in a general way and then move on to consider simple analytic models of two planet systems that can be close to first order commensurabilities.</p><p>2.1 Two interacting planets in circular orbits for which energy is dissipated at fixed total angular momentum Consider two interacting planets with orbital energies E 1 and E 2 respectively. The associated orbital angular momenta for assumed circular orbits are −2E 1 /n 1 and −2E 2 /n 2 respectively. Here n 1 and n 2 are the mean motions associated with the two planets. Suppose now the system dissipates energy while conserving its total angular momentum. This is expected to be the case during orbital circularization when this occurs as a result of stellar tides dissipated in the planets because the planets themselves cannot contain a significant amount of angular momentum. Accordingly we write</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">dE 1 dt + dE 2 dt = −L,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where L is the rate of energy dissipation. Angular momentum conservation implies that</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 n 1 dE 1 dt = − 1 n 2 dE 2 dt<label>(2)</label></formula><p>from which we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">dE 1 dt = − L 1 − n 2 /n 1 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">dE 2 dt = − L 1 − n 1 /n 2 .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Supposing that n 1 &gt; n 2 , the above two equations imply that planet 1 moves inwards losing energy while planet 2 moves outwards, taking up the angular momentum lost by planet 1. This is the generic form for the evolution of an accretion disc (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lynden-Bell &amp; Pringle 1974)</ref>. We now go on to discuss some simplified models for the interaction of two planets that may be either very close to or some distance away from a strict first order commensurability. In these contexts we show how tidal dissipation induced by forced eccentrcities causes the system to separate. When the resonance is close, this causes the system to depart further from commensurability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Coordinate system</head><p>We consider a general system of N planets orbiting a central mass. We adopt Jacobi coordinates <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Sinclair 1975</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, Papaloizou &amp; Szuszkiewicz 2005</ref> for which the radius vector of planet i, r i , is measured relative to the centre of mass of the system comprised of a dominant central mass M and all other planets interior to i, for i = 1, 2..., N. The planets are assumed to maintain an ordering with increasing i corresponding to greater distances |r i | from the dominant central mass. Thus the innermost planet has i = 1. The Hamiltonian, correct to second order in the planetary masses, can be written in the form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">H = N i=1 1 2 m i |˙ r i | 2 − GM i m i |r i | − N −1 i=1 N j=i+1 Gm i m j 1 |r ij | − r i · r j |r j | 3 .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Here M i = M + m i and r ij = r i − r j .</p><p>The equations of motion for motion for planet i assumed to move in a fixed plane, about a dominant central mass, may be written in the form (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Papaloizou 2003</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, Papaloizou &amp; Szuszkiewicz 2005</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">˙ E i = −n i ∂H ∂λ i (6) ˙ L i = − ∂H ∂λ i + ∂H ∂∂ i<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">˙ λ i = ∂H ∂L i + n i ∂H ∂E i<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">˙ i = ∂H ∂L i .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Here the orbital angular momentum of planet i which has reduced mass m i = m i0 M/(M + m i0 ), with m i0 being the actual mass, is L i and the orbital energy is E i . For motion around a central point mass M we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">L i = m i GM i a i (1 − e 2 i ),<label>(10)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">E i = − GM i m i 2a i ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">M i = M + m i0</formula><p>, a i denotes the semi-major axis and e i the eccentricity of</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">planet i. The mean longitude of planet i is λ i = n i (t − t 0i ) + i , where n i = GM i /a 3 i</formula><p>is its mean motion, with t 0i denoting its time of periastron passage and i the longitude of periastron. From equations (6) and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(7)</ref> an equation for the evolution of the eccentricity of planet i may be readily obtained in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">˙ e i = 1 − e 2 i e i m i n i a 2 i ∂H ∂λ i 1 − e 2 i − 1 + ∂H ∂∂ i .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>The Hamiltonian may be expanded in a Fourier series involving linear combinations of the (2N −1) angular differences i − 1 , i = 2, 3..N and λ i − i , i = 1, 2, ..N.</p><p>In the limit of small eccentricities of interest here, only terms that are of first order in the eccentricities need to be retained (terms that are of zero order do not lead to changes to eccentricities or to resonances). If this is done the possibility of first order resonances, for which the ratio of the periods of two planets is the ratio of successive integers, is allowed for. The above approximation scheme should be valid when circularization times are small enough to ensure that the eccentricities remain small. This situation is realized for examples of low mass protoplanets migrating in protoplanetary discs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Papaloizou &amp; Szuszkiewicz 2005)</ref>. Near a first order p + 1 : p resonance, p being an integer, we expect that terms in the Hamiltonian involving angles of the type φ p,j,i,j = (p + 1)λ j − pλ i − j , and φ p,j,i,i = (p+ 1)λ j − pλ i − i , where the subscripts on the left hand side correspond to those on the right hand reading from left to right, will be slowly varying and thus be dominant. Accordingly we shall retain only terms of this type. Motion away from resonances may also be considered having made this approximation although neglected high frequency modulations may be more significant then.</p><p>The Hamiltonian may be written in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">H = N i=1 E i + N −1 i=1 N j=i+1 H i,j ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where the component of the interaction Hamiltonian H i,j that is first order in the eccentricities is given, given that j &gt; i, by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">H i,j = − Gm i m j a j ∞ p=1 (e j C p,j,i,j cos(φ p,j,i,j ) + e i D p,j,i,i cos(φ p,j,i,i )) ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">C p,j,i,j = 1 2 x d(b (p) 1/2 (x)) dx + (2p + 1)b (p) 1/2 (x) − 4xδ p 1 and (15) D p,j,i,i = − 1 2 x d(b (p+1) 1/2 (x)) dx + 2(p + 1)b (p+1) 1/2 (x) .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Here</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">b (p) 1/2</formula><p>(x) denotes the usual Laplace coefficient (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brouwer &amp; Clemence 1961</ref>) with the argument x = a i /a j and δ p 1 denotes the Kronnecker delta. We remark that the subscripts associated with the coefficients C p,j,i,j and D p,j,i,i correspond to the related angles as in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref>. We shall also make the approximation of replacing M i by M and equivalently m i0 by m i .</p><p>The governing equations for motion, retaining only terms that are of the lowest order in the eccentricities, follow from Hamilton's equations <ref type="formula">(6)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(9)</ref> for the Hamiltonian (13) discussed above as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">de i dt = − ∞ p=1   N j=i+1 Gm j D p,j,i,i sin(φ p,j,i,i ) n i a 2 i a j + i−1 j=1 Gm j C p,i,j,i sin(φ p,i,j,i ) n i a 3 i   (17) dn i dt = − ∞ p=1   N j=i+1 3Gm j p a 2 i e i D p,j,i,i sin(φ p,j,i,i ) a j + e j C p,j,i,j sin(φ p,j,i,j ) a j − i−1 j=1 3Gm j (p + 1) a 2 i e j D p,i,j,j sin(φ p,i,j,j ) a i + e i C p,i,j,i sin(φ p,i,j,i ) a i   (18) dd i dt = ∞ p=1   N j=i+1 Gm j D p,j,i,i cos(φ p,j,i,i ) e i n i a 2 i a j + i−1 j=1 Gm j C p,i,j,i cos(φ p,i,j,i ) e i n i a 3 i   . (19)</formula><p>In addition, consistent with the above approximation scheme, the rate of change of the mean longitudes may be obtained from</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">dλ i dt = n i (20)</formula><p>which also enables evaluation of the rate of change of the angles φ p,j,i,i , φ p,j,i,j etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The incorporation of disk tides</head><p>We incorporate the effects of orbital circularization by adding additional terms to the right hand sides of equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(18)</ref>. Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> is modified through the straightforward prescription</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">de i dt → de i dt − e i t c,i ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where t c,i is the circularization time for planet i. Similarly equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(18)</ref> is modified according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">dn i dt → dn i dt + 3n i e 2 i t c,i .<label>(22)</label></formula><p>This adjustment is necessary to account for the orbital energy dissipation occurring as a result of circularization correct to the lowest order in e i . This dissipation is assumed to occur with out changing the angular momentum of the system because the planets can only potentially contain a negligible amount of angular momentum compared to that in the orbit. It follows from the energy dissipation rate for planet, i, given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">dE i dt = − m i n 2 i a 2 i e 2 i (1 − e 2 i )t c,i .<label>(23)</label></formula><p>For small eccentricities, e 2 i may be neglected in the denominator of the above expression and the total rate of energy dissipation in the system is obtained by summing over all planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Two planets in a p + 1 : p commensurability</head><p>It is possible to investigate solutions of equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> - <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(19)</ref> modified to incorporate circularization, that illustrate the geometrical separation of the system as energy is dissipated while the total angular momentum is conserved, in a number circumstances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">A tight commensurability</head><p>We begin with an example where two successive planets k and k + 1 maintain a p + 1 : p commensurability with the associated angles in a state of at most small amplitude libration while their semi-major axes separate. We later go on to consider a simple restricted example where the angle circulates. The effects of planets other than the resonant pair is neglected. Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> - <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(19)</ref> with the modifications given by (21) and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(22)</ref> to incorporate circularization give the governing equations for planet k in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">de k dt = − Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k sin(φ p,k+1,k,k ) n k a 2 k a k+1 − e k t c,k<label>(24)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">dn k dt = − 3Gm k+1 p a 2 k e k D p,k+1,k,k sin(φ p,k+1,k,k ) a k+1 + e k+1 C p,k+1,k,k+1 sin(φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ) a k+1 + 3n k e 2 k t c,k<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">dd k dt = Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k cos(φ p,k+1,k,k ) e k n k a 2 k a k+1 .<label>(26)</label></formula><p>Similarly the governing equations for planet k + 1 are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">de k+1 dt = − Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 sin(φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ) n k+1 a 3 k+1 − e k+1 t c,k+1<label>(27)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">dn k+1 dt = 3Gm k (p + 1) a 2 k+1 e k D p,k+1,k,k sin(φ p,k+1,k,k ) a k+1 + e k+1 C p,k+1,k,k+1 sin(φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ) a k+1 + 3n k+1 e 2 k+1 t c,k+1<label>(28)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">dd k+1 dt = Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 cos(φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ) e k+1 n k+1 a 3 k+1 . (29) Setting φ p,k+1,k,k → φ p,k+1,k,k ± ∆φ p,k+1,k,k and φ p,k+1,k,k+1 → φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ± ∆φ p,k+1,k,k+1</formula><p>, where the positive sign is taken when the equilibrium value of the angle is zero and the negative sign is taken when it is π, and ∆ indicates a small shift such that the sines of the angles may be replaced by the angles themselves. Then assuming that the evolutionary time scale is much longer than the circularization times so that the time derivatives of the eccentricities may be neglected, we can then find expressions for the small angular shifts in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">∆φ p,k+1,k,k = − e k n k a 2 k a k+1 Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k t c,k . (30) ∆φ p,k+1,k,k+1 = − e k+1 n k+1 a 3 k+1 Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 t c,k+1 .<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Substituting these into the equations for the evolution of the mean motions yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">dn k dt = 3(p + 1)e 2 k n k t c,k + 3pm k+1 e 2 k+1 n k+1 a 2 k+1 m k a 2 k t c,k+1<label>(32)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">dn k+1 dt = − 3(p + 1)m k e 2 k n k a 2 k m k+1 t c,k a 2 k+1 − 3pe 2 k+1 n k+1 t c,k+1 .<label>(33)</label></formula><p>The above pair of equations express the conservation of energy and angular momentum for the system in the limit of small eccentricity. We remark that the latter follows in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">m k+1 a 2 k+1 dn k+1 dt + m k a 2 k dn k dt = 0,<label>(34)</label></formula><p>while the former follows from using the fact that E j ∝ m j n 2/3 j to find equations for dE j /dt, j = k, k + 1 and then adding. We may also obtain an equation showing how the period ratio increases with time in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">d dt n k n k+1 = 3n k J n k+1 (p + 1)e 2 k t c,k J k+1 + pe 2 k+1 t c,k+1 J k ,<label>(35)</label></formula><p>where J k = m k a 2 k n k , and J = J k + J k+1 . In order to proceed further we need to calculate the eccentricities. These may be obtained from the governing equations for the evolution of the angles that may be obtained from <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(20)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(26)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">(29)</ref> in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">dφ p,k+1,k,k dt = (p + 1)n k+1 − pn k − Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k cos(φ p,k+1,k,k ) e k n k a 2 k a k+1 . (36) dφ p,k+1,k,k+1 dt = (p + 1)n k+1 − pn k − Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 cos(φ p,k+1,k,k+1 ) e k+1 n k+1 a 3 k+1 .<label>(37)</label></formula><p>As the angles are quasi-steady and close to zero or π, these expressions enable the calculation of the squares of the eccentricities e k and e k+1 which are required in order to calculate the rate of period separation through (35). They are found to be given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">e 2 k = Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k n k a 2 k a k+1 [(p + 1)n k+1 − pn k ] 2 and<label>(38)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">e 2 k+1 = Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 n k+1 a 3 k+1 [(p + 1)n k+1 − pn k ] 2 respectively.<label>(39)</label></formula><p>Using these in (35) we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">d dt n k n k+1 − p + 1 p 3 = 9n k J n k+1 F,<label>(40)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">F = (p + 1) t c,k J k+1 Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k pn k n k+1 a 2 k a k+1 2 + p t c,k+1 J k Gm k C p,k+1,k,k+1 pn 2 k+1 a 3 k+1 2 .<label>(41)</label></formula><p>When the system starts to move away from a commensurability taken to be exact at t = 0, we may treat the right hand side of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(40)</ref> as being constant and integrate with respect to time to obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">n k n k+1 − p + 1 p = 9n k J n k+1 F t 1/3 .<label>(42)</label></formula><p>A similar scaling for which the separation from a commensurability increases ∝ t 1/3 was obtained for a three planet system by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Papaloizou &amp; Terquem (2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">The interaction between two planets away from a close commensurability</head><p>In this case we again assume interaction between planets k and k + 1. In this case we consider the situation away from a strict commensurability where significant libration or circulation may occur. This is a natural development as tidal evolution causes the system to evolve away from a tight commensurability of the type described above towards such a situation. We make the additional simplification of assuming that m k+1 m k . In that case, a circular restricted 3 body problem may be adopted. Only the motion of planet k is considered with e k+1 = 0.</p><p>Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> - <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(20)</ref> apply and as e k+1 = 0, only terms involving the angles φ p,k+1,k,k , p = 1, 2... appear. These give the equations governing the evolution as</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">de k dt = − e k t c,k − ∞ p=1 Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k sin(φ p,k+1,k,k ) n k a 2 k a k+1<label>(43)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">dn k dt = 3n k e 2 k t c,k − ∞ p=1 3Gm k+1 pe k D p,k+1,k,k sin(φ p,k+1,k,k ) a k+1 a 2 k (44) dφ r,k+1,k,k dt = (r + 1)n k+1 − rn k − ∞ p=1 Gm k+1 D p,k+1,k,k cos(φ p,k+1,k,k ) e k n k a 2 k a k+1 , r = 1, 2, 3 . . .<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Although we consider the effect of more than one angle, we focus on a particular one with r = q which might be considered to be the one closest to resonance, though that is not essential. Setting x = e k cos(φ q,k+1,k,k ) and y = e k sin(φ q,k+1,k,k ) in equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(43)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">( 45 )</ref> leads to a system that, unlike the original one, does not contain an apparent singularity as e k → 0 in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">dx dt = −ωqy − x t c,k − ∞ p=1 =q αp sin[(p − q)(λ k+1 − λ k )]<label>(46)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">dy dt = −αq + ωqx − y t c,k − ∞ p=1 =q αp cos[(p − q)(λ k+1 − λ k )],<label>(47)</label></formula><p>where, recalling that k is fixed, we define αq = Gm k+1 D q,k+1,k,k /(n k a 2 k a k+1 ) and ωq = (q + 1)n k+1 − qn k .</p><p>We now remark that if we consider the limit e k → 0, which occurs far enough away from resonance, we may neglect the evolution of n k and asume that it remains constant and equal to n k0 . To see this it follows from (43) that e k scales as m k+1 while (44) then indicates that the change in n k , δn k = n k − n k0 scales as m 2 k+1 or e 2 k . Accordingly, for q of order unity, the induced variation of wq, δωq, is such that δωq ∼ n k0 e 2 k . By comparing the variation of the first two terms on the right hand side of equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(47)</ref>, it readily follows in the low eccentricity limit that provided</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">n k0 e 3 k αq or e k Gm k+1 D q,k+1,k,k n 2 k a 2 k a k+1 1/3 ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>the variation of n k may be neglected so that it may be taken to be equal to n k0 . Similarly a k is replaced by the corresponding fixed value a k0 . The above approximation scheme applies in the low eccentricity limit or sufficiently far away from strict commensurability such that |ωq| = |(q + 1)n k+1 − qn k0 | | n</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">1/3 k0 α 2/3 q .</formula><p>Given that in the same approximation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(20)</ref> implies that λ k+1 − λ k = (n k+1 − n k0 )t, equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(46)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(47)</ref> describe a linear system with prescribed harmonic forcing that is easily solved exactly. The solution in the limit tc → ∞ may be written</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">x = x 0 + ∞ p=1 =q αp cos[(p − q)(λ k+1 − λ k )] (p + 1)n k+1 − pn k (49) y = − ∞ p=1 =q αp sin[(p − q)(λ k+1 − λ k )] (p + 1)n k+1 − pn k ,<label>(50)</label></formula><p>where x 0 = αq/ωq. This indicates oscillation about the mean value of x = x 0 .</p><p>In the absence of the periodic forcing circularization would cause the solution to approach x = x 0 , y = 0 corresponding to a precise commensurability with zero libration amplitude. When the forcing is present, there is either libration or circulation depending on the ratio of the forcing amplitude to x 0 . When q + 1 : q is the closest commensurability, this can be small resulting in small amplitude libration. When some other commensurability is dominant, the motion in the (x, y) plane is around an approximately circular curve that encloses the origin and so corresponds to circulation. Thus as the system moves through a commensurabilty the motion is expected to change from circulation to libration to circulation (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Terquem &amp; Papaloizou 2007</ref> for an example of evolution away from a first order commensurability driven by orbital circularization). Note that in all of these cases the time dependent averages of quantities such as e k cos(φ q,k+1,k,k ) ≡ x and cos(φ q,k+1,k,k ) are generally non zero (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Papaloizou &amp; Terquem 2010)</ref>. In order to calculate the rate of energy dissipation resulting from orbital circularization and hence the rate of evolution it causes, we require the time average of the square of the eccentricity. This is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">e 2 k = x 2 + y 2 = ∞ p=1 α 2 p [(p + 1)n k+1 − pn k ] 2 .<label>(51)</label></formula><p>We remark that this expression connects to that found for the tight resonance example (38). The latter expression is identical to that given by (51) if only one term is retained that corresponds to the tight commensurability considered. Thus we expect the evolution to continue to be dominated by the closest comensurability until another becomes closer and takes over governing the evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">The orbital evolution of the planet</head><p>The rate of change of the orbital energy may be obtained from consideration of (51) and (23) together with the discussion leading to equation (3) given in section 2.1 with the result that</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">dE k dt ≡ − m k a 2 k n k n k+1 3 d dt n k n k+1 = − m k n 2 k a 2 k (1 − n k+1 /n k )t c,k ∞ p=1 α 2 p [(p + 1)n k+1 − pn k ] 2</formula><p>(52) which means that the orbit of m k contracts and separates from that of m k+1 . In the limit m k /m k+1 → 0 in which n k+1 becomes fixed, and close to a commensurability (52) becomes equivalent to (40). Thus it enables the discussion of the situation corresponding to a tight commensurability to be extended to conditions away from close commensurability. In view if the fact that n k /n k+1 must always increase, such a discussion leads to the conclusion that the evolution will be controlled by successive first order comensurabilities as the system widens (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Terquem &amp; Papaloizou 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Numerical Simulations</head><p>We here describe simulations of model planetary systems in which commensurabilties have been formed subsequently evolving under the influence of circularization tides.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Model and initial conditions</head><p>We consider a primary star together with N planets embedded in a gaseous disk surrounding it. The planets undergo gravitational interaction with each other and the star and are acted on by tidal forces from the disk and star. The system is solved as an N -body problem. Tidal interactions are incorporated by applying appropriate dissipative forces (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Terquem &amp; Papaloizou 2007 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Papaloizou &amp; Terquem 2010</ref> for more details and examples). The equations of motion may be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">d 2 r i dt 2 = − GM r i |r i | 3 − N j=1 =i Gm j0 (r i − r j ) |r i − r j | 3 − Γ + Γ i + Γr ,<label>(53)</label></formula><p>where M , m j0 and r j denote the mass of the central star, that of planet j and the position vector of planet j, respectively. The acceleration of the coordinate system based on the central star (indirect term) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">Γ = N j=1 Gm j0 r j |r j | 3 ,<label>(54)</label></formula><p>and that due to tidal interaction with the disk and/or the star is dealt with through the addition of dissipative forces (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Papaloizou &amp; Larwood 2000)</ref>. Thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">Γ i = − 1 t mg,i dr i dt − 2 |r i | 2 t e,i dr i dt · r i r i − 2 t i,i dr i dt · ez ez,<label>(55)</label></formula><p>where t mg,i , t e,i and t i,i are the timescales over which, respectively, the angular momentum, the eccentricity and the inclination with respect to the unit normal ez to the assumed fixed gas disk midplane change. Evolution of the angular momentum and inclination is assumed to be due to tidal interaction with the disk, whereas evolution of the eccentricity is assumed to occur due to both tidal interaction with the disk and the star. We have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">1 t e,i = 1 t d c,i + 1 t c,i ,<label>(56)</label></formula><p>where t d c,i and t c,i are the contribution from the disk and tides raised by the star, respectively. Relativistic effects are modeled through Γr ( see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Papaloizou &amp; Terquem 2001)</ref>.</p><p>Because a low mass planet cannot contain a significant quantity of angular momentum, tides raised on it by interaction with the star are assumed not to modify the angular momentum of the orbit. We remark that the orbital decay timescale, due to tides raised on the star, is readily estimated to be much longer than any timescale of interest (eg. Barnes et al 2009) thus these tides are ignored from now on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Orbital circularization due to tides from the central star</head><p>The circularization timescale due to tidal interaction with the star, in the small eccentricity limit appropriate here, is taken to be <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">( Goldreich &amp; Soter 1966)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_52">t c,i = 4.65 × 10 4 M M 3/2 M ⊕ m i0 2/3 20a i 1 au 6.5 Q years,<label>(57)</label></formula><p>where a i is the semi-major axis of planet i. Here we have adopted a mass density of 1 g cm 3 for the planets (uncertainties in this quantity could be incorporated into a redefinition of Q ). The parameter Q = 3Q/(2k 2 ), where Q is the tidal dissipation function and k 2 is the Love number. For solar system planets in the terrestrial mass range, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Goldreich &amp; Soter (1966)</ref> give estimates for Q in the range 10-500 and k 2 ∼ 0.3, which correspond to Q in the range 50-2500. We remark that this parameter should be regarded as being very uncertain for extrasolar planets. As computations with increasing Q become prohibitive on account of long evolution times, we have considered values of Q of 1.5 and 3 in this paper. However, we have obtained scaling relations which indicate how to scale results to larger Q .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Type I migration</head><p>When a planet is in contact with the disk, disk-planet interactions occur leading to orbital migration as well as eccentricity and inclination damping (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ward 1997)</ref>. However, the migration rates to be used are uncertain even when the disk surface density is known, largely because of uncertainties regarding the effectiveness of coorbital torques (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Paardekooper &amp; Melema 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">, Pardekooper &amp; Papaloizou 2008</ref>. In this context there are indications from modelling the observational data that the adopted type I migration rate should be significantly below that predicted by the linear calculations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Tanaka et al. (2002)</ref> (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Schlaufman et al 2009)</ref>. Hence we have carried out simulations with t mg,i and t d e,i for any system <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> The evolution of two planets that form a 3:2 commensurability. The early evolution of the period ratio during convergent migration is shown in the upper left panel. The upper right panel shows the evolution of the period ratio under orbital circularization after disk migration ceases. The uppermost curve is for Q = 1.5 and the lower curve is for Q = 3. The triangles/diamonds correspond to the analytic predictions made from equation (42) adapted to the case of a 3:2 commensurability for Q = 1.5/Q = 3 respectively. The evolution of the eccentricity of the outermost planet is plotted in the lower left panel for Q = 1.5. The evolution of the resonant angle 3λ 2 − 2λ 1 − 1 is plotted in the lower right panel for Q = 1.5.</p><p>taken, as for type I migration, to be proportional to 1/m i and adopted t i,i = t d e,i . A range of scaling constants was explored. These are quoted together with corresponding numerical results below.</p><p>We remark that provided that eccentricity damping limits eccentricities to small values, the commensurabilities that are formed in the system as a consequence of convergent migration depend on the ratio of the adopted migration rate to the local orbital frequency, with commensurabilities of low order and low degree forming when this ratio is small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Numerical results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">A system with a 3:2 commensurability</head><p>For the calculatioas presented in this section we adopted masses for the two planets and the central star that coincided with those for the star and two innermost planets of the GJ581 system. Thus the inner planet was taken to have a mass m 1 = 1.94M ⊕ and to be in circular orbit at 0.16au. The outer planet was taken to have a mass m i = 15.64M oplus and to be in a circular orbit at 0.32au. Tests indicate that the results of simulations of the type described here do not depend on the longitudes at which the planets are inserted on such circular orbits. The central mass was 0.31M . The initial semi-major axes were chosen to be larger than the corresponding ones in the GJ581 system so as to allow for some inward migration. The disk migration and circularization rates adopted were given by </p><p>However, they were only applied when the semi-major axis of a planet exceeded 0.041au. This procedure results in the final semi-major axis of the outer planet to coincide with the second planet in the GJ581 system. The termination of disk migration could be regarded as either being due to entry into an inner cavity, or simply removal of the disk. The migration rate was chosen so as to enable the planets to settle into a 3:2 commensurability through convergent migration. A very much slower rate would allow trapping in a 2:1 commensurability, while a very much faster one would result in the system passing through the 3:2 commensurability (see eg. <ref type="bibr">Papaloizou &amp; Szuskewicz 2010)</ref>. We remark that although the specific parameters chosen correspond to the GJ581 system, the aruments presented above indicate that the form of evolution we find should be generic for two low mass planets attaining a first order commensurability through convergent migration. The evolution of the system is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. The early evolution of the period ratio during convergent migration is shown in the upper left panel. It is seen that the system is trapped in a 2:1 commensurability for a while before escaping to be subsequently trapped in a 3:2 commensurability. After about 2 × 10 4 yr. the forces from the disk cease to act and the system evolves under tidal circularization. The upper right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> shows the evolution of the period ratio. Results for simulations with Q = 1.5 and Q = 3 are illustrated and compared to analytic predictions derived from equation (42) adapted to the cases on hand. Interestingly the numerical results are in quite good agreement with what is expected from the analytic discussion given in section 3 which assumed a small libration amplitude and which led to equation (42), even in regimes where the amplitude of libration of the resonant angle is quite large. However, the simulations show additional sudden small jumps in the period ratio which occur when the system passes through the 5:3 resonance. This jump was larger for the Q = 1.5 case than for the Q = 3 case. The evolution of the resonant angle 3λ 2 − 2λ 1 − 1 for Q = 1.5. shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> indicates an increasing amplitude libration that tends to break down near the end of the simulation when the period ratio ∼ 1.7 as in GJ581. But note that there is also a short temporary breakdown as the system passes through 5:3 resonance. Note that the anlaytic treatment suggests the time for the period ratio to evolve <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> The evolution of two planets that form a 5:3 commensurability. The early evolution of the period ratio during convergent migration is shown in the upper left panel. The upper right panel shows the evolution of the period ratio under orbital circularization after disk migration ceases. The uppermost curve is for Q = 1.5 and the lower curve is for Q = 3. The evolution of the eccentricity of the outermost planet is plotted in the lower left panel. The evolution of the resonant angle 3λ 2 − 2λ 1 − 1 is plotted in the lower right panel. from 1.5 to 1.7 to be ∼ 5 × 10 6 yr. The simulation with Q = 1.5. rather fortuitously agrees very well with this. The analytic prediction for Q = 3 is 10 7 yr. while the simulations discussed in this and the next section indicate 1.3 × 10 7 yr. Given the expectation that evolution times are ∝ Q , this indicates that values of Q as large as a few hundred could have allowed the period ratio to move from 1.5 to the present value within the lifetime of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6">A system with a 5:3 commensurability</head><p>For the calculations presented in this section we adopted the same values for the central mass and the planet masses as in section 4.5. However, we adopted initial conditions, migration and circularization rates so as to enable the system to settle into a 5:3 commensurability. Thus the inner planet was started in circular orbit at 0.08au and the outer planet in a circular orbit at 0.16au in this case. The disk migration and circularization rates adopted were given by </p><p>Thus the convergent migration rate was two and a half times faster and the circularization rate four times slower than for the calculation in section 4.5. However, they were applied in the same way. The faster migration rate and the slower eccentricity damping rate allows trapping in the 5:3 resonance. The early evolution of the period ratio during convergent migration is shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. It is seen that the system becomes trapped in a 2:1 commensurability before escaping to form a 5:3 commensurability. After about 8 × 10 4 yr. the forces from the disk cease to act and the system evolves under tidal circularization.</p><p>The upper right panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> shows the evolution of the period ratio under orbital circularization after disk migration ceases for Q = 1.5 and Q = 3. Although the system started in a 5:3 commensurability, the evolution can be regarded as matching onto that illustrated in the previous section which can be regarded as being driven by the 3 : 2 comensurability. This is also confirmed by the evolution the resonant angle 3λ 2 − 2λ 1 − 1 also plotted in <ref type="figure">Fig.2</ref>. We also remark that the time for the period ratio to move from 5/3 to 1.7 is about twice as large for Q = 3 as for Q = 1.5 as expected. However, these times are only approximately 1.8 × 10 6 and 3.6×10 6 yr. respectvely indicating that values of Q up to 10 3 could be effective within the lifetime of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.7">Adding additional planets</head><p>Here the effect of adding additional planets to the simulation described above is investigated. To do this we take the calculation of section 4.6 at the point at which forces arising from the disk cease to act. Two additional planets of masses 5.36M ⊕ and 7.09M ⊕ are added in circular orbits with semi-major axes 0.07au and 0.22au respectively. These correspond to the two outermost planets in the GJ581 system. We remark that the eccentricities of these planets were determined to be consistent with zero by <ref type="bibr">Vogt et al. (2010)</ref>. As before we considered runs for which Q = 1.5 and Q = 3. In this case the same value of Q was adopted for each planet.</p><p>The results are plotted in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. The evolution in this case is for the most part similar to that illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> for two planets. In particular approximately the same time is taken for the period ratio for the innermost pair of planets to move from 5/3 to 1.7. However, a significant difference is that the evolution of the period ratio slows down briefly between 1.5×10 7 and 2.0×10 7 yr. in the simulation with Q = 3. During this time the eccentricity of the second innermost planet is increased. Although the reasons for this are unclear, it is associated with an interaction between the second and third innermost planets. The innermost planet continues to move inwards but the angular momentum ends up being transferred to the third rather than the second innermost planet. There does not seem to be any clear resonance associated with this. However, we comment that in a many planet system like this, we could consider a tension between possible interacting pairs. The <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> The evolution of two planets illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> but with two additional outer planets added after the disk migration phase as indicated in the text. The upper right panel shows the evolution of the period ratio of the innermost two planets under orbital circularization. The uppermost curve is for Q = 1.5 and the lower curve is for Q = 3. The evolution of the eccentricity of the second innermost planet is plotted in the upper left panel. The evolution of the resonant angle 3λ 2 − 2λ 1 − 1 is plotted in the lower left panel. The behaviour of the angle between the apsidal lines of the orbits of the second innermost and innermost planets is illustrated in the lower right panel.</p><p>second and third planets would separate on account of tidal circularization if the innermost planet were absent. Similarly the innermost pair can couple as in section 4.6. In some circumstances, dependent on their masses, orbital parameters, and values of Q etc., different interacting pairs may have varying levels of importance in the simulation. This requires a more detailed study than we have been able to perform at this preliminary stage that will be the subject of future work. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> The evolution of two planets in a 3:1 commensurability is illustrated. The left uppermost panel shows the evolution of the semi-major axes of the two planets. The initial period of disk migration is short &lt;∼ 4.5 × 10 6 yr. The subsequent evolution is driven by tidal circularization with Q = 100 and the gravitational interaction between the planets. The upper left panel shows the evolution of the period ratio. This remains 3:1 for some time after disk migration has ceased before finally increasing as the planets separate. The lower left panel shows the evolution of the eccentricities of the two planets, the uppermost curve corresponding to the inner planet. The lower right panel shows the angle between the apsidal lines of the orbits of the outer and inner planets, which ultimately remains close to π.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.8">A system with a 3:1 commensurability</head><p>Finally we describe a situation in which a 3 : 1 commensurability could be formed under convergent migration and then subsequently maintained. The parameters of this simulation were chosen to lead to a separation of pairs similar to the third and fourth innermost planets in the HD 10180 system for which there may have been a past proximity to a 3:1 commensurability.</p><p>In this case the central mass was taken to be 1M ⊕ . The inner planet mass was taken to be 11.73M ⊕ and the outer planet taken to be 25.07M ⊕ . Their initial semi-major axes were 0.387au and 1.2au respecively. The outer planet was started in circular orbit while the inner planer was started at apocentre with an eccentricity e = 0.24. The disk migration and circularization rates adopted were given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">t mig = t c,i = 1.4 × 10 8 M ⊕ m i yr.<label>(60)</label></formula><p>These were applied only when the planets semi-major axes exceeded 0.29au. Note that this migration rate is very much lower than the previous cases so as to enable trapping in the 3 : 1 resonance. The ecentricity damping rate is taken to be equal to the migration rate so that the eccentricities do not damp too quickly so enabling the 3:1 resonance to persist. Rates like these are not readily produced in calculations of disk planet interactions for which the planets are fully embedded. They may be possible if the planets are located within a wide cavity. However, this aspect remains to be investigated. Here we simply adopt these rates and explore their consequences. Because of the larger planetary masses and larger orbital eccentricities in this run, it was possible to consider larger values of Q . We adopted Q = 100. The evolution of the two planets in this simulation is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. The planets undergo convergent migration and attain a 3:1 resonance. The eccentricity of the inner planet grows up to ∼ 0.56. The growth ceases after ∼ 4 × 10 6 yr. when effects arising from the disk cease to act. After this time the planets evolve under tidal circularization. For about 50 million years the commensurability is maintained while the eccentricty of the inner planet decreases and that of the outer one increases. In this process angular momentum is transferred to the inner planet. However, this form of evolution cannot be maintained and it reverts to the situation where the planets separate in semi-major axis as descibed in section 2.1 while the eccentricities decrease. The period ratio secularly increases while the angle between the apsidal lines of the orbits of the outer and inner planets remains close to π.</p><p>Interestingly at least five resonance passages were seen during this later evolutionary stage. As the period ratio increased, these corresponded to the 19:6, 16:5, 13:4, 10:3 and 7:2 resonances. They are manifested as local blips in the eccentricity evolution of both planets as shown in the lower left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. The resonance passages are of decreasing order with increasing time and so the consequent changes induced in the planetary eccentricities increase in magnitude. The fact high order resonances such as 19 : 6 were manifest in this run is because of the relatively high eccentricities, in particular of ∼ 0.3 for the inner planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>In this paper we have studied systems of close orbiting planets evolving under the influence of tidal circularization. We considered the situation where the system evolved under the influence of disk tides to form a commensurability. After the disk tides ceased to operate, either because of entry into an inner cavity, or because of loss of the disk, the operation of tidal circularization caused increasing departure from any close commensurability as time progressed.</p><p>In section2.1 we pointed out that a system of planets in near circular orbits is expected to separate on average as energy is dissipated while angular momentum is conserved. This is also expected in the very similar situation of an accretion disk evolving under a viscosity (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lynden-Bell &amp; Pringle 1974)</ref>. In the simplest case of two planets, this inevitable increasing physical separation has to lead to the increasing departure from any initial commensurability.</p><p>In sections 2.2, 2.3 and 3, we developed a formalism that could be adapted study the evolution of two planets near to a first order commensurability under the influence of tidal circularization. This was then applied to a system with a tight commensurability in section 3.1. An expression for the departure from commensurability, indicating this to be ∝ t 1/3 , was given (see equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(42)</ref>). The discussion was then extended to the situation when the two planets were not necessarily in a close commensurability in section 3.2. The orbital evolution of the planet in that case, leading to a neighbouring commensurability, was then considered in section 3.3.</p><p>In order to confirm the analytic modeling, numerical simulations were under taken in section 4. We were able to set up systems of low mass planets in varying commensurabilities, depending on the strengths of the disk tides leading to orbital migration and circularization, with weaker tides in general leading to more widely separated commensurabilities. We focused on a two planet system which had the same parameters as the innermost two planets as the GJ581 system in section 4.5. This formed a 3:2 commensurability which then evolved under orbital circularization. This model system attained the period ratio of the actual system after ∼ 10 8 yr. when Q ∼ 1. Simple extrapolation thus indicates that tidal evolution could have moved the system to the present period ratio of 1.7 from a 3:2 commensurability if Q ∼ 100. Similarly the situation when the system initially attained a 5:3 commensurability was studied in section 4.6. In this case the evolution quickly adapted to evolve as for the case with the initial 3:2 commensurability when that had reached the same period ratio. However, a larger value Q would suffice to cause the period ratio to move from 5:3 to the observed one within a given life time. The effect of adding the additional planets in the GJ581 system was considered in section 4.7. In that case over the long term the extra planets did not greatly affect the evolution. However, for a brief period the third planet moved outwards taking up the angular momentum of the innermost planet rather than the second, with the consequence that the period separation rate for the innermost pair was slowed. Thus a pair of planets may not always evolve independently of others in the system, a feature that requires further study.</p><p>Finally the evolution of a system that formed a 3:1 commensurability was considered in section 4.8. The model system adopted had similar parameters to the third and fourth innermost planets in the HD 10180 system. This case required slow disk migration and weak circularization with the result that the resonance involved high eccentricities. Because of these the commensurability could be maintained for a while under orbital circularization. However, eventually the system increasingly departed from it as in the other cases. Finally all of our results indicate that if Q &lt;∼ 100, commensurabilities would have been significantly affected by tidal effects related to orbital circularization. Thus the survival of close commensurabilities in observed systems may be indicative of the presence of large Q values, a feature which in turn may be related to the internal structure of the planets involved.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>t</head><label></label><figDesc>mig = 4.375 × 10 5 M ⊕ m i yr. and t c,i = 5 × 10 2 M ⊕ m i yr.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>t</head><label></label><figDesc>mig = 1.75 × 10 5 M ⊕ m i yr. and t c,i = 2 × 10 3 M ⊕ m i yr.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The HD 40307 Planetary System: Super-Earths or Mini-Neptunes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">695</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1006" to="1011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets. VI. A Neptune-mass planet around the nearby M dwarf Gl 581</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">443</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Methods of celestial mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Clemence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1961" />
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="421" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origin and nature of Neptune-like planets orbiting close to solar type stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brunini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cionco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Q in the Solar System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets. XXVII. Up to seven planets orbiting HD 10180: probing the architecture of lowmass planetary systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sgransan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of viscous discs and the origin of the nebular variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lynden-Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pringle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets. XVIII. An Earth-mass planet in the GJ 581 planetary system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">507</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="494" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="644" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>XIII. A planetary system with 3 super-Earths (4.2, 6.9</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Solar System Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="255" />
			<pubPlace>Cambridge England</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disc-Planet Interactions: Migration and Resonances in Extrasolar Planetary Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cel. Mech. and Dynam. Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the orbital evolution and growth of protoplanets embedded in a gaseous disc</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Larwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="833" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the migration-induced resonances in a system of two planets with masses in the Earth mass range</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Szuszkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditions for the occurrence of mean-motion resonances in a low mass planetary system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Szuszkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EAS Publications Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical relaxation and massive extrasolar planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Terquem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the dynamics of multiple systems of hot super-Earths and Neptunes: tidal circularization, resonance and the HD 40307 system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Terquem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">405</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="592" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Halting type I planet migration in non-isothermal disks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mellema</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On disc protoplanet interactions in a nonbarotropic disc with thermal diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">485</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="877" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On corotation torques, horseshoe drag and the possibility of sustained stalled or outward protoplanetary migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2283" to="2296" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observable consequences of planet formation models in systems with close-in terrestrial planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="674" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Signature of the Ice Line and Modest Type I Migration in the Observed Exoplanet Mass-Semimajor Axis Distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schlaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Apj</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">691</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1322" to="1327" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The orbital resonance amongst the Galilean satellites of Jupiter</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="72" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-Dimensional Interaction between a Planet and an Isothermal Gaseous Disk. I. Corotation and Lindblad Torques and Planet Migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1274" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migration and the Formation of Systems of Hot SuperEarths and Neptunes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Terquem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">654</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1110" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The HARPS search for southern extra-solar planets. XI. Super-Earths (5 and 8 M ⊕ ) in a 3-planet system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Lick-Carnegie Exoplanet Survey: A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M ⊕</forename><surname>Planet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">the Habitable Zone of the Nearby M3V Star Gliese 581</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">723</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="965" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protoplanet Migration by Nebula Tides</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
