<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Why exomoons must be rare?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rosaev</forename><forename type="middle">A E</forename></persName>
							<email>hegem@mail.ru</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Research and Educational Center &quot;Nonlinear Dynamics&quot;</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yaroslavl State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yaroslavl</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Why exomoons must be rare?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Despite the discovery of thousands of exoplanets and significant efforts to find, no exomoons have been detected so far <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>A survey of 41 Kepler Objects of Interest (KOIs) for exomoons finds no compelling evidence for exomoons although thirteen KOIs yield spurious detections driven by instrumental artifacts, stellar activity and/or perturbations from unseen bodies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> The light curve of 1SWASP J140747.93-394542.6, can be interpreted as the transit of a giant ring system that is filling up a fraction of the Hill sphere of an unseen secondary companion, J1407b. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> There are few methods suggested to exomoon search for. New method to determine an exomoon's described and tested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Two methods to determine an exomoon's suggested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Simulations show that the required measurements will be possible with the European Extremely Large Telescope (E-ELT). Both new methods can be used to probe the origin of exomoons, that is, whether they are regular or irregular in nature. <ref type="bibr">[</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2]</head><p>But how many exomoons we may expect to discover? There are large numbers of satellites are known in our Solar System. But dynamical conditions for moons are remarkable different in exoplanetary systems and in our solar system. There are few types of the satellites instabilities occur in exoplanetary systems.</p><p>Authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> show the dynamical instability that can happen to close-in satellites when planet oblateness is not accounted for in non-coplanar multiplanet systems. With a spherical host planet, moons within a critical planetocentric distance experience high inclinations and in some cases high eccentricities, while more distant moons orbit stably with low inclinations and eccentricities, as expected. Instability occurs while the nodal precession of the satellite and the central star (as seen from the host planet's frame) approaches the 1:1 secular resonance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> The instability of close-to-planet exomoon due to evection resonance perturbation is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. According their results, orbits of exomoons close to planets (within 10 planet radius) cannot have long lifetime. Here we give a very simple example of the other type of exomoon's instability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The idea description</head><p>Let to consider planar three body problem (RTBP). Geometry of problem is given in <ref type="figure">fig.1</ref>. Main notations are: m 1 -main body or reduced mass in barycentre, m 2 -secondary mass m 3 -infinitesimal test particle, f -is a gravity constant, V i -respective velocities, ij  -distances between points. <ref type="figure">Fig.1</ref>. Problem geometry.</p><p>Let to consider a limit case m 3 =0. Hill sphere method is well known for studying stability of asteroid small satellite. If the mass of the smaller body (e.g. planet) is m, and it orbits a heavier body (e.g. Sun) of mass M with a semi-major axis a and an eccentricity of e, then the radius r of the Hill sphere for the smaller body (e.g. planet or asteroid primary) is, approximately <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">3 3 ) 1 ( M m e a r   (1)</formula><p>It means, that the stability zone for the satellite is decrease with eccentricity increasing. Moreover, the solar perturbations of satellite orbit of binary eccentric are strong If eccentricity decrease or constant, 0 ) (   t e , then relative energy is negative and m 3 orbit forever on as a satellite around m 2 . However, if eccentricity increase with time, 0 ) (   t e , then energy can become positive, the satellite is loosed.</p><p>Let us to consider Solar System case as an example. Secular resonances play an important role in the evolution of our Solar system. The inner edge of the belt nearly coincides with the ν6 secular resonance which is defined by g ≈ g6, where g is the rate of precession of the longitude of pericenter of an asteroid and g6 is the sixth eigenfrequency of the solar system planets (approximately the rate of precession of Saturn's longitude of pericenter). During the era of planet migration, the g6 resonance swept through the present position of inner asteroid belt (semimajor axis range 2.1-2.8 AU). The g6 sweeping leads to either an increase or a decrease of eccentricity depending on an asteroid's initial orbit.</p><p>The eccentricity change depends on initial value of eccentricity and Saturn migration rate. In according with theory Malhotra <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, maximal eccentricity when secular resonance crossing estimated by expression:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">a e e         ,<label>(2)</label></formula><note type="other">Where ) 2 exp( 10 5 . 3 6 9 g a     in range 4 2 6   g a and 11 13 10 10      depends on</note><p>planet migration rate. This result is confirmed by numeric integration. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. For example, increasing eccentricity from e 0 =0.1 up to e 0 = 0.3 -0.4 was observed. Authors studying case of massive satellite show, that estimation (1) need to be corrected and binary systems (like Earth-Moon in our Solar system) are rather less stable <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numeric experiment</head><p>In details, the method of modeling is described in <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref>. We have a Sun in the center of our system, planet with Jupiter mass in initially circular orbit. We add Earth and Saturn on fixed circular orbits as addition perturbers. We start with circular orbit of massless satellite at different distance from planet. After that, we numerically integrate motion of satellite during the planet eccentricity increase with different rate.</p><p>We start from initially circular orbits of satellite. Satellite orbits strongly perturbed and obtain significant eccentricity in a short time after their formation.</p><p>Extrasolar planets have orbits with significant eccentricity and close to resonances in many cases. Both circumstances make satellite lost easier. As a possible mechanism of eccentricity increasing, the crossing of secular and mean motion resonances is supposed.</p><p>First, we choose orbit close to action sphere radius. Results are given in tables 1-2. For satellite close to action sphere boundary, in all cases we observe ejection satellite when planetary eccentricity increases. As it is seems in table 1, time of satellite ejection and final eccentricity nonlinearly depends on rate of eccentricity growth. The dependence of time of satellite ejection on rate of eccentricity growth is very close to parabolic ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig.2)</ref>. In general, finally we have very chaotic unstable heliocentric orbit of ejected satellite. But in some cases we obtain low-eccentric heliocentric orbit of minor mass after ejection <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(table 2,</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">fig  3)</ref>.     After that, we continue calculations with satellite on initial orbit deeply inside planets Hill sphere. In this case ejection of satellite is not took place, but perturbations of initially circular satellite orbit are very significant.</p><p>During of their migrations, planets in multiplanetary systems cross a few secular resonances, with increasing their eccentricity. Observed large eccentricities of exoplanets point out on their strong perturbations in the process of migrations, when number of primordial exomoons are lost. In combination with conclusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> about close-to planets exomoons instability and observation evidence that number of exoplanets are very close to host stars (as following, have small Hill sphere), we cannot expect a large number of exomoons.</p><p>We can note, that exoplanets with large orbital periods in single-planetary systems are most probable candidates for exomoons search for.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The principal possibility of destruction a satellite system at heliocentric orbit eccentricity growth is shown in a very simple numeric model. As a possible mechanism of eccentricity increasing, the crossing of secular and mean motion resonances is supposed. Extrasolar planets have orbits with significant eccentricity and close to resonances in many cases. As a result, we cannot expect a large number of exomoons.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig.2.The dependence of satellite lifetime on eccentricity variation rate</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. The example of the satellite heliocentric eccentricity evolution at the planet eccentricity increasing</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Results of modeling of satellite ejection at planetary eccentricity growth</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Orbits 
# 

Planetocentric orbital elements 
Planet 
eccentricity rate 

e  , yr -1 

Planet 
eccentricity 
at satellite 
loss 

Time of 
satellite 
loss 

a R, km 
e 
i, o 

2 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.03 
0.25 
2550 
3 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.04 
0.30 
2320 
4 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.05 
0.23 
1400 
5 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.06 
0.23 
1200 
6 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.07 
0.32 
1420 
7 
20000000. 
0 
25 
0.08 
0.26 
1000 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . Final heliocentric orbit minor body after escape.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Orbits # 
a 
e 
i 

2 

4.1076272 
0.38365309 
4.1381682 

3 

3.0060638 
0.19886854 
2.9385271 

4 

5.6227030 
0.23397107 
2.6866698 

5 

8.0488002 
0.34716545 
5.4186269 

6 

11.3134293 
0.44063665 
14.428551 

7 

11.0543336 
0.58052517 
1.9007700 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Table 3 . Results of modeling of satellite ejection at planetary eccentricity growth</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Orbits 
# 

Planetocentric orbital 
elements 

Planet 
eccentricity 

rate e Time of 
satellite 
loss 

Planet 
eccentricity 

rate e  

yr-1 

a R, km 
e 
i, o 

2 
20000000. 
0 
5 
0.03 
1850 
0.00010 
3 
20000000. 
0 
5 
0.04 
1750 
0.00013 
4 
20000000. 
0 
5 
0.05 
1440 
0.00016 
5 
20000000. 
0 
5 
0.06 
1175 
0.00020 
6 
20000000. 
0 
5 
0.07 
1040 
0.00023 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 4 . Results of modeling of satellite ejection at planetary eccentricity growth</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Orbits 
# 

Planetocentric orbital 
elements 

Planet 
eccentricity 

rate e Time of 
satellite 
loss 

Planet 
eccentricity 

rate e  

yr-1 

a R, km 
e 
i, o 

2 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.03 
1940 
0.00010 
3 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.04 
1620 
0.00013 
4 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.05 
1175 
0.00016 
5 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.06 
1170 
0.00020 
6 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.07 
1010 
0.00023 
7 
20000000. 
0 
45 
0.08 
870 
0.00026 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the detection of exomoons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hippke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1502.05033v1[astro-ph.EP</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-02-17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How to determine an exomoon&apos;s sense of orbital motion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1409.7245v1[astro-ph.EP</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The hunt for exomoons with kepler (hek). v. a survey of 41 planetary candidates for exomoons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1503.05555v1[astro-ph.EP</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-03-18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">E: Modeling giant extrasolar ring systems in eclipse and the case of J1407B: sculpting by exomoons?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenworthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mamajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1501.05652v1[astro-ph.SR]22</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Orbital instability of close-in exomoons in non-coplanar systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y-S</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tiscareno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nicolson Ph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lunine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1502.04747v1[astro-ph.EP</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-02-16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resonant Removal of Exomoons during Planetary Migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Spalding Ch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Batygin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal, V</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">817</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orbital stability zones about asteroids. II -The destabilizing effects of eccentric orbits and of solar radiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Solar System Formation and Evolution: ASP Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Secular resonance sweeping of the main asteroid belt during planet migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Minton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1102.3131v1[astro-ph.EP]15</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secular resonance sweeping of asteroids during the late heavy bombardment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Minton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malhotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LPSC</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2481</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rosaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>arXiv:1304.6 892</idno>
		<title level="m">Stability of binary on highly eccentric orbit</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>astro-ph</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
