<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PRECISE POINTING OF CUBESAT TELESCOPES: COMPARISON BETWEEN HEAT AND LIGHT INDUCED ATTITUDE CONTROL METHODS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ravi</forename><surname>Teja Nallapu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jekan</forename><surname>Thangavelautham</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PRECISE POINTING OF CUBESAT TELESCOPES: COMPARISON BETWEEN HEAT AND LIGHT INDUCED ATTITUDE CONTROL METHODS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>CubeSats are emerging as low-cost tools to perform astronomy, exoplanet searches and earth observation. These satellites can target an object for science observation for weeks on end. This is typically not possible on larger missions where usage time is shared. The problem of designing an attitude control system for CubeSat telescopes is very challenging because current choice of actuators such as reaction-wheels and magnetorquers can induce jitter on the spacecraft due to moving mechanical parts and due to external disturbances. These telescopes may contain cryo-pumps and servos that introduce additional vibrations. A better solution is required. In our paper, we analyze the feasibility of utilizing solar radiation pressure (SRP) and radiometric force to achieve precise attitude control. Our studies show radiometric actuators to be a viable method to achieve precise pointing. The device uses 8 thin vanes of different temperatures placed in a near-vacuum chamber. These chambers contain trace quantities of lightweight, inert gasses like argon. The temperature gradient across the vanes causes the gas molecules to strike the vanes differently and thus inducing a force. By controlling these forces, it&apos;s possible to produce a torque to precisely point or spin a spacecraft. We present a conceptual design of a CubeSat that is equipped with these actuators. We then analyze the potential slew maneuver and slew rates possible with these actuators by simulating their performance. Our analytical and simulation results point towards a promising pathway for laboratory testing of this technology and demonstration of this technology in space.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>A spacecraft's attitude is typically controlled by reaction-wheels 1 , which are flywheels that trade their angular momentum with that of the spacecraft. However, as the reaction-wheels fight disturbance torques, they keep accumulating angular momentum; and eventually they reach their maximum rated angular momentum reaching saturation 2 . Despite low disturbance torques in space, the reaction wheel saturation is a problem for extended space missions in deep space such space telescope missions. Techniques to desaturate a reaction-wheel do exist such as magnetotorquer desaturation using the Earth's magnetic field or propulsion based desaturation in deep space <ref type="bibr">3</ref> . However, in the absence of a planetary magnetic field 4 , the magnetorquers become nonfunctional. Other techniques such as using an additional reaction wheel 5 becomes both expensive and limit the allowable mass and volume of the spacecraft. Hence there is a need for an attitude control actuator that is functional in deep-space and does not require propellant. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(Preprint)</head><p>For an Earth orbiting spacecraft, typical disturbances include atmospheric drag 6 , gravity gradient <ref type="bibr">7</ref> and solar radiation pressure (SRP) <ref type="bibr">8</ref> . However, in deep space the atmospheric drag and gravity gradient can be eliminated, leaving the SRP as the only known dominant disturbance. The SRP is the pressure exerted by the solar flux on an object in space and depends on the optical properties of the object exposed to the photons, such as specular reflectivity and absorptivity. Hence, one strategy to control the attitude can be to manipulate these properties, thus controlling the magnitude of the disturbance.</p><p>The IKAROS spacecraft 9 , launched by JAXA in 2010 used this technique to maneuver itself to Venus. Their spacecraft had a large, square solar-sail of diagonal length 20 m, and LCD cells embedded along the perimeter of the sail as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(left) to control the attitude of the spacecraft. These LCD cells are turned "on" and "off", which varies the reflectivity, thus changing the SRP acting upon the surface. In retrospect, the binary operation of switching the LCDs "on" or "off" can be further improved by advances in technology. Devices like the Transflector® <ref type="bibr">10</ref> and Smart Windows® 11 that switch states from a transparent glass to a mirror present interesting alternatives.</p><p>Another technology which has not yet been applied to space missions, but can be of great importance is radiometric forces, which are exemplified by the Crookes Radiometer 12 , shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(right). The Crookes Radiometer consists of 4 plates, called vanes that are colored white and black on opposite ends. The vanes are mounted on a spindle, and placed inside a partial vacuum chamber, typically consisting of trace amounts of argon. When the setup is exposed to sunlight, the vane-spindle starts to spin. This phenomenon has been widely misunderstood, with many proposing photons hitting the vanes and causing the force. However it is Thermal Creep force <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">13</ref> , which is a radiometric force that causes the vane to spin and is further described in the paper.</p><p>This paper intends to apply and compare the performance of these two phenomena: light and heat to the small satellite attitude control problem. Specifically, we compare the magnitudes of these two forces, in their scalar form, and then analyze their application to an on-orbit centrifuge science laboratory mission such as AOSAT 1 14,24,25 using a CubeSat <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">17</ref> . We begin by briefly introducing the two phenomena. Following this, the application of this technology to CubeSats is discussed by designing hypothetical actuators. We then compare the magnitudes of the forces fol-lowed by performance comparison of these two actuators in the results section. Finally, we summarize the findings in the conclusion section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PHYSICS OF THE PHENOMENA</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Solar Radiation Pressure Force</head><p>The SRP force is caused by photons striking the surface of a spacecraft. Consider a spacecraft whose position vector relative to the sun is as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. Let A be the area of each face, and let the face under consideration have an outward normal vector whose direction is . Let the normal subtend an angle θ with the unit vector (direction of ). In this case, the magnitude of SRP 15 acting on the whole spacecraft is given by:</p><p>(1)</p><p>Here G 1 denotes the solar constant whose value is 1E14 kg-km/s 2 , and 'i' denotes the index of all those faces that face the sun, i.e.,</p><p>. Since the SRP depends on the inclination between the sun-vector and the spacecraft normal, we look at the maximum value of SRP, which occurs when θ i =0 Degrees, i.e., when aligns with . Hence the maximum available SRP is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(2)</formula><p>The positive coefficients, c dif and c sr, when added constitute the total coefficient of reflection which varies between 0 and 1 and hence we can relate these coefficients as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(3)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radiometric Forces</head><p>The radiometric force is observed when a gas is exposed to a surface with a temperature gradient. In the above example, the gradient is created by the vanes as the black side of the vane absorbs more light and becomes hotter than the white side. In this setup, two forces are generated <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">13</ref> : A normal pressure force exerted by the gas molecules as they strike the black side with higher momentum, and a thermal creep force occurs as the gas molecules strike the edges of the vanes. The two forces are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. The net radiometric force then is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">F R = F N + F' S<label>(4)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3. Radiometric forces acting on a vane with a temperature gradient</head><p>Consider a vane with a temperature gradient as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>, where the hotter side is at a temperature T h and the colder side is at T c . Let l, w, and d, represent the length, width, and thickness respectively. Let this vane be placed in a rarefied gas with a gas kinetic diameter σ. In this case, the normal force 16 is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(5)</formula><p>where, α is the coefficient of thermal accommodation, ∆T is the temperature difference T h -T c , P is the perimeter of the vane, and k is the Boltzmann constant. The Thermal Creep force 17 is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(6)</formula><p>where, x is a correction factor to compensate for slip reduction due to opposing forces, l' and w' are reduced length and width of the vane due to non-reactive drag forces given by equations 7 and 8 respectively and are associated with a numerical factor β. Also, w grad is the width of the gradient given by equation 9. The thermal creep force only comes into play when the thickness of the vane is comparable to the gas mean free path λ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(7) (8)<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Both the pressure force (equation 5) and the creep force (equation 6) are directed from the hot side towards the cold side. We refer the readers to Scandurra <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">16</ref> and Wolfe 17 for a complete derivation of equations 5 through 9.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application to Spacecrafts</head><p>In this section, we describe the actuators that use light and heat respectively to control the attitude of a 3U CubeSat <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">18</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SRP based actuators.</head><p>We let the chassis walls of the spacecraft be covered by a switchable glass-mirror technology such as an E-TransFlector®, and the spacecraft walls are embedded with sun sensors 19 that can track the sun vector. With this setup, a feedback controller can be developed to orient the spacecraft as desired. A conceptual design of this spacecraft is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>, the blue tinted areas represent the surface that has transformed to a mirror, while the white surfaces are transparent. By switching between the 'mirror' and 'transparent glass' modes we can induce SRP as desired. The moment arm vector, R 1 , joins the center of gravity g to the center of pressure p 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radiometric Actuators</head><p>Let's consider an alternate attitude actuator that exploits the radiometric force 20 . We let the chassis walls of the CubeSat be covered with a glass chamber filled with trace amounts of argon. The chamber contains 8 vane plates arranged in a 2×2 matrix. The 2 matrices touch each other, and are affixed to the glass chamber as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>. The vanes are equipped with ThermoElectric Devices (TED) such as the one mentioned in Reference 21 and temperature sensors so that their temperature can be controlled and measured.   Vanes in red represent the 'hot' vanes while vanes in blue represent the 'cold' vanes. Also, as seen in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>, the vanes in contact have contrasting temperature to create the temperature gradient. The center of mass of the spacecraft is shown as g, while p 2 is the center of pressure on the face shown. The moment arm vector R 2 joins g and p 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PERFORMANCE COMPARISION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Force Magnitudes</head><p>Consider a single face of the SRP actuator, and 1 hot-cold vane pair shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figures 5 and 6</ref>. Let the two faces being compared have the same geometry. The parameters considered for this simulation are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The magnitude of the SRP force and radiometric forces are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 7</ref>. As seen here, the radiometric force can be up to 2 orders of magnitude greater than the maximum available SRP. It should be noted that the maximum SRP cannot be realized because of nonalignment with the sun vector and due to the inequality of equation 3. On the contrary, the radiometric forces can vary linearly with temperature as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 7</ref> (right).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single Axis Spin</head><p>Consider the same single faces of actuators shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figures 5 and 6</ref>, now let the SRP face be modified such that the top half is purely specular (c sr =1), and its bottom half is purely absorptive (c sr =0), this is to ensure that the SRP torque generated is a maximum. Also, let the radiometric actuator being compared have 4 vanes that are arranged as 2 2×1 matrices facing each other, creating a temperature gradient between them. In the case of the radiometric actuator we assume a temperature gradient of ∆T =5 o C across the thickness and perform a dynamics simulation in software. The two actuators are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref>, along with the direction of the intended slew. Attitude propagation was done by solving Euler's equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">22</ref> with quaternions <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">23</ref> . In this case, the spin is about the body x-axis as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref>, which is the spacecraft roll. The propagated roll angles in both the cases are presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 9</ref>. As seen here, it takes about 72 minutes to perform a complete 360 o rotation with SRP, whereas, it only takes about 3.5 minutes with a radiometric force actuator which is a 20-fold improvement.</p><p>Most spacecraft missions can just be realized with slew maneuvers, however with science-led missions like AOSAT 1, there is a critical need to perform attitude maneuvers throughout the mission. AOSAT 1 for instance will be spinning at 1 RPM in Low Earth Orbit (LEO). We examine the applicability of these methods to AOSAT 1. Specifically, we compare the angular velocity response of the two methods ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>). Inferring from the slope of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> (left), it takes an SRP based system about 2 days to reach up to 1 RPM, which makes it impractical. On the other hand, a radiometric actuator system can reach 1 RPM within 7 minutes with a ∆T of 5 o C, as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> (right). This shows that the radiometric actuator has a 400-fold advantage over SRP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper compares two new methods to control attitude of a spacecraft, using solar radiation pressure method (light) and radiometric method (heat), for deep space missions at 1 AU. The magnitudes of the maximum available solar radiation pressure force and the radiometric forces were compared. It was found that the radiometric actuator for a temperature gradient of about 50 o C, can provide a force that is 2 orders of magnitude greater than the maximum solar radiation pressure force. The two actuators were also compared based on their roll and slew rate performance. It was found that the SRP actuators were much slower when compared to the radiometric actuators. These results lead us to the conclusions that the solar radiation pressure actuators are slow, and that can be applied to missions that need precise pointing, because of the finer slew rates. However, due to the inverse square law dependence of the solar distance, their application can be practical only in the inner solar system. On the other hand, the radiometric actuators provide greater force magnitudes, and therefore faster slew and spin performance. Also, since these are not dependent on an external source, the radiometric actuators can work anywhere in deep space. However, the challenge of creating the required temperature gradient does exist, and will be fully addressed in a future paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REFERENCES</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 . Technologies that exemplify photometric and radiometric forces: IKAROS Spacecraft (left) and Crookes Radiometer (Right)</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Technologies that exemplify photometric and radiometric forces: IKAROS Spacecraft (left) and Crookes Radiometer (Right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 . CubeSat face exposed to solar radiation.</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. CubeSat face exposed to solar radiation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 . Conceptual spacecraft utilizing solar radiation pressure to control its attitude (left). A cross-section view shows the moment arm (right).</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Conceptual spacecraft utilizing solar radiation pressure to control its attitude (left). A cross-section view shows the moment arm (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 . Conceptual Radiometric actuator, Front view (left) and back view (right).</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Conceptual Radiometric actuator, Front view (left) and back view (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 shows</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6 shows the actuators fixed onto the walls of a 3U CubeSat, along with the moment arm vector shown on the right.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 . Conceptual CubeSat with radiometric actuators (left) with an cross-section view to show the moment arm (right).</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Conceptual CubeSat with radiometric actuators (left) with an cross-section view to show the moment arm (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Comparing magnitudes of maximum SRP (left) and radiometric forces (right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Two actuators being compared: SRP (left) and Radiometric (Right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Roll propagation with SRP (left) and radiometric forces (right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 10 . Angular velocity propagation with SRP (left) and radiometric forces (right)</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Angular velocity propagation with SRP (left) and radiometric forces (right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Simulation Parameters</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Parameter 
Value (Units) 

Length 
30 cm 

Width (vane-pair and SRP film) 
10 cm 

Each length 
15 cm 

Thickness (vane-pair and SRP film) 
0.1 cm 

Distance from Sun 
1 AU 

Gas for Radiometric actuator 
Argon 

Thermal accommodation coefficient 
0.83 

x 
0.5 

b 
0.5 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> I. Proper, &apos;Reaction Wheel Design, Construction and Qualification Testing&apos;, Master&apos;s Thesis, York University, Canada, 2010. 2 F. L. Markley, R. G. Reynolds, F. X. Liu, et al. &apos;Maximum Torque and Momentum Envelopes for Reaction Wheel Arrays&apos;, Journal of Guidance, Control, and Dynamics, vol. 33, no. 5, 2010, pp. 1606-1614. 3 J.-F. Tregouet, D. Arzelier, D. Peaucelle, et al. &apos;Reaction Wheels Desaturation using Magnetorquers and Static Input Allocation&apos;, IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology, vol. 23, no. 2, 2015, pp. 525-539. 4 N.A. Matteo, and Y. T. Morton. &apos;Ionosphere Geomagnetic Field: Comparison of IGRF Model Prediction and Satellite Measurements&apos;, Radio Science, vol. 46, no. 4, 2011. 5 Yoon, Hyungjoo, Hyun Ho Seo, and Hong-Taek Choi. &apos;Optimal Uses of Reaction Wheels in the Pyramid Configuration using a New Minimum Infinity-Norm Solution&apos;, Aerospace Science and Technology, vol. 39, 2014, pp. 109-119. 6 D.A. Vallado, D. Finkleman. &apos;A Critical Assessment of Satellite Drag and Atmospheric Density Modeling&apos;, Acta Astronautica, vol. 95, no. 1, 2014, pp. 141-165. 7 Y. Wang, and S. Xu. &apos;Attitude Stability of a Spacecraft on a Stationary Orbit Around an Asteroid Subjected to Gravity Gradient Torque&apos;, Celestial Mechanics and Dynamical Astronomy, vol. 115, no. 4, 2013, pp. 333-352. 8 C. R. McInnes, Solar Sailing: Technology, Dynamics, and Mission Applications, Springer, New York, 1999. 9 Y. Tsuda,&apos;Achievement of IKAROS --Japanese Deep Space Solar Sail Demonstration Mission&apos;, Acta Astronautica, vol. 82, no. 2, 2013, pp. 183. 10 N. Verhaegh, D. De Boer., M. Johnson., B. V.D. Heijden. &apos;Switchable Transflector and Transflective Display&apos;, Patent, US 20070159678, 2006</note>

			<note place="foot" n="25"> J. Thangavelautham, A. Thoesen, F. Gadau, G. Hutchins, E. Asphaug, I. Alizadeh, &quot;Low-Cost Science Laboratory in Microgravity Using a CubeSat Centrifuge Framework,&quot; Proceedings of the 65th International Astronautical Congress, Toronto, Canada, 2014.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electrochromics for Smart Windows: Oxide-Based Thin Films and Devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Granqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thin Solid Films</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Dynamic Mechanism of a Moving Crookes Radiometer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics of Fluids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111701</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic Theory of Gases, with an Introduction to Statistical Mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kennard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Anonymous Translator</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York and London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill book company, inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1938" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asteroid Regolith Mechanics and Primary Accretion Experiments in a Cubesat</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Asphaug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thangavelautham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">45 th Lunar and Planetary Science Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Houston, Texas</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper 2306</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Analytical Theory for the Perturbative Effect of Solar Radiation Pressure on Natural and Artificial Satellites</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gas Kinetic Forces on Thin Plates in the Presence of Thermal Gradients</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scandurra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Iacopetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Colona</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review. E, Statistical, Nonlinear, and Soft Matter Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26308</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pt</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Larraza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37103</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CubeSat: A new generation of picosatellite for education and industry low-cost space experimentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Heidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Puig-Suari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakasuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Twiggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">14 th Annual USU Conference on Small Satellites</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Space Mission Analysis and Design</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kluwer, Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Radiometric Actuators for Spacecraft Attitude Control</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nallapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tallapragada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thangavelautham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical Examination of the Performance of a Thermoelectric Cooler with Peltier Heating and Cooling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nyung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Electronic Materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3586" to="3591" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Markley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Crassidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fundamentals of Spacecraft Attitude Determination and Control</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representing attitude: Euler angles, unit quaternions, and rotation vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Diebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Matrix</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asteroid Origins Satellite (AOSAT) I: An On-orbit Centrifuge Science Laboratory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lightholder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thoesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Adamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jakubowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nallapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smallwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Raura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Klesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Asphaug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thangavelautham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronautica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
