<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Transit Timing Variations and linear ephemerides of confirmed Kepler transiting exoplanets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date>20xx</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pavol</forename><surname>Gajdoš</surname></persName>
							<email>pavol.gajdos@student.upjs.sk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pavol JozefŠafárikJozefˇJozefŠafárik University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Košice</settlement>
									<country key="SK">Slovakia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Vaňko</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Astronomical Institute, Slovak Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>059 60</postCode>
									<settlement>Tatranská Lomnica</settlement>
									<country key="SK">Slovakia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andštefan</forename><surname>Andˇandštefan Parimucha</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pavol JozefŠafárikJozefˇJozefŠafárik University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Košice</settlement>
									<country key="SK">Slovakia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Transit Timing Variations and linear ephemerides of confirmed Kepler transiting exoplanets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Research in Astron. Astrophys</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">0</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
							<date type="published">20xx</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.17909/T9059R</idno>
					<note>(L A T E X: document Research in Astronomy and Astrophysics</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Stars: planetary systems -Eclipses -Techniques: photometric</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We determined new linear ephemerides of transiting exoplanets using long-cadence de-trended data from quarters Q1 to Q17 of Kepler mission. We analysed TTV diagrams of 2098 extrasolar planets. The TTVs of 121 objects were excluded (because of insufficient data-points, influence of stellar activity, etc). Finally, new linear ephemerides of 1977 exoplanets from Kepler archive are presented. The significant linear trend was observed on TTV diagrams of approximately 35% of studied exoplanets. Knowing correct linear ephemeris is principal for successful follow-up observations of transits. Residual TTV diagrams of 64 analysed exoplanets shows periodic variation, 43 of these TTV planets were not reported yet.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The Kepler satellite, launched in 2009, provided during its primary mission high-precision, high-cadence and continuous photometric data ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Borucki et al., 2010)</ref>. After losing two reaction wheels in 2013, so-called K2 mission started and still continue ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Howell et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>During the primary mission, Kepler discovered 2327 extrasolar planets (up to <ref type="bibr">May 31 st , 2018)</ref>. Almost the half of them (1125) are located in 447 multi-planet systems. The final catalogue (DR25) of Kepler planet candidate was released in 2017 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Thompson et al., 2018)</ref>. It consists of more than four thousand of planet candidates.</p><p>In many of known exoplanets, the variations in times of transits were already observed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Holczer et al. (2016)</ref> detected 260 planet candidates with significant long-term variations. These variations could be caused by gravitational interaction with another bodies in the system. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Steffen et al. (2012)</ref> determined the masses of planets in the systems <ref type="bibr">Kepler-25, Kepler-26, Kepler-27</ref> and Kepler-28 using transit timing. Similar method is also used to confirm the planets in multi-planetary systems (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Fabrycky et al. (2012)</ref>). Many of planet pairs are captured into mean motion resonances (MMRs) ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wang &amp; Ji, 2017</ref>). The MMRs 3:2 and 2:1 are the most common( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wang &amp; Ji, 2014</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">LINEAR EPHEMERIS DETERMINATION</head><p>In our analysis we used long-cadence (sampled every 29.4 minutes) de-trended data (PDCSAP FLUX) from quarters Q1 to Q17 of Kepler mission, obtained from Mikulski Archive  <ref type="figure">Input Catalog )</ref> -name of exoplanet, P -orbital period, T 0 -an initial time of transit (uncertainties are given in parenthesis), χ 2 -sum of squares of the best fit, χ 2 /n -reduced sum of squares, n -number of data points in TTV diagram, Note -changes of residual TTV after new ephemeris is removed, 1 -no significant changes, 2 -periodic or quasi-periodic variations, 3 -chaotic variations (see text for a detailed description). The full table is available as a supplementary material to this manuscript.   <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Names</head><p>for Space Telescopes (MAST) 1 . For the analysis of data, we used the same pipeline as in our study of transit-timing variations (TTVs) in the system <ref type="bibr">Kepler-410 (Gajdoš et al., 2017</ref>). We used same approach for all studied planets and got homogeneous set of times of transits by one method. It can be summarized in the following steps:</p><p>1. Parts of the light curve (LC) of the individual system were extracted around detected transits (using ephemeris given by NASA Exoplanet Archive 2 (Akeson et al., 2013)), with an interval two times bigger than the transit duration. 2. Additional residual trends caused by the stellar activity and/or instrumental long-term photometric variation were removed by the fitting out-of-transit part of LC by the secondorder polynomial function. 3. All individual parts of the LC with transits were stacked together. This can be done, because one expects that the physical parameters of the host star and the exoplanet did not change during the observational period of about 3.5 years and we want to cancel-out the effect of stellar activity. To estimate the quality of the statistical model, we have calculated sum of squares χ 2 and reduced sum of squares χ 2 /n where n is the number of data points in TTV diagram. 7. Finally, new linear trend determined by new ephemeris was removed and residual TTV was visually inspected for another changes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</head><p>We started our analysis of TTV diagrams with 2098 extrasolar planets from Kepler database. We excluded 121 objects with TTV diagrams consisting less than 4 points or with diagrams strongly affected by stellar activity. New linear ephemeris were determined for 1977 exoplanets. They are all presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. Our analysis revealed that in many cases (∼ 35%), linear trend could be observed on the TTV diagrams which were calculated according to original ephemerides given by NASA Exoplanet Archive. Cumulative shift in the minima times of studied exoplanets can reach up to ∼ 130 minutes (e.g. Kepler-4 b) over 3.5 years of Kepler observations. The example of such a significant trend detected in the system Kepler-114 c is shown on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1 (left)</ref>. The period of Kepler-114 c given by the NASA Exoplanet Archive is 8.041 days. But the reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Xie, 2014)</ref> for it is quite old and had used only data up to Q16 quarter. We used also Q17 data in this paper. Also in many other cases, the ephemeris given by the Archive is not the latest one. The incorrect value of period could cause that the transit will be really observed few hours earlier or latter than it will be calculated, after few years. And the observer with outdated ephemeris will not see any transit at all. After removing linear trend determined by the new ephemeris, we can obtain residual TTV with no other significant changes (right) (note 1 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>).</p><p>Residual TTV of 64 planets shows periodic or quasi-periodic variations (note 2 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>). The examples of such systems with more or less significant changes are depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>. TTV of 17 planets from this group were already analysed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Holczer et al. (2016)</ref>. We compared our  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>). Periods and amplitudes of these changes are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Tables 2 and 3.</ref> results with their in the  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref> with periods and amplitudes of TTV changes. We used sinusoidal model of these variations to determined their period and amplitude. For finding correct values of sinusoidal model's parameters, we ran simple Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Marquardt, 1963)</ref>. Amplitudes of found variations vary between approximately 2 and 70 minutes and periods vary from only 80 to more than 1500 days. These changes could be caused by interaction with another body(ies) (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Agol et al. (2005)</ref>), stellar activity (e.g. spots) or other effects in studied systems. 95 exoplanets shows chaotic or abnormal TTVs (note 3 in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>). This type of variations is the most probably caused by stellar activity (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Oshagh et al. (2013)</ref>) and/or gravitational interaction with another bodies in the systems. Examples of these systems are shown on <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING INFORMATION</head><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the on-line version of this article: </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1: TTV of Kepler-114 c determined from original ephemeris from NASA Exoplanet Archive with new linear fit (solid line), right -residual TTV of Kepler-114 c (note 1 in Table 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2: Examples of planets with periodic variations on the residual TTV diagram (note 2 in Table 1). Periods and amplitudes of these changes are listed in Tables 2 and 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3: Examples of exoplanets with chaotic (abnormal) TTVs (note 3 in Table 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 : The new linear ephemerides of Kepler exoplanets: Kepler, KOI (Kepler Object of Interest) and KIC (Kepler</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 : Comparison of periods and amplitudes of TTV changes found in this paper with values given by Holczer et al. (2016): Kepler, KOI and KIC -name of exoplanet, P -period of variation, A -amplitude (uncertainties are given in parenthesis).</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Names 
Holczer et al. (2016) 
This paper 
Kepler 
KOI 
KIC 
P (d) 
A (m) 
P (d) 
A (m) 
Kepler-25 b 
244.02 
4349452 
326(3) 
3.8(3) 
334(2) 
4.3(3) 
Kepler-51 b 
620.01 
11773022 
790(12) 
7.9(4) 
749(17) 
5.5(5) 
Kepler-81 c 
877.02 
7287995 
536(12) 
9(2) 
516(9) 
10(1) 
Kepler-111 c 
139.01 
8559644 
2213(79) 
211(22) 
1050(20) 
38(2) 
Kepler-139 c 
316.02 
8008067 
1008(84) 
29(8) 
913(30) 
35(3) 
Kepler-209 c 
672.02 
7115785 
1061(76) 
9(2) 
1141(63) 
10(1) 
Kepler-221 e 
720.03 
9963524 
-
∼9 
1697(115) 
11(1) 
Kepler-278 c 
1221.02 
3640905 
829(41) 
144(32) 
960(69) 
112(16) 
Kepler-312 c 
1628.01 
6975129 
471(17) 
6(2) 
478(14) 
7(1) 
Kepler-359 c 
2092.01 
6696580 
1270(130) 
23(6) 
1246(125) 
20(6) 
Kepler-540 b 
374.01 
8686097 
1388(84) 
38(6) 
1457(54) 
37(4) 
Kepler-561 b 
464.01 
8890783 
482(11) 
3.9(6) 
480(12) 
4.1(7) 
Kepler-591 b 
536.01 
10965008 
454(37) 
6(4) 
579(35) 
9(2) 
Kepler-765 b 
1086.01 
10122255 
1630(150) 
20(4) 
1445(133) 
37(3) 
Kepler-827 b 
1355.01 
7211141 
124(1) 
6(2) 
398(36) 
6(1) 
Kepler-1040 b 
1989.01 
10779233 
-
∼15 
901(30) 
17(4) 
Kepler-1624 b 
4928.01 
1873513 
110(1) 
2.1(7) 
118(3) 
1.9(2) 

4. Stacked LC was fitted by our software implementation of Mandel &amp; Agol (2002) model 
where we used a quadratic model of limb darkening with values of coefficients from Sing 
(2010). Our package use Markov Chain Monte-Carlo (MCMC) simulation to obtain statis-
tically significant value of parameters and their errors. 
5. Obtained template was used to fit all individual transits, where only the time of transit was 
updated. 
6. Determined times of transits were used for a creation of transit timing variations (TTV) 
diagram of the object. It was subsequently fitted by the linear function to obtain new values 
of linear ephemeris parameters, initial time of transit T 0 and orbital period P . To achieve 
statistically significant estimation of parameter's uncertainties, we used MCMC simulation. 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 3 : Planets with periodic variations in TTV diagram not reported in Holczer et al. (2016).</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Names 
Variation 
Kepler 
KOI 
KIC 
P (d) 
A (m) 
Kepler-39 b 
423.01 
9478990 
1393(81) 
1.9(3) 
Kepler-52 d 
775.03 
11754553 
1493(300) 
9(4) 
Kepler-89 c 
94.02 
6462863 
395(10) 
10(2) 
Kepler-110 b 
124.01 
11086270 
767(23) 
12(4) 
Kepler-110 c 
124.02 
11086270 
1245(13) 
6(2) 
Kepler-122 e 
232.04 
4833421 
1135(59) 
42(6) 
Kepler-142 d 
343.03 
10982872 
1400(5) 
57(9) 
Kepler-166 c 
481.03 
11192998 
1419(81) 
20(5) 
Kepler-196 c 
612.02 
6587002 
1431(197) 
7(1) 
Kepler-201 c 
655.02 
5966154 
828(88) 
11(4) 
Kepler-222 d 
723.02 
10002866 
770(23) 
5(1) 
Kepler-222 c 
723.03 
10002866 
606(11) 
3.2(5) 
Kepler-227 c 
752.02 
10797460 
1041(12) 
14(8) 
Kepler-230 c 
759.02 
11018648 
776(60) 
19(6) 
Kepler-233 c 
790.02 
12470844 
1057(127) 
12(5) 
Kepler-267 d 
1078.03 
10166274 
818(24) 
8(2) 
Kepler-283 c 
1298.02 
10604335 
1212(36) 
68(11) 
Kepler-299 e 
1432.04 
11014932 
1427(102) 
74(46) 
Kepler-300 c 
1435.01 
11037335 
1365(104) 
58(10) 
Kepler-310 c 
1598.01 
10004738 
1004(10) 
5(2) 
Kepler-310 b 
1598.03 
10004738 
1134(49) 
15(3) 
Kepler-358 c 
2080.01 
10864531 
810(3) 
19(6) 
Kepler-362 c 
2147.01 
10404582 
851(85) 
14(6) 
Kepler-364 c 
2153.01 
10253547 
696(66) 
23(4) 
Kepler-509 b 
276.01 
11133306 
1506(138) 
4(1) 
Kepler-549 c 
427.03 
10189546 
978(43) 
42(8) 
Kepler-672 b 
773.01 
11507101 
707(32) 
14(3) 
Kepler-795 b 
1218.01 
3442055 
731(27) 
10(4) 
Kepler-797 b 
1238.01 
6383821 
895(60) 
37(11) 
Kepler-807 b 
1288.01 
10790387 
1327(97) 
1.8(5) 
Kepler-852 b 
1444.01 
11043167 
1123(76) 
15(3) 
Kepler-966 b 
1828.01 
11875734 
1162(120) 
7(2) 
Kepler-1036 b 
1980.01 
11769890 
1382(84) 
16(2) 
Kepler-1097 b 
2102.01 
7008211 
729(29) 
9(1) 
Kepler-1126 b 
2162.01 
9205938 
1327(133) 
23(6) 
Kepler-1129 c 
2167.03 
6041734 
1236(117) 
19(4) 
Kepler-1184 b 
2309.01 
10010440 
1108(51) 
24(5) 
Kepler-1185 b 
2311.03 
4247991 
820(89) 
9(3) 
Kepler-1388 b 
2926.01 
10122538 
370(19) 
18(7) 
Kepler-1389 b 
2931.01 
8611257 
1312(101) 
43(8) 
Kepler-1453 b 
3280.01 
10653179 
1078(2) 
22(10) 
Kepler-1524 b 
3878.01 
4472818 
974(77) 
4(1) 
Kepler-1527 b 
3901.01 
9480535 
1024(25) 
44(5) 
Kepler-1530 c 
3925.03 
10788461 
86.4(6) 
13(3) 
Kepler-1552 b 
4103.01 
3747817 
998(125) 
28(8) 
Kepler-1593 b 
4356.01 
8459663 
1465(134) 
28(9) 
Kepler-1638 b 
5856.01 
11037818 
840(51) 
197(32) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Periodic TTV signals of six planets (Kepler-52 d, Kepler-
89 c, Kepler-122 e, Kepler-166 c, Kepler-283 c and Kepler-549 c) were already reported by 
Thompson et al. (2018) but they did not determine any parameters of these changes. 43 of these 
planets with periodic TTV were not reported in any other paper. Discovering these new TTV 
systems was a result of using our method of LC de-trending and time of transit measurement. 
The all planets with unreported periodic TTV and six planets reported (but not analysed) by 
Thompson et al. (2018) are listed in </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 1 . The new linear ephemeris of Kepler exoplanets.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> doi:10.17909/T9059R 2 We used Confirmed Planets table available at https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu/cgi-bin/TblView/nph-tblView?app=ExoTbls&amp;config=planets. Downloaded at April 2018</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Gajdoš et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>This work was supported by the Slovak Research and Development Agency under the contract No. APVV-15-0458. M.V. would like to thank the project VEGA 2/0031/18. The research of P.G. was supported by the VVGS-PF-2017-724 internal grant of the Faculty of Science, P. J. ˇ Safárik University in Košice.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Clarkson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">567</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Akeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">989</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">977</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">750</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gajdoš</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">ˇ</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Parimucha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">ˇ</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hambálek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaňko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2907</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Holczer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nachmani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">225</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sobeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">398</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mandel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">580</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">171</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marquardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J Appl Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">431</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1963" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oshagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Boisse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">556</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2342</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">235</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">236</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
