<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">EVIDENCE THAT THE PLANETARY CANDIDATE CVSO30C IS A BACKGROUND STAR FROM OPTICAL, SEEING-LIMITED DATA</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-12-23">23 Dec 2017 Draft version December 27, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chien-Hsiu</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Subaru Telescope</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NAOJ</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>650 North Aohoku Place</addrLine>
									<postCode>96720</postCode>
									<settlement>Hilo</settlement>
									<region>HI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Po-Shih</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate Institute of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Central University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>No. 300</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Jhongli District</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jhongda Rd</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Taoyuan City</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">EVIDENCE THAT THE PLANETARY CANDIDATE CVSO30C IS A BACKGROUND STAR FROM OPTICAL, SEEING-LIMITED DATA</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-12-23">23 Dec 2017 Draft version December 27, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">(Received December 27, 2017; Revised xxx xx, 2017; Accepted xxx xx, 201x) Submitted to ApJL</note>
					<note>Typeset using L A T E X default style in AASTeX61</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>stars: pre-main sequence -planetary systems -planets and satellites: atmospheres - planets and satellites: detection</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We report serendipitous optical imaging of CVSO30c, an exoplanet candidate associated with the pre-main sequence T Tauri star CVSO30 resides in the 25 Ori stellar cluster. We perform PSF modeling on our seeing limited optical image to remove the lights from the host star (CVSO30), allowing us to extract photometry of CVSO30c to be g = 23.2 ± 0.2 (statistic) ± 0.1 (systematic) and r = 21.5 ± 0.1 (statistic) ± 0.1 (systematic) magnitudes, respectively. This is 170 and 80 times too bright in the g and r-band, respectively, if CVSO30c were an L0 substellar object as suggested by previous studies. The optical/infrared colors of CVSO 30c are indicative of a stellar, not substellar object, while the object&apos;s color-magnitude diagram position is strikingly inconsistent with expected values for a low mass member of 25 Ori. Broad-band photometry for CVSO30c is instead better fit by contaminants such as a background K3 giant or M subdwarf. Our study demonstrates that optical seeing limited data can help clarify the nature of candidate wide separation planet-mass companions in young star-forming regions.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>CVSO30 <ref type="bibr">(or PTFO 8-8695 van Eyken et al. 2012</ref>) is an intriguing candidate exoplanet system in several aspects. First of all, it resides in the nearby and young stellar group 25 <ref type="bibr">Orionis (Briceño et al. 2007</ref>). The 25 Ori stellar group has nearly 200 low-mass PMS (confirmed photometrically and kinematically) within 1 degree of the bright B star 25 Ori in the Orion OB1a sub-association located at ∼330 pc. With an age of ∼ 7 Myr, 25 Ori stellar cluster if of special interests to exoplanet studies. This is because pre-main-sequence (PMS) stars, especially with an age of 10 Myr, play essential roles in our understanding of the formation and evolution of proto-planetary disks, and planet formation process.</p><p>Follow-ups of the 25 Ori group have been carried out by Young Exoplanet Transit Initiative <ref type="bibr">(YETI, Neuhäuser et al. 2011</ref>) and Palomar Transient Factory (PTF) by van <ref type="bibr">Eyken et al. (2011)</ref>, leading to the discovery of an exoplanet candidate CVSO30b. This is a 3-4 Jovian mass exoplanet candidate transiting a M3 T Tauri star CVSO30 <ref type="bibr">(van Eyken et al. 2012</ref>) with a period of 0.45 days and a separation of 0.008 AU. In addition, high contrast near-infrared direct imaging with AO also yielded another 4.7 Jovian mass exoplanet candidate, CVSO30c, associated with the same host star at a separation of 662 AU ( <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. 2016</ref>). If both CVSO30b and CVSO30c turned out to be true exoplanets, they can provide insight on the formation of exoplanets at wide separation. This is because wide separation exoplanets are difficult to be reconciled with the core accretion formation mechanism, and require planet-planet scattering mechanism to explain their wide separation. One prediction from the planet-planet scattering is that while one exoplanet is scattered to a wide separation, there will be another exoplanet in the same system to migrate to very close-in orbits. The existence of a close-in exoplanet CVSO30b, and a wide separation exoplanet CVSO30c seems to match the planet-planet scattering scenario.</p><p>However, there have been challenges to the exoplanet nature of CVSO30b ( <ref type="bibr">Yu et al. 2015</ref>). Further simultaneous multi-band observations of CVSO30b by <ref type="bibr">Onitsuka et al. (2017)</ref> also contradicted the exoplanet nature, suggesting an origin of circumstellar dust clump instead. On the other hand, the exoplanet nature of CVSO30c also needs to be examined. Here we report a serendipitous detection of CVSO30c in the optical band under seeing-limited conditions. This serendipitous optical imaging contradicts the exoplanetary candidacy as suggested by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. Our paper is organized as follows: We describe our observations and data reduction in section 2. We present our analysis and results, including several tests on the exoplanet candidacy of CVSO30c using empirical colors of substellar objects, color magnitude diagram, and synthetic spectra of substellar objects in section 3. We discuss and conclude our results in section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">OBSERVATION AND DATA REDUCTION</head><p>We performed high cadence time-series photometry monitoring of CVSO30 with the 3.5m WIYN telescope 1 at Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona, USA. The observations were carried out by the One Degree Imager with the 48'×40' field of view and a pixel scale of 0.11"/pixel 2 . The observations were conducted on the nights of February 3rd and 4th, 2017, through the NASA founded NOAO-WIYN observation program NN-Explore (PI: Lee, ID: 2017-0111). These data were acquired with the goal of detecting the transit of CVSO 30 b in two filters (g and r-band) to better assess whether or not the object is a planet. After observations, the data are reduced in a standard manner. The One Degree Imager Pipeline, Portal, and Archive (ODI-PPA <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Gopu et al. 2014</ref>) performed bias subtraction, dark subtraction, flat fielding, and bad pixel masking. ODI-PPA further aligned each of the individual exposures astrometrically, and calibrated the photometry using nearby SDSS standard star field observations. During the photometric monitoring campaign, we noticed traces of a faint object close to the host star CVSO30 in images with seeing &lt; 0.8" in both Sloan g-and r-band images. To further strengthen our detection, we stacked several exposures using SWarp ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bertin et al. 2002)</ref> to increase the signal-to-noise ratio. This includes 3 × 120-sec exposures in the g-band with on-chip seeing of 0.72-0.73" and 6 × 60-sec exposures in the r-band with on-chip seeing of 0.75-0.79", respectively. The estimated precision of image registering is 0.03" and 0.04" for g, and r-band, respectively. As the zero-point magnitudes of each individual exposure is different, we calibrate the stacked images photometrically using the Pan-STARRS Data Release stars for our calibration. During the photometric calibration, we found a systematic error at the level of 0.1 mag in both g and r-band. After stacking, we also model and remove the host star's light with a point spread function (PSF). The PSF was constructed using bright and isolated stars in the stacked images using the IRAF routine psf. With the PSF in hand, we then used GALFIT ( <ref type="bibr">Peng et al. 2002</ref><ref type="bibr">Peng et al. , 2010</ref> to subtract the host star's flux, yielding to a clear detection of this faint object (as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). We then obtained optical photometry of this faint object from the stacked images using SExtractor <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bertin &amp; Arnouts 1996)</ref>, deriving g = 23.2 ± 0.2 (statistic) ± 0.1 (systematic) and r = 21.5 ± 0.1 (statistic) ± 0.1 (systematic) magnitudes. We note that <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> also carried out z-band observations using lucky image technique with AstraLux onboard the Calar Alto 2.2m telescope. While they did not detect CVSO30c with AstraLux, they were able to constrain an upper limit of 20.5 mag in z-band. This is consistent with our faint detection in the g-and r-bands.</p><p>Finally, we measured the separation of this faint object to the star CVSO30 to be 1.83"±0.04", with a position angle of 71.6±0.8 degrees (East from North). We note that the imager has a north position angle uncertainty of ∼ 0.26 degrees. The separation and positional angle of this object in the optical are in good agreement with the separation of ∼ 1.85" and the position angle of ∼ 70 degrees from <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>, hence confirmed this optically faint object is indeed CVSO30c.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS</head><p>With the optical photometry, we can test whether the exoplanetary candidacy of CVSO30c holds. First of all, <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> reported that this object is a young and substellar, with a spectral type later than L0. For comparison, we check other known substellar objects with similar spectral type and age. ROXs 42B, for example, has an effective temperature of ∼ 2,000 K, a spectral type of L0±1, and a low gravity due to its youth. Another case is β Pic b, which has an effective temperature of 1,600-1,700 K, a spectral type of L3 or later, and also a low gravity due to its youth. In addition, young, low gravity L and L/T transition objects have redder colors than their field counterparts. Therefore, the comparison to L0 is a best-case scenario for CVSO30c being a planet. The intrinsic optical and infrared colors of objects as late as L0 are well well known and described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kraus &amp; Hillenbrand (2007)</ref>. The predicted g-J and r-J colors are 9.2 and 6.7 magnitudes. According to <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>, CVSO30c has J=19.6 mag; assuming the object is an L0 substellar object, it should be fainter than g=28.8 and r=26.3 magnitudes. However, given our measurement of CVSO30c, it is 180 (in g) and 70 (in r) times brighter than an L0 objects, as suggested by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>.</p><p>Secondly, we can also check whether CVSO30c resides in the 25 Ori stellar cluster using color magnitude diagram, by combing the optical photometry presented here and the infrared photometry in <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Downes et al. (2014)</ref> have identified 77 low mass members of the 25 Ori stellar cluster spectroscopically. Their members all follow a well-defined 7 Myr isochrone from <ref type="bibr">Baraffe et al. (1998)</ref> on the I vs. I-J color magnitude diagram. We cross matched the catalogue by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Downes et al. (2014)</ref> with the PS1 DR1 catalog ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chambers et al. 2016</ref>) to retrieve g and r magnitudes of the cluster members.</p><p>In addition to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Downes et al. (2014)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Suárez et al. (2017)</ref> also reported 50 low mass members (including their positions and SDSS photometry) in the 25 Ori stellar group and Orion OB1a sub-association, which are all co-distant at 338±66 pc. Color-magnitude diagrams clarify whether CVSO30c is consistent with being a low-mass member of 25 Ori. As shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, CVSO30c is strikingly inconsistent with the color-magnitude diagram position expected for a low-mass member of 25 Ori.</p><p>Further more, we can examine whether the SED of CVSO30c fits an L0 substellar object as suggested by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. From the Phoenix Web Simulator 4 , we retrieved the synthetic spectrum of an object with logg = 3.5 and effective temperature of 1,600 K, as suggested by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. For comparison, we scaled the synthetic spectrum to match the infrared photometry, as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. The results indicate that while we can match the synthetic spectrum to the infrared photometry, the optical photometry does not follow the synthetic spectrum, and is off by 5 magnitudes in both the g and r-band. This suggests that the optical photometry of CVSO30c is in tension with the exoplanetary scenario.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</head><p>To summarize, our serendipitous optical detection and analysis of CVSO30c provides evidence against the object being a directly-imaged planetary companion as proposed by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. Its optical/infrared color disagrees with values expected for an L0 or later substellar object from the SED library of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kraus &amp; Hillenbrand (2007)</ref>. Furthermore, the optical/infrared color-magnitude diagram position of CVSO30c is strongly inconsistent with the locus of spectroscopically confirmed low mass 25 Ori members and with theoretical isochrones appropriate for young stars and substellar objects. Finally, CVSO30c's broadband photometry strongly disagrees with the synthetic spectrum of a low gravity L0 model atmosphere from the BT-Settl grid.</p><p>Given the optical detection, it is intriguing to understand the inconsistency between our analysis and that from <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. First of all, <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> argued that the z' non-detection ruled out objects hotter than 3,300 K. However, consulting to the intrinsic colors of stellar objects compiled by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kraus &amp; Hillenbrand (2007)</ref>, we can see that the optical and infrared colors by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> can only rule out objects with spectral type of K2 or earlier, i.e. T ef f &gt; 5,000 K. This then allows objects with effective temperatures of 3,300 to 5,000 K as possible contaminants, which are not considered in <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. Yet from our r-J colors the CVSO30c seems reasonable well matched to a K5-M0 star (as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Secondly, while <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> argued that their IR data analysis rules out a background star, they did not fully explore the range of background objects. For example, the giants they considered are all later than M4.5. In fact, when we compare the broad-band photometry with a wide variety of spectral types, we found that CVSO30c is more likely to be a reddened K3 super giant or a metal-poor early-M subdwarf <ref type="figure">(Fig. 4</ref>, which were not considered by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>.</p><p>We note that it might be possible that our optical detection is not associated with CVSO30c, i.e. a background star that is not detected at longer wavelengths in JHK. However, consulting the SED library of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kraus &amp; Hillenbrand (2007)</ref>, the g-r colors alone suggest an object with an M2-M3 spectral type -not an L0 or later object -which correspondingly have r-J and r-K colors of 3.03-3.46, 3.9-4.34, respectively. Such and object, with an apparent magnitude of J=18-18.5  <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. g vs. g-J and r vs. r-J color magnitude diagram of the 25 Ori stellar group. We plot the spectroscopically confirmed 25 Ori stellar group low mass members from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Downes et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Suárez et al. (2017)</ref>, marked in solid and empty circles. We also plot the isochrone by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baraffe et al. (2015)</ref> assuming a distance modulus of 7.6 magnitudes, with ages of 8 Myr (solid line) and 5 Myr (dashed line), respectively. CVSO30c (marked in red), on the contrary to the spectroscopically confirmed low mass members of 25 Ori stellar group, does not follow the isochrones. This suggests that CVSO30c does not belong to the 25 Ori stellar group. Wavelength <ref type="bibr">[µm]</ref> BT-Settl logg=3.5, T=1600K <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Spectral energy distribution of CVSO30c. We show the optical photometry from this work and the infrared photometry from <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>, both marked in squares. We also show the z'-band upper limit by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>, marked in open triangle. We compare the broad-band photometry to a synthetic spectrum of a slightly reddened L0 substellar object with logg = 3.5, effective temperature of 1600 K, and Av=0.3, as suggested by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref>. The synthetic spectrum (shown in gray) is retrieved from the Phoenix Web Simulator, adopting the BT-Settl model ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allard et al. 2012</ref>). For comparison, we scaled the synthetic spectrum to the infrared photometry of CVSO30c. While the infrared photometry is in good agreement with the synthetic spectrum of a substellar object, the optical photometry is in tension with this synthetic spectrum by 5 magnitudes brighter in both g and r-band. and K=17.2-17.6 at the distance of 25 Ori (without extinction correction), would have been comparable in brightness to CVSO30c or brighter and detectable in the <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> near-IR data. Combined with the consistent spatial alignment between our optical detection and the infrared, we conclude that our optical detection is the same object seen by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> and labeled CVSO30c. This work demonstrates that optical imaging under good seeing-limited conditions can clarify the nature of candidate, very wide-separation companions to young stars in star-forming regions. Given the large implied physical separations of these objects (hundreds of au), proper motion analyses are poorly suited to identify background stars. However, the optical/infrared colors of young planetary-mass objects significantly differ from most contaminating background sources. Such observations are also efficient. In this case, optical imaging using a 3.5-meter telescope with a 2 minute integration time in g-band or 1 minute in r-band can already rule out a candidate planetary companion. Follow-up spectroscopic observations can then focus on candidates whose optical data do not reveal them to be background objects.</p><p>We are indebted to the referee, whose insightful comments and suggestions improved this manuscript significantly. Based on observations at Kitt Peak National Observatory, National Optical Astronomy Observatory (NOAO Prop. ID: 2017A-0111; PI: Lee), which is operated by the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA) under a cooperative agreement with the National Science Foundation. K3 giant M subdwarf <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Comparison of CVSO30c broad-band photometry with an K-giant and a M subdwarf. The grJHK photometry are marked in red solid circles, while the z-band upper limit by <ref type="bibr">Schmidt et al. (2016)</ref> is marked in red open circle. We show the synthetic spectra of a K3 Giant from the spectral library of <ref type="bibr">Pickles (1998)</ref>, with an Av=0.6, as well as a synthetic spectra of a M subdwarf with T ef f =3,800K, logg=5.5, Z=-2.0 from BT-Settl ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allard et al. 2012)</ref>, with an Av=0.26. Both provide a good fit to the CVSO30c broad-band photometry, suggesting that it is a background star.</p><p>Data presented herein were obtained at the WIYN Observatory from telescope time allocated to NN-EXPLORE through the scientific partnership of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the National Science Foundation, and the National Optical Astronomy Observatory.</p><p>Facilities: <ref type="bibr">WIYN(ODI)</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Optical imaging of CVSO30c (North is up and East is to the left). Left panel: stacked images, where CVSO30c can be seen as a small blob right next to the host star. Right panel: residual images after subtracting the host star with PSF modeling. CVSO30c is indicated by the red marker.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> The WIYN Observatory is a joint facility of the University of Wisconsin-Madison, Indiana University, the National Optical Astronomy Observatory and the University of Missouri. 2 https://www.noao.edu/wiyn/ODI/ 3 https://panstarrs.stsci.edu</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> https://phoenix.ens-lyon.fr/simulator/index.faces</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Briceño</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">661</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Freytag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2765</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baraffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">577</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bertin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arnouts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">393</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bertin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mellier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Radovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Systems XI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Magnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Metcalfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1612.05560</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">729</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">128</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Madhusudhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">776</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Daemgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">787</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Downes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Briceño</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mateu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1793</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gopu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91520</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hillenbrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2340</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">654</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">151</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Morzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Males</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Skemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">815</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
