<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:09+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A New Concept for Direct Imaging and Spectral Characterization of Exoplanets in Multi-planet Systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Taro</forename><surname>Matsuo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">National Astronomical Observatory of Japan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-0015</postCode>
									<settlement>Osawa, Tokyo</settlement>
									<region>Mitaka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wesley</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Traub</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4800 Oak Grove Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>91109</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Makoto</forename><surname>Hattori</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Tohoku University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6-3 Aoba, Aoba-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>980-8578</postCode>
									<settlement>Aramaki, Sendai</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Motohide</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">National Astronomical Observatory of Japan</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-21-1</addrLine>
									<postCode>181-0015</postCode>
									<settlement>Osawa, Tokyo</settlement>
									<region>Mitaka</region>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A New Concept for Direct Imaging and Spectral Characterization of Exoplanets in Multi-planet Systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>infrared: planetary system -techniques: interferometric</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present a novel method for direct detection and characterization of exoplanets from space. This method uses four collecting telescopes, combined with phase chopping and a spectrometer, with observations on only a few baselines rather than on a continuously rotated baseline. Focusing on the contiguous wavelength spectra of typical exoplanets, the (u,v) plane can be simultaneously and uniformly filled by recording the spectrally resolved signal. This concept allows us to perfectly remove speckles from reconstructed images. For a target comprising a star and multiple planets, observations on three baselines are sufficient to extract the position and spectrum of each planet. Our simulations show that this new method allows us to detect an analog Earth around a Sun-like star at 10pc and to acquire its spectrum over the wavelength range from 8 to 19µm with a high spectral resolution of 100. This method allows us to fully characterize an analog Earth and to similarly characterize each planet in multi-planet systems.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Since the first discovery of an exoplanet orbiting a main-sequence star by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Mayor &amp; Queloz (1995)</ref>, more than 500 exoplanets have been discovered so far through radial velocity and several other ongoing indirect observations. On the other hand, the first success of direct imaging was reported 12 years after the first detection of an exoplanet. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Marois et al. (2008)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Kalas et al. (2008)</ref> imaged exoplanets orbiting A-type Vega-like stars of HR8799 and Fomalhaut with Keck/Gemini and Hubble Space Telescope, respectively. Following these successes, a snapshot of a planet candidate orbiting a fairly old G star, GJ758B, has been taken with Subaru/HiCIAO ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Thalman et al. 2009</ref>). In addition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Lagrange et al. (2010)</ref> confirmed a planet around beta Pic with Very Large Telescope, originally reported in 2008. Thus, the number of directly imaged exoplanets has recently increased but extraordinary efforts are required for direct detection of even these young self-luminous gas giants. However, direct detection of the Earth-like planets in the habitable zones of other planetary systems involves a more significant technical challenge, compared with the direct imaging of young gas giants. This is because much higher contrast values of 10 -10 and 10 -7 at a close angular distance to a central star are required at visible and infrared wavelengths, respectively. Several possibilities for direct detection of the Earth-like planets have been proposed: space-based coronagraphs operating at visible wavelengths, space-based nulling interferometers operating at mid-infrared wavelengths. In this paper, we concentrate on the latter approach. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bracewell (1978)</ref> proposed the simplest nulling interferometer for direct imaging of Earth-like planets in the habitable zones at mid-infrared wavelengths. This type of interferometer comprises two collecting apertures separated by baseline length B , and introduces an achromatic phase-shift of π between the two arms such that the light from an on-axis source is canceled at the beam combiner output. The transmission pattern on the sky is a sinusoidal corrugation with a null at the center of the field of view and an angular periodicity of λ / B , where λ is the observing wavelength.</p><p>Regarding the null depth, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Angel and Woolf (1997)</ref> proposed some improvements to the single-Bracewell configuration. However, even if the on-axis source is perfectly suppressed with the nulling technique, emissions from the local zodiacal and the exo-zodiacal dust disks are much brighter than those from Earth-like planets in the mid-infrared wavelength range. A first step toward detecting a planet against a bright zodiacal background is the sine phase chopping technique proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Mennesson and Mariotti (1997)</ref>. The method can separate asymmetrical sources, such as the planets, from symmetrical ones such as the central stars, local zodiacal lights, and exozodiacal light. A dual-Bracewell configuration, which is composed of two single nulling interferometers combined with the phase chopping technique, overcomes the disadvantages of the original single-Bracewell configuration. This type of interferometer can clearly identify the location of a planet through the maximum correlation method, analogous to Fourier transformation used for standard radio interferometers. However, the relative phase between successive rolls needs to be maintained. Otherwise, speckles are produced in a reconstructed image. Previously, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref> proposed a new concept for direct detection and spectral characterization of the Earthlike planets by focusing on the fact that observing wavelengths can be contiguously obtained in space. Thus, the (u, v) plane can be simultaneously filled by observing spectra at only a few discrete orientations instead of continuously rotating the baselines, which is the case with the original Bracewell approach. There are several advantages to this concept. First, observations on two baselines are sufficient to extract the position of a single planet and its spectrum. Second, the higher spectral resolution leads to more dense filling of the (u,v) plane. Third, the phase at each roll angle is irrelevant in this method. As a result, there is no speckle in the reconstructed image. Thus, this concept could be a promising method for direct detection of exoplanets. However, it cannot be directly applied to multi-planet systems, such as Gliese 876 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Rivera et al. 2010</ref>), 55Cancri (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">McArthur et al. 2004</ref>), and Gliese 581 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Mayor et al. 2009</ref>), as explained next. In this paper, we extend the original concept proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref> for the multi-planet systems. For these, observations on two baselines are not sufficient to estimate each planet's position even if the separations of each signal from the host star along orthogonal two axes can be clearly extracted from two one-dimensional images of the planetary system. This is because there is an ambiguity in extracting the two-dimensional positions of more planets, given only two projected images on orthogonal axes. In Section 3 we perform its numerical simulation to validate the concept. In Section 4 we show how to extract exoplanet spectra and discuss the capability of characterization of the Earth-like planets, and in Section 5 we give our conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">THEORY</head><p>In this section, we expand the original concept proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref> to include the multi-planet systems. The method for extraction of each planet's position is presented in Section 2.1. The spectrum of each planet is analytically derived in Section 2.2. An improvement of signal-to-noise ratio (S/N) for the spectrum of each planet is introduced in Section 2.3. Finally, the field of view of this method is discussed. We assume that the target is composed of a star and n multiple planets. A dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer with a sine phase chopping and a spectrometer is assumed. We assume that the exozodiacal light has a symmetric brightness distribution with respect to the star.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Direct Imaging of a Planetary System</head><p>Based on the previous studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lay 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Draper et al. 2006</ref>), the spectrally resolved signal, in unit of detected photoelectrons of the dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer for the individual chop state, is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">O ± λ ( ) = 1 2 d 2 θ I λ,  θ </formula><p>α is position vector on the sky, and λ min and λ max are the minimum and maximum observing wavelengths, respectively. On a related issue, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ohta et al. (2006)</ref> established a theory for imaging of extended sources in radio, focusing on broadband ground-based radio observations. From the reconstructed image of the planetary system, we can estimate the separation of each signal from the host star along the imaging baseline vector. As described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref>, if the target is a single planet system, the two-dimensional position of the planet could be estimated from the two one-dimensional images of the planetary system. However, the observations on two baselines are not sufficient for extraction of the position of each planet because no one knows which signal appearing in one of the two reconstructed images corresponds to which signal in the other reconstructed image. As a result, the separations of each signal from the host star along the two orthogonal axes cannot be transformed in principle into the position of each signal in the twodimensional plane. We can break this degeneracy with two planets by adding a third position of the array. The coordinate system on the sky is set as a rectangular Cartesian coordinate system, (x, y). We assume that the separation of each planet from the host star along the two orthogonal axes is already known from the first and second observations, and the rotation angles of the array in the third measurement and the kth planet are φ B and φ p,k from the x-axis, respectively; the pair of the separations of the kth planet from the host star along the two orthogonal axes is satisfied by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">a p, k cos φ B − φ p, k ( ) = x p, k 2 + y p, k 2 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where a p,k is the measured separation of the kth planet from the host star along the imaging baseline in the third measurement, x p, k and y p, k are the separation of the kth planet along the x-and the y-axes, respectively, and φ p,k is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">φ p, k = tan −1 x p, k y p, k ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Here, no one knows the right pair of separations of each planet from the host star along the two orthogonal axes. Therefore, we apply all of the combinations of the pairs to Equation (6) and then choose a combination of them which is best satisfied by Equation (6). The chosen pairs represent the separations of planets from the host star along the two orthogonal axes. Thus, observations on three baselines are sufficient for extraction of the two-dimensional position of each planet. On the other hand, the information on the spectrum of each planet is lost through Fourier transformation of the spectrally resolved signal along the observing wavelength. Therefore, the spectrum of the planet should be reconstructed for characterization of the planet, as we discuss next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Spectrum of Each Planet</head><p>In the section, we present a new method for reconstruction of the spectrum of each planet from its two-dimensional position of each planet from its two-dimensional position. Given that the number of the planets within the field of view is n and the two-dimensional position of each planet is clearly revealed through the procedure shown in the previous section, the demodulated spectrally resolved signal at λ can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">O λ ( ) = O * λ ( ) + O local − zodi λ ( ) + O exozodi λ ( ) + O p, k λ ( ) k n ∑ ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">O * λ ( ) , O local − zodi λ ( ) , O exozodi λ ( ) ,</formula><p>and O p, k λ ( ) are the demodulated spectrally resolved signals of the stellar leakage, the local zodiacal light, the exozodiacal light, and the kth planet at λ , respectively. Here, as described in the previous section, the star, the local zodiacal light, and the exozodiacal light are centro-symmetric sources. As a result, we can express Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(8)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">O λ ( ) = O s λ ( ) + O p, k λ ( ) k n ∑ ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where represents the sum of the demodulated signals from the symmetric sources. Keeping the array configuration unchanged during rotation of the array on the optical axis of the array, the signal of the symmetric source is unchanged:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">O s,1 λ ( ) ≈ O s,2 λ ( ) ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where is the demodulated signal of the symmetric source in the nth measurement. On the other hand, the planet as an off-axis source produces the modulated signal during rotation of the array. Therefore, the observations on the rotation of the array can separate the planets from the centro-symmetric sources. The observations on n+1 baselines are required for extraction of the spectra of n planets:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">O 1 λ ( )  O n +1 λ ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ = Q O s λ ( )  I p,n λ ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>and then</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">O s λ ( )  I p,n λ ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ = Q −1 O 1 λ ( )  O n +1 λ ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>The element of the matrix Q in the lth row and the mth column, except for the first column, is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">q l, m = sin 2 π λ  b l ⋅  θ m ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ sin 2π λ  B l ⋅  θ m ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where  B l and  b l are respectively the imaging and the null baseline vectors in the lth measurement, and the  θ m is the position angle vector of the mth planet. On the other hand, the elements of the matrix Q in the first column are 1. The reconstructed spectrum of the mth planet is</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">I p, m λ ( ) = ′ q m, k O k λ ( ) k n ∑ ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where q' l,m represents the element of the inverse matrix Q -1 in the lth row and the mth column. When n=1, the above equation can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">I p,1 λ ( ) = O 2 λ ( ) − O 1 λ ( ) sin 2 π λ  b 2 ⋅  θ p,1 ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ sin 2π λ  B 2 ⋅  θ p,1 ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ − sin 2 π λ  b 1 ⋅  θ p,1 ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ sin 2π λ  B 1 ⋅  θ p,1 ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ . (15)</formula><p>This result is equal to that derived by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref>. On the other hand, the sky transmission of each planet in the multi-planet system is very complicated but it can be derived analytically. In general, the SNR is</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">SNR ≈ I p λ ( ) 2 O λ ( ) ,<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where is the photon variance of the total signal per spectral element in each chop state. The factor of 1/2 in Equation (16) results from subtracting the (+) and (-) chop states. Here, the wavelength dependence of the sky transmission for each planet is determined from the position of each planet and the imaging and the null baseline vectors. Generally, the dependency is much stronger as the number of the planets increases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Observations on n+2 baselines</head><p>We introduce an additional observation to avoid the wavelength dependency of the sky transmission because the number of independent acquired spectra corresponds to the combination of the observations. For simplicity, when n = 1, we take observations on three baselines and independently acquire the planet's spectrum three times. Here, these spectra are weighted with SNR and then are summed:</p><p>,</p><p>where SNR m − n λ ( ) and are the SNR and the planet's spectrum derived by combination of the mth and nth observations. The averaged SNR is defined as .</p><p>As shown in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(18)</ref>, the wavelength dependency of SNR could be relaxed, and then the SNR would improve over the whole observed wavelength range. Thus, observations on n+2 baselines can more effectively characterize n exoplanets. In this case the matrix Q is not square, and the inverse is replaced by the singular value decomposition (SVD) matrix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Field of View</head><p>Finally, we discuss the field of view of this method. Generally, the field of view of stellar interferometers are characterized by the sampling theorem. In other words, the field-of-view is limited by an incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane. On the other hand, according to this new method, the spectral resolution corresponds to incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane because the image of the planetary system can be reconstructed through Fourier transformation along the observing wavelengths. As described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref>, the radius of the field-of-view is limited by the spectral resolution:</p><p>.</p><p>where is the average of the observing wavelengths and λ δλ</p><p>is the spectral resolution of this system. In the case that the spectral resolution is 100 and the imaging baseline length is 100m, the field-of-view of this system is 2 arcsec.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SIMULATION</head><p>We performed numerical simulations to validate the proposed method. Based on the method, an image of a target planetary system is extracted and then the spectrum of each planet is estimated. In this section, we introduce the parameters required for the numerical simulations and show the reconstructed image of the target system and the estimated spectrum of each planet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Parameters</head><p>The target system is composed of a star, two planets, and a symmetric exozodiacal light distribution. The distance of this target system is 10pc. The target star is a Sun-like star (G2V) with an effective temperature Ts = 5784K and one solar luminosity. The physical size of the target star is one solar radius. These parameters are same as those of the Sun. One of the target planets, defined as "P1", is taken to be an analog Earth with an Earth radius R E = 6300km. It is positioned at (x, y) = (0.6AU, 0.8AU) around the star, where (x, y) is the coordinate system on the sky. The orbital radius of the planet corresponds to 1.0AU. The atmospheric composition of the target planet includes ozone, carbon dioxide, water, and methane. Another target planet, defined as "P2", is assumed to be a super-Earth with a radius of two Earth radii. The position of another target planet is at (1.6AU, 1.2AU) around the star. The semi-major axis of the planet is 2.0AU. The effective temperature of the planet is determined through its thermal equilibrium:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">T P = 265K a 1AU ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ −1/2 L 1L  ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ 1/ 4</formula><p>, where a is the semi-major axis of planet and L is the luminosity of host star. The effective temperatures of the planets P1 and P2 are 265K and 187K, respectively. The spectrum of the P2 planet is taken to be a blackbody. The azimuth angles of the planet P1 and P2 from the x-axis are defined as ϕ P1 and ϕ P 2 . A diagram of the system is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure   2</ref>.  In this paper, we extend the original concept proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref> to the case of multi-planet systems. For these, observations on two baselines are not sufficient to estimate each planet's position even if the separations of each signal from the host star along orthogonal two axes can be clearly extracted from two one-dimensional images of the planetary system. This is because there is an ambiguity in extracting the two-dimensional positions of more planets, given only two projected images on orthogonal axes. In Section 3 we perform numerical simulations to validate the concept. In Section 4 we show how to extract exoplanet spectra and discuss the capability of characterization of the Earth-like planets, and in Section 5 we give our conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">THEORY</head><p>In this section, we expand the original concept proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Matsuo et al. (2010)</ref> to include multi-planet systems. The method for extraction of each planet's position is presented in Section 2.1. The spectrum of each planet is analytically derived in Section 2.2. An improvement of the signal-to-noise ratio (S/N) for the spectrum of each planet is introduced in Section 2.3. Finally, the field of view of this method is discussed. We assume that the target is composed of a star and n multiple planets. A dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer with a sine phase chopping and a spectrometer is assumed. We assume that the exozodiacal disk has a symmetric brightness distribution with respect to the star.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Direct Imaging of a Planetary System</head><p>Based on the previous studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Lay 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Draper et al. 2006</ref>; see also the Appendix), the spectrally resolved signal, in unit of detected photoelectrons of the dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer for the individual chop state, is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">O ± (λ) = 1 2 d 2 θ I (λ, − → θ ) sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ × 1 ± sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where − → θ is the position vector on the sky, I (λ, − → θ ) is the signal from the source on the sky at λ with a single-dish telescope, − → b is the nulling baseline vector, and − → B is the imaging baseline vector. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows the locations and dimensions of the array. The I (λ, − → θ ) represents a product of the intensity of the source, total collecting area, bandwidth in a spectral element, detector efficiency, and beam efficiency. The + and − notations express the plus (+) and minus (−) chop states, respectively. Here, there is no fundamental limitation on the spectral resolution in this method. The spectral resolution of the planet is a priori chosen based on its S/N.</p><p>In order to apply this concept to multi-planet systems, we assume that a target comprises a single star, n planets, and local zodiacal plus exozodiacal light. The spectrally resolved signal is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">O ± (λ) = 1 2 Ω * d 2 θ I (λ, − → θ ) sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ × 1 ± sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ + 1 2 n k I p,k (λ, − → θ p,k )Ω p,k sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ p,k × 1 ± sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ p,k + 1 2 Ω fov I lz (λ) + I ez (λ, − → θ ) sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ × 1 ± sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where − → θ p,k is the position vector of the kth planet. Ω * and Ω p,k are the solid angles subtended by the star and the kth planet, and Ω fov is the field of view of this nulling interferometer.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">I * (λ, − → θ ), I p,k (λ, − → θ ), I lz (λ, − → θ )</formula><p>, and I ez (λ, − → θ ) are the intensities of the star, the kth planet, the local zodiacal light, and the exozodiacal light at λ, respectively. The demodulated signal is</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">O(λ) = O + (λ) − O − (λ) = Ω * d 2 θ I (λ, − → θ ) sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ + n k I p,k (λ, − → θ p,k )Ω p,k sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ p,k × sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ p,k + 1 2 Ω fov I lz (λ) + I ez (λ, − → θ ) sin 2 π λ − → b · − → θ × sin 2π λ − → B · − → θ .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>2  In addition, we apply a dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer with four 2.0m diameter correcting mirrors to this system (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>). The coordinate system on the aperture plane is ξ,η ( ) , where the ξ -and η -axes are parallel to the xand y-axes on the sky, respectively. The peak-to-peak pointing jitter of the array is set as 0.50mas based on a previous study <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Beichman &amp; Velusamy 1999</ref>). This pointing jitter of the array leads to breaking of the above centro-symmetric assumption. In other words, the target star can no longer be considered as an on-axis star, and an offset of the exozodiacal cloud produces an asymmetric brightness distribution. As a result, the stellar leakage becomes very large at wavelengths less than 10µm but the offset does not significantly affect the signal. We also consider the quantum efficiency, the read noise, and the dark current of the detector. Assuming that the detector array used for this simulation is the Si:As Impurity Band Conductor arrays developed for JWST MIRI, the quantum efficiency is 0.8, the read noise is 19e-, and the dark current is 0.03e-/s ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Love et al. 2004</ref>). The photoelectron signals of the target star, the exozodiacal light, and the local zodiacal light in one-hour integration time are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>729:50 (10pp), 2011 March 1</head><p>Matsuo et al.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Parameters</head><p>omposed of a star, two planets, and light distribution. The distance of c. The target star is a Sun-like star temperature T s = 5784 K and one ysical size of the target star is one eters are the same as those of the nets, defined as P1, is taken to be an radius R E = 6300 km. It is positioned AU) around the star, where (x, y) is the sky. The orbital radius of the 0 AU. The atmospheric composition es ozone, carbon dioxide, water, and lanet, defined as P2, is assumed to be s of two Earth radii. The position of (1.6 AU, 1.2 AU) around the star. The et is 2.0 AU. The effective temperature ed through its thermal equilibrium:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">) 1/4</formula><p>, where a is the semimajor axis minosity of host star. The effective ts P1 and P2 are 265 K and 187 K, m of the planet P2 is taken to be a ngle of the planets P1 and P2 from the d φ p2 , respectively. A diagram of the 2. dual-Bracewell nulling interferometer collecting mirrors to this system (see system on the aperture plane is (ξ, ζ ), are parallel to the x-and y-axes on peak-to-peak pointing jitter of the ased on a previous study (Beichman pointing jitter of the array leads to ntro-symmetric assumption. In other no longer be considered as an onof the exozodiacal cloud produces distribution. As a result, the stellar rge at wavelengths less than 10 µm gnificantly affect the signal. We also ciency, the read noise, and the dark ssuming that the detector array used i:As Impurity Band Conductor arrays I, the quantum efficiency is 0.8, the he dark current is 0.03e − s −1 (Love ectron signals of the target star, the e local zodiacal light in one-hour n in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ition of Each Planet</head><p>observations on three baselines to ch planet. Based on this method, we r the first measurement and then run Additionally, we rotate the array by ermine the positions of the two target re 1 shows the array configuration f the array for each measurement. e length is set as 300 m for accurate seline is set as 14 m for suppression he transmission of the target planet it of the habitable zone is 0.5 at 8 µm. itable zone is assumed to be 0.6 AU implicity, we assume that the imaging the first and second measurements <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Signals with a spectral resolution R = 100 in one-hour integration time for one of the two chop states. The black and the gray solid lines are the spectra of the analog Earth and the super-Earth, respectively. The dotted, dash-dotted, and dashed lines represent the spectra of the stellar leakage, the exozodiacal light, and the local zodiacal light, respectively. The null depth of this system is 10 −5 at 10 µm when the null and the imaging baseline lengths are 14m and 300 m, respectively. The fluxes of the local zodiacal light and the exozodiacal light are estimated, based on previous studies (e.g., Beichman &amp; Velusamy 1999). We assume that the amount of exozodiacal light is three times higher than that of our solar system. The Earth-like planet shows methane absorption at 7.4 µm, ozone at 9.6 µm, carbon dioxide at 15 µm, and water absorptions at 6.3 µm and beyond 12 µm while the super-Earth planet is taken to be just a blackbody object.</p><p>are perfectly parallel to the x-axis and the y-axis on the sky, respectively (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>). The azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, φ B1 , is set as 4π 9</p><p>. According to Equation (4), Fourier transformation of the spectrally resolved signals along the observing wavelengths for each measurement gives the one-dimensional position of the planet projected by each imaging baseline.</p><p>We use the signals at wavelengths between 9 and 18 µm but the observing wavelength range we assume is 6-20 µm. This is because the stellar leakage is large at wavelengths less than 8 µm due to the pointing jitter of the array and the local zodiacal light is very large at wavelengths greater than 18 µm. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> shows the reconstructed image of the planetary system through Fourier transformation of the spectrally resolved signals. An enlarged view of the central region of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 4 and 5</ref>, there appear two strong peaks, which are positioned at 0.6 and 1.6 AU for the first measurement, 0.8 and 1.2 AU, and 0.89 and 1.46 AU for the third measurement. The positions of the two planets on the sky are determined such that the separations of the fringe peaks from the host star along the imaging baseline vectors are satisfied by Equation (5). As a result, the positions of the Earthlike planet and the Jupiter-like planet are, respectively, obtained as (0.6 AU, 0.8 AU) and (4.0 AU, 3.0 AU) from our simulation. Here, the error in the position of each planet is determined by the spatial resolution, which is defined as λ/2B. In this simulation, because the FWHMs of the fringes are about 0.04 AU, the error in the position of each planet is ±0.02 AU from the observation on one baseline. Therefore, from observations on more than three baselines, the maximum error in the position of the planet for each projected semimajor axis is 0.02 √ 2 AU. 5 <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Signals with a spectral resolution R = 100 in one-hour integration time for one of the two chop states. The black and the gray solid lines are the spectra of the analog Earth and the super-Earth, respectively. The dotted, dashdotted, and dashed lines represent the spectra of the stellar leakage, the exozodiacal light, and the local zodiacal light, respectively. The null depth of this system is 10 −5 at 10 µm when the null and the imaging baseline lengths are 14m and 300m, respectively. The fluxes of the local zodiacal light and the exozodiacal light are estimated, based on previous studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Beichman &amp; Velusamy 1999</ref>). We assume that the amount of exozodiacal light is three times higher than that of our solar system. The Earth-like planet shows methane absorption at 7.4µm, ozone at 9.6µm, carbon dioxide at 15µm, and water absorptions at 6.3 µm and beyond 12 µm while the super-Earth planet is taken to be just a blackbody object.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Position of Each Planet</head><p>First, we perform the observations on three baselines to extract the position of each planet. Based on this method, we rotate the array by 90 degrees after the first measurement and then run the second measurement. Additionally, we rotate the array by ϕ B1 from the ξ -axis to determine the positions of the two target planets on the sky. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows the array configuration and the azimuth angle of the array for each measurement. Here, the imaging baseline length is set as 300m for accurate measurement. The null baseline is set as 14m for suppression of the stellar leakage. The transmission of the target planet positioned on the inner limit of habitable zone is 0.5 at 8µm. The inner limit of habitable zone is assumed to be 0.6AU in the target system. For simplify, we assume that the imaging baselines of the array in the first and the second measurements are perfectly parallel to the x-axis and the y-axis on the sky, respectively (See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2)</ref>. The azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, ϕ B1 , is set as 4π 9</p><p>. According to Equation (4), Fourier transformation of the spectrally resolved signals along the observing wavelengths for each measurement gives the onedimensional position of the planet projected by each imaging baseline. We use the signals at the wavelengths between 9 and 18µm but the observing wavelength range we assume is 6 -20µm. This is because the stellar leakage is large at the wavelengths less than 8µm due to the pointing jitter of the array and the local zodiacal light is very large at wavelengths greater than 18µm. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> shows the reconstructed image of the planetary system through Fourier transformation of the spectrally resolved signals. An enlarged view of the central region of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> and 5, there appear two strong peaks, which are positioned at 0.6AU and 1.6AU for the first measurement, 0.8AU and 1.2AU, and 0.89AU and 1.46 AU for the third measurement. The positions of the two planets on the sky are determined such that the separations of the fringe peaks from the host star along the imaging baseline vectors are satisfied with Equation (5). As a result, the positions of the Earth-like planet and the super Earth-like planet are respectively obtained as (0.6AU, 0.8AU) and (1.6AU, 1.2AU) from our simulation. Here, the error in the position of each planet is determined by the spatial resolution, which is defined as /2B. In this simulation, because the FWHMs of the fringes are about 0.04 AU, the error in the position of each planet is 0.02 AU from the observation on one baseline. Therefore, from observations on more than three baselines, the maximum error in the position of the planet for each projected semimajor axis is 0.02/2 AU. On the other hand, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>, the noise increases beyond 5.0AU, for each measurement. This comes from the incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane. In other words, the field-of-view in this case is around 1.0 arcsec, corresponding to that derived from Equation (17). In summary, we can measure the planets within the field of view and accurately determine the two-dimensional position of each one. It requires at least half a day to extract the image of the multiple planet system at 10pc.    On the other hand, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>, the noise increases beyond 5.0 AU, for each measurement. This comes from the incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane. In other words, the field of view in this case is around 1.0 arcsec, corresponding to that derived from Equation (17). In summary, we can measure the planets within the field of view and accurately determine the two-dimensional position of each one. It requires at least half a day per baseline orientation to extract the image of the multi-planet system at 10 pc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Spectrum of Each Planet</head><p>Next, we reconstruct the spectrum of each planet for its characterization. In this phase, the long imaging baseline is no longer required because the position of the target planet is accurately determined. Therefore, we set the imaging baseline length as 40 m for more suppression of the stellar leakage while we keep the null baseline length unchanged. As in the case of the observations for reconstruction of the image, the imaging baselines in the first and the second measurements are parallel to the x-and the y-axes, respectively. According to Equation (11), the spectrum of each planet can be reconstructed from the observations on three baselines. We set the azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, φ B1 , as 5π 9 . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> shows the wavelength dependence of the S/N for each planet. The S/ N of the reconstructed spectrum for each planet is more than five at the very limited wavelengths. This is because the S/N is directly related to the sky transmission, which is determined by the phases of each planet for the imaging and the null baselines. As a result, the reconstructed spectrum of each planet is very noisy in most of the observing wavelength range.    On the other hand, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>, the noise increases beyond 5.0 AU, for each measurement. This comes from the incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane. In other words, the field of view in this case is around 1.0 arcsec, corresponding to that derived from Equation (17). In summary, we can measure the planets within the field of view and accurately determine the two-dimensional position of each one. It requires at least half a day per baseline orientation to extract the image of the multi-planet system at 10 pc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Spectrum of Each Planet</head><p>Next, we reconstruct the spectrum of each planet for its characterization. In this phase, the long imaging baseline is no longer required because the position of the target planet is accurately determined. Therefore, we set the imaging baseline length as 40 m for more suppression of the stellar leakage while we keep the null baseline length unchanged. As in the case of the observations for reconstruction of the image, the imaging baselines in the first and the second measurements are parallel to the x-and the y-axes, respectively. According to Equation (11), the spectrum of each planet can be reconstructed from the observations on three baselines. We set the azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, φ B1 , as 5π 9 . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> shows the wavelength dependence of the S/N for each planet. The S/ N of the reconstructed spectrum for each planet is more than five at the very limited wavelengths. This is because the S/N is directly related to the sky transmission, which is determined by the phases of each planet for the imaging and the null baselines. As a result, the reconstructed spectrum of each planet is very noisy in most of the observing wavelength range. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Spectrum of Each Planet</head><p>Next, we reconstruct the spectrum of each planet for its characterization. In this phase, the long imaging baseline is no longer required because the position of the target planet is accurately determined. Therefore, we set the imaging baseline length as 40m for more suppression of the stellar leakage while we keep the null baseline length unchanged. As in the case of the observations for reconstruction of the image, the imaging baselines in the first and the second measurements are parallel to the x-and the y-axes, respectively. According to <ref type="bibr">Equation (11)</ref>, the spectrum of each planet can be reconstructed from the observations on three baselines. We set the azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, ϕ B1 , as 5π 9</p><p>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> shows the wavelength dependence of the SNR for each planet. The SNR of the reconstructed spectrum for each planet is more than five at the very limited wavelengths. This is because the SNR is directly related to the sky transmission, which is determined by the phases of each planet for the imaging and the null baselines. As a result, the reconstructed spectrum of each planet is very noisy in most of the observing wavelength range.  On the other hand, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>, the noise increases beyond 5.0 AU, for each measurement. This comes from the incomplete coverage of the (u, v) plane. In other words, the field of view in this case is around 1.0 arcsec, corresponding to that derived from Equation (17). In summary, we can measure the planets within the field of view and accurately determine the two-dimensional position of each one. It requires at least half a day per baseline orientation to extract the image of the multi-planet system at 10 pc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Spectrum of Each Planet</head><p>Next, we reconstruct the spectrum of each planet for its characterization. In this phase, the long imaging baseline is no longer required because the position of the target planet is accurately determined. Therefore, we set the imaging baseline length as 40 m for more suppression of the stellar leakage while we keep the null baseline length unchanged. As in the case of the observations for reconstruction of the image, the imaging baselines in the first and the second measurements are parallel to the x-and the y-axes, respectively. According to Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(11)</ref>, the spectrum of each planet can be reconstructed from the observations on three baselines. We set the azimuth angle of the array in the third measurement, φ B1 , as 5π 9 . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> shows the wavelength dependence of the S/N for each planet. The S/ N of the reconstructed spectrum for each planet is more than five at the very limited wavelengths. This is because the S/N is directly related to the sky transmission, which is determined by the phases of each planet for the imaging and the null baselines. As a result, the reconstructed spectrum of each planet is very noisy in most of the observing wavelength range. In order to decrease the wavelength dependency of the SNR, we introduce an additional observation. We rotate the array such that ϕ B2 is equal to the azimuth angle of the analog Earth from the x-axis, ϕ P1 . The separations projected on to the imaging baseline vector in the fourth measurement are 0.68 AU for the analog Earth and 1.92 AU for the super-Earth. Here, thanks to the fourth measurement, the number of the combinations of four measurements increases to four. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure  7</ref> shows the SNRs of each planet for the combinations of four measurements. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">Figure 8</ref> shows the averaged SNR of each planet, which is estimated according to <ref type="bibr">Equation (15)</ref>. The averaged SNR of each planet improves over the whole observing wavelengths except for around 11.5µm. The dip in SNR around 11.5µm results not from the intrinsic behavior of this method but is an artifact of the observing parameters. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">Figure 9</ref> shows the SNR-weighted spectra of the two target planets. These are much closer to the model spectra, compared with those derived from the observations on only three observations on only three observations, but the spectrum of each planet is still noisy at 11.5µm. The observing time in each baseline is 10 days and the total integration time is 40 days.    In order to decrease the wavelength dependence of the S/N, we introduce an additional observation. We rotate the array such that φ B2 is equal to the azimuth angle of the analog Earth from the x-axis, φ P 1 . The separations projected on to the imaging the averaged S/N of each planet, which is estimated according to Equation <ref type="bibr">(15)</ref>. The averaged S/N of each planet improves over the whole observing wavelength except for around 11.5 µm. This dip in S/N around 11.5 µm results not from the intrinsic    In order to decrease the wavelength dependence of the S/N, we introduce an additional observation. We rotate the array such that φ B2 is equal to the azimuth angle of the analog Earth from the x-axis, φ P 1 . The separations projected on to the imaging baseline vector in the fourth measurement are 0.68 AU for the analog Earth and 1.92 AU for the super-Earth. Here, thanks to the fourth measurement, the number of combinations of four measurements increases to four. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 7</ref> shows the S/Ns of each planet for combinations of four measurements. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">Figure 8</ref> shows the averaged S/N of each planet, which is estimated according to <ref type="bibr">Equation (15)</ref>. The averaged S/N of each planet improves over the whole observing wavelength except for around 11.5 µm. This dip in S/N around 11.5 µm results not from the intrinsic behavior of this method but is an artifact of the observing parameters. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">Figure 9</ref> shows the S/N-weighted spectra of the two target planets. These are much closer to the model spectra, compared with those derived from the observations on only three observations, but the spectrum of each planet is still noisy    In order to decrease the wavelength dependence of the S/N, we introduce an additional observation. We rotate the array such that φ B2 is equal to the azimuth angle of the analog Earth from the x-axis, φ P 1 . The separations projected on to the imaging baseline vector in the fourth measurement are 0.68 AU for the analog Earth and 1.92 AU for the super-Earth. Here, thanks to the fourth measurement, the number of combinations of four measurements increases to four. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 7</ref> shows the S/Ns of each planet for combinations of four measurements. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">Figure 8</ref> shows the averaged S/N of each planet, which is estimated according to <ref type="bibr">Equation (15)</ref>. The averaged S/N of each planet improves over the whole observing wavelength except for around 11.5 µm. This dip in S/N around 11.5 µm results not from the intrinsic behavior of this method but is an artifact of the observing parameters. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">Figure 9</ref> shows the S/N-weighted spectra of the two target planets. These are much closer to the model spectra, compared with those derived from the observations on only three observations, but the spectrum of each planet is still noisy 7 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">Figure 9</ref>. Reconstructed spectra (black solid line) of the Earth-like planet (left) and the Jupiter-like planet (right). The gray solid lines represent the model spectrum.</p><note type="other">. S/Ns of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j −k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</note><note type="other">. S/Ns of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j −k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CHARACTERIZATION</head><p>In the previous section, the positions of analog Earth and super-Earth were extracted and those spectra were also reconstructed based on the proposed method. In this section, we evaluate the reconstructed spectra and examine whether this method allows us to characterize the planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Biomarkers</head><p>There are various absorption lines in the mid-infrared: CH 4 at 7.5µm, O 3 at 9.6µm, H 2 O around 6µm and beyond 16µm, CH 4 at 7.5µm, and several nitrogen compounds, N 2 O at 7.8, 8.5, and 17µm, NH 3 at 9.6 -11µm, NO at 5.4µm, and NO 2 at 6.2µm. Detection of these absorption lines allows us to examine the existence of biological activity on planets (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Selsis et al. 2005</ref>  <ref type="bibr">3</ref> can be more easily formed instead of the fast recombination of CO 2 as the abundance of CO 2 increases in the atmosphere. According to their simulation on an accumulation of O 2 and O 3 through the abiotic processes in the atmosphere on exoplanets, a CO 2 absorption band appears at 9.4 and 10.5µm and also masks the ozone absorption line at 9.6µm when the CO 2 pressure is more than 50 mbar. Therefore, a much higher spectral resolution (R = 100) can separate the O 3 band at 9.6µm from the CO 2 band at 9.4 and avoid a false positive detection. The other absorption lines of CH4, NH3, and NO2 are still questionable biological signatures because the possibility of abiotic synthesis of these compounds has not been fully studied. Indeed, an atmospheric level of CH4 equal to that of the Earth can also be supplied through an impact of cometary ice, which contains 0.5%-1% of CH4 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Selsis et al. 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">SNR</head><p>Based on this discussion, we focus on H 2 O, O 3 , and CO 2 bands and examine how much SNR is required for detection of these bands. The depths of the absorption features are characterized by the atmospheric profiles of abundance and temperature. For example, the depth of the ozone band strongly depends on a temperature contrast between the surface and the stratosphere. The depth of each absorption feature in the current Earth's atmosphere is approximately 0.8 and 0.2 for H 2 O around 6µm and beyond 16µm, 0.5 for O 3 at 9.6µm, and 0.6 for CO 2 at 15 µm. Therefore, the discrepancy between the reconstructed and the model spectra should be less than ±10% for detection of these strong absorption features. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 10</ref> shows the ratio of the reconstructed to the model spectra for each planet as a function of SNR. The discrepancy between the reconstructed and the model spectra is very large for SNR of less than 5. In other words, the reconstructed spectra are very noisy at the specific wavelengths, where SNR is less than 5. On the other hand, the ratio of the reconstructed to the model spectra is close to 1 as SNR increases. The difference is less than ±10% for most of the data with SNR of more than 5. Conclusively, the SNR required for detection of the strong absorption lines should be more than 5. We extract only the data with SNR of more than 5 and then reconstruct the spectrum of each planet. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 11</ref> shows the spectra of analog Earth and super-Earth with SNR of more than 5. The reconstructed spectrum agrees well with the model one for each planet. H 2 O, O 3 , and CO 2 absorption features can be detected with a spectral resolution of 100. This method also allows us to resolve the O 3 at 9.6 µm and the CO 2 bands at 9.4 and 10.5µm appearing in the CO 2 -rich atmosphere and thus avoid a false positive detection. So it allows us to adequately characterize the analog Earth around the Sun-like star at 10 pc and examine whether biological activity on the planet exists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Error in the Position of the Planet</head><p>The finite imaging baseline length produces the error in the position of each planet. As a result, the error introduces differences between the measured and the model spectra, which can be estimated from Equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(12)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">(14)</ref>. We derive the difference here through numerical simulation. For simplicity, we evaluate the impact of only the error in the position of the planet on the reconstructed spectrum. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 12</ref> shows the reconstructed spectrum of the analog Earth in the case that the error in its position is (−0.014 AU, 0.014 AU). The applied value is equal to the maximum ambiguity in the planet's position along each axis determined through the observations on more than three baselines. In this case, the difference between the model and the reconstructed spectra is less than ±10% over the observing wavelengths except for those longer than 19 μm. Therefore, an additional criterion is required for avoiding artificial noise. A study on this criterion will be made in the future.  at 11.5 µm. The observing time in each baseline is 10 days and the total integration time is 40 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CHARACTERIZATION</head><p>In the previous section, the positions of analog Earth and super-Earth were extracted and those spectra were also reconstructed based on the proposed method. In this section, we evaluate the reconstructed spectra and examine whether this method allows us to characterize the planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Biomarkers</head><p>There are various absorption lines in the mid-infrared: CH 4 at 7.5 µm, O 3 at 9.6 µm, H 2 O around 6 µm and beyond 16 µm, CH 4 at 7.5 µm, and several nitrogen compounds, N 2 O at 7.8, 8.5, and 17 µm, NH 3 at 9.6-11 µm, NO at 5.4 µm, and NO 2 at 6.2 µm. Detection of these absorption lines allows us to examine the existence of biological activity on planets (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Selsis et al. 2005</ref> absorption band appears at 9.4 and 10.5 µm and also masks the ozone absorption line at 9.6 µm when the CO 2 pressure is more than 50 mbar. Therefore, a much higher spectral resolution (R = 100) can separate the O 3 band at 9.6 µm from the CO 2 band at 9.4 µm and avoid a false positive detection. The other absorption lines of CH 4 , NH 3 , and NO 2 are still questionable biological signatures because the possibility of abiotic synthesis of these compounds has not been fully studied. Indeed, an atmospheric level of CH 4 equal to that of the Earth can also be supplied through an impact of cometary ice, which contains 0.5%-1% of CH 4 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Selsis et al. 2005</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">S/N</head><p>Based on this discussion, we focus on H 2 O, O 3 , and CO 2 bands and examine how much S/N is required for detection of these bands. The depths of the absorption features are characterized by the atmospheric profiles of abundance and temperature. For example, the depth of the ozone band strongly depends on a temperature contrast between the surface and the stratosphere. The depth of each absorption feature in the current Earth's atmosphere is approximately 0.8 and 0.2 for H 2 O around 6 µm and beyond 16 µm, 0.5 for O 3 at 9.6 µm, and 0.6 for CO 2 at 15 µm. Therefore, the discrepancy between the reconstructed and the model spectra should be less than ±10% for detection of these strong absorption features. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 10</ref> shows the ratio of the reconstructed to the model spectra for each planet as a function of S/N. The discrepancy between the reconstructed and the model spectra is very large for S/N of less than 5. In other words, the reconstructed spectra are very noisy at the specific wavelengths, where S/N is less than 5. On the other hand, the ratio of the reconstructed to the model spectra is close to 1 as S/N increases. The difference is less than ±10% for most of the data with S/N of more than 5. Conclusively, the S/N required for detection of the strong absorption lines should be more than 5.</p><p>We extract only the data with S/N of more than 5 and then reconstruct the spectrum of each planet. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 11</ref> shows the spectra of analog Earth and super-Earth with S/N of more than 5. The reconstructed spectrum agrees well with the model one for each planet. H 2 O, O 3 , and CO 2 absorption features can be detected with a spectral resolution of 100. This method also allows us to resolve the O 3 at 9.6 µm and the CO 2 bands at 9.4 and 10.5 µm appearing in the CO 2 -rich atmosphere and thus avoid a false positive detection. So it allows us to adequately characterize the analog Earth around the Sun-like star at 10 pc and examine whether biological activity on the planet exists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Error in the Position of the Planet</head><p>The finite imaging baseline length produces the error in the position of each planet. As a result, the error introduces differences between the measured and the model spectra, which can be estimated from Equations (12)-(14). We derive the difference here through numerical simulation. For simplicity, we evaluate the impact of only the error in the position of the planet on the reconstructed spectrum. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 12</ref> shows the reconstructed spectrum of the analog Earth in the case 8 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 10</ref>. Ratio of the reconstructed spectrum to the model one for each planet as a function of SNR.      that the error in its position is (−0.014 AU, 0.014 AU). The applied value is equal to the maximum ambiguity in the planet's position along each axis determined through the observations on more than three baselines. In this case, the difference between the model and the reconstructed spectra is less than ±10% over the observing wavelengths except for those longer than 19 µm. Therefore, an additional criterion is required for avoiding artificial noise. A study on this criterion will be made in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we presented a novel concept for direct detection and characterization of exoplanets in the mid-infrared. There are several advantages to this method. We show that the (u, v) plane can be simultaneously and uniformly filled by use of the continuous observing wavelengths instead of continuously rotating the baselines. As a result, this concept allows us to acquire a clean reconstructed image and to perfectly 9 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 12</ref>. Impact of the error in the position of the analog Earth on its reconstructed spectrum (dots). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum and 0.9 or 1.1 times its spectrum, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we presented a novel concept for direct detection and characterization of exoplanets in the mid-infrared. There are several advantages to this method. We show that the (u,v) plane can be simultaneously and uniformly filled by use of the continuous observing wavelengths instead of continuously rotating the baselines. As a result, this concept allows us to acquire a clean reconstructed image and to perfectly remove speckles from the reconstructed images. Furthermore, observations on only three and n + 1 baselines respectively are sufficient to extract an image of the planetary system and the spectrum of each planet, although the SNR will improve with more baselines. We validated the concept using numerical simulations. Two target planets, an analog Earth and a super-Earth, orbiting a Sun-like star at 10 pc were taken as an example. The position of each planet on the sky and its spectrum were derived through this method. The analog Earth and the super-Earth could be detected from the observations on three baselines and the spectrum of each planet could be successfully obtained with a spectral resolution of 100 from observations on four baselines. We also discussed characterization of the planets in the mid-infrared and mentioned the possibility of detection of false biological features produced by an abiotic process. Based on current studies, a simultaneous signature of H2O, O3, and CO2 is a potential biological indicator. On the other hand, in a CO2-rich atmosphere, O2 and O3 could be photochemically accumulated through photolysis of CO2. In addition, two CO2 absorption bands appear at 9.4 and 10.5 μm and then mask the O3 absorption feature at 9.6 μm. We found that an SNR of 5 or more is required for secure detection of H2O, O3, and CO2 absorption features. The reconstructed spectrum can be acquired at observing wavelengths from 8 to 19 μm for the observing time of 40 days. Thanks to the high spectral resolution R = 100, this method also resolves the O3 and the CO2 bands produced in the CO2-rich atmosphere and avoids a false positive detection. Thus, this method allows us to fully characterize the planet and examine whether biological activity exists. We need further analysis of this concept, but already the basic idea is clear: measurements on a few discrete baselines are sufficient to extract images and spectra from multi-planet systems. We also need to include the effect of asymmetries in the exozodiacal distributions:Defrère et al. (2010) estimated the impact of these asymmetrical disks on the previous method and concluded that this effect could produce artificial planet signals. We reserve these modifications for a future paper.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Array configuration for each measurement. The azimuth angles of the array in the third measurement and the fourth measurement from the ξ -axis are set as φ B1 and φ B2 , respectively. The ξ -axis is parallel to the x-axis on the sky.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Array configuration for each measurement. The azimuth angles of the array in the third measurement and the forth measurement from the ξ axis are set as ϕ B1 and ϕ B2 , respectively. The ξ axis is parallel to the x-axis on the sky.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Conceptual diagram of the target planetary system (left) and the center region of the target system (right). P1 and the P2 represent an analog Earth and super-Earth, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Images of the planetary system along the x-axis (left) and y-axis (right). The integration time for each baseline is 12 hr. The target planets are positioned at (x, y) = (0.6 AU, 0.8 AU).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Enlarged views of the central region, −2.0 AU &lt; a &lt; 2.0 AU, of Figure 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Wavelength dependency of the S/N for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>6 Figure 4 .</head><label>64</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Images of the planetary system along the x-axis (left) and y-axis (right). The integration time for each baseline is 12 hr. The target planets are positioned at (x, y) = (0.6 AU, 0.8 AU).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Images of the planetary system along the x-axis (left) and y-axis (right). The integration time for each baseline is 12 hr. The target planets are positioned at (x, y) = (0.6 AU, 0.8 AU).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Enlarged views of the central region, −2.0 AU &lt; a &lt; 2.0 AU, of Figure 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Wavelength dependency of the S/N for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>6 Figure 5 .</head><label>65</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Enlarged views of the central region, −2.0AU &lt; a &lt; 2.0AU of Figure 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Enlarged views of the central region, −2.0 AU &lt; a &lt; 2.0 AU, of Figure 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Wavelength dependency of the S/N for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>6 Figure 6 .</head><label>66</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Wavelength dependency of the S/N for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The Astrophysical Journal, 729:50 (10pp), 2011 March 1 Matsuo et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. S/Ns of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j −k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Average of the three S/Ns for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Reconstructed spectra (black solid line) of the Earth-like planet (left) and the Jupiter-like planet (right). The gray solid lines represent the model spectrum.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. SNRs of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j−k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. S/Ns of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j −k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Average of the three S/Ns for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Reconstructed spectra (black solid line) of the Earth-like planet (left) and the Jupiter-like planet (right). The gray solid lines represent the model spectrum.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>7 Figure 8 .</head><label>78</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Average of the three SNRs for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. S/Ns of the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right) in combinations of four measurements. The black solid, black dashed, gray solid, and black dotted lines are, respectively, S/Ns in the 1-2-3, 1-3-4, 1-2-4, and 2-3-4 measurements, where i−j −k represents the combination of the ith, jth, and kth measurements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Average of the three S/Ns for the analog Earth (left) and the super-Earth (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Reconstructed spectra (black solid line) of the Earth-like planet (left) and the Jupiter-like planet (right). The gray solid lines represent the model spectrum.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_29"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Ratio of the reconstructed spectrum to the model one for each planet as a function of S/N.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_30"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The Astrophysical Journal, 729:50 (10pp), 2011 March 1 Matsuo et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_31"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Reconstructed spectra with S/N of more than 5 (dots) for the analog Earth (upper) and the super-Earth (lower). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum and 0.9 or 1.1 times its spectrum, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_32"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12. Impact of the error in the position of the analog Earth on its reconstructed spectrum (dots). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_33"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Reconstructed spectra with S/N of more than 5 (dots) for the analog Earth (upper) and the super-Earth (lower). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum and 0.9 or 1.1 times its spectrum, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_34"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Reconstructed spectra with S/N of more than 5 (dots) for the analog Earth (upper) and the super-Earth (lower). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum and 0.9 or 1.1 times its spectrum, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_35"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12. Impact of the error in the position of the analog Earth on its reconstructed spectrum (dots). The gray solid and the dotted lines represent the model spectrum and 0.9 or 1.1 times its spectrum, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). The O 3 composition is the most important for an indication of biological activity because oxygenic photosynthesis in the biosphere, the dominant metabolism of cyanobacterias and plants, builds up the current O 2 -rich atmosphere on the Earth.</figDesc><table>Here, an O 2 molecule is photochemically decomposed into two O atoms by UV radiation. A 
chemical reaction among the O atoms, the O 2 molecules, and any compound, called a three-body reaction, results in 
buildup of an O 3 atmosphere. O 3 is a tracer of O 2 , but the amount of O 3 depends only weakly on the total amount of O 2 
(L eger et al. 1993). 
Selsis et al. (2002) investigated a possibility of abiotic synthesis of O 2 and O 3 and found that O 2 and O </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEGEMENT</head><p>We very much thank an anonymous referee whose sugges-tions improved this study. In this work, T.M. was supported as a Research Fellow of the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, and he thanks the Jet Propulsion Laboratory for its hospitality.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R P</forename><surname>Angel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Woolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">475</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Beichman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Velusamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ASP Conf. Ser. 194, Working on the Fringe: Optical and IR Interferometry from Ground and Space</title>
		<editor>S. Unwin &amp; R. Stachnik</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ASP</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page">408</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bracewell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Absil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Den Hartog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hanot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Draper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Noecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dumont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1822</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1345</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lèger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pirre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Marceau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">309</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Love</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5499</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1348</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7734</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">; M</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">487</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">614</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mennesson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Mariotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">208</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ohta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hattori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Matsuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2576</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">719</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">890</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Despois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Parisot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">985</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lèger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ollivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lectures in Astrobiology</title>
		<editor>M. Gargaud, B. Barbier, H. Martin, &amp; J. Reisse</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">385</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Thalman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">707</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
