<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:18+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Exoplanet Orbital Eccentricity -Multiplicity Relation and the Solar System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mary</forename><forename type="middle">Anne</forename><surname>Limbach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08544</postCode>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The Kavli Institute for the Physics and Mathematics of the Universe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The University of Tokyo</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>227-8568</postCode>
									<settlement>Kashiwa</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08544</postCode>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Exoplanet Orbital Eccentricity -Multiplicity Relation and the Solar System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Submitted to Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</note>
					<note>i i &quot;ecc103014&quot; -2014/12/2 -1:44 -page 1 -#1 i i i i i i</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The known population of exoplanets exhibits a much wider range of orbital eccentricities than Solar System planets and has a much higher average eccentricity. These facts have been widely interpreted to indicate that the Solar System is an atypical member of the overall population of planetary systems. We report here on a strong anti-correlation of orbital eccentricity with multiplicity (num-ber of planets in the system) among catalogued radial velocity (RV) systems. The mean, median and rough distribution of eccentricities of Solar System planets fits an extrapolation of this anti-correlation to the eight planet case rather precisely despite the fact that no more than 2 Solar System planets would be detectable with RV data comparable to that in the exoplanet sample. Moreover, even if regarded as a single or double planetary system, the Solar System lies in a reasonably heavily populated region of eccentricity-multiplicity space. Thus, the Solar System is not anomalous among known exo-planetary systems with respect to eccentricities when its multiplicity is taken into account. Specifically, as the multiplicity of a system increases the eccentricity decreases roughly as a power law of index -1.20. A simple and plausible but ad hoc and model-dependent interpretation of this relationship implies that approximately 80% of the one planet and 25% of the two planet systems in our sample have additional, as yet undiscovered, members but that systems of higher observed multiplicity are largely complete (i.e., relatively rarely contain additional undiscovered planets). If low eccentricities indeed favor high multiplicities, habitability may be more common in systems with a larger number of planets. planetary systems-fundamental parameters, orbital eccentricities, dynamical evolution , Solar System; techniques-radial velocity Significance Statement The Solar System planets have near-circular orbits (i.e. unusually low eccentricity) compared with the known population of exoplanets, planets that orbit stars other than the Sun. This fact has been widely interpreted to indicate that the Solar System is an atypical member of the overall population of planetary systems. We find a strong anti-correlation of or-bital eccentricity with the number of planets (multiplicity) in a system that extrapolates nicely to the eight-planet, Solar System case despite the fact that no more than 2 Solar System planets would be detectable in the sample in which the anti-correlation was discovered. Habitability may be more common in systems with a larger number of planets which have lower typical eccentricities.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Solar System orbital eccentricities are unusually low compared to those of exoplanets. This fact is one of the most frequently noted major surprises revealed by the discovery and early explorations of the exoplanet population orbiting Sun-like stars and has been widely interpreted to indicate that the Solar System is not a representative example of a planetary system (reviews by (1; 2; 3) and references therein). Many planetary formation theories developed prior to the discovery of exoplanets suggested planets would have eccentricities similar to the Solar System planets (4; 5). Several attempts have been made to accurately model the dynamical evolution of planetary systems since then with the goal of explaining the observed eccentricity distribution <ref type="bibr">(6; 7; 8; 9; 10)</ref>. These papers invoke planet-planet interactions as the primary mechanism determining the distribution of orbital eccentricities. The most recent of these papers, (10), concludes that there would be a dependence of eccentricity on multiplicity (the number of planets in the system) in this scenario. We use existing RV exoplanet data to test that prediction.</p><p>Our dataset consist of 403 of the 441 cataloged radial velocity (RV) exoplanets obtained since the 1990s (exoplanet.org). Of these 127 are members of known multiple-planet systems with multiplicities of up to six. The data are sufficient to allow an estimate of the relationship of eccentricity to multiplicity. It has been noted that eccentricity in two planet systems tends to be lower than in single planet systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. This paper explores the relation at higher multiplicities and notes its unexpected and surprising consistency with the Solar System case.</p><p>The dataset is discussed in the next section. We then show the trend in eccentricity with multiplicity and comment on possible sources of error and bias. Next we measure the mean, median and probability density distribution of eccentricities for various multiplicities and fit them to a simple power-law model for multiplicities greater than two. This fit is used to make a rough estimate of the number of higher multiplicity systems likely to be contaminating the one and two planet system samples due to as yet undiscovered members under plausible, but far from certain, assumptions. Finally, we conclude with some discussion of the implications of this result.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Dataset</head><p>Only radial velocity (RV) exoplanet data obtained from exoplanet.org are used for this analysis. All of the RV exoplanets listed on the website that have a measured eccentricity are included in the analysis. If the eccentricity of the planet was not listed or if it was given as zero, the exoplanet was excluded from our sample. Thirty-eight systems were excluded on the latter basis, of which twenty-nine had their eccentricity constrained to zero in the orbital fit. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i i i i i i</formula><p>The 5-and 6-planet systems, one of each, were combined into one bin so that there was sufficient data for a statical analysis. Note that the total number of planets with a given multiplicity is not necessarily a multiple of the multiplicity of the system because not all planets in some systems have measured eccentricities. In the cases where a certain parameter of an exoplanet or exoplanet system is under debate, we used the exoplanet.org value. For instance, the multiplicity of a system may be three planets based on observations, however the motion of those three planets may imply that there are additional companions and therefore the multiplicity of the system may be listed as four planets rather than three on exoplanet.org. In all such cases, we simply adopt the data listed on the website for consistency. The data were taken from the website over the course of several weeks in February and March 2014. We used RV data only for our analysis since the planets in that subset of the data set typically have known and relatively reliably measured eccentricities. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref> shows the cumulative eccentricity distribution function in exoplanet systems and the Solar System for systems of various multiplicities. There is a clear trend towards lower eccentricities in higher multiplicity systems. This trend is perhaps most noticeable in the top (high eccentricity) half of the plot. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref> shows the eccentricity vs. semi-major axis relation at each multiplicity and also displays the strong tendency towards lower eccentricity at higher multiplicity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Trend in Multiplicity verses Eccentricity</head><p>The strength and nature of the anti-correlation of orbital eccentricity with multiplicity is even more dramatically revealed by plotting the mean and median eccentricity as a function of multiplicity, as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Two features of this figure are worthy of special note: 1 -The divergence of the one-planet systems, and two-planet systems to a lesser extent, from what appears to be a power-law relation at higher multiplicities is noticeable in both the mean and median curves. 2 -The Solar System fits the eccentricity trend at higher multiplicity quite well despite the fact that the RV data quality for the exoplanetary systems would only allow the detection of Jupiter and perhaps Saturn. In other words, it would be more statistically consistent to plot the SS point in these figures at a multiplicity of one or two, as also shown in the figure. In either case, the Solar System does not appear to have unusually low orbital eccentricities with respect to exoplanet systems, but rather the Solar System planet eccentricities are consistent with the exoplanet eccentricity distribution when multiplicity is taken into account.</p><p>The uncertainties of the mean eccentricities shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> were calculated by bootstrapping. The bootstrap method gave an uncertainty of approximately two-thirds of the usual rms estimator, which is consistent with the limited extent of the eccentricity distribution tail. The uncertainties in the medians correspond to the one-third and two-thirds points in the distributions shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref> divided by √ N − 1, where N is the number of points in the multiplicity bin.</p><p>A 2-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov (K-S) test was used to determine the significance of the differences in the eccentricity distributions of systems with different multiplicities. The test was applied both to the entire data sample and to the subsamples consisting of the highest 75% of the eccentricities in each multiplicity subsample. Use of the latter subset of the data is motivated by the possibility that low multiplicity systems with low eccentricity orbits may have undiscovered members and thus actually be of higher multiplicity.</p><p>In both cases, the p-values consistently decrease for larger difference in the multiplicities of the two samples being compared. This is consistent with the systematic trends visible in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1 and 3</ref>. The results of the tests for the full sample and the high eccentricity subsamples are shown in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. In high eccentricity subsample case, for samples which have multiplicities that differ by at least two planets, the K-S test yield a statistically significant difference (p ≤ 0.05). At higher multiplicities, the significance (1 -p) of the difference between distributions with adjacent multiplicities generally decreases. This may well be an artifact of the smaller sample sizes at higher multiplicities rather than an actual convergence of the eccentricity distributions.</p><p>Sources of Error. Systematic errors in the eccentricity distribution of exoplanets are possibly due to the techniques used for measuring this parameter and biases associated with exoplanet detection methods. Shen &amp; Turner (12) studied the systematic bias of RV determinations of eccentricity using the conventional χ 2 fitting and showed that such measurements are biased high and significantly so for low values of N 1/2 K/σ, where K is the velocity semi-amplitude and σ is the typical uncertainty of each of the N velocity measurements. One might then be concerned that higher multiplicity systems receive more telescope time and thus have a higher value of this parameter and a more accurately determined eccentricity values than lower multiplicity systems. If this were the case, one might observe a multiplicity-eccentricity trend due to observational bias rather than a true physical phenomena. To ensure that this effect is negligible for our dataset, we conducted a careful analysis of the measured N 1/2 K/σ values and found that there is no significant effect in our sample. Furthermore, higher-multiplicity systems tended to have N 1/2 K/σ values similar to those of lower-multiplicity systems. <ref type="bibr">Shen &amp; Turner (12)</ref> only expect eccentricity to increase for N 1/2 K/σ 15 and most of the measurements in our sample have higher N 1/2 K/σ value than that threshold. For these reasons, we do not believe that the multiplicity-eccentricity trend we reported here is influenced by this potential bias.</p><p>A probable shortcoming of the data is undetected companions, especially in low-multiplicity systems. Given the eccentricity-multiplicity relation, this would add low eccentricity planets to the low-multiplicity subsamples. And indeed there does appear to be an excess of low eccentricities in the low-multiplicity systems relative to a smooth extrapolation of their higher-eccentricity distributions (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>), and this ?excess? of low-eccentricity orbits is particularly noticeable in the single-planet and two-planet distributions. This raises the question of whether or not the turnover in the trend at low-multiplicities in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> is real or due to contamination of the low-multiplicity by high-multiplicity systems with so far undiscovered planets. In the next section we give a crude and model-dependent estimate of the number of higher-multiple systems contaminating the one-and two-planet distributions by fitting a power law to the higher-multiplicity data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anaylsis</head><p>For each multiplicity, the probability density distributions of eccentricities were derived from the cumulative eccentricity distributions and is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>. The probability density distributions were obtained by taking the derivative of polynomials that were fit to the cumulative eccentricity distribution function (the data shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). This procedure yields a heavily smoothed estimate of the true differential distributions. Second order polynomials were fit to the data except in the one planet case. A K-S test indicated that a second order polynomial was inconsistent (p &lt; 0.01) with the one planet</p><note type="other">i i "ecc103014" -2014/12/2 -1:44 -page 3 -#3 i i i i i i</note><p>data, and a third order polynomial was necessary to obtain an acceptable fit.</p><p>If we knew the true occurrence rate of planetary systems as a function of multiplicity, these probability density distributions would allow determination of the likelihood of a planet with any given eccentricity belonging to a system of a particular multiplicity. While that conditional is clearly not satisfied at the present time, it is clear that if one wants to find companions to existing exoplanets, one-and two-planet systems with low eccentricities are relatively good targets for further investigation.</p><p>A power law was fit to the median eccentricity vs. multiplicity relationship and is shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. The fit is only for the higher multiplicity data, specifically M &gt; 2 where M is the multiplicity or number of planets in the system. The oneand two-planet systems were excluded from the fit on the assumption that they are likely contaminated with planets that belong in higher-multiplicity bins due to so far undetected additional planets in those systems. If the eccentricity (e) verses multiplicity (M ) relation obeys this power law</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">e (M ) ≈ 0.584M −1.20 [ 1 ]</formula><p>fit, then the relationship can be used to estimate the number of systems in the one-and two-planet bins that belong to highermultiplicity systems. Proceeding on the basis of this hypothesis leads to the conclusion that approximately 80% of the one-planet systems and 25% of the two-planet systems belong to higher-multiplicity systems with as yet undiscovered members. While this scenario seems quite plausible, we emphasis that the estimates of companions in the one-and two-planet bins is dependent on the assumption that the true eccentricitymultiplicity trend behaves like a power law of constant index at all multiplicities and that the M &gt; 2 subsamples are not significantly contaminated by yet higher multiplicity systems due to undiscovered members. It is also quite possible that the turn-over or plateau seen in the eccentricity distribution is an actual physical phenomena. The power law fit can also be used to predict the median eccentricity of as yet undiscovered high-multiplicity RV systems. For example, we estimate that 7-planet RV systems, when discovered, will have a median eccentricity of 0.06±0.01.</p><p>In addition to studying the relation between eccentricity and multiplicity, we also checked for a trend in semi-major axis with multiplicity but found no significant relationship with the exception of the trend noted by (13) that extremely short period exoplanets ( 10 days) typically have lower orbital eccentricities, presumably due to tidal circularization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The distribution of orbital eccentricities as a function of multiplicity provides an important new constraint (or clue) for planetary system formation and evolution models. The observational evidence for the multiplicity-eccentricity relation can perhaps be explained by planet-planet interactions and dynamical evolution. The general trend of decreasing eccentricity with increasing multiplicity was predicted by (10) using dynamical evolution simulations. Although the relationship reported here is qualitatively similar to that prediction, the observed dependence of e on M is steeper and extends to smaller eccentricities than the one produced by the simulations carried out by <ref type="bibr">Juric &amp; Tremaine (10)</ref>.</p><p>Although we are aware of no reason to suspect that the strong dependence of orbital eccentricity on multiplicity among RV exoplanet systems reported here is due to some defect or bias in the available data, it is undeniable that it is based on an inhomogeneous and statistically ill-conditioned data set. However, even if it were the case that the trend shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> is somehow a spurious non-physical one, the empirical correlation is still an important one which merits detailed future study because such a situation would imply that either a large number of low-eccentricity, low multiplicity exoplanetary systems or high-eccentricity, high-multiplicity ones have been systematically missed in RV searches.</p><p>The rather precise consistency of the eccentricity distribution, as well as its mean and median, of the 8-planet Solar System with the observed correlations presented above is rather puzzling because existing RV data has neither the precision nor the duration required to detect Solar System planets other than Jupiter and, perhaps, Saturn. Thus the fair comparison to the RV sample would regard the Solar System as a multiplicity one or two case, as illustrated in the figures. There are at least two possible interpretations: One is that this is simply a statistical fluke and that the comparison of the Solar System to exoplanetary systems would be quite different if the RV data used to construct our sample were of sufficient quality to detect all eight Solar System planets. Another is that the comparison is valid because much better RV data would not result in the detection of a significant number of additional planets in the M &gt; 2 systems.</p><p>Intriguingly, the Solar Systems position in eccentricitymultiplicity space is not particularly unusual even if it is regarded as an M = 1 or M = 2 case, as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref> which shows that the Solar System lies in a reasonably densely populated region of the space at M = 1 or M = 2 as well as fitting an extrapolation to M = 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>We find that the orbital eccentricities of the Solar System planets are consistent with those found in exoplanetary systems when multiplicity is taken into account. Specifically, we find that as the multiplicity of a system increases the eccentricity decreases. This relation can be well fit by a power law at multiplicities greater than two. A simplistic and model-dependent interpretation of this fit implies that ∼80% of one-planet systems and ∼25% of two-planet systems are likely members of higher-multiplicity systems. The distribution of orbital eccentricities as a function of multiplicity provides an important new constraint for planetary system formation and evolution models. Any theory that accounts for this trend would be adequate to explain the distributions of eccentricities seen both in our Solar System and exoplanetary systems.</p><p>Because low eccentricity is arguably advantageous for habitability <ref type="bibr">(14; 15)</ref>, this relationship suggests that highmultiplicity systems may be more likely to host habitable exoplanets.   The abbreviation 'SS' is for 'Solar System' planets. A black x is shown for where Jupiter would appear on the 1-and 2-planet distributions, and a gray circle is shown for Saturn on the 2-planet curves. This demonstrates that even if the Solar System was detected via RV as a one or two planet system, it would still be consistent with the data. The 'SS' denotes 'Solar System' planets. A red dot is shown for where Jupiter would appear on the 1-and 2-planet distributions, and for Saturn on the 2-planet distribution. This demonstrates that even if the Solar System was detected via RV as a one or two planet system, it would still be consistent with the data.  <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Mean and Median Eccentricities in RV exoplanet systems and the Solar System as a function of multiplicity (number of planets in the system). As the number of planets increases, eccentricity decreases. A plateau in eccentricity at low multiplicity is noticeable especially in the median. This is possibly due to contamination of the one-planet data with higher-multiplicity systems. The 'SS' denotes 'Solar System' planets. If the Solar System was detected via RV, it is mostly likely that only Jupiter (1 planet) or Jupiter and Saturn (2 planets) would be detected. The mean eccentricity in these scenarios is marked on the plot by black x's and labeled SS1 and SS2, respectively. If the entire Solar System was detected it would appear in the 8-planet bin -this case is labeled SS8. Note that the SS8 point is consistent with the the trend in the mean whereas the SS1 and SS2 points are not (which should suggest to a hypothetical alien RV exoplanet hunter studying the Solar System from afar that it contains more than one or two planets).  polynomial fits to the cumulative distribution functions (CDF). Lower eccentricity systems are more likely to belong to higher multiplicity systems. Second-order polynomials were fit to the cumulative distributions for all multiplicities except the single-planet systems in which case a third-order polynomial was used. The 'SS' denotes 'Solar System' planets.  <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Power-law fit to median eccentricity in systems with multiplicity &gt;2 planets. The fit suggests that the one-and two-planet data are contaminated with higher-multiplicity systems due to so far undiscovered members. The 'SS' denotes 'Solar System' planets.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Cumulative eccentricity distributions in RV exoplanet systems and the Solar System for various multiplicities. There is a trend towards lower eccentricities at higher multiplicities. The abbreviation 'SS' is for 'Solar System' planets. A black x is shown for where Jupiter would appear on the 1-and 2-planet distributions, and a gray circle is shown for Saturn on the 2-planet curves. This demonstrates that even if the Solar System was detected via RV as a one or two planet system, it would still be consistent with the data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Eccentricity verses semi-major axis going from low-(left) to high-multiplicity (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Eccentricity probability density distributions for various multiplicities based on</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 lists</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>the number of 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . No. planets in dataset for given multiplicity</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Multiplicity 
Total number of planets 
(no. planets in system): with given multiplicity 1 : 
1 
276 
2 
81 
3 
25 
4 
12 
5 or 6 
9 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> www.pnas.org --Footline Author</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> www.pnas.org --Footline Author</note>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> This value is not necessarily a multiple of the system multiplicity since not all exoplanets have measured eccentricities.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS. We thank Adam Burrows, AJ Eldorado Riggs and Scott</head><p>Tremaine for useful conversations and comments. An anonymous referees comments improved our understanding of valid interpretations of the empirical results presented in the paper. This research has been supported in part by the World Premier International Research Center Initiative, MEXT, Japan.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observed properties of exoplanets: Masses, orbits, and metallicities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hra</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog of Theo Phys Sup</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical properties of exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Exoplanet Handbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Urey prize lecture: On the diversity of plausible planetary systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proximity of jupiter-like planets to lowmass stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Boss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical instabilities and the formation of extrasolar planetary systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rasio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="956" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gravitational scattering as a possible origin for giant planets at small stellar distances</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Weidenschilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migration and dynamical relaxation in crowded systems of giant planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Laughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical origin of extrasolar planet eccentricity distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Juric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical relaxation by planet-planet interactions as the origin of exoplanet eccentricity distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Juric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Extreme Solar Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">398</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ASP Conference Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Which radial velocity exoplanets have undetected outer companions?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rodigas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">702</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the eccentricity distribution of exoplanets from radial velocity surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">685</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistics of low-mass companions to stars: Implications for their origin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stepinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">356</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="912" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Earth-like worlds on eccentric orbits: excursions beyond the habitable zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pollard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interna J of Astrobio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitable climates: The influence of eccentricity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dressing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scharf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">721</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1307" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
