<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:13+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Single mode, extreme precision Doppler spectrographs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-12-19">19 Dec 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Schwab</surname></persName>
							<email>christian.schwab@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sergio</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Leon-Saval</surname></persName>
							<email>sergio.leon-saval@sydney.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Photonics &amp; Optical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Betters</surname></persName>
							<email>c.betters@physics.usyd.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Photonics &amp; Optical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joss</forename><surname>Bland-Hawthorn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Photonics &amp; Optical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Suvrath</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
							<email>suvrath@astro.psu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>State College</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Single mode, extreme precision Doppler spectrographs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-12-19">19 Dec 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>*** TITLE *** Proceedings IAU Symposium No. **VOLUME**, 2012 ***NAME OF EDITORS*** c 2012 International Astronomical Union DOI: 00.0000/X000000000000000X</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The &apos;holy grail&apos; of exoplanet research today is the detection of an earth-like planet: a rocky planet in the habitable zone around a main-sequence star. Extremely precise Doppler spectroscopy is an indispensable tool to find and characterize earth-like planets; however, to find these planets around solar-type stars, we need nearly one order of magnitude better radial velocity (RV) precision than the best current spectrographs provide. Recent developments in astrophotonics (Bland-Hawthorn &amp; Horton 2006, Bland-Hawthorn et al. 2010) and adaptive optics (AO) enable single mode fiber (SMF) fed, high resolution spectrographs, which can realize the next step in precision. SMF feeds have intrinsic advantages over multimode fiber or slit coupled spectrographs: The intensity distribution at the fiber exit is extremely stable, and as a result the line spread function of a well-designed spectrograph is fully decoupled from input coupling conditions, like guiding or seeing variations (Ihle et al. 2010). Modal noise, a limiting factor in current multimode fiber fed instruments (Baudrand &amp; Walker 2001), can be eliminated by proper design, and the diffraction limited input to the spectrograph allows for very compact instrument designs, which provide excellent optomechanical stability. A SMF is the ideal interface for new, very precise wavelength calibrators, like laser frequency combs (Steinmetz et al. 2008, Osterman et al. 2012), or SMF based Fabry-Perot Etalons (Halverson et al. 2012). At near infrared wavelengths, these technologies are ready to be implemented in on-sky instruments, or already in use. We discuss a novel concept for such a spectrograph.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Key astrophotonic and AO technologies</head><p>A so-called photonic lantern is a device which converts a multimode fiber input into a number of single mode fiber outputs <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Leon-Saval et al. 2010</ref>)(see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). If the number of modes in the multimode fiber is preserved by coupling to the same number of single mode fibers, the conversion can be very efficient; &gt; 90% throughput has been demonstrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Noordegraaf et al.(2010)</ref>. This technology alleviates the problem of direct coupling to a SMF, which easily leads to unacceptable losses even in the case of highly corrected point spread functions (Coudé du <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Foresto et al. 2000</ref>). The spatial size of a seeing limited star necessitates the use of large multimode fibers for efficient coupling, typically around 200 microns diameter at f/5 for an 8m class telescope. This corresponds to 878 vector modes, or 439 fibers, at a wavelength of 1.5 micron, and exceeds the current manufacturing limits for photonic lanterns. Furthermore, as each SMF output needs to be recorded separately, such a spectrograph would require an enormous number of detector pixels. However, the advent of powerful AO systems which achieve excellent correction on bright natural guide  stars enables the use of small, few-mode lanterns. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Esposito et al.(2011)</ref> demonstrated Strehl ratios in excess of 85% in H-band with the large binocular telescope (LBT) and its adaptive secondary mirror <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2)</ref>. A photonic lantern with seven output fibers in Hband has a multimode end corresponding to 90 milliarcseconds diameter at the LBT, and would enclose the AO-corrected point spread function (PSF) to the first minimum in the diffraction pattern. As a consequence, we believe that photonic lanterns can efficiently couple a diffraction limited spectrograph to a large telescope equipped with a powerful AO system. For a high precision radial velocity program, the bright science target stars provide ideal guide stars for a natural guide star AO system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Photonic lantern fed, high resolution Echelle spectrograph</head><p>The SMF fiber output from the photonic lantern provides a diffraction limited entrance aperture for the spectrograph <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref>. In this case, the image size (or line width) corresponds to the PSF of the spectrograph optics, and for a well-corrected optical design is determined by diffraction on the spectrograph pupil stop. Very high resolution can be achieved with small beam diameters and grating dimensions. With an R4 (76 degrees blaze angle) grating, R &gt; 100.000 is possible with a 25 mm diameter beam. Further, to sample the spectrum with common detectors, the focal ratio of the spectrograph camera has to be very slow, to match the point spread function to the pixel size. The combination of slow camera and small optics opens up new opportunities for the optical design that cannot be used for classical spectrographs. It is important to note that the spectra from all fibers need to be recorded separately, so as not to introduce modal noise. As a result, the SMFs can be lined up either in a linear fashion, or in a more compact arrangement, for example in a slightly rotated hexagonal pattern as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Leon-Saval et al. (2012)</ref>, resulting in a constant offset between the fibers in dispersion direction. The optical design has to provide enough cross dispersion to separate the spectra on the detector. Another advantage of the compact size is that the spectrograph bench can be mechanically and thermally stabilized to an unprecedented degree, compared with classical spectrographs, and easily evacuated. The small optics can be made to stricter tolerances than large substrates, keeping cost down at the same time. This helps to further suppress any variations in the spectrum due to the spectrograph optics itself. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Schematic layout of our spectrograph concept. A photonic lantern couples to the telescope via an AO system. The single mode fibers at the output provide diffraction limited sources to a compact Echelle spectrograph. The cross dispersion is chosen such that the spectra of the N fibers are clearly separated on the detector. Each Echelle order consists of N spectra.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Breadboard testing a single mode Echelle spectrograph</head><p>We set up a single mode Echelle spectrograph based on commercial off-the-shelf components to verify line shape and resolution, and to test the integration of a photonic lantern. We chose to test the concept in the visible wavelength region due to the better availability of optics and detectors. The breadboard shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> is very simple and compact, yet it provides excellent resolution. We used a 25 × 50 mm, 31.6 g/mm R2 Echelle grating, with a theoretical resolving power close to 60.000. We employ a reflective, one inch fiber collimator based on an off-axis parabola. The light is directed towards the R2 grating with the help of a non-polarizing beamsplitter cube, which allows us to use the grating in true Littrow configuration. The cross disperser is a 300 g/mm transmission grating; the dispersion is high enough to fit a lantern with 7 output cores between the orders. The camera is a commercial, apochromatic telephoto lens with 350 mm focal length, coupled to CCD camera based on a front illuminated Kodak CCD that has 5.4 micron pixels. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> is an Echelle spectrum of a supercontinuum source, centered at 550 nm, taken with a single SMF. The inset shows the easily resolved peaks of a Fabry-Perot etalon. The peak to peak distance corresponds to a resolution of ∼37.000.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Calibration Sources</head><p>The use of a single-mode fiber presents some challenges for a calibration source. Th-Ar ( <ref type="bibr">Baranne et al.1996</ref>) or U-Ne ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Redman et al. 2012</ref>) lamps that are used in optical and NIR are not suitable sources since their extended cathodes do not couple well to the single mode fibers. Laser frequency combs (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Ycas et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">, Steinmetz et al. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">, Osterman et al. 2012</ref>) offer one possibility for the highest precision applications. Commercially available supercontinuum white light sources enable fiber gas cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Mahadevan &amp; Ge 2009</ref>) or fiber-Fabry-Perot devices ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Halverson et al. 2012</ref>) to be used effectively with single-mode spectrographs. Some combination of these sources will satisfy most needs, ranging from the need for the highest precision (5-10 cm/s) to having inexpensive commercially available sources (1-5 m/s precision) to enable such AO fed spectrograph systems to be built for a fraction of the cost of large evacuated spectrographs. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Left: Photo of a breadboard spectrograph. Right: Example of a single mode spectrum recorded with our breadboard setup. We inserted a fused silica solid Etalon with a free spectral range of 0.5 cm −1 from Lightmachinery. In the magnified insert, it can be seen that the Etalon peaks are well defined and separated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Summary</head><p>We are developing a concept for an ultra-stable single mode spectrograph that will be used for high precision Doppler searches for extrasolar planets on large telescopes. To couple the spectrograph to the telescope, we aim to use a photonic lantern behind an AO system. We are currently testing components in the lab, and designing an optimized, efficient, and highly stable spectrograph bench with R &gt; 100.000.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. (top panel) Schematic illustration of the photonic lantern. (bottom panel) Microscope pictures at different positions along the down taper transition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. High-order AO-corrected PSF in H-band using a 6.5 mag star under median seeing conditions, obtained with the LBT AO system (Esposito et al. 2011).</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> C. Schwab, S. G. Leon-Saval, C. H. Betters, J. Bland-Hawthorn, S. Mahadevan</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baranne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baudrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">851</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bland-Hawthorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Horton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">6269</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bland-Hawthorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page">7735</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Coudé Du Foresto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Faucherre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gitton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">305</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Esposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riccardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pinna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8149</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Halverson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1209.2704</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ihle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Avila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kastinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page">7739</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Leon-Saval</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Argyros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bland-Hawthorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Optics Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8430</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Leon-Saval</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Betters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bland-Hawthorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8450</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">692</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1590</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Noordegraaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M W</forename><surname>Skovgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Maack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Optics Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4673</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ycas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Diddams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8450</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Redman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kerber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8446</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Steinmetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wilken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Araujo-Hauck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1335</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ycas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Quinlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Diddams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Optics Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6631</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
