<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2007-01-19">19 Jan 2007</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2007-01-19">19 Jan 2007</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Exosphere-formation and the onset of planetary mass loss</head><p>The overall evolution of a planet can be split into (1), the formation period during which the planet is formed and its mass grows, and (2), the mature period with the planet detached from gas reservoirs and exposed to loss processes driven by its host star. During the formation period the planet is in contact with a mass reservoir having certain pressure: the protoplanetary nebula. During an isolated period planets are surrounded by vacuum with no continuum pressure and an exosphere as the interface. The overall mass history of a planet is thus determined by pressure gradients as long as there is a nebula pressure and by exosphere properties once there is no nebula pressure. The formation of the exosphere separates these two eras and the regimes of early mass-gain from the nebula and the eon long period of particle loss processes. An exosphere exists if there is a layer in an atmosphere or generally in a gas sphere where the mean free path of the particles is sufficiently large to allow them to escape from a planet. Protoplanets fill their Roche-lobe because that is where they are in contact with the nebula. For a small planet/star mass-ratio the size of the Roche lobe can be well approximated by the Hill-radius,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">R Hill = d(M pl /[3M star ]) 1/3 ,</formula><p>where d is the orbital distance. Equating this to the mean free path for hydrogen and assuming P = nkT we obtain an exosphere formation pressure P exo−form at the Hill-sphere boundary</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">P exo−form = kT dσ H 3M star M pl 1 3 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where σ H is the hydrogen collision cross section. Assuming an exponential decay of the nebula pressure, P 0 with a time-scale τ neb , we calculate the time it takes for the lowest pressure around the planet to reach P exo−form and an exosphere to form within the Hill-sphere</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">t exo−form = τ neb ln P 0 P exo−form .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>We take σ H = πa 2 0 , with the Bohr-radius, a 0 as a lower limit for collisions under typical nebula-conditions. For typical nebula pressures and temperatures at the planet formation time, taken from the predicted CoRoT-planet population ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Wuchterl et al. 2006</ref>), we arrive at t exo−form ≈ 30 − τ neb . With a typical global τ neb of ∼ 10 Myr representing a compromise between various empirical methods (τ neb ∼ 1 -100 Myr) (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Hillenbrand et al. 2005</ref> for a recent update focused on dust IR-emission), one obtains average exosphere formation-times, t exo−form ≈ 50-300 Myr. Thus exospheres may form at significant ages after the planets' host star arrived at the Zero-Age-Main Sequence (ZAMS).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Thermal mass loss</head><p>In order to study the evolution of the maximum possible thermal hydrogen loss rates from close-in Exosolar Giant Planets in a mass range of 10 29 g (EGP I) to 10 30 g (EGP II) at different orbital distances we estimate the thermal mass loss from the evolution of the XUV flux which arrives from the host star at the planet's orbit. We use in the present study a scaling law derived from XUV flux observations of solar-like G stars with different age Φ XUV = 6.13t −1.19 f XUV ( <ref type="bibr">Ribas et al. 2005</ref>), where t is the age of the star in Gyr, while f XUV = 8.5 × 10 −4 W m −2 is the flux at 1 AU averaged over the planetary sphere. It is scaled to the different orbital distances by using an r −2 dependency. The maximum possible thermal mass loss rate Γ th can be calculated by assuming that an atmosphere contains no efficient IR-cooling molecules and by using the energy-limited equation which was originally derived for Earth-like planets by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Watson et al. (1981)</ref>. Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Erkaev et al. (2006</ref>) modified the energy-limited equation for the application to "Hot Jupiters"</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Γ th = 4πR pl r 2 XUV Φ XUV mM pl GK ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where R pl and M pl are the planetary radius and mass, K is a factor which is related to the Roche-lobe effect ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Erkaev et al. 2006</ref>) and is ≈ 0.5 for the considered planet, r XUV is the distance in the thermosphere where the optical thickness τ XUV → 1 and the main part of the XUV radiation is absorbed. One should note that r XUV is much closer to the planetary radius R pl than the distance used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Watson (1981)</ref>. By using Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(3)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">CME-induced nonthermal mass loss</head><p>Taking into account that tidal-locking of short periodic exoplanets may result in weaker planetary magnetic moments, as compared to fast rotating Jupiter-class planets at larger orbital distances ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Grießmeier et al. 2004</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Khodachenko et al. (2006)</ref> found that the encountering CME plasma may compress the magnetosphere and force the magnetospheric standoff distance down to heights where ionization and ion pick-up of the planetary neutral atmosphere by the CMEs plasma flow takes place. Assuming for the G-type host star of HD209458b the average CME occurrence rate as the one observed on the Sun, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Khodachenko et al. (2006)</ref> found that, depending on magnetic protection "Hot Jupiters" at 0.045 AU could have lost over their lifetime a mass from 2 % up to more than M Jup . For estimating the orbital distance at which Jupiter-class exoplanets maintain the main part of their initial mass, we calculate the "maximum" possible CME-induced mass loss between orbital distances of 0.015 -0.2 AU.</p><p>In the case of our Sun the maximum expected CME plasma density n CME at orbital distances ≤ 0.2 AU is estimated from the analysis of CME associated brightness enhancements in the white-light coronagraph images. By using an analogy between the Sun and solar-type stars the maximum CME density dependence on the orbital distance d from the star can be assumed as a power-law (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Khodachenko 2006</ref>, and references therein) n CME (d) = n 0 (d/d 0 ) −3.6 , which for n 0 = 5 × 10 5 ...5 × 10 6 cm −3 and d 0 = 3R Sun gives a good approximation for the values estimated from the SOHO/LASCO coronograph images. The average mass of CMEs, M CME , is ≈ 10 15 g and the average duration of CMEs, τ CME , at distances (6...10)R Sun is ≈ 8 h. The collision rate between CMEs and "Hot Jupiters" can be estimated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Khodachenko et al. (2006)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">f col = ∆ CME + δ pl sin (∆ CME + δ pl )/2 2π sin Θ f CME ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where f CME is the CME occurrence rate, ∆ CME and δ pl are the CME and planetary angular sizes, Θ is the latitude distribution of CME producing regions. Assuming an average stellar CME occurrence rate f CME of ∼ 3 CMEs per day ( <ref type="bibr">Khodacheno et al. 2006</ref>; and references therein), and taking the size, duration and latitude distribution of CMEs close to the solar values (∆ CME = π/4 to π/3, t CME = 8 h, Θ = π/3), with the angular size δ pl related to the orbital distance between 0.015-0.2 AU of 0.045 -0.0034 rad, one obtains a CME collision rate f col of ∼ 0.17 -0.3 hits per day. Using these values an average total CME exposure time t CME ≈ 1.2 × 10 16 s during a period of 5 Gyr is obtained.</p><p>To calculate atmospheric erosion rates we apply the same time-dependent numerical algorithm, which is able to solve the system of hydrodynamic equations through the transonic point for calculation of the upper atmospheric hydrogen density as used by <ref type="bibr">Khodachenko</ref>   <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. Maximum CME-induced H + pick up ion mass loss rates per CME collision for "Hot Jupiters" with different substellar planetary magnetopause obstacles as a function of orbital distance.</p><p>The obtained density profiles are in agreement with the density profiles calculated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Yelle (2004)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Tian et al. (2005)</ref>. For studying the expected maximum possible atmospheric erosion due to CMEs we assume magnetospheres which build obstacles against the CME plasma flow at substellar distances of 1.3, 1.5 and 2.0 R pl . For the CME-induced H + pick-up loss rates caused by the CME plasma flow we take into account the ionization processes produced by CMEs during the interaction with the neutral atmosphere above the assumed planetary obstacles. The H + pick up loss calculations are performed with a numerical test particle model which was successfully used for the simulation of ion pick-up loss rates from various planetary atmospheres ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lichtenegger et al. 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Erkaev et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Khodachenko et al. 2006</ref>). The calculation of the particle fluxes is performed by dividing the space above and around the planetary obstacle onto a number of volume elements ∆V i . Production rates of planetary H + ions are obtained by calculation of the CME plasma flow absorption along streamlines due to charge exchange, photo-ionization, and electron impact ionization with the extended upper atmosphere. The CME plasma flux Φ CME in a volume element ∆V i at a given position r i with respect to the planetary center is determined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Φ CME (r i ) = Φ (0) CME (r i )e − s i ∞ H n H σ i H ds ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where the integration is performed from the upstream CME plasma flow to the corresponding point s i at position r i on the streamline. Φ (0) CME is the unperturbed CME plasma flux, n H is the neutral hydrogen density as a function of planetary distance, σ i H is the energy dependent cross section of hydrogen ionization processes, and ds is the line element along the streamline. The total planetary ion production rate from atmospheric hydrogen atoms in each volume element can be written as the sum  <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows the maximum expected CME-induced H + pick up mass loss rates due to CME collisions from weakly magnetized "Hot Jupiters" with substellar planetary obstacles at 1.3 R pl , 1.5 R pl , and 2.0 R pl at various orbital distances. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> shows the residual mass after 5 Gyr of the maximum CME plasma exposure of weakly magnetized "Hot Jupiters" with planetary obstacles at 1.3 R pl , 1.5 R pl , and 2.0 R pl as a function of orbital distance compared to 5 known low-mass exoplanets (Gliese 876d, 55 Cnc e, HD69830b, HD160691d, HD69830c) (http://exoplanet.eu/catalog.php). The results obtained from the numerical ion pick up test particle model simulations indicate that weakly magnetized gas giants at orbital distances ≤ 0.05 AU or periods ≤ 4 days may lose a mass equivalent to that of Jupiter during a 5 Gyr time period. By comparing the results of the integrated CME-induced mass loss with the thermal evaporation loss shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>, one can see that for magnetically unprotected planets nonthermal loss processes are much more efficient than thermal evaporation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baraffe et al. (2004)</ref> compared the ratio of the mass loss timescale t ˙ M to the thermal timescale t th , which is characterized by the Kelvin-Helmotz timescale, found that, when t ˙ M /t th becomes &lt; 1 the evolution of the "Hot Jupiter" changes drastically which results in rapid expansion of the planetary radius and enhances the mass loss. Depending on the strength of the planetary magnetic field, XUV flux and exosphere formation time, closein gas giants at orbital distances ≤ 0.05 AU may experience this violent mass loss effect.</p><p>One can also see from <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref> that it is very unlikely that the three low mass exoplanets HD69830b, HD160691d, and HD69830c are remaining cores of eroded gas giants. They could have lost their hydrogen-envelopes but their initial mass was not much larger than that of Neptune. The two other low mass exoplanets Gliese 876d and 55 Cnc e are located at orbital distances where they could have been strongly affected by mass loss. Therefore, both exoplanets can be remaining cores of eroded weakly magnetized gas giants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>Our study indicates that mass loss of weakly magnetized short periodic "Hot Jupiters" can produce the observed masses of Gliese 876d and 55 Cnc e, while the three other known lower mass close-in exoplanets HD69830b, HD160691d and HD69830c belonged most likely since their origin to the Neptune-mass domain. The results of our study indicate that only a combination of the size detection with CoRoT and ground-based follow-up mass determinations together with theoretical mass loss studies over the exoplanets' history can bring reliable information on the statistics of remaining cores, shrinked gas giants and "unaffected" lower mass exoplanets, like Super Earths or Ocean planets. Furthermore, thermal evaporation from "Hot Jupiters" at orbits &lt; 0.02 AU, together with CME-triggered nonthermal mass loss processes and tidal interactions <ref type="bibr">(Patzold and Rauer 2002)</ref> can be a reason that so far no "Hot Jupiter" is observed at these close distances to its host star.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Residual mass after 5 Gyr exposure of dense CMEs in units of M Jup of weakly magnetized "Hot Jupiters" as a function of orbital distance compared with planetary obstacles at 1.3 R pl (solid line), 1.5 R pl (dashed line), and 2.0 R pl (dotted line). The horizontal dashed-dotted lines indicate the masses of Saturn, Uranus, Neptune, the horizontal dotted lines corresponds to the mass of the Earth (lower line) and to the "Super-Earth" (M pl ≈ 10M Earth ) mass domain (upper line), and the black circles show the so far observed lower mass close-in exoplanets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>d] EGPI : L th [%] EGP II: L th</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>with r XUV 
of ∼ 1.3R pl (Yelle 2004) we can calculate the maximum ex-
pected thermal mass loss rate for HD209458b (R pl = 1.43 R Jup , 
M pl = 0.69 M Jup ) at present time. It is ∼ 1.7 × 10 11 g s −1 
and appears to be in good agreement with Vidal-Madjar et al. 
(2003), Yelle (2004) and Tian et al. (2005). The mass loss rate 
for HD209458b at about 200 Myr after its host star arrived at 
the ZAMS is ∼ 6.0 × 10 12 g s −1 . We note that Lammer et al. 
(2003) applied Watson's assumption for "Hot Jupiters" and over-
estimated the energy-limited loss rate by an order of magnitude. 
One can see from Table 1 that thermal evaporation may be an 
efficient loss process for close-in gas giants at d &lt; 0.05 AU 
with M pl &lt; 5 × 10 29 g (&lt; 0.25M Jup and exosphere formation 
times ≤ 200 Myr. If one proceeds to longer exosphere forma-
tion times the integrated mass loss is gradually decreasing. At 
larger orbital distances, the thermal mass loss is ≤ 1 %. Thermal 
evaporation from close-in lower mass exoplanets may be strong 
enough to remove their hydrogen envelopes from their cores. 
One should also note that exoplanets with orbits &lt; 0.02 AU will 
experience an even higher thermal mass loss due to the higher 
XUV flux and the mass loss enhancement due to the Roche-lobe 
effect (Erkaev et al. 2006). d [AU] P [[%] 
0.02 
1 
∼ 87 
∼ 8.7 
0.05 
4 
∼ 14 
∼ 1.4 
0.013 
16 
∼ 2 
∼ 0.2 

Table 1. Thermal mass loss in % of the initial planetary mass of 
EGP I and EGP II integrated over the history of the stellar system 
for a representative exosphere formation time t exo−form ≈ 200 
Myr. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>p i H + = p ei H + + p ce H + + p γ H + , with p ei</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>H + the electron impact ionization, 
p ce 
H + the charge exchange rate, and p 

γ 

H + the photo-ionization rate. 
The total H + ion mass loss rate finally becomes 

Γ CME = 


i 

p i 
H + ∆V i m H + 
(6) 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baraffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hauschildt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">419</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Penz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Lichtenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wurz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Grießmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">396</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kulikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Langmayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Grießmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stadelmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Penz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Guinan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Motschmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">425</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">753</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hillenbrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:astro-ph/0511083</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ArXiv Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>eprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Khodachenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Lichtenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Langmayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Grießmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Penz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Motschmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Rucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Space Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Guinan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">598</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lecavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal-Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mcconnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Lichtenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schwingenschuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dubinin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lundin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21659</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pätzold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">568</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Penz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Langmayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Erkaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kulikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cecchi-Pestellini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Micela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deleuil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Guis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Léger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planet. Space Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ribas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Guinan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Güdel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Audard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">622</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">680</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lasota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bonnazola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of &quot;Brown Dwarfs and Extrasolar Planets</title>
		<meeting>&quot;Brown Dwarfs and Extrasolar Planets</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Toon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pavlov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sterck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">621</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1049</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vidal Madjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Levavelier Des Etangs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Desert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ballester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ferlet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">143</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Donahue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C G</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wuchterl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">170</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
