<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:09+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Rapid inward migration of planets formed by gravitational instability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-11-08">2011. 8 November 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Clément</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">DAMTP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wilberforce Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0WA</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Farzana</forename><surname>2⋆</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>95064</postCode>
									<settlement>Santa Cruz</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Meru</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Exeter</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Stocker Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>EX4 4QL</postCode>
									<settlement>Exeter</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institut für Astronomie und Astrophysik</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universität Tübingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Auf der Morgenstelle 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>72076</postCode>
									<settlement>Tübingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sijme-Jan</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">DAMTP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wilberforce Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0WA</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Rapid inward migration of planets formed by gravitational instability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011-11-08">2011. 8 November 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Accepted 2011 June 1. Received 2011 May 30; in original form 2011 March 25</note>
					<note>(MN L A T E X style file v2.2)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>accretion, accretion discs -turbulence -methods: numerical - planetary systems: formation -planetary systems: protoplanetary discs</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The observation of massive exoplanets at large separation (10 AU) from their host star, like in the HR 8799 system, challenges theories of planet formation. A possible formation mechanism involves the fragmentation of massive self-gravitating discs into clumps. While the conditions for fragmentation have been extensively studied, little is known of the subsequent evolution of these giant planet embryos, in particular their expected orbital migration. Assuming a single planet has formed by fragmentation, we investigate its interaction with the gravitoturbulent disc it is embedded in. Two-dimensional hydrodynamical simulations are used with a simple prescription for the disc cooling. A steady gravitoturbulent disc is first set up, after which simulations are restarted including a planet with a range of masses approximately equal to the clump&apos;s initial mass expected in fragmenting discs. Planets rapidly migrate inwards, despite the stochastic kicks due to the turbulent density fluctuations. We show that the migration timescale is essentially that of type I migration, with the planets having no time to open a gap. In discs with aspect ratio ∼ 0.1 at their forming location , planets with a mass comparable to, or larger than Jupiter&apos;s can migrate in as short as 10 4 years, that is, about 10 orbits at 100 AU. Massive planets formed at large separation from their star by gravitational instability are thus unlikely to stay in place, and should rapidly migrate towards the inner parts of protoplanetary discs, regardless of the planet mass.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The large majority of exoplanets have been discovered by the radial velocity and transiting techniques. Recent progress in the adaptive optics technique has revealed about 20 exoplanets by direct imaging. Since the latter requires a high brightness contrast between the planet and the parent star, massive planets have been observed at separations 10 AU (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Kalas et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Marois et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lagrange et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Lafrenì ere et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marois et al. 2010)</ref>. One such example is the HR 8799 system ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Marois et al. 2010</ref>), which comprises four planets with masses evaluated between 7 and 10 Jupitermass, and estimated separations of 14, 24, 38 and 68 AU, respectively.</p><p>⋆ E-mail: C. <ref type="bibr">Baruteau@damtp.cam.ac.uk</ref> How can the large orbital separations of such massive planets be explained? With the standard core accretion formation scenario (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Safronov 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Mizuno 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Pollack et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Ida &amp; Lin 2004</ref>), it is difficult to form Jupiter-like planets in isolation further than ∼ 10 AU from a Sun-like star. Still, the formation of a first gap-opening planet close to the snow line <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Ida &amp; Lin 2004</ref>) could pave the way for the formation of a second-generation planet at the outer edge of the first planet's gap <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Bryden et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Thommes 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ida &amp; Lin 2008)</ref>. Provided that the second planet opens a gap, its outer edge could also trigger the formation of a third-generation planet. Subsequent planet formation could proceed as a sequence, as long as there are enough planetesimals and gas left.</p><p>The tidal interaction between a planet and its nascent protoplanetary disc alters the planet's semi-major axis, causing its orbital migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Goldreich &amp; Tremaine 1980)</ref>. Assuming the central object is a Sun-like star, a planet typically more massive than Saturn opens a gap around its orbit and generally migrates inwards. It is thus unlikely that a massive planet formed through the core-accretion scenario within ∼ 10 AU of its host star could migrate to a separation as large as 100 AU. A notable exception was proposed by , who showed that the tidal interaction between a pair of resonant massive planets embedded in a common gap, and their protoplanetary disc, could drive both planets to orbital separations much larger than that of their birth place, providing some specific conditions on the planets mass ratio and on the disc's turbulent viscosity.</p><p>Another in-situ formation scenario is based on the gravitational instability (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cameron 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Boss 1997)</ref>. It involves early-stage protoplanetary discs, which are massive enough for its self-gravity to play a part in its evolution. The probability that discs form fragments is described by two dimensionless parameters. One is the Toomre Q-parameter, Q = csκ/πGΣ, where G is the gravitational constant, cs and Σ denote the disc's sound speed and surface mass density, and κ is the epicyclic frequency. For Keplerian discs, κ approximately equals the angular frequency Ω. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Toomre (1964)</ref> showed that, for an infinitesimally thin disc to fragment, Q 1. The second parameter describing the stability of a self-gravitating disc is the disc's cooling timescale in units of the orbital timescale, β = t cool Ω, where t cool = e(de/dt) −1 is the cooling timescale and e the disc's thermal energy density <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Gammie 2001</ref>). The critical value of the cooling parameter β, below which fragmentation will occur if Q 1, depends on the disc's adiabatic index ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rice et al. 2005</ref>), and on the local disc to primary mass ratio <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Meru &amp; Bate 2011b)</ref>. Its exact value is currently somewhat uncertain as <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Meru &amp; Bate (2011a)</ref> have recently shown that previous simulations that determined this critical value were unresolved. However, current simulations show that the critical value for β could be in the range 3 − 18 (Gammie 2001; <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Rice et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Meru &amp; Bate 2011a,b)</ref>.</p><p>The vast majority of studies of planet formation by gravitational instability have focused on the conditions to fragment discs into bound objects. It is thought to operate at separations larger than 30 − 50 AU from the central (Sun-like) star (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Rafikov 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Matzner &amp; Levin 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Stamatellos &amp; Whitworth 2008)</ref>. However, little is known of the evolution of these objects, in particular their expected migration resulting from the gravitational interaction with the gravitoturbulent disc they are embedded in. A few numerical studies have observed that clumps could drift inwards (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Mayer et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Boss 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cha &amp; Nayakshin 2010)</ref>, and some of them have focused on the early phases of disc formation and evolution following the collapse from the prestellar core stage <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Vorobyov &amp; Basu 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">, 2010a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Machida et al. 2011</ref>). As these giant planet embryos migrate inwards, they may become tidally disrupted (when their radius becomes comparable to the clump's Hill radius), thereby delivering a variety of planets in the inner parts of protoplanetary discs <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Nayakshin 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we examine the orbital evolution of a single planet embedded in its nascent gravitoturbulent disc, following the assumption that the planet has formed by gravitational instability. We show that the planet migrates inwards in a timescale very similar to that of type I migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Paardekooper &amp; Papaloizou 2009</ref>) in the absence of turbulence. Our physical and numerical models are described in Section 2. In Section 3, we present our results of simulations. Conclusions and future directions are drawn in Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MODEL</head><p>We investigate the tidal interaction between a massive planet and the protoplanetary disc it formed in through the gravitational instability scenario. Once a gaseous clump has formed by fragmentation, it contracts until H2 dissociation occurs, causing a rapid collapse of the clump down to planetary sizes. Our study does not address the formation of the planet, and we consider the clump and the planet as one object. In the following, our system of interest (clump and planet) is referred to as the planet. Our study focuses on its migration driven by the interaction with the disc, following the assumption that the planet has formed by gravitational instability. As described below, our approach is to first set up a steady state gravitoturbulent disc, then include a single planet and follow its orbital migration. The disc's properties after fragmentation are poorly constrained. They depend on how many clumps form, and how massive they are. In our study, we assume that the disc properties (density, temperature) are virtually unchanged by the fragmentation stage. In particular, we assume that the disc remains gravitoturbulent. This assumption is motivated by the findings of previous numerical studies on disc fragmentation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Meru &amp; Bate 2011b)</ref>, where the images of the discs show similar structures after the formation of a clump.</p><p>We carried out two-dimensional (2D) hydrodynamical simulations using the grid-based, staggered-mesh code FARGO 1 (Masset 2000), for which a self-gravity solver based on fast Fourier transforms was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baruteau &amp; Masset (2008b)</ref>. When calculating the selfgravitating acceleration, all mass is assumed to be confined to the disc midplane (the razor-thin disc approximation). The thermal energy density e satisfies the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">∂e ∂t + ∇ · (ev) = −(γ − 1)e∇ · v + Q + bulk − e τ cool ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where v denotes the gas velocity, and γ is the adiabatic index (its value can be mapped to a threedimensional adiabatic index, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Gammie 2001</ref>, and references therein). In Eq. (1), the cooling timescale τ cool = βΩ −1 , with β taken to be constant, and the heating source term Q + bulk is provided by artificial viscous heating at shocks arising from the gravitoturbulence. A von Neumann-Richtmyer artificial bulk viscosity is used, as  <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Azimuthally-averaged surface density (left panel), temperature (middle panel), and Toomre Q-parameter (right panel) obtained at 30 orbits for our three values of β = t cool Ω (solid curves). The azimuthal average of Q was calculated as csΩ/πGΣ, where . stands for the azimuthal average. Dashed curves depict the initial value of each quantity. described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Stone &amp; Norman (1992)</ref>, where the coefficient C2 is taken equal to 1.4 (C2 measures the number of zones over which a shock is spread over by the artificial viscosity). Providing angular momentum transport driven by gravitoturbulence occurs locally, which is not necessarily the case <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Balbus &amp; Papaloizou 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cossins et al. 2009</ref>), the alpha parameter associated with the angular momentum flux density is given by (Gammie 2001)</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">α = 4 9 1 γ(γ − 1)β ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>which indicates that varying β is equivalent to varying the viscous stress in the disc. Preliminary calculations with our fiducial setup (initial profiles and grid's resolution are described below) showed that the critical value of β below which fragmentation occurs ranges from 10 to 15. Since we require the disc to be in a gravitoturbulent state, but we do not require further fragmentation so as to focus on the migration of a single planet, we simulated three disc models with β = 15, 20 and 30. Each of our three models initially comprises a 0.4M⊙ 2D disc around a star of fixed mass M⋆ = 1M⊙, and spanning a radial range 20 &lt; r &lt; 250 AU. (As will be shown in Section 3.1, the disc mass rapidly decreases to about 0.2 − 0.25M⊙ after 30 orbits at 100 AU). The initial surface mass density decreases as r −2 , and it equals ≈ 20 g cm −2 at 100 AU. The initial disc's temperature is ≈ 15 K at 100 AU, and it decreases as r −1 (we assume a mean-molecular weight µ = 2.4 and an adiabatic index γ = 5/3). This corresponds to setting the initial disc aspect ratio h (pressure scale height to radius ratio H/r) equal to 0.1 at 100 AU. The disc's initial Toomre Q-parameter is thus uniform, equal to 2. A small level (∼ 0.1%) of white noise is added initially to break the disc's axisymmetry. Here and in the following, disc and planet quantities are expressed in physical units. Since our simulations are scale-free, all the results presented throughout this paper can be easily rescaled by using different units of mass, length and temperature.</p><p>In all our simulations, the grid is covered with 512 and 1536 cells along the radial and azimuthal directions, respectively. A logarithmic spacing is used along the radial direction, as required by the self-gravity module in FARGO. Grid cells are approximately square, and the initial pressure scale height is resolved by about 20 cells along each direction. The radial and azimuthal components of the self-gravitating acceleration are smoothed over a softening length, εsg. We take εsg = 3 × 10 −4 r throughout this study, which is a factor 3 × 10 −3 times the initial pressure scale height. The influence of a large εsg, which can be seen as a crude treatment of the effects of finite thickness, will be examined in Sect. 3.2.4, where we find that the choice for εsg does not significantly alter the orbital evolution of a planet embedded in a gravitoturbulent disc. Outflow boundary conditions are used at the grid's inner and outer edges. Hydrodynamical equations are solved in the frame centred onto the central star.</p><p>Since a non-inertial frame of reference is adopted, the indirect terms in the expression for the disc's gravitational potential are included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS OF HYDRODYNAMICAL SIMULATIONS</head><p>Our numerical simulations were carried out in two steps. In a first step, a gravitoturbulent disc model was set up, whose properties are described in Section 3.1. We then restarted the simulations, including planets of several masses, and following the time-evolution of their orbital separation. The results of the restart simulations are presented in Section 3.2. Further investigation on the impact of the disc's temperature follows in Section 3.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Gravitoturbulent stage</head><p>We describe in this section the results of our three disc models with cooling parameters β = 15, 20 and 30. The absence of heating source initially leads to decrease the disc's temperature, and thus the Toomre Qparameter, until gravitoturbulence sets in. As both the initial Q-profile and β are taken to be uniform (the cooling timescale thus scales proportional to the orbital timescale), gravitoturbulence progressively develops through the disc, starting from the inner edge. After a few orbits at the disc's outer edge, a thermal quasiequilibrium is reached over the whole disc, where cooling is approximately balanced by shock heating due to gravitoturbulence.</p><p>The disc's initial surface density that we assume does not correspond to a mechanical equilibrium with the gravitoturbulent stress. The disc therefore adjusts both its surface density and temperature profiles to satisfy a mechanical equilibrium along with a uniform Toomre-Q profile. This is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, where the azimuthally-averaged surface mass density, temperature, and Toomre Q-parameter are depicted at 30 orbits at 100 AU. Their initial value is shown with a dashed curve. In this quasi-steady state, the surface density profile decreases approximately as r −3/2 , and the disc's temperature is almost uniform, as is the Toomre Q-parameter. We comment that the high initial disc mass (0.4M⊙) promotes global modes that, along with the outflow boundary condition at the grid's inner edge, lead to a rapid decrease in the disc mass. After 30 orbits at 100 AU, the latter ranges from 0.21M⊙ to 0.24M⊙ for β increasing from 15 to 30. The rate at which the disc mass decreases is maximum at the onset of gravitoturbulence, and then declines (but does not vanish) as a quasi-steady state is attained.</p><p>The alpha parameters associated with the Reynolds and gravitational turbulent stresses are denoted by αRey and αsg, respectively. Details of their calculation in a 2D disc model are given in the Appendix. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> displays the azimuthally-and time-averaged radial profiles of αRey, αsg and of αtot = αsg + αRey. Time average is done from 30 to 60 orbits at 100 AU (that is, over ≈ 8 orbits at the grid's outer edge). Results are shown for β = 20. We note that αsg and αRey take very similar values over the whole disc. The same behavior was obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Gammie (2001)</ref> with 2D local shearing-sheet calculations. The decrease in both αsg and αRey at large ( 200 AU) separation is most probably due to the decreasing grid's resolution, as a logarithmic spacing is used along the radial direction. We comment that αtot is locally up to 50% larger than the value expected from viscous (local) transport theory, given by Eq. (2). The difference is probably due to our large disc mass ( 0.2M⋆) and large aspect ratio (h ∼ 0.1), which tend to foster global transport 2 of angular momentum (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Lodato &amp; Rice 2004)</ref>. Although not shown here, very similar results were obtained for β = 15 and β = 30.</p><p>Finite resolution effects (numerical diffusion) leads to a negligible transport of angular momentum compared to gravitoturbulence (see e.g., Lin &amp; Papaloizou 2010, who estimated the numerical "alpha viscosity" in the FARGO code to be 10 −5 for a number of grid cells similar to ours). Artificial bulk viscosity most likely leads to a small, if not negligible transport of angular momentum compared to gravitoturbulence, but note that it is unclear how its contribution can be isolated in our simulations. We point out that if artificial bulk viscosity induced a net transport of angular momentum on average, it would lead to a discrepancy between the value of αsg + αRey measured in local, steady-state disc models and the alpha value given in Eq. (2). Gammie (2001) carried out 2D local shearing-sheet simulations of gravitoturbulent disc models using the ZEUS code, which is very similar to the FARGO code. In particular, both codes use the same prescription for the artificial bulk viscosity. He found that αsg + αRey agrees with the value given by the expression in Eq. (2) to within ∼ 10%, which shows that artificial bulk viscosity should lead to a small transport of angular momentum compared to gravitoturbulence. Also, although not shown here, we have checked that increasing the amount of artificial bulk viscosity (the coefficient C2 in Stone &amp; Norman 1992) by a factor of 3 leads to a negligible change in the values of αRey and αsg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Restart with an embedded planet</head><p>We restarted the simulations of Section 3.1 at 30 orbits, including a single planet at 100 AU. The disc's temperature and surface mass density at this location are close to their initial value for our three values of β (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>). Note in particular that the disc aspect ratio at the planet's initial location is ≈ 0.1. Akin to the clump's contraction timescale, the final mass of planets formed by gravitational instability is uncertain (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boley et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Helled &amp; Bodenheimer 2011)</ref>, and may substantially differ from the clump's initial mass. The latter is estimated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boley et al. (2010)</ref> as ∼ h 3 p M⋆ for Q ∼ 1.5, with hp the disc aspect ratio at the clump's forming location. This estimate of the clump's initial mass, which is based on the fragmentation of spiral arms, is typically a factor 5 − 10 smaller than the Toomre mass (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boley et al. 2010, their</ref>  <ref type="figure">figure 1</ref>, and references therein). We considered three planet masses corresponding to a planet to primary mass ratio q = Mp/M⋆ around h 3 p : a Saturn-mass planet (q = 3×10 −4 , q/h 3 p ∼ 0.3), a Jupitermass planet (q = 10 −3 , q/h 3 p ∼ 1), and a 5 Jupiter-mass planet (q = 5 × 10 −3 , q/h 3 p ∼ 5). The planets gravitational potential is softened over a smoothing length ε = 3 × 10 −2 rp, with rp the planet's orbital separation, and it takes its maximum value at the restart time (we do not gradually ramp up the planet's mass). We will show in Section 3.2.4 that our results are not altered by a more gentle introduction of the planet's potential in the disc over a dynamical timescale, the typical formation timescale of a clump. We comment that in selfgravitating discs, the mass that is relevant for disc-planet interactions is the mass of the planet and of the gas envelope surrounding it. Although for simplicity the planet's mass is fixed, gas can be accreted onto its envelope (circumplanetary disc), thereby contributing to increasing the effective planet's mass. Note however that this accretion rate is probably not realistic due to our simple prescription for the disc cooling. Since the disc is fully self-gravitating, the calculation of the force exerted on the planet takes all the disc into account, it does not partly exclude the planet's Hill radius ( ). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref> displays the surface density obtained for the disc model with β = 30, perturbed by a Jupiter-mass planet. Density contours are shown only three orbits after the restart, the planet is now located at ≈ 60 AU from the central object. The density perturbation due to the planet's potential is comparable to the turbulent density perturbations. This similarity stresses that the magnitude of the stochastic torque acting on the planet can be similar to that of the disc-planet tidal torque obtained in the absence of turbulence (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Nelson &amp; Papaloizou 2004</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baruteau &amp; Lin 2010)</ref>. In such turbulent configurations, the migration timescale must be evaluated in a statistical way, by running several simulations. For each planet mass and each value of β, we performed a suite of eight simulations, varying the planet's azimuth at restart as ϕp = π/4 × i, i ∈ [0 − 7] (that is, independently of the disc's density structure at restart). The migration timescales obtained for these series of runs are presented in Section 3.2.1. The impact of stochastic density fluctuations is described in Section 3.2.2. A comparison with predictions of laminar disc models follows in Section 3.2.3, and a brief discussion on the impact of numerics is given in Section 3.2.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Migration timescale</head><p>The time evolution of the planets' orbital separation is displayed in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Planet mass increases from left to right, and the cooling parameter β increases from top to bottom. In all panels, time is expressed in years (bottom x-axis), and in orbital periods at 100 AU (top x-axis). Results are shown for the eight evenly-spaced values of the planet's azimuth ϕp at restart (increases with increasing color's wavelength).</p><p>The net trend coming out of our results is that, in spite of the stochastic kicks triggered by turbulence, planets migrate inwards very rapidly. Averaging over ϕp and β, the migration timescale (defined as the time to migrate from 100 AU to 20 AU, the location of the grid's inner edge) is typically as short as 3 orbits for the 5 Jupitermass planet, 6 orbits for the Jupiter-mass planet, and about 8 orbits for the Saturn-mass planet. In addition, at fixed β, the amplitude of stochastic kicks increases with decreasing planet mass, and so does the spread in the migration timescale. Both results may be qualitatively interpreted as follows. The torque exerted by the disc on the planet may be decomposed as a background tidal torque, plus a stochastic torque due to turbulent fluctuations. In the mass regime that we consider (q/h 3 p ∼ 1), the amplitude of the tidal torque should increase with increasing planet mass. However, like in discs with turbulence driven by the magneto-rotational instability, it is unclear if the value of the tidal torque is similar to that predicted in laminar disc models, in the absence of turbulence <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Nelson &amp; Papaloizou 2004)</ref>. A detailed comparison with results of laminar disc models will be presented in Section 3.2.3. The standard deviation of the stochastic torque's distribution is primarily controlled by αtot, and therefore by the cooling parameter β (see Eq. 2). For a given β, the smaller the planet mass, the smaller the tidal torque to stochastic torque ratio, the more sensitive the planet is to stochastic kicks, and therefore the larger the spread in the migration timescale. In the same vein, at fixed planet mass, the spread in the migration timescale should increase with decreasing β. This trend does not clearly show up in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, most probably because our minimum and maximum values of β only differ by a factor of 2. Some further insight into the effect of stochastic kicks is given in Section 3.2.2. We finally point out that the disc's density and temperature profiles do not significantly decrease over the planets migration timescale (for the longest simulation with the Saturn-mass planet, the disc's mass decreases by at most 10%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Stochastic kicks</head><p>The results of Section 3.2.1 show that planets formed by gravitational instability should rapidly migrate inwards. Even for the Saturn-mass planet, whose mass is smaller than the estimated initial clump's mass (see first paragraph of Section 3.2), inward migration occurs in typically less than 10 orbits. As illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, planet migration in gravitoturbulent discs is not a smooth process. Planets may experience large kicks, either inwards or outwards, depending on the local density perturbations they encounter. An example of outward kick is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>, which displays the gas density obtained for the restart simulation with β = 30 and the Saturn-mass planet that experiences a significant episode of outward migration in the bottom-left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> (red curve). Time increases by 0.1 orbital periods at 100 AU from left to right. In each panel, the planet's location is indicated with a filled black circle.</p><p>We first comment that, because the planet's mass is low enough (q/h 3 p ≈ 0.3), the wakes it generates are</p><note type="other">c0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 0 1 2 3 4 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0</note><p>Log (Surface density [g cm <ref type="bibr">-2</ref> ]) at t = 34.3Torb</p><note type="other">60 70 80 90 100 110 Radius [AU] -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 Azimuth 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 0 1 2 3 4 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0</note><p>Log (Surface density [g cm <ref type="bibr">-2</ref> ]) at t = 34.4Torb  <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. Contours of the gas surface density obtained for the restart simulation with β = 30, and the Saturn-mass planet with restart azimuth equal to 7π/4. This simulation corresponds to the red curve in the bottom-left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, where a significant episode of outward migration occurs from 3 to 6 orbits after restart. Orbital separation is shown on the x-axis, and azimuth on the y-axis. In all panels, the planet's location is depicted with a filled black circle. invisible, their density contrast being much weaker than that of the turbulent perturbations. In the case depicted in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>, the planet finds itself with an underdense region behind it, and a (comparatively) overdense region in front of it. This density contrast yields a large, positive coorbital corotation torque that is responsible for the vigorous outward kick experienced by the planet. This kick increases the planet's orbital separation from ∼ 75 AU to ∼ 95 AU in only 0.2 orbital periods at 100 AU (that is, in 200 years). Similarly, inward kicks are obtained as the planet experiences a negative coorbital corotation torque induced by an underdense region ahead of it, and a (comparatively) overdense region behind it. As is shown for instance in the bottom-left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, kicks excite planets epicyclic motion, which is rapidly damped as the underlying disc-planet tidal torque takes over.</p><note type="other">60 70 80 90 100 110 Radius [AU] -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 Azimuth 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 0 1 2 3 4 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.</note><p>The stochastic kicks induced by gravitoturbulence are reminiscent of type III runaway migration. This migration regime relies on the formation of a coorbital mass deficit in the planet's horseshoe region, which takes the form of an asymmetric density structure behind and in front of the planet <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Masset &amp; Papaloizou 2003)</ref>. In massive (Q 1) laminar discs with moderate viscosity (α is a few ×10 −3 ), runaway migration is particularly relevant for planets with q ∼ h 3 p (Masset &amp; Papaloizou 2003), like the planets considered in our study. However, in our model, the disc's turbulent viscosity (αtot is a few percent) is too large to allow planets to open a partial dip around their orbit before they reach the disc's inner edge. Thus, planets do not build up a coorbital mass deficit. But, through the density fluctuations it triggers, gravitoturbulence may provide an effective mass deficit on each side of the planet, and induce an effective type III migration. However, this effective mass deficit is not coorbital with the planet (as can be seen in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5)</ref>, and therefore cannot lead to a runaway. Consequently, the relative fast inward migration that we obtain cannot be attributed to type III runaway migration. Also, although the planets we consider are massive, their short formation and migration timescales compared to their gap-opening timescale suggests they are subject to type I-like migration instead of type II, perturbed by stochastic kicks. This point will be clarified in Section 3.2.3.</p><p>Stochastic kicks provide a source of very fast relative motion between the planet and the disc. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 6</ref> displays the migration speed in units of the local sound speed for the three runs with β = 30, and zero azimuth at restart. The migration rate can be a significant fraction of the local sound speed, and short episodes of supersonic motion are even obtained. We note that the maximum value for the migration speed to sound speed ratio tends to increase with decreasing planet mass, as less massive planets are more sensitive to stochastic kicks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Comparison to laminar disc models</head><p>Our results of simulations indicate that the migration of planets embedded in gravitoturbulent discs is driven by both a vigorous (negative) tidal torque, and a (positive or negative) stochastic torque. As the planet mass increases, the former prevails over the latter. In this section, we compare the results of our turbulent disc model with β = 30 to those of an equivalent laminar disc model, including the viscous force in the momentum equation. A constant alpha viscosity is used, approximately equal to 1.3%. The comparison is done for the same three planet masses as previously considered. As the initial conditions for the laminar calculations, we take surface density and temperature profiles that fit those time, and (ii) one with an energy equation with both viscous heating (α ≈ 1.3%) and β−cooling (β = 30). For the latter series, the aforementioned 3 value for α leads to an initial thermal balance between viscous heating and β−cooling, see Eq. (2).</p><p>All laminar calculations include the axisymmetric component of the disc's self-gravity. This is meant to avoid a large mismatch between the disc's and the planet's angular velocities due to the disc gravity, which would yield a spurious shift inwards of all Lindblad resonances, and therefore an artificial acceleration of the inward migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Baruteau &amp; Masset 2008b</ref>). Also, in all laminar runs, the calculation of the force exerted by the disc on the planet excludes the planet's circumplanetary disc ( ). All other parameters are otherwise the same as in the gravitoturbulent calculations.</p><p>The results with the laminar disc model and an energy equation are depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 7</ref> as solid curves. It takes about 5 orbits for the 5 Jupiter-mass planet to migrate from 100 AU to 50 AU, and about 7 orbits for the Jupiter-mass planet. This corresponds to migration rates ∼ half those of the gravitoturbulent calculations (see bottom row of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4)</ref>. Interestingly, the difference in migration rates is larger for the Saturn-mass planet, which drifts from 100 to 60 AU in 20 − 25 orbits in the laminar run, and (on average) in only 5 − 6 orbits in the gravitoturbulent run. We note that the migration timescales of the Saturn-and Jupiter-mass planets differ by a factor approximately equal to their mass ratio, as expected in the type I migration regime, wherein the tidal torque encompasses the differential Lindblad torque and the horseshoe drag <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Paardekooper &amp; Papaloizou 2009)</ref>. We comment that it is the large disc aspect ratio (h ∼ 0.1) that makes the Saturn-mass planet (q/h 3 ∼ 0.3) and the Jupiter-mass planet (q/h 3 ∼ 1) relevant to type I migration. The 5 Jupiter-mass planet (q/h 3 ∼ 5 ≫ 1) is, however, more prone to non-linear effects (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Masset et al. 2006</ref>). This is presumably why the migration timescales of the Jupiter-and the 5 Jupiter-mass planets do not differ by a factor of their mass ratio. It may seem surprising that the 5 Jupiter-mass planet does not open a gap and migrates in a very short timescale. The gap-opening criterion for a planet on a fixed circular orbit in a laminar viscous disc takes the form ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Crida et al. 2006</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1.1 q h 3 −1/3 + 50 α h q h 3 −1 1,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where α and h are to be evaluated at the planet's orbital separation. Although it is unclear to what extent the gap-opening criterion in Eq. (3) may be applied to planets migrating in gravitoturbulent discs, it provides some insight into the fact the planets in our disc models are not expected to clear a gap. Notwithstanding that the large values of h and α imply the 5 Jupiter-mass planet does not quite satisfy the above gap-opening criterion (the left-hand side of Eq. (3) typically ranges from 2 to 4 in the disc inner parts), we stress that the vigorous tidal torque exerted by the disc, which is partly due to the large masses of the disc and the planet, conspires to make the planet migrate in a timescale shorter than the timescale required to open a gap (a few libration timescales, which would correspond here to a few tens of orbits). In other words, the 5 Jupiter-mass planet migrates very fast because it has no time to open a gap.</p><p>The results of laminar simulations with an isothermal equation of state are overplotted as dashed curves in 2008; <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Masset &amp; Casoli 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Paardekooper et al. 2010</ref>, in our case, the radial profile of the disc entropy scales in proportion to the orbital separation).</p><p>Further insight into the impact of the horseshoe drag may be obtained by comparing the migration timescales of our laminar calculations to those predicted by type I migration theory. Note that the predicted migration timescales are inferred from the torque exerted on a planet held on a fixed circular orbit. In the isothermal series, where Σ ∝ r −3/2 and T is uniform, the total torque reduces to the differential Lindblad torque. <ref type="bibr">Us- ing Eq. (14)</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Paardekooper et al. (2010)</ref>, we find migration timescales of about 75 and 20 orbits for the Saturn-and Jupiter-mass planets, respectively. This is in good agreement (to within ∼ 25%) with our findings (dashed curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 7</ref>). In the series with the energy equation, the total torque comprises the differential Lindblad torque and the horseshoe drag. Despite the large value of α in our disc model, the horseshoe drag is found to be fully unsaturated, as the diffusion timescale across the planet's horseshoe region remains larger than the U-turn timescale ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baruteau &amp; Masset 2008a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Masset &amp; Casoli 2010;</ref>). Using Eqs. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(45)</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Paardekooper et al. (2010)</ref>, we now find migration timescales of about 35 and 10 orbits for the Saturn-and Jupiter-mass planets, respectively. This is shorter than what we find (see solid curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 7</ref>), although still in decent agreement. The difference presumably arises from the large velocity difference between the disc and the planet, which sets asymmetric horseshoe streamlines around the planet's orbital radius <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Masset 2002)</ref>, an effect that is not taken into account in the horseshoe drag expression of <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Paardekooper et al. (2010)</ref>.</p><p>We further comment on having a positive entropy gradient in our gravitoturbulent disc model. Let us assume the disc profiles of surface density and temperature scale as r −σ and r −̟ , respectively. The disc entropy s, which we define as s ≡ pΣ −γ , where the disc pressure p verifies the ideal gas equation of state, scales as r −ξ , with ξ = ̟ − (γ − 1)σ. As the disc evolves towards a steady state with approximately uniform Toomre-Q profile, ξ ∼ −3 + σ(3 − γ). Steady-state gravitoturbulent discs may thus have a globally decreasing profile of entropy only for surface density profiles steeper than r −9/4 , assuming γ = 5/3. Furthermore, for γ = 5/3 and our fiducial softening length 0.3H(rp), the fully unsaturated horseshoe drag Γ hs reads ( <ref type="bibr">Paardekooper et al. 2010, their Eq. 45)</ref> γΓ hs /Γ0 ≈ −20.5 + 8.6σ,</p><p>where Γ0 = (q/hp) 2 Σpr 4 p Ω 2 p , and all quantities with the subscript p are to be evaluated at the planet's location. Eq. (4) shows that, in discs with a uniform Toomre-Q parameter, the horseshoe drag is negative whenever the surface density profile is shallower than r −2.4 , assuming γ = 5/3. The differential Lindblad torque ΓL can be similarly recast as ( <ref type="bibr">Paardekooper et al. 2010, their Eq. 14)</ref> γΓL/Γ0 ≈ 3.2 − 4.0σ,</p><p>and the total torque Γtot as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">γΓtot/Γ0 = −17.3 + 4.6σ.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Using Eq. (6), the type I migration timescale, τI = r 2 p ΩpMp/2Γtot, reads</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">τI T orb ≈ 5.6 × (3.8 − σ) −1 γQp q h 3 p −1 hp 0.1 −2 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where T orb stands for the orbital period at the planet's orbital radius. The estimate in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> applies to planets with q ∼ h 3 p , and is approximate, since it is based on the torque expression for a planet on a fixed orbit. As we have already stressed above, the fast relative motion between the disc and planet is likely to affect this estimate. Nevertheless, it indicates that the type I migration of planets formed by fragmentation (q ∼ h 3 p , Qp ∼ 1.5) in discs with moderate aspect ratio (hp ∼ 0.1) should typically occur in a few tens of orbits at 100 AU, that is a few 10 4 years.</p><p>Still, the migration timescales in our gravitoturbulent simulations are a factor of a few shorter than obtained in laminar disc models. In addition to the stochastic kicks due to turbulence, the following two mechanisms may account for the larger migration rates in the gravitoturbulent disc model:</p><p>-The non-axisymmetric component of the disc's selfgravity shifts Lindblad resonances towards the planet's orbital radius <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Pierens &amp; Huré 2005)</ref>. For discs close to marginal stability, and for our softening parameter (ε/H ∼ 0.3), this shift increases the differential Lindblad torque by typically a factor of 2 (Baruteau &amp; Masset 2008b, their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 10</ref>). Note however that this mechanism has been investigated in laminar disc models. It is therefore not straightforward whether it should behave identically with turbulence. Still, numerical simulations indicate that, on average, the Lindblad torque behaves similarly in laminar and turbulent disc models ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baruteau &amp; Lin 2010</ref>, where wave-like turbulence is generated by stochastic forcing of the disc).  <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>. Migration of a Jupiter-mass planet in a disc with cooling parameter β = 30. In the left panel, the planet mass is gradually ramped up over one orbit, while the planet is held on a fixed circular orbit. After this first stage (not shown in this panel), the planet is released in the disc. The middle panel shows results at higher resolution <ref type="bibr">(1024 × 2048)</ref>, and the right panel shows results with increased self-gravitating softening length (εsg = 3 × 10 −2 r). All three panels should be compared to the mid-bottom panel in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>, which displays the results of our fiducial setup (no gradual increase of the planet mass, grid resolution is 512 × 1536, and εsg = 3 × 10 −4 r).</p><p>-In fully self-gravitating discs, the effective mass that dictates the strength of the tidal torque and thus the migration rate not only includes the planet mass, but also the mass of the gas surrounding the planet's location. For massive planets (q &gt; h 3 p ), the latter corresponds to the planet's circumplanetary disc, which is a fraction of the planet's Hill sphere ( ). It is unclear what it corresponds to for smaller planets; we speculate that it might be the planet's Bondi sphere. For illustration purposes, the time evolution of the mass inside the planet's Hill radius is shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref> for three gravitoturbulent runs with β = 30. It is comparable to, albeit somewhat larger than the planet mass. It progressively grows as the planet moves inwards, despite the decrease in the planet's Hill radius with decreasing orbital separation. It is possible that the short cooling timescales used in our simple cooling prescription (a few dynamical timescales, depending on β) implies that the gas in the planet's Hill radius can contract more rapidly than it would do with a more realistic cooling function. Again, notwithstanding the uncertain dynamical role of the planet's Hill sphere in turbulent disc models, it is likely that the increased effective mass is responsible for an increase in the migration rate by a factor of a few compared to laminar calculations (which only include the axisymmetric component of the disc's self-gravity). We comment that both the increase in the effective planet mass, and the decrease in the disc aspect ratio with radius (in discs with flat temperature profile, h ∝ r 1/2 ), make planets less and less sensitive to stochastic kicks as they migrate inwards. This explains why in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> the amplitude of the stochastic kicks decreases with decreasing orbital separation. This also implies that, if a planet undergoes a vigorous inward kick, it will be increasingly harder to reverse the trend. However, should a planet experience a large outward kick, it would take longer for the tidal torque to take over and lead to inward migration again.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4">Impact of numerics</head><p>We briefly assess in this section the impact of numerics on our results of gravitoturbulent calculations. We have performed an additional suite of simulations with the Jupiter-mass planet and β = 30, with the planet's mass first smoothly ramped up over one orbit, while the planet is held on a Keplerian orbit. After this, the planet is released in the disc. This procedure is meant to mimic the clump formation, which typically occurs over a dynamical timescale, much shorter than the gap-opening timescale (see Section 3.2.3). The time evolution of the planet's orbital separation is depicted in the left panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>. It shows the very same trend as obtained without smoothly increasing the planet's mass (see the midbottom panel of <ref type="figure">Fig. 4)</ref>.</p><p>To assess the influence of resolution on our simulation results, we have varied the grid's resolution, and the softening length εsg over which the self-gravitating acceleration is smoothed. We have run two additional disc models with β = 30, one with an increased grid resolution <ref type="bibr">(1024 × 2048)</ref>, and one with a larger εsg (3 × 10 −2 r). In the latter case, εsg is 0.3 times the initial pressure scale height, and it can be regarded as a crude treatment for the effects of the disc's finite thickness. The value of εsg at r = rp equals the softening length of the planet's gravitational potential. We have checked that before the introduction of the planet at 30 orbits the disc properties (density and temperature profiles) in both additional models are in close agreement with those of the corresponding run at our fiducial resolution and softening length value. We restarted these simulations with a Jupiter-mass planet. Again, in each case, a series of eight simulations was performed with evenly-spaced values for the planet's azimuth at restart. Results with increased grid resolution, and increased εsg are depicted in the middle and right panels of <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>, respectively. Overall, the amplitude of the stochastic fluctuations is somewhat larger in the high-resolution simulations. Still, except in one run that features a rather long episode of outward migration, the migration timescale of the high-resolution simulations ranges from about 3 to 9 orbits, which is broadly consistent with the results at our fiducial resolution. Furthermore, increasing εsg from 3 × 10 −4 r to 3 × 10 −2 r does not significantly change the amplitude of the stochastic kicks experienced by the planet, and the migration timescales obtained with both values of εsg are in reasonable agreement. The results of both additional disc models indicate that the planet's orbital evolution is essentially unaltered by density structures arising from gravitoturbulence with typical size 0.3H.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Results at lower disc temperature</head><p>As shown in Section 3.2, the migration of planets formed by gravitational instability results from a competition between the background disc-planet tidal torque, and the stochastic torque due to turbulence. At least in the early stages of their evolution, such planets should have a planet-to-primary mass ratio q ∼ h 3 p , and be subject to type I-like migration (see Section 3.2.3). As far as the tidal torque is concerned, Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref> shows that the migration timescale is essentially controlled by three dimensionless parameters: q/h 3 p , which should be ∼ 1 in the early stages of the planet evolution, Qp, which is 1.5 in a steady state, and hp. The disc model that we have considered so far has hp ∼ 0.1, which leads to rapidly formed Jupiter-mass planets. However, it is possible that the disc initially has a lower aspect ratio, thereby forming less massive planets. The latter may still become Jupitersized objects if mass growth is efficient.</p><p>To evaluate the impact of a lower disc temperature on our results, we restarted the simulation of Section 3.1 with β = 15 at 85 orbits. At this time, the disc aspect ratio at the planet's restart location (100 AU) has decreased from 0.1 to about 0.06, and the disc's mass from 0.2M⋆ to 0.15M⋆. We choose again three planet masses corresponding to a planet-to-primary ratio q around h 3 p : a 20 Earth-mass planet (q = 6 × 10 −5 , q/h 3 p ∼ 0.3), a ∼ Saturn-mass planet (q = 2 × 10 −4 , q/h 3 p ∼ 1), and a Jupiter-mass planet (q = 10 −3 , q/h 3 p ∼ 5). As previously, we take eight evenly-spaced planet's azimuths at restart. The time evolution of the planets' orbital separation is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 10</ref>. Compared to the results with hp = 0.1, planets with the same q/h 3 p are now more sensitive to stochastic fluctuations, the tidal torque becoming less vigorous. This can be seen from Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(7)</ref>, which indicates that at fixed values of q/h 3 p and Qp, the migration timescale due to the tidal torque scales with h −2 p . The mean migration timescales that we obtain for hp ∼ 0.06 (about 6, 12, and 50 orbits with decreasing q/h 3 p ) are typically a factor of 3-5 longer than in the corresponding runs with hp ∼ 0.1, which is roughly consistent with the aforementioned scaling τI ∝ h −2 p .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">CONCLUDING REMARKS</head><p>Planets observed at large orbital separation from their host star (typically 50 AU) are thought to be potential candidates for the formation scenario based on the gravitational instability of massive discs. A number of studies have shown that the formation of clumps by fragmentation is possible at such separations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Rafikov 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Matzner &amp; Levin 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Stamatellos &amp; Whitworth 2008)</ref>. The orbital evolution of clumps formed by gravitational instability has been investigated in a few studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Mayer et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Boss 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Vorobyov &amp; Basu 2010a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Cha &amp; Nayakshin 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Machida et al. 2011</ref>). Clumps are often observed to migrate inwards on short timescales, although in some disc models the formation of several clumps and/or the use of different cooling functions has a significant impact on migration, which sometimes appears to be suppressed <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Boss 2005)</ref>. In this paper, we have studied the interaction between a single planet and the gravitoturbulent disc it is embedded in, following the assumption that the planet has formed by gravitational instability. We have performed 2D hydrodynamical simulations with a simplified prescription for the disc's cooling. Three disc models with different cooling timescales have been considered, giving rise to different levels of gravitoturbulence. After having set up a quasi-steady state gravitoturbulent disc, we have restarted our simulations including a single planet with a range of masses approximately equal to the expected initial mass of clumps formed by fragmentation ( h 3 M⋆, with h the disc aspect ratio at the fragmenting location; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Boley et al. 2010)</ref>.</p><p>We find that a planet interacting with its nascent gravitoturbulent disc migrates inwards on very short timescales, despite the stochastic kicks due to turbulent density fluctuations. In a disc with aspect ratio ∼ 0.1, it takes less than 10 orbits at 100 AU (that is, about 10 4 years) for a Jupiter-mass planet to migrate from 100 AU to 20 AU (the inner edge of our computational grid). Planets less massive than the expected fragmenting mass are more sensitive to stochastic kicks, but also migrate inwards relatively fast. Their formation and migration timescales being shorter than their gap-opening timescale (partly because of the disc's vigorous turbulence), planets formed by fragmentation do not open a dip or a gap around their orbit, and are therefore not subject to the type II and runaway type III migration regimes. Turbulent density fluctuations may provide an effective mass deficit in the planet's horseshoe region that kicks the planet either inwards or outwards (see Section 3.2.2). These kicks can be seen as an effective, temporary type III migration coming on top of the inward migration due to the background disc-planet tidal torque.</p><p>The comparison of our results with those of laminar disc models shows that the averaged tidal torque driving the net inward migration in gravitoturbulent discs is essentially the one that would lead to type I migration in the absence of turbulence (see Section 3.2.3). Part of the reason as to why planets rapidly migrate inwards in our model is due to the set up of a positive entropy gradient in a steady state, which yields a large negative horseshoe drag, adding up to the negative differential Lindblad torque. We argue that in gravitoturbulent discs with uniform Toomre-Q profiles and coolingto-orbital timescale ratios (that is, with a uniform alpha parameter), the horseshoe drag should be negative, unless the surface density decreases very steeply (see <ref type="bibr">Eq. 4)</ref>. Although this possibility cannot be excluded, we believe that fast inward migration should be a generic expectation for planets formed by gravitational instability.</p><p>The main conclusion of this present study is that a single planet formed by gravitational instability should migrate inwards on a timescale much shorter than the expected lifetime of protoplanetary discs. However, it is not possible at this stage to say that massive planets at large separation from their host star, such as the HR 8799 system, could not have formed by gravitational instability. The simulations presented here contain a number of simplifications that need to be addressed. We have considered a simplified cooling prescription, causing the entire disc to be gravitoturbulent. In reality, we would expect the inner parts of a disc to be too hot to be gravitationally unstable, and other sources of turbulence such as the magnetorotational instability could prevail (see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Zhu et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Rice &amp; Armitage 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Clarke 2009</ref>, who studied the radial dependence of the alpha viscosity parameter in self-gravitating discs with realistic cooling). It is thus possible that the rapid type I migration of planets formed by gravitational instability gets slowed down in the disc inner parts, resulting in gap formation. A more realistic cooling prescription will also impact the rate at which planets can contract, with various outcomes for the evolution of the planet mass over its orbital migration (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Nayakshin 2010)</ref>. Also, we have focused on the orbital evolution of a single planet assumed to have formed by fragmentation, whereas the formation of multiple clumps is a likely outcome of gravitational instability. It is fully expected that the interaction between clumps may significantly impact their migration. We will address these issues in future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: CALCULATION OF THE ALPHA PARAMETERS IN A TWO-DIMENSIONAL DISC</head><p>When mass is confined to a razor-thin disc, the calculation of the alpha parameters associated with the Reynolds and gravitational stresses may be inferred from the general three-dimensional case by substituting the volume mass density ρ with Σδ(z), where Σ is the surface mass density of the razor-thin disc, δ is Dirac's delta function, and z denotes the vertical coordinate. </p><p>In both previous equations, vr, vϕ and cs are to be evaluated in the razor-thin disc (z ≡ 0) and are therefore directly computed in a 2D simulation. However, the vertical dependence of gr and gϕ, the radial and azimuthal components of the self-gravitating acceleration, needs to be determined as the gravitational field outside the disc contributes to the shear stress despite mass being confined to the disc. The potential Φ from which gr and gϕ can be derived is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Φ = − D GΣ(r ′ , ϕ ′ )r ′ dr ′ dϕ ′ r 2 + r ′2 − 2rr ′ cos(ϕ − ϕ ′ ) + z 2 + ε 2 sg (A3)</formula><p>where D is the domain where Σ does not vanish, and εsg is a small softening length required to avoid numerical divergences when z = 0. From the surface density of our 2D simulations, gr(r, ϕ, z) and gϕ(r, ϕ, z) can be conveniently calculated by fast Fourier transforms provided that z is taken proportional to r, condition required for gr and gϕ to read as convolution products (another necessary condition is that a grid with logarithmic radial spacing is used). The same condition applies to εsg for the calculation of gr and gϕ at z = 0. Writing εsg = Br and z = ηr, with B and η constants, the expressions for gr(r, ϕ, z) and gϕ(r, ϕ, z) are given by Eqs. (A1) and (A3) of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baruteau &amp; Masset (2008b)</ref> with B 2 → B 2 + η 2 . The vertical integral in Eq. (A2) is then numerically calculated from the values of gr and gϕ obtained with a range of values for η.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Gravitational, Reynolds and total alpha parameters, azimuthally-and time-averaged from 30 to 60 orbits at 100 AU (that is, over ≈ 8 orbits at 250 AU, the location of the disc's outer edge). Results are displayed for the disc model with cooling parameter β = 20. The dashed curve shows the total alpha parameter expected from viscous transport theory, given by Eq. (2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Contours of the disc's surface density obtained in a restart simulation with β = 30, where a Jupiter-mass planet has been introduced at 100 AU. Results are displayed three orbits after the restart time. The planet is now located at about 60 AU from the central star (at x ∼ −60 AU, y ∼ 60 AU).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Time (orbits after restart) M p = 5M Jup , β = 30 Figure 4 .</head><label>304</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Time evolution of the orbital separation of a Saturn-mass planet (left column), a Jupiter-mass planet (middle column), and of a 5 Jupiter-mass planet (right column) in a gravitoturbulent disc with β = 15 (top row), β = 20 (middle row), and β = 30 (bottom row). Time is displayed in years (bottom x-axis), and in orbital periods at 100 AU (top x-axis). Results are obtained for eight evenly-spaced planet's azimuths at restart (azimuth increases with wavelength's color).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>of the gravitoturbulent run with βFigure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Time variation of the (absolute value of the) migration speed, in units of the local sound speed, obtained for the restart simulations with β = 30 and zero azimuth at restart. They correspond to the results shown with black curves in the bottom row of Fig. 4. The migration speed is measured as the time derivative of the planet's orbital separation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Time evolution of the planets' orbital separation obtained for the laminar disc model with initial profiles of surface density and temperature similar to those of the gravitoturbulent run with β = 30 before restart. Solid curves show the results with inclusion of an energy equation (with viscous heating and β-cooling), and dashed curves those with an isothermal equation of state.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .Figure 8 .</head><label>78</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Time variation of the mass enclosed in the planet's Hill radius in units of the planet mass, obtained for the restart simulation with β = 30 and and zero azimuth at restart. The mass ratio is displayed before the planet crosses the inner edge of the computational domain.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Time evolution of the planets' orbital separation for the disc model with β = 15 restarted at 85 orbits, when the disc aspect ratio is ≈ 6%. From left to right, results are shown for a 20 Earth-mass planet (q = 6 × 10 −5 , q/h 3 ∼ 0.3), a ∼ Saturn-mass planet (q = 2 × 10 −4 , q/h 3 ∼ 1.5), and a Jupiter-mass planet (q = 10 −3 , q/h 3 ∼ 5). As in the previous figures, results are obtained for eight evenly-spaced planet's azimuths at restart (increasing with increasing wavelength's color).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>0</head><label>0</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Log (Surface density [g cm -2 ]) at t = 34.5Torb 

60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
110 
Radius [AU] 

-3 

-2 

-1 

0 

1 

2 

3 

Azimuth 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> See fargo.in2p3.fr. c</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> C. Baruteau et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> Similar gravitoturbulent disc models, but with reduced aspect ratio in a steady state, have been simulated by Paardekooper et al. (2011) with the same hydrodynamical code and similar grid resolution. Using the same method to calculate the stresses as described in the appendix, they find an averaged value of αtot in very good agreement with the value given in Eq. (2). c</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> C. Baruteau et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="8"> C. Baruteau et al.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> As in the case with β = 20, this value of α, given by viscous transport theory, is slightly smaller than what we measured in the gravitoturbulent disc model (αtot ≈ 1.8%). We have checked that a higher value of α does not change our results of laminar calculations, presented below.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>CB is supported by a Herchel Smith Postdoctoral Fellowship. FM is grateful for funding from the EC Sixth Framework Programme and also acknowledges the support of the German Research Foundation (DFG) through grant KL 650/8-2 within the Collaborative Research Group FOR 759: The formation of Planets: The Critical First Growth Phase. SJP is supported by an STFC Postdoctoral Fellowship. Numerical simulations were performed on the Pleiades and Grape clusters at U.C. Santa Cruz. Part of this project was done during the 2010 edition of the ISIMA summer school, whose support is gratefully acknowledged. We thank John Papaloizou and Andrew Youdin for useful discussions, Min-Kai Lin for detailed comments on a first draft of this manuscript, and the referee for useful comments.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Balbus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">521</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">650</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">709</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">759</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">672</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1054</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">678</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">483</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Boley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hayfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Durisen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">509</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Boss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1836</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Boss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">629</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bryden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ró˙ Zyczka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">540</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1091</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G W</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
			<publisher>Moon and Planets</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nayakshin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1066</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cossins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lodato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">502</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">679</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">705</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">148</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morbidelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">587</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gammie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">174</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">241</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">425</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Helled</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">939</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">604</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">388</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">673</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">487</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Clampin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stapelfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lafrenì Ere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jayawardhana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van Kerkwijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">497</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bonnefoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Apai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ehrenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boccaletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gratadour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rouan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mouillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lacour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kasper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-K</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">405</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1473</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lodato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">630</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lynden-Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kalnajs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Machida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Inutsuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">729</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zuckerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Patience</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lafrenì Ere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1348</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zuckerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Konopacky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Macintosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">468</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1080</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">387</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">605</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Casoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">703</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">857</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Casoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">723</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1393</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Angelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">652</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">730</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">494</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Matzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">628</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">817</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wadsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stadel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1756</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">410</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">559</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mizuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Progress of Theoretical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nayakshin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">849</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">401</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1950</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">410</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">293</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baruteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mn-Ras</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paardekooper S.-J</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">485</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">877</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Paardekooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Papaloizou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2283</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pierens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Huré</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">433</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pollack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hubickyj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bodenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Podolak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Greenzweig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rafikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">621</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lodato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>MN-RAS</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evoliutsiia doplanetnogo oblaka</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Safronov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moscow: Nakua Stamatellos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whitworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">480</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">879</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">753</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Thommes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">626</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1033</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Toomre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Vorobyov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">650</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">956</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Vorobyov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">714</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Vorobyov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">719</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1896</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gammie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">694</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="1045" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ApJ</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
