<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:45+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A combined transmission spectrum of the Earth-sized exoplanets TRAPPIST-1 b and c</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-06-03">3 Jun 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Julien</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth, Atmospheric and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Tech-nology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>77 Massachusetts Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hannah</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">NASA Goddard Space Flight Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20771</postCode>
									<settlement>Greenbelt</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michaël</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique et de Géophysique</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université deLì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000 Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nikole</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Space Telescope Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3700 San Martin Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Space Telescope Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3700 San Martin Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brice-Olivier</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">Astrophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Cavendish Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>19 J J Thomson Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0HE</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burgasser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Astrophysics and Space Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laetitia</forename><surname>Delrez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique et de Géophysique</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université deLì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000 Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emmanuël</forename><surname>Jehin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique et de Géophysique</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université deLì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000 Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Susan</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lederer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">NASA Johnson Space Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2101 NASA, 77058</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkway, Houston</settlement>
									<region>Texas</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amaury</forename><forename type="middle">H M J</forename><surname>Triaud</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Astronomy</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Madingley Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0HA</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><surname>Valérie</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Van</forename><surname>Grootel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique et de Géophysique</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université deLì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000 Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A combined transmission spectrum of the Earth-sized exoplanets TRAPPIST-1 b and c</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-06-03">3 Jun 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Three Earth-sized exoplanets were recently discovered close to the habitable zone 1, 2 of the nearby ultracool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1 3. The nature of these planets has yet to be determined , since their masses remain unmeasured and no observational constraint is available for the planetary population surrounding ultracool dwarfs, of which the TRAPPIST-1 planets are the first transiting example. Theoretical predictions span the entire atmospheric range from depleted to extended hydrogen-dominated atmospheres 4-8. Here, we report a space-based measurement of the combined transmission spectrum of the two inner planets made possible by a favorable alignment resulting in their simultaneous tran-sits on 04 May 2016. The lack of features in the combined spectrum rules out cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmospheres for each planet at ≥10-σ levels; TRAPPIST-1 b and c are hence unlikely to harbor an extended gas envelope as they lie in a region of parameter space where high-altitude cloud/haze formation is not expected to be significant for hydrogen-dominated atmospheres 9. Many denser atmospheres remain consistent with the featureless transmission spectrum-from a cloud-free water vapour atmosphere to a Venus-like atmosphere. On May the fourth 2016, we observed the simultaneous transits of the Earth-sized planets TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c with the Hubble Space Telescope (HST). This rare event was phased with HST&apos;s visibility window of the TRAPPIST-1 system, allowing for the complete monitoring of the event (Figure 1). Observations were conducted in &quot;Round-trip&quot; spatial scanning mode 10 using the near-infrared (1.1-1.7 µm) G141 grism on the Wide Field Camera 3 2 (WFC3) instrument (details in Methods). Following standard practice, we monitored the transit event through four HST orbits taking observations before, during, and after the transit event to acquire accurate stellar baseline flux levels. We discarded the first orbit due to differing sys-tematics caused by the thermal settling of the telescope following target acquisition 11-13. The raw light curve presents primarily ramp-like systematics on the scale of HST orbit-induced instrumental settling discussed in previous WFC3 transit studies 11, 12, 14 (Figure 1). We reduced, corrected for instrumental systematics, and analyzed the data using independent methods (see Methods) that yielded consistent results. We reached an average standard deviation of normalized residuals (SDNR) of 650 part per million (p.p.m.) per 112 s exposure (Figure 2) on the spectro-photometric time-series split in 11 channels (R = λ/∆λ ∼ 35). Summing over the entire WFC3 spectral range, we derived a &quot;white&quot; light curve with a 240 p.p.m. SDNR (Figure 1). We first analyzed the white light curve fitting for the transits of TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c simultaneously while accounting for instrumental systematics. Due to the limited phase coverage of HST observations, we fixed the system&apos;s parameters to the values provided in the discovery report 3 while estimating the transit times and depths. However, we let the band-integrated limb darkening coefficients (LDCs) and the orbital inclinations for planet b and c, i b and i c respectively, float under the control of priors, to propagate their uncertainties on the transit depth and time estimates with which they may be correlated. These priors were derived from the PHOENIX model intensity spectra 15 for the LDCs (see Methods) and from the discovery report 3 3 for the planets&apos; orbital inclinations. We find that TRAPPIST-1 c initiated its transit 12 minutes before TRAPPIST-1 b (transit time centers [BJD T BD-2457512]: T 0,b = 0.88646±0.00030 and T 0,c = 0.88019±0.00016 ; transit durations 3 [min]: W b = 36.12±0.46 and W c = 41.78±0.81). The difference between the planets&apos; transit duration of 5.6 ± 0.9 minutes implies that no planet-planet eclipse 16 occurred during the observed event, given the well-established orbital periods. Standard transit models 17 are therefore adequate for the analysis of the present dataset. We find an orbital inclination and transit depth across the full WFC3 band of i b = 89.39 ± 0.32 • and ∆F b = 8015 ± 220 p.p.m. for TRAPPIST-1 b and i c = 89.58 ± 0.11 • and ∆F c = 7290 ± 240 p.p.m. for TRAPPIST-1 c. In the context of double transit observations, the data primarily constrain the combined transit depths (∆F b+c = 15320±160 p.p.m.). Therefore, although the partial transit of TRAPPIST-1 c-before TRAPPIST-1 b initiates its transit-yields some constraints on ∆F c , it is not sufficient to completely lift the degeneracy between ∆F b (= ∆F b+c − ∆F c) and ∆F c. This explains the ∼ 30% better precision obtained on the combined transit depth-and, hence, also on the combined transmission spectrum. The transit depths derived over WFC3&apos;s band are in agreement within ∼2-σ with the values reported at discovery 3. We then analyzed the light curves in 11 spectroscopic channels, fitting for wavelength-dependent transit depths, instrumental systematics, and stellar baseline levels (Figure 2). We tried both quadratic and 4-parameter limb darkening relationships 18 for each spectroscopic 4 channel because transit depth estimates may depend on the functional form used to describe limb darkening. We found, however, that our conclusions are not sensitive to which limb darkening relationship was chosen, as long as the wavelength dependence of the LCDs is taken into account. The resulting transmission spectra are consistent with a flat line (Figure 3). The transit depth variations expected over the WFC3 band if TRAPPIST-1 b and/or TRAPPIST-1 c were harboring a cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmosphere are shown in Figure 3 (red lines and circles). Our transmission spectrum model 19 sets atmospheric temperature to the planet&apos;s equilibrium temperature (T eq,b = 366 K and T eq,c = 315 K) assuming a 0.3 Bond albedo. Since the planetary masses remain unmeasured, we conservatively use a mass of ∼0.95 and ∼0.85 M ⊕ for TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c, the maximum masses allowing them to possess H 2-He envelopes greater than 0.1% of their total masses given their radii 20. The precision achieved on the combined transmission spectrum (∼350 p.p.m. per bins) is sufficient to detect the presence of a cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmosphere via the detection of water or methane absorption features. The featureless spectra rule out a cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmosphere for TRAPPIST-1 b and c at the 12 and 10σ level, respectively. We also show in Figure 3 alternative atmospheres for TRAPPIST-1 b and c that are consistent with the data; volatile (water) rich atmospheres and H 2-dominated atmospheres with a cloud deck at 10 mbar in blue and in yellow, respectively. Many alternatives for the atmospheres of TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c still remain. The atmospheric screening of sub-Neptune-5 sized exoplanets with current observatories is a step-by-step process 14, 21, 22. As was done for the super-Earth GJ 1214 b 21 , the first observations of TRAPPIST-1&apos;s planets with HST allow us to rule out a cloud-free H 2-dominated atmosphere for either planet at the 10-σ level. If the planets&apos; atmospheres are hydrogen-dominated, then they must contain clouds or hazes that are grey absorbers between 1.1 and 1.7µm at pressures less than ∼10 mbar. However, theoretical investigations for hydrogen-dominated atmospheres 9 predict that the haze and cloud formation efficiencies at the irradiation levels of TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c should be dramatically reduced compared to, e.g., GJ 1214 b (insolation ratios: S GJ1214b /S b ∼ 4 and S GJ1214b /S c ∼ 8), leading to cloud formation at pressure level 100 mbar with marginal effects on their transmission spectrum 19. In short, H 2-dominated atmospheres can thus be considered as unlikely for TRAPPIST-1 b and c. Planets with the sizes and equilibrium temperatures of TRAPPIST-1 b and c could possess relatively thick H 2 O, CO 2 , N 2 , or O 2 dominated atmospheres or potentially tenuous atmospheres composed of a variety of chemical species 4-8, 23. All these denser atmospheres are consistent with our measurements because the amplitude of a planet&apos;s transmission spectrum scales directly with its atmospheric mean molecular weight µ-the amplitude of an exoplanet&apos;s transmission spectrum can be expressed as 2R p h ef f /R 2 , where R p and R are the planetary and stellar radii and h ef f is the effective atmospheric height (that is, the extent of the atmospheric annulus) which is directly proportional to the atmospheric scale height, H = kT /µg, where k is Boltzmann&apos;s constant, T is the atmospheric temperature, and g is the surface gravity. 6 Therefore, everything else being equal the transmission spectrum amplitude of denser atmosphere is significantly damped compared to the one of a H 2-dominated atmosphere (e.g., by a factor ∼7 for a H 2 O-dominated atmosphere). As a result, no constraint on the presence and minimum pressure-level of clouds/hazes for such denser atmospheres can be infered from our data. TRAPPIST-1 b and c could, for instance, harbor a cloud-free water-vapor atmosphere or a Venus-like atmosphere with high-altitude hazes 24, 25. We shall be able to distinguish between such atmospheres. The transmission spectrum of Venus as an exoplanet would present broad variations of ∼2 p.p.m. from 0.2 to 5 µm 26 which, rescaled to the TRAPPIST-1 star, correspond to variations ∼160 p.p.m.(= 2 × R 2 Sun /R 2 T RAP P IST −1), currently below our errors, but eventually reachable.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>before TRAPPIST- 1 b</head><label>1</label><figDesc>(transit time centers [BJD T BD -2457512]: T 0,b = 0.88646±0.00030 and T 0,c = 0.88019±0.00016 ; transit durations 3 [min]: W b = 36.12±0.46 and W c = 41.78±0.81).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>are therefore adequate for the analysis of the present dataset. We find an orbital inclination and transit depth across the full WFC3 band of i b = 89.39 ± 0.32 • and ∆F b = 8015 ± 220 p.p.m. for TRAPPIST-1 b and i c = 89.58 ± 0.11 • and ∆F c = 7290 ± 240 p.p.m. for TRAPPIST-1 c.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The transit depth variations expected over the WFC3 band if TRAPPIST-1 b and/or TRAPPIST- 1 c were harboring a cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmosphere are shown in Figure 3 (red lines and circles). Our transmission spectrum model 19 sets atmospheric temperature to the planet's equilibrium temperature (T eq,b = 366 K and T eq,c = 315 K) assuming a 0.3 Bond albedo. Since the planetary masses remain unmeasured, we conservatively use a mass of ∼0.95</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Hubble/WFC3 white-light curve of TRAPPIST-1 b and c double transit of 04 May</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Hubble/WFC3 spectrophotometry of TRAPPIST-1 b and c double transit of 04 May</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 3: Transmission spectra of TRAPPIST-1 b and c compared to models. Theoretical</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Methods HST WFC3 Observations. We observed the transit of TRAPPIST-1 c followed 12 minutes later by the transit of TRAPPIST-1 b on 04 May 2016. Observations were conducted using HST/WFC3 IR G141 grism (1.1-1.7µm) in Round-trip scanning mode 10 . Using the Round-trip scan mode involves exposing the telescope during an initial forward slew in the cross-dispersion direction, and exposing during an equivalent slew in the reverse direction (details on the trade- offs behind round-trip scanning below). Scans were conducted at a rate of ≈0.236 pixels per second, with a final spatial scan covering ≈26.4 pixels in the cross-dispersion direction on the detector. We use the IMA output files from the CalWF3 pipeline which have been calibrated using flat fields and bias subtraction. We applied two different extraction techniques which lead to the same conclusions. The first technique extracts the flux for TRAPPIST-1 from each exposure by taking the difference between successive non-destructive reads. A top-hat filter is then applied around the target spectrum measured ±18 pixels from the center of the TRAPPIST-1 scan, and sets all external pixels to zero. Next, the images are reconstructed by adding the individual reads per exposure back together. Using the reconstructed images we extracted the spectra with an aperture of 31 pixels around the computed centering profile for both forward and reverse scan observations. The centering profile is calculated based on the pixel flux boundaries of each ex- posure, which was found to be fully consistent across the spectrum for both scan directions. The second technique uses the final science image for each exposure and determines for each frame the centroid of the spectrum in a 28x136 pixel box, which corresponds to the dimensions of the irradiated region of WFC3's detector for the present observations. It then extracts the flux for 120 apertures of sizes ranging along the dispersion direction from 24 to 38 pixels (1 pixel incre- ment) and along the cross-dispersion direction from 120 to 176 pixels (8 pixel increment)-we</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>dian flux,</head><label></label><figDesc>and cleaning cosmic ray detections with a customized procedure 27 . Our observations present three cosmic ray detections that were not flagged by the CalWF3 pipeline. The exposure times were converted from Julian Date in universal time (JD U T ) to the Barycentric Julian Date in the Barycentric Dynamical Time (BJD T DB ) system 28 . Both extraction methods result in the same relative flux measurements from the star and SDNR (≈ 240 p.p.m. in the white-light curve), as the build up of flux over successive reads is stable.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>measurable differences in the total flux of the forward scan exposures compared to the reverse scan exposures. This effect has been seen for previous WFC3 observations 14, 29 in Round-trip mode and has been corrected for in two main ways. The first method involves splitting the data into two sets, one for forward scan exposures and one for reverse scan exposures, effec- tively halving the number of exposures per light curve, but doubling the number of light curves obtained. Each of these datasets are then analysed separately and the results combined at the end 14 . The second method uses the median of each scan direction to normalize the two light curves which are then recombined and normalized prior to the light curve analysis to obtain the transit parameters 29 . In the TRAPPIST-1 data we measure ∼0.1% difference in flux level</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>tematic models which include corrections in time, HST orbital phase, and positional shifts in wavelength on the detector and marginalize over all possible combinations to obtain the transit parameters. It fits the lightcurves for each systematic model and approximates the evidence-based weight of each systematic model using the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) 30 . It does so while keeping fixed the LDCs to the best estimates presented below and the orbital inclinations to the estimates from ref. 3 . The highest weighted systematic models include linear corrections in time, and linear corrections in HST orbital phase or in the shift in wavelength position over the course of the visit. Using marginalization across a grid of stochastic models allows us to therefore account for all tested combinations of systematics and obtain robust tran- sit depths for both planets separately and in combination. For this dataset the evidence-based weight approximated for each of the systematic models applied to the data indicates that all of the systematic models fit equally well to the data and no one systematic model contributes to the majority of the corrections required to obtain the precision presented (Extended Data Figure 1). In other words, instrumental systematics affect marginally our observations. Independent analyses were carried out on the data using adaptive Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) im- plementations described in previous studies 31, 32 . For each HST light curve, the transit models 17 of TRAPPIST-1 b and c are multiplied by baseline models accounting for the visit-long trend observed in WFC3 light curves, WFC3's ramp, and "HST breathing" effect 12 . For these anal- yses, priors are used for the LDCs and the orbital inclinations. The visit-long trend is found to be adequately accounted for with a linear function of time, the ramp with a single exponen- tial in time, and the breathing with a second order polynomial in HST's orbital phase. More complex baseline models were tested and gave consistent results, as previously revealed by the marginalization study. We calculated the transmission spectrum by fitting the transit depth of TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c simultaneously in each spectroscopic lightcurve. We divided the spectral range between 1.15-1.7µm into 11 equal bins of ∆λ=0.05µm. We applied again the two tech- niques described above to analyse each spectroscopic light curve, resulting in the combined and independent transmission spectra of TRAPPIST-1 b and TRAPPIST-1 c. A least-squared mini- mization fitting (L-M) implementation 12 and the adaptive Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) implementations produced consistent results for each stage of the analysis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Extended Data Figure 2 shows the limb darkening fits for the 12 wavelength intervals in our transit light curve analysis. We calculated fits for four stellar models with effective temperatures of 2500 and 2600 K and logarithmic surface gravities of 5.0 and 5.5. We then linearly interpolated the limb darkening coefficients to an effective temperature of 2550 and gravity 5.22, appropriate for TRAPPIST-1 3 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Extended Data Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Marginal effects of the instrumental systematics on the transit depth estimates. a Evidence-based weight, W q for each systematic model 12 applied to the white light curve. b Combined transit depth estimate (∆F b+c ) obtained correcting the data using each sys- tematic model. c and d show similarly the individual transit depth estimates of TRAPPIST-1 b and c, ∆F b and ∆F c respectively. The horizontal lines indicate the final marginalized measure- ments and the associated uncertainties. The scale of the values here indicates that all of the systematic models fit equally well to the data. Extended Data Figure 2: TRAPPIST-1's limb darkening. Stellar limb darkening relationships for TRAPPIST-1 (black curves) and four stellar models (colored curves) that bracket the ef- fective temperature and surface gravity of TRAPPIST-1. The circles are theoretical 15 specific intensities (I) relative to disc centre (I c ) as a function of µ , the cosine of the angle between an outward radial vector and the direction towards the observer. We fitted I/I c averaged over the indicated wavelength intervals to determine the quadratic (dashed curves) and 4-parameter (solid curves) limb darkening coefficients.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Habitable Zones around Main-sequence Stars: New Estimates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kopparapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">765</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards the Minimum Inner Edge Distance of the Habitable Zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zsom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Stamenkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">778</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperate Earth-sized planets transiting a nearby ultracool dwarf star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kepler Planets: A Tale of Evaporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">775</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planetary Population Synthesis Coupled with Atmospheric Escape: A Statistical View of Evaporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Evolution of Stellar Rotation and the Hydrogen Atmospheres of Habitable-zone Terrestrial Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">815</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extreme Water Loss and Abiotic O2Buildup on Planets Throughout the Habitable Zones of M Dwarfs</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitability of terrestrial-mass planets in the hz of m dwarfs i. h/he-dominated atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mohanty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4088" to="4108" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermal Emission and Reflected Light Spectra of Super Earths with Flat Transmission Spectra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Morley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">815</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Considerations for using Spatial Scans with WFC3</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mackenty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infrared Transmission Spectroscopy of the Exoplanets HD 209458b and XO-1b Using the Wide Field Camera-3 on the Hubble Space Telescope</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">774</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marginalizing Instrument Systematics in HST WFC3 Transit Light Curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">819</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A continuum from clear to cloudy hot-Jupiter exoplanets without primordial water depletion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clouds in the atmosphere of the super-Earth exoplanet GJ1214b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kreidberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new extensive library of PHOENIX stellar atmospheres and synthetic spectra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T.-O</forename><surname>Husser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planet-Planet Eclipse and the Rossiter-McLaughlin Effect of a Multiple Transiting System: Joint Analysis of the Subaru Spectroscopy and the Kepler Photometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">759</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analytic Light Curves for Planetary Transit Searches</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mandel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">580</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">We have opted not to make available the codes used for the data extraction as they are currently a significant asset of the researchers&apos; tool kits. We have opted not to make available all but one of the codes used for the data analyses for the same reason. The MCMC software used by M.G. to analyse independently the photometric data is a custom Fortran 90 code that can be obtained upon request</title>
		<ptr target="http://astroutils.astronomy.ohiostate.edu/time/utc2bjd.html" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>The custom IDL code used to determine limb-darkening coefficients can be obtained upon request</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An HST optical-to-near-IR transmission spectrum of the hot Jupiter WASP-19b: detection of atmospheric water and likely absence of TiO</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Huitson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3252" to="3274" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving Better Than 1 Minute Accuracy in the Heliocentric and Barycentric Julian Dates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eastman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Siverd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publ. Astron. Soc. Pac</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hubble Space Telescope Near-IR Transmission Spectroscopy of the Super-Earth HD 97658b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">794</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliable inference of exoplanet light-curve parameters using deterministic and stochastic systematics models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">445</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3401" to="3414" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The TRAPPIST survey of southern transiting planets. I. Thirty eclipses of the ultra-short period planet WASP-43 b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">542</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct Measure of Radiative And Dynamical Properties of an Exoplanet Atmosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">820</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Limb darkening and exoplanets: testing stellar model atmospheres and identifying biases in transit parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Espinoza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jordán</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">450</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1879" to="1899" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric Retrieval for Super-Earths: Uniquely Constraining the Atmospheric Composition with Transmission Spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">753</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
