<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:19+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">HUBBLE SPACE TELESCOPE HIGH RESOLUTION IMAGING OF KEPLER SMALL AND COOL EXOPLANET HOST STARS *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-09-29">29 Sep 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ronald</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kimberly</forename><forename type="middle">M S</forename><surname>Cartier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elisabeth</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Kalas</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">HUBBLE SPACE TELESCOPE HIGH RESOLUTION IMAGING OF KEPLER SMALL AND COOL EXOPLANET HOST STARS *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-09-29">29 Sep 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">(Received July 3, 2014; Accepted September 24, 2014) Accepted by AJ</note>
					<note>Accepted by AJ Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 5/2/11</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Subject headings: planetary systems -stars: binaries -stars: late-type -stars: statistics</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>High resolution imaging is an important tool for follow-up study of exoplanet candidates found via transit detection with the Kepler Mission. We discuss here HST imaging with the WFC3 of 23 stars that host particularly interesting Kepler planet candidates based on their small size and cool equilibrium temperature estimates. Results include detections, exclusion of background stars that could be a source of false positives for the transits, and detection of physically-associated companions in a number of cases providing dilution measures necessary for planet parameter refinement. For six KOIs, we find that there is ambiguity in which star hosts the transiting planet(s), with potentially strong implications for planetary characteristics. Our sample is evenly distributed in G, K, and M spectral types. Albeit with a small sample size, we find that physically-associated binaries are more common than expected at each spectral type, reaching a factor of 10 frequency excess at M. We document the program detection sensitivities, detections, and deliverables to the Kepler follow-up program archive.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The NASA Kepler Mission has presented a catalog of over 2000 stars with over 2700 planet-like transit signatures ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Borucki et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Batalha et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Burke et al. 2014</ref>). The number of planets confirmed (much more likely to be a real exoplanet than a false positive) from the Kepler sample has reached 977, with the vast majority of these following from the <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lissauer et al. (2014)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Rowe et al. (2014)</ref> validation of planets in systems showing more than one set of periodic transits. Perhaps more impressive than these large numbers that have qualitatively expanded the sample of exoplanets are the large number of specific cases for which detailed studies have allowed qualitatively new discoveries, e.g., circumbinary planets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Doyle et al. 2011</ref>), planet properties constrained by transit timing variations ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Holman et al. 2010</ref>), density constraints across the rocky to gaseous planet domain using radial velocities ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Marcy et al. 2014</ref>), and significant improvements that follow from Kepler asteroseismology results for planet hosts ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Huber et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>Clearly the spectacular time-series data collected from the Kepler Mission ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Borucki et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Koch et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Jenkins et al. 2010</ref>) have been the primary basis for new advances. Also important has been an emphasis from the mission's start to carefully discriminate between planet candidates as found from apparent transits, and validated or confirmed planets. The chance for false positives in transit detection experiments is high, with numerous channels potentially contributing apparent results that are not in fact due to extrasolar planets <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Brown 2003)</ref>.</p><p>The Kepler data are used directly to eliminate the vast majority of false positives arising from the most common case of blended, background eclipsing binaries through measurement of centroid motion ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bryson et al. 2013</ref>) in difference images in-and out-of-transit. Although very powerful, the Kepler data centroiding still allows for both false positives to slip through and for blended stars, whether physically associated or chance superpositions, to introduce dilution that needs to be corrected for in arriving at accurate interpretations of planets.</p><p>Fundamental to the Kepler Mission results has been a vigorous program to obtain supporting spectroscopy and high-resolution imaging for recognizing false positives, for confirming planets, and for refining parameters of detected exoplanets. Spectroscopy is particularly important for detecting tight binaries via induced radial velocity variations, and blended objects in cross-correlations with templates. High resolution imaging gains relevance in picking up wider bound components and chance superpositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Morton &amp; Johnson 2011</ref>) important to establishing planetary status.</p><p>The primary HST program, data characteristics and basic image analyses are discussed in Section 2. Defining point spread functions, conducting searches, avoiding spurious detections, establishing completeness limits for the HST high-resolution imaging, and placing these results in context of other similar observations are the topics in Section 3. Section 4 presents results on using isochrone matching to assess the probability of spatially close stars being physically associated, and documents all companions that could be the transit host, or source of false positives for our sample.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PROGRAM, DATA AND BASIC IMAGE ANALYSES</head><p>In early 2012, when this GO-12893 program was proposed, the Kepler Mission follow-up programs were relying on 3-6m telescopes and adaptive optics or speckle imaging for high resolution imaging. Many of the Kepler targets are rather faint -with the interesting M-dwarf hosts of candidates often near V = 16. With transits only a few hundred parts-per-million (ppm), deep imaging to delta magnitudes of at least 8 was needed to securely detect all possible false positives. This need for many Kepler Objects of Interest (KOIs) to reach the equivalent of V = 24 severely challenged then available ground-based resources. A test <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gilliland &amp; Rajan 2011)</ref> showed that HST imaging over half an orbit could provide superior results to full-night efforts from the ground for the most challenging targets. In later seasons with the more capable Keck-AO imaging in routine use some aspects of the HST advantage have gone away, with these having comparable resolution, and depth limits. HST retains an advantage of allowing imaging in optical bandpasses that are standard and well-calibrated, allowing accurate transformation to the Kepler bandpass as needed for use in establishing dilution corrections.</p><p>The HST imaging program was proposed to concentrate on a small subset of the Kepler planet candidates: (1) those that were faint with shallow transits severely challenging available ground-based imaging resources, (2) planet candidates that had estimated parameters R p below 2.5R ⊕ and equilibrium temperatures below 500 K, thus emphasizing candidates with a chance of being rocky and in some cases within Habitable Zones (HZ; Kasting, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Whitmire &amp; Reynolds (1993)</ref>). The GO-12893 SNAPshot program contained 158 targets, with the bulk being G-type stars mirroring the overall Kepler target list. In the end, and contrary to advertised expectations, the executed SNAPshot visits often corresponded to our faintest stars and longest visits. Thus the M dwarf targets were executed at a higher relative fraction. HST observations were obtained for only 22 of the proposed sample of 158, however those executed were among both the most interesting and most challenging for ground-based study. For example, our sample of 22 KOIs included 6 of 11 highlighted in the Dressing &amp; Charbonneau (2013) study of M dwarf KOIs with candidates in or near the HZ, and all 3 (KOIs 854, 1422, and 2626) identified as most favorably placed with respect to the HZ. The observations listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> span 2012 October 27 to 2014 January 7; any further visits that occur after 2014 May 1 will be processed, with deliveries made as discussed in Section 3.3, but are not included in this paper.</p><p>An advantage of our HST imaging is a very uniform data set. All observations were acquired with a standard set of five dithered exposures in each of the WFC3 filters F555W and F775W, chosen to sample the Kepler bandpass optimally. Four exposures used the DITHER-BOX pattern with exposure times chosen to reach 90% of saturation for cases with the image centered on a pixel. A fifth exposure at six times the length of those in the pattern, thus saturating the core, was added to bring up signal-to-noise (S/N) in the wings and allow reaching delta magnitudes near 10. For about one-half of the The left panels show deep (upper), and shallower by ×1000 displays of the image drizzled at 0. ′′ 03333 for F775W. The middle panels show the point spread function, as discussed in the text shown to the same stretch. The right panels show the difference in sense of drizzled image minus the PSF. The apparent star offset by ∼2 ′′ near 10 o'clock is a filter artifact also represented in the PSF that disappears in the difference image, while a true source near ∼2 ′′ offset at 5 o'clock becomes the most obvious feature in the difference image. Diffraction spikes and filter artifacts are removed to very high fidelity. The lower panels are meant to illustrate the inner part of the PSF, the upper panels the extended domain to ∼5 ′′ .</p><p>faintest targets the long exposure was limited to 300 seconds in one of the two filters (three targets were limited in both filters), thus yielding slightly shallower depths as listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The lost depth due to truncated exposure times is calculated separately as Def 555 and Def 775 for the two filters by using the WFC3 Exposure Time Calculator provided by ST ScI. This takes into account the five exposures in each bandpass and realistic background levels. The deficits are defined as the difference in magnitudes required to reach signal-to-noise of 5 at the actual exposure time compared to the exposure time that would have been used for the full, standard depth. The deficit applies to 2 ′′ radius and beyond. At closer offsets from the target star deficits are likely smaller since other factors enter to limit relative depth, but for discussion we conservatively assume these apply everywhere. Also included in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> is KIC-12557548 added from GO-12987 (PI Rappaport, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Croll et al. 2014</ref>) for which nearly identical exposures were available. Image FWHM values (Gaussian fit) are 0. ′′ 077 ± 0. ′′ 004 for F555W and 0. ′′ 079 ± 0. ′′ 003 for F775W with no outliers to statistically unexpected deviations. WFC3/UVIS consists of two backside illuminated 2048×4096 CCDs with a scale of 0. ′′ 04 per pixel, and a full well depth of about 72000 electrons. For a centered stellar image in our bandpasses ∼15% to 18% of the light falls on the central pixel in F555W and F775W respectively. Further details of WFC3 may be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Dressel (2014)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> illustrates the very similar data for each target, KIC-10004738 in particular. Note. -KIC, and corresponding KOI numbers are given for all targets, with the Kepler planet number given for validated cases. The number of multiple candidates or planets (Np), Kp, and the shallowest transit depth (Depth in ppm) over multiple systems are taken from CFOP. The δ-mag shows how much fainter a false positive source could be assuming 90% deep eclipses, and hence the relative depth to which high resolution imaging is needed. Def 555 and Def 775 are the net shortfalls in magnitudes in reaching standard depth due to slightly truncated exposure times. T eff is from the KIC, and Dist (in pc) is calculated using the HST photometry as discussed in the text.</p><p>Discussion of data processing through drizzlecombinations of all available exposures to a scale of 0. ′′ 03333 is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cartier et al. (2014)</ref>. Critical to this study the final drizzled image products were all shifted to be nearly (to within a few 0.01 of a WFC3 UVIS pixel) centered on a pixel, thus allowing all images to be "stacked" as discussed in Section 3.1 for an empirical point spread function (PSF) definition.</p><p>The WFC3 UVIS images were obtained using the 1024×1024 subarray nearest the readout amplifier of UVIS2, thus minimizing the effects of charge transfer efficiency. To further minimize limitations from the loss of charge transfer efficiency all exposures used a post-flash (brief illumination using an LED internal to WFC3 immediately after the exposure, and before CCD readout) to generate a physical background of about 12 electrons per pixel including allowance for the expected small sky background.</p><p>The UVIS subarray spans just over 40 ′′ ×40 ′′ . A few pixels near the boundary were trimmed to retain an area of exactly 1600 square arcseconds searched for companions to simplify later statistics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">COMPANION DETECTIONS AND COMPLETENESS</head><p>The primary product to be obtained from these HST observations is a list of all stars within the field of view, pushing as close to the bright target as allowed by the data and PSF, and providing accurate photometry and positions. Associated with this will be extensive simulations and analyses to quantify limits to false detections, detection completeness as a function of depth in delta magnitudes relative to the target star, and offset (angular separation from the primary) distance from the target.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Empirically Defined PSF and Subtraction</head><p>HST imaging is characterized by great stability compared to ground-based imaging, whether direct or with adaptive optics. However, over the course of HST orbits the telescope is thermally stressed and the focus varies by an amount that does influence the cores of PSFs in a significant way. Also, through broadband filters the PSFs will vary slightly as a function of the underlying spectral energy distribution. A goal of these HST observations is to make use of the general imaging stability, account for deviations from this, and thereby enable deep relative imaging near the core of the bright KOIs by subtracting a model PSF from each individual image.</p><p>We define a model PSF for each individual image by "stacking" all available images, except for those in which close-in companions are found, and then for each pixel relative to the target centers developing the PSF model as a function of target color, telescope focus, and minor deviations with respect to sub-pixel phase of the target centering. Photometry in the standard WFC3 Vegamag system (see Section 3.3) was developed for each target as discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cartier et al. (2014)</ref>, we then adopt the F555W -F775W magnitudes as the color. For telescope focus we utilized STScI's Observatory Support portal 6 that provides an estimated secondary-primary mirror despace at the time of observations using a modeling of observatory support structure temperature changes. For residual offsets from perfect centering we used an initial guess based on first moments over the central 3×3 pixels. We used 20 of the 23 targets for the PSF definition, ignoring KIC-6263593, KIC-11497958, and KIC-11768142 for which the binary or triple nature with small delta magnitudes and offsets &lt;0. ′′ 5 made these useless for determining a PSF. For five of the other targets we pre-subtracted a total of six much fainter companions that if left would have perturbed the resulting PSF model. A sample of 20 images in each filter to define the PSF as a function of color, focus and residual centering is smaller than desired, but clearly works well for eliminating to near perfection diffraction spikes and any filter artifacts.</p><p>The model PSFs in F555W and F775W are developed over an area of 201×201 of the 0. ′′ 03333 pixels, thus including an area of at least 3. ′′ 33 radius extending to 4. ′′ 7 on the diagonals to include the full domain of diffraction spike influence. Although other options were experimented with, we adopted a PSF model that was a linear function of color, focus, and the always small x and y offsets from perfect image-to-image alignment.</p><p>After an initial fit at each pixel to determine a zero point plus the four coefficients of linear terms, the solution was iterated for each image by fitting the model PSF to each individual target providing updated linear coefficients for focus and offset positions, with the known color being held fixed. With revised focus and offset coefficients for each target in hand, the model PSF at each pixel was again derived. This was iterated four times at which point convergence was reached.</p><p>The result of this approach can be assessed from inspection of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> showing one of the input images, the model PSF evaluated at the color, focus and offset applicable to this target, and the result of subtracting the scaled PSF to create a difference image. The PSF resulting from stacking 20 individual images shows a much lower noise level than the single target drizzled imageas should be the case. Also as should be the case, easily recognized features such as the diffraction spikes, and a filter artifact are sufficiently well subtracted to leave no discernible trace with careful inspection of difference images, while nearby faint stars are preserved. However, within the inner ∼0. ′′ 2 the PSF subtraction does not leave residuals that are near the Poisson limit, although detection sensitivity is gained even at these small offsets from using the PSF model subtraction. This lack of reaching a fundamental limit at small offsets could follow from a number of things. Our model for the PSF might be inadequate, e.g. perhaps other terms than the assumed linear dependence of color, focus, and small offsets should apply. We did try quadratic dependence on focus with no improvement. Perhaps the sample size of 20 targets spanning a significant range of color (mid G through mid M stars), focus (deviations to about ± 5 microns predicted), and residual centering imperfections to 0.05 pixels was insufficient for a solid solution; we had argued that 50 targets observed would be a good number for supporting robust PSF subtractions. In the end, though, the limiting factor seems likely to be the extent to which each individual exposure's position relative to the other four to be drizzled together could be determined. Given the small sub-array, there are generally only a small handful of other stars in the field of view at magnitudes remotely comparable to the target from which to establish relative positions. Minor errors at the order of 0.01 pixels in determining relative offsets of the under-sampled component dithered exposures would suffice to introduce errors to the PSF of individual combined drizzle products that would not be amenable to correction through our stacking process. Our PSF subtractions are in fact quite good, and there is a ready explanation for subpar performance in the core. Given that, coupled with small sample size, we have not exhaustively pursued improvements in this area. Rather, we focus on properly quantifying the detection limits that follow from the data subtractions as described.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">DAOFIND Searches, Avoiding False Detections</head><p>We use the DAOFIND task within IRAF based on <ref type="bibr">Stet- son (1987)</ref> to find stellar sources within our difference images from which the primary target has been suppressed. We have adopted a four-fold approach to avoiding false detections: (1) A number of images equal to our target set (23) have been simulated using simple Gaussian noise at the level of 9 electrons characterizing our real data. We then run DAOFIND on these images adopting increasingly conservative cuts on the adjustable parameter threshold for the feature detection in sigma until no false detections result over the full sample. A value of threshold = 5.0 resulted in no false detections for this null limit test, but is recognized as perhaps not sufficiently conservative for the real data. (2) Our goal is to retain most stars to a delta magnitude beyond 9.0, but to reject background galaxies to the extent possible. We therefore generated a grid of 2500 delta-mag 9 stars at random sub-pixel centering phase per each of the 23 pure Gaussian noise simulated, 1024×1024 images and then plotted the distribution of DAOFIND output parameters on sharpness, sround, and ground and adopted bounds on these as tight as possible while eliminating no more than ∼1% of these targets near the expected limiting depth. We adopted a range of [0.4,0.85] for sharpness, [-0.95, 0.95] for sround, and [-0.5, 0.6] for ground. (3) We performed extensive inspections of results on the actual images after using the above parameters. The only change following from this was to adopt a more conservative threshold of 6, rather than 5 σ, on the underlying detection significance to minimize detections which upon inspection seemed to not always be confidently stellar. (4) Near bright stars we boosted the required magnitude returned from DAOFIND based on a 5th order polynomial fit to the mean noise in annuli spanning 0. ′′ 1 to 2. ′′ 0 away from target stars on average. Without this step a large number of spurious detections occur at small offsets in the difference images simply from increased Poisson noise levels, but also from increasingly imperfect PSF subtractions at small offset radius.</p><p>This approach results in high completeness in detecting any stellar companions that could result in a false positive for the shallow transits in question. That is, outside of ∼1. ′′ 4 where noise from the stellar wings provides little lost sensitivity 22 of 23 cases in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> are imaged deeply enough to exclude EBs with 90% depth. Closer to the stellar core at a working radius of ∼0. ′′ 4 the detection limit (adjusted for deficits due to shortened exposures) is at about the median of depths needed to fully probe for the worst case 90% deep eclipsing binaries. At the same time we have been rather liberal in the retention cuts in the sense that we likely are not pushing as near the limiting depth as might be possible. In this approach we are placing a greater emphasis on avoiding false detections than reaching limiting depth, and will rely upon quantified completeness simulations to characterize the results. Furthermore, we will individually discuss in Section 4 any close-in detections that are not unambiguously real.</p><p>In setting up the difference images upon which DAOFIND is run to detect stars we subtract not only the primary target, but also perform PSF fits to and subtract all other stars within a delta-magnitude of three of the primary. This was found to be necessary to avoid spurious detections, e.g. along diffraction spikes on any stars within the images. For the three cases in which tight binaries or triples were detected we performed simultaneous fits of the PSF to these to create the difference image as discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cartier et al. (2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Simulations to Define Completeness</head><p>For defining completeness we have chosen to insert an equal number of simulated targets on each of 22 (of 46 total) images, half in the F555W filter, and half in F775W. We use all images for this simulation except: (1) The three cases of obvious binary and triple stars; (2) the KIC-12557548 images from GO-12897, since these went slightly deeper than the GO-12893 set; (3) the ∼1/4 of images from <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> for which one or both filters were not  taken to the full nominal depth. This leaves exactly half of the images from GO-12893 all of which by design used identical dither patterns, and exposure times that were designed to take the primary target to the same count level. Since the F555W and F775W images were designed to reach the same exposure level, we do not separate detection completeness by filter. The background level is nearly identical by design in using post-flash across all cases. The number of cosmic rays will of course vary frame-to-frame, but the longest total integration time in any filter was 673 seconds summed over 5 exposures, and cosmic rays have been well eliminated in the drizzling process and so are not a major factor. Nor do we take into consideration differences in stellar crowding imageto-image, while at the Kepler pixel scale of 4. ′′ 0 many of these are quite crowded fields, at the HST WFC3 scale of 0. ′′ 04 per pixel these are all sparse. While minor deviations in completeness level surely exist image-to-image, this is likely below the level of fidelity to which any reasonable effort could quantify this.</p><p>We have chosen to determine completeness on a relatively fine grid of offset positions from the primary targets: 0. ′′ 10, 0. ′′ 12, 0. ′′ 16, 0. ′′ 2, 0. ′′ 3, 0. ′′ 4, 0. ′′ 6, . . . 1. ′′ 8, and positions at and larger than 2. ′′ 0. Simulated images are generated at a series of delta magnitudes using the PSF appropriate (Section 3.1) to each image. The simulated images are always placed at random positions with respect to sub-pixel centering. The positions of real stars, other than the primary target, in the real-data difference images were ignored in placing the simulated stars. Different approaches to accumulating a sufficient number of simulations were adopted for different offset positions. Outside of 2. ′′ 0 simulated stars in each of the 22 images were placed on a regular grid (set at random sub-pixel position for each realization) every 25 pixels in x and y per image, thus resulting in over 50,000 cases. For the smallest offsets the central 41×41 pixels in each dif-  ference image were rastered into standard sized images, thus replicated over 900 times per image, and one simulated star was added at the correct radial offset for the trial, but at a random position angle. For intermediate offsets a few realizations were placed on the offset circle at non-interfering separation in angle. A sufficient number of simulations were used to result in Poisson counting statistics errors of 1% for the smallest and largest offset positions up to ∼5% for a few intermediate offset separations.</p><p>Our simulated images use difference images from which the target has been subtracted as the basis. For small offsets and magnitude differences a concern existed that the presence of a nearby companion might influence the primary target fit and subtraction, thus invalidating use of difference images as the basis. We therefore also performed a large number of simulations based on injections to the original images, and found no difference with respect to conclusions using the difference images.</p><p>After setting up the simulated images at any offset and delta magnitude combination the images were processed with DAOFIND, and the same cuts on output parameters as used on the real images were applied. A target returned from DAOFIND was counted as real if it falls within 0. ′′ 07 of the known position of the simulation input.</p><p>The resulting completeness levels are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig- ure 3</ref>. At an offset of 0. ′′ 10, 90% of stars with a delta magnitude of 2.0 are detected, while the 50% recovery level occurs at about δ-mag of 3. At and outside of 2 ′′ , 90% completeness is at δ-mag 8.9 and 50% at 9.4 per filter. Clearly beyond an offset of 0. ′′ 8 the completeness levels change very little, with most of the sensitivity change for offsets 0. ′′ 5.</p><p>We believe that at 0. ′′ 2 these completeness levels have been reached with essentially no chance of false positives coming in. That view is based on having performed careful visual inspections of all such detections in both F555W and F775W images and assuring that all detections are qualitatively secure. At yet lower offsets, we expect few if any false positives, but cannot argue that none have occurred in the real data given non-Gaussian behavior of the difference images in the PSF cores, or at least PSF variations that are not adequately captured by our modelling. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> shows a sensitivity curve developed as the 70% completeness level (following this use in the LilloBox, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy (2014)</ref> comparative study) for all offsets as plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>, as well as all detections within 2. ′′ 5 offsets shown as δ-magnitude deviations from the target Kp. The dashed line in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> corresponds to the boosted magnitude near bright stars (as discussed in Section 3.2) based on the noise in annuli spanning 0. ′′ 1 to 2 ′′ in steps of 0. ′′ 08 near the bright targets in the PSF-subtracted images. The dashed line is 2.5×log(noise/ref erence), where ref erence is the mean noise level of 9.0 electrons per drizzled pixel at &gt;1. ′′ 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Comparison with Other High Resolution Imaging</head><p>Although the high-resolution imaging observations available under CFOP in support of vetting and interpreting Kepler exoplanet candidates is expanding rapidly, these HST observations fill a useful niche. These observations are of very interesting targets in general, and are unique in covering both a large 40×40 ′′ domain, and providing resolution better than 0. <ref type="bibr">′′</ref>   <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Horch et al. 2012</ref>) with the 8 m Gemini North telescope on Mauna Kea, as well as the extensive robotic AO observations (optical) obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Law et al. (2014)</ref> with the 1.5 m Palomar telescope on Mt. Palomar. We will also comment on Keck 10 m telescope on Mauna Kea near-IR adaptive optics imaging, which is extensively used in the Kepler literature, although lacking an over-arching summary paper.</p><p>An ideal set of high-resolution imaging observations would include all KOIs, include a large enough area (40 ′′ would be good) to cover all potential companions of interest for analyzing KOIs while at the same time building up observational statistics on background object density across the Kepler field, reaching limiting depths of 9-10 magnitudes beyond the target brightness in order to detect (with comfortable margin) all possible sources of false positives (shallower okay for deeper transit cases), use at least two well-calibrated bandpasses in the optical allowing robust transformation to Kp and interpretation with published stellar isochrones, and have near diffraction limited resolution on large telescopes to probe as near the target as possible. All existing highresolution surveys to analyze the Kepler targets fail in at least one of the attributes of an ideal program. The primary weakness of our HST program is that it provides data for only 23 (&lt;1% of total sample) KOIs, but is probably better than any other program on the balance of other desired attributes. Therefore these HST results may provide useful insights through comparison of over-lapping observations from other programs.</p><p>A valuable observational element available through CFOP for nearly all KOIs are UKIRT near-IR images and resulting source tables. However, those were based on rather shallow, natural seeing imaging. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref> we have highlighted two detections at offsets and position angles from the KOI of about 14 ′′ and 203 degrees, and 19. ′′ 7 and 149 degrees. In the UKIRT-based source tables both of those were flagged as probably galaxies, and had Kp magnitudes projected from J of 21.5 and 21.0 respectively. On the much deeper, much higher resolution HST images both objects are stellar in appearance and have more accurately determined Kp magnitudes of 24.5 and 21.5 respectively.</p><p>We have only one target in common with the 6.5 m AO ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dressing et al. 2014</ref>), the unusually faint for MMT AO, KOI-886 at Kp = 15.85. The MMT AO provides a primary working angle of 0. ′′ 3 -10 ′′ to a contrast usually better than 5 magnitudes in K s . Within the 10 ′′ radius where <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dressing et al. (2014)</ref> report no detections we see four. Three of these have δKp 8, while a fourth has an offset angle from the target of 3. ′′ 7, δKp = 3.86 and is fairly blue. None of these should have been reported from the MMT AO given their listed sensitivity limits for this faint star.</p><p>We have six targets in common with Robo-AO ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Law et al. 2014</ref>): <ref type="bibr">KOIs 854, 886, 1085</ref><ref type="bibr">KOIs 854, 886, , 1422</ref><ref type="bibr">KOIs 854, 886, , 1598</ref><ref type="bibr">KOIs 854, 886, , and 2045</ref>. Within the typical offset working angle of ∼0. ′′ 2 -2. ′′ 5 and limiting depth of about 6 magnitudes for Robo-AO no detections were made for these six targets. For the same set we have three detections within the same offset distance. The KOI-1422 δ-Kp 1.56 companion at 0. ′′ 22 was not found by Robo-AO that deeper HST imaging reveals. This is a very interesting target <ref type="bibr">(Dressing &amp; Charbon- neau 2013</ref>) hosting multiple planets in or near the habitable zone, that will be strongly modified in interpretation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Cartier et al. 2014</ref>) through the recognition that this is a stellar binary. This is near the advertised working domain for Robo-AO, but in the low-performance domain for this faint KOI detection was not expected. Also not found was the 2. ′′ 3 offset δ-Kp of 7.36 physical companion to KOI-1598 -this is fainter than the claimed Robo-AO limit. Similarly the 1. ′′ 3 δ-Kp of 6.9 detection near KOI-2045 is not detected by Robo-AO. Although strong in covering many (eventually all is the goal) KOIs, the Robo-AO program by design does not succeed in detecting a large number of relevant companions.</p><p>We have no overlap with the lucky imaging (Lillo-Box, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy 2014</ref>), but note that the sensitivity curve of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> for HST is much better than lucky imaging, especially at offsets &lt;1 ′′ , see their <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>.</p><p>Lillo-Box, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy (2014)</ref> discuss the limitations of the extensive 3.5 m speckle imaging ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Howell et al. 2011</ref>) which has neither a field of view large enough, nor a detection depth deep enough to provide much of an effect in delimiting possible target contamination. We have KOIs 812 and 3259 in common with the more capable Gemini 8 m speckle imaging discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Horch et al. (2012)</ref>. For neither of these targets does the speckle imaging result in any detections. For KOI-3259 the HST imaging turns up a companion at 1. ′′ 36 just inside the speckle field of view, but at a δ-Kp of 7.8 is some 3.8 magnitudes beyond the 5-σ limiting depth as quoted on CFOP for either of these Gemini speckle targets. For the two targets in common with our HST program, the Gemini speckle imaging appears relatively uninteresting from the perspective of field of view and limiting depth. However, the speckle imaging provides the best resolution limit of any other available options in common use.</p><p>J. Lillo-Box provided evaluation of the Blended source confidence (BSC) parameter used in Lillo-Box, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy (2014)</ref> for our HST observations. The BSC parameter measures how effectively high resolution imaging observations eliminate the phase space of background objects bright enough to be false positives. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Gilliland &amp; Rajan (2011)</ref> had introduced a similar parameter and estimated that HST observations would eliminate 95-98% of possible background sources. The Lillo-Box, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy (2014)</ref> BSC result came out quite similar with typical rejections above 99%, and averaging well above 95%. In contrast the other high resolution imaging observation programs discussed in Lillo-Box, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Barrado &amp; Bouy (2014)</ref> succeed in eliminating only a small fraction of possible background objects bright enough to matter.</p><p>Finally we note that several of our targets have been observed with the Keck NIRC2-AO system of the 10 m Mauna Kea telescope, as was used for all of the objects discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Marcy et al. (2014)</ref>. The Keck AO images generally have a FWHM some 30% better than the HST value, and reach comparable limiting depth in many uses. However, the field of view, and limitation to near-IR bandpasses introduces limitations relative to the ideal. Our most challenging target, KOI-2626 (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cartier et al., 2014</ref>), with a triple at the 0. ′′ 2 level, was first detected in Keck AO imaging, then in short order also observed with Gemini 8 m speckle and our HST imaging. In all three of these observation sets the triple is cleanly resolved. Arguably the HST imaging is most valuable in providing well-calibrated optical photometry supporting determination of light fraction of each component in the Kepler bandpass, as well as matching up with published stellar isochrones.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">TESTING FOR PHYSICAL ASSOCIATION</head><p>Spatially close companions near and below the arcsec offset level are common in our high-resolution imaging. Since knowing whether a given companion is a chance superposition or a star likely bound in physical association with the target influences interpretation of planetary candidates, we seek a means of determining this nature. Canonical approaches would be to check for common proper motions, or similar radial velocities -neither is available in this study. We know only the angular separation, and photometry in two HST bandpasses with WFC3, F555W and F775W. Since the companions are fainter than the targets, and many of our targets are already K and M dwarfs, if physically bound the companions will often be M dwarfs. We will use matching of closely separated stars to isochrones, arguing that if the multiple stars can be represented by a single isochrone, then they are likely a bound system. We also adopt a Bayesian argument providing odds ratios in individual cases for the associations being a physical companion versus chance alignment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Use of Isochrones -M dwarfs and Optical</head><p>Bandpasses If two stars can be placed on a common stellar evolution isochrone, then this is solid evidence (in an Occam's razor sense) that the two objects are at nearly the same distance, likely share similar ages and metallicities, and hence are likely to be physically bound. The Dartmouth stellar evolution isochrones ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Dotter et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Feiden, Chaboyer &amp; Dotter 2011</ref>) conveniently include magnitudes in our WFC3 bandpasses, and have been extensively used for the interpretation <ref type="bibr">(Dressing &amp; Char- bonneau 2013)</ref> of Kepler M-dwarf KOIs. Modeling of M-dwarfs is challenging: especially problematic is obtaining the correct spectral energy distribution at short wavelengths where the complexity of molecular opacities couples with a part of the spectrum containing only a small fraction of the stellar flux. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> illustrates the problems arising for interpretation of early-to-mid M dwarfs, roughly those beyond F555W-F775W of 2.0, using standard isochrones. In this figure about 50 very nearby stars with V , I c photometry, and large, accurately known parallaxes from the RE-CONS project <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Henry et al. 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Henry et al. , 2006</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Cantrell, Henry &amp; White 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Jao et al. 2014</ref>) are shown following application of a minor transformation to F555W and F775W based on synthetic photometry using the <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Pickles (1998)</ref>   and more extensive discussion in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Boyajian et al. (2012)</ref>. Recognizing this disconnect for the M dwarfs that will likely be the most common companions in these analyses, we used the Pickles (1998) set of standardized, composite spectra to develop synthetic photometry using the SYNPHOT package under IRAF/STSDAS. This empirical approach to setting an isochrone results in a curve that at least parallels the observed color-magnitude distribution in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref>, but by mid-M is offset by over a magnitude.</p><p>For our purposes we only care about whether the stars at small spatial offsets are at near equal distances, and thus likely to be physically associated. We are not attempting to derive accurate stellar parameters. Thus we are free to adopt a purely empirical fit within the F775W, F555W-F775W CMD to represent a mean solar neighborhood isochrone. The adopted fit shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig- ure 5</ref> is a fourth order polynomial over F555W-F775W = 0.5 to 3.3 with a linear extension beyond this. Although there is a significant scatter of individual stars around this empirical fit, likely due to generally unknown starto-star metallicities, this represents the empirical CMD much better than more direct options such as the Dartmouth isochrones, or our attempt to obtain an empirical isochrone from published composite spectra. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> should raise a strong note of caution in using the Dartmouth isochrones to interpret M dwarfs if relying on optical bandpass photometry. The reddest stars plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> extend only to M6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Odds Ratios for Companion versus Chance</head><p>Alignment We follow the approach used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Torres et al. (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fressin et al. (2011)</ref> to establish the probability that planetary candidates are real exoplanets, instead of false positives. In their case an odds ratio based upon the established frequency of exoplanets, and the frequency of potential false positives was established. In our case this will be very similar -a ratio based on the known physically-associated companion rate, compared to our own empirically developed rate of false associations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Odds Ratio = N expected bound N random alignments<label>(1)</label></formula><p>The recent synthesis of an extensive literature on the commonality of binary and higher order associations by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Duchêne &amp; Kraus (2013)</ref> is adopted to provide the prior expectation on frequency of bound systems and thus N expected bound for each target. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Duchêne &amp; Kraus (2013)</ref> present results that FGK dwarfs have a mean companion frequency of 0.62, while M dwarfs have a lower fraction of 0.33 companions per star. For the G dwarfs companions follow a log-normal distribution with mean semi-major axis of 45 AU and a σ on log(Period) in days of 2.3, and 5.3 AU and σlog(Period) of 1.3 for M dwarfs.</p><p>Our high-resolution imaging is sensitive primarily to binaries at relatively large physical separations, the high period tail of the log-normal distributions. To evaluate the statistically expected number of companions for each of our targets we proceeded as follows: (1) For each target, estimate its distance using the observed F775W magnitude, the reddening given in the KIC ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brown et al. 2011</ref>), and the empirical fit to absolute F775W versus color as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref>. These distances are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table  1</ref>. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> For each companion map the observed spatial offset and estimated distance into AU ignoring projection effects. (3) Integrate over the G and M distributions of companion frequency separately from 0.5 to 2.0 times the offset distance in AU. <ref type="formula">(4)</ref> If the spectral type of the target is G use the G star result, if M the M star result, and if K the geometric mean of G and M. We use the KIC T eff from <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> and 5250 K as the G -K boundary, and 3850 K (Pickles 1998) as the K -M boundary. The expected number of companions, N expected bound , within the search range is usually 0.02 -0.08, i.e., an order of magnitude smaller than the integral number of companions expected on average over all possible offsets.</p><p>Assessing the N random alignments is developed from our own stellar detections and depends on three factors: (1) The mean stellar density (number per unit area) as a function of galactic latitude. (2) The mean stellar density as a function of apparent brightness. (3) How often unassociated stars reach various levels of consistency with isochrone matching. For the odds ratio of companion versus chance association we used the full set of GO-12893 images to establish the frequency at which two physically-unrelated stars match to a given χ 2 in:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">χ 2 = [(∆(F555W − F775W) A /σ A ) 2<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">+ (∆(F555W − F775W) B /σ B ) 2 + (∆F775W B−A /σ B−A ) 2 ]/2</formula><p>where the color differences are F555W-F775W per star minus the same quantity for the fit to local stars as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref> for the two stars tested, A and B, and the magnitude difference is the observed B-A value minus the corresponding value of the absolute F775W from the fit. For each of the 23 primary targets test matches were made to each of the non-primary targets in the other 22 images. For each χ 2 evaluation a minimum was evaluated by testing against all colors in the underlying fit of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 5</ref>. In addition the observed colors were dereddened by all possible values (in steps of 0.01) from zero to twice the KIC value for E(B − V ) of the primary star. From our set of 23 images, the smallest separation between two images on the sky is about 0.75 degrees. Our targets have a mean distance of ∼660 pc. Thus the phys- <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. Cumulative fraction of χ 2 matches using Eq. (2) for randomly paired stars across frames that are not physically associated with each other. Solid curve is a polynomial fit used in evaluating odds ratio for physical association test.</p><p>ical separation between stars in the two images nearest each other would be of order 10 pc. We thus assumed that no stars in any image are physically associated with stars in other images. Using all detected stars in each of the 23 images to evaluate Eq. (2) against all target stars in separate images gave about 11,000 matches. For the σ's in Eq. (2) we adopted formal estimates of precision from fitting a PSF to the data, with a floor of 0.015. At 21st magnitude errors were ∼0.02, increasing to typically 0.1 at 24th. The χ 2 comparison of two physicallyunassociated stars was usually large, with the most common values of order 1000 indicative of extremely poor matches relative to the empirical isochrone. The cumulative fraction of matches as a function of χ 2 is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. Random pairings of stars do occasionally have good matches to the isochrone, e.g., 5% have χ 2 1.0. Since these stars cannot be physically associated, it is clear that merely having a close match with the isochrone does not suffice to argue for physical association.</p><p>The test matching of ∼11,000 pairs covered an equivalent of 23×22 times the 1600 square arcseconds of each image. To evaluate the denominator for the odds ratio we adopted the same annulus area used for the prior expectation of companions discussed above and multiplied this by the number density per unit solid angle of test matches up to the χ 2 level of the star in question. We adjusted this value by two additional factors affecting the number density of stars: (1) a general dependence on galactic latitude as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 7</ref> after normalization to a mean of unity, and (2) the dependence of number counts as a function of brightness Kp as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> evaluated up to the estimated brightness of the test star plus a 1σ error.</p><p>This approach to evaluating an odds ratio for likelihood that a given companion is physically associated as opposed to a chance alignment provides a good indication of status, but for a few ambiguous cases additional inputs would be needed to establish the true nature. The results of testing the 481 total detections over 23 images for physical association is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> for all cases in which the odds ratio favors association, and for which  the χ 2 value is less than 10. (Two cases had odds ratios of 1.1 and 2.3 respectively for which the corresponding isochrone χ 2 were at 27 and 154.)</p><p>The split in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> between dominance by companions within 0. ′′ 5 and chance alignments prevailing outside of 0. ′′ 5 is striking. At the distances of our targets 0. ′′ 5 -2. ′′ 5 already projects to the high-period tail of the lognormal, physically-associated distributions. Given the values from <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Duchêne &amp; Kraus (2013)</ref> we expect about twice as many physically associated companions within 0. ′′ 5 as within 0. ′′ 5 -2. ′′ 5, i.e., consistent with <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>. The density of chance alignments should be uniform, and the area over 0. ′′ 5 -2. ′′ 5 is 25 times that at &lt;0. ′′ 5. In qualitative terms the split in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> is fully expected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Close Companions That Could Be Transit Host</head><p>We now consider all detections which complicate consideration of the true transit host based on our high resolution imaging. For close companions that we have de- Note. -KIC, and corresponding KOI numbers are given for all stars having a positive odds ratio for physical association as discussed in Section 4.2. Offset is in arcseconds, PA in degrees E of N, δ-mag in Kp, color is F555W-F775W, with χ 2 and odds ratio as in Section 4.2.</p><p>termined are likely in physical association with the target the complication would be not knowing the true host star of the planet candidates. For chance alignments the nearby star remains as a false positive possibility. In tabulating these cases of interest we consider two factors: (1) Whether the offset distance of the companion star is within the 3-σ centroiding error based on analysis of difference images in-and out-of-transit ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bryson et al. 2013)</ref>. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> Whether the companion star is bright enough such that even with 90% eclipse depths it could produce the observed transit depth when diluted by the target.</p><p>We take the 3-σ centroiding error from the Data Validation reports for Quarters 1-16 from CFOP. Two entries from <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> are not included here, since for both the 3. ′′ 3 offset star for KIC-5358241, and the companion to KIC-10004738 the Kepler -based centroiding eliminates these from contention. On the other hand we find that newly detected close companions to KIC-6263593 = KOI-3049 that are not physically associated with the target cannot be eliminated as possible false positive sources for the apparent transits.</p><p>The primary and companions for the 6 targets in Table 3 are shown in relation to each other in the CMD <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 9</ref>. KOI-3049/KIC-6263593 provides a good illustration -the closest companion in physical offset and δ-mag has an odds ratio of nearly 2000 favoring physical association. The other three companions in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref> have odds ratios favoring chance alignment and χ 2 isochrone match values (Eq. 2) of 154 to 816.</p><p>Over the 23 KOIs considered in this paper we find that 5 have physically-associated companions that could be the true transit host, and one of these has additional chance alignments that could be the source for a false positive. The results are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref>. Refined analyses, e.g., application of BLENDER ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Torres et al. 2011</ref>), might well eliminate some of these possibilities.</p><p>The 'Depth if host' in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref> follows from the observed depth in an unrecognized blend and the correction for dilution. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Daemgen et al. (2009)</ref> provide the by now often used correction for dilution in the case of the host being the brighter star. With the assumed host being the fainter star the equation takes the same form, with a change of sign in the exponent:</p><p>Depth if host = Depth obs (1 + 10 δKp/2.5 )</p><p>For several cases the inferred depth if the companion is the host exceeds 10% making a planet interpretation Note. -KIC, and corresponding KOI numbers are given for all stars leading to ambiguity as to the host star. The 3-σ error is the extreme offset still allowed from Kepler centroid analysis, offset is in arcseconds, the "Depth if host" is the intrinsic transit or eclipse depth (for shallowest transit of multi-planet systems) in ppm if the star is the host, and the final column indicates whether the companion is physically associated with the primary target star.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, and all companions within 4 ′′ . Target and companion are adjusted in color by dereddening of up to twice the KIC E(B − V ) to yield best fit. The distinction between likely physical associations and chance alignments is generally obvious. The target is the brightest star, and by design falls on the selected isochrone. A circle is superposed on the location of each star.</p><p>unlikely, although this must be balanced by considering the host star radius as well which is beyond the scope of this paper.</p><p>Of the stars listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3 or Table 4</ref> one deserves a special note of caution. The companion to KIC-5358241 at an offset of 0. ′′ 107 and a δKp of 2.39 is in a region of detection parameter space where reliability is difficult to assess. Until this detection is confirmed by a second high-resolution imaging experiment, the reality of this star remains open to question. All of the other detections listed in these tables are considered unambiguously real with parameters as listed within nominal uncertainties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Statistics on Physical Association</head><p>As shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> we have detected six companions to five targets that have odds ratios above 50, which we take as confirmation of physical association. Two additional cases have positive indications of being bound to the target, but are not certain. We wish to tabulate here the total number of detections as a function of target spectral type and compare this with the a priori number of expected companions <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Duchêne &amp; Kraus 2013)</ref>. For the two cases with modest odds ratios of 1.3 and 6.3 we assign fractional detections as 1 -1/(odds ratio + 1). We also only count the KIC-5358241 source offset by 0. ′′ 107 as 0.5 of a detection from conservatism as to the basic reality of its existence.</p><p>Over the 21 targets considered, ignoring the two sources <ref type="bibr">(KIC-6149553 and KIC-11306996</ref>) that in the interim had been shown to be false positives, we have 7, 8, and 6 stars at G, K, and M spectral types respectively. To evaluate expected number of companions in our data we sum over the log-normal distributions <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Duchêne &amp; Kraus 2013</ref>) corresponding to search offsets of 0. ′′ 12 to 22. ′′ 57. This yields an expected total number of companions of: 1.52, 0.67, and 0.31 for the G, K, and M stars in our sample. We detect 1.93, 2.0, and 3.0 across the three spectral types. Overall we detect 6.93 compared to an expected number of 2.50, for an over-detection ratio of ×2.8. The fraction of times that Poisson fluctuations with an expectation of 2.5 exceed 7 is 1.4% suggesting that the general over-abundance of companions is significant at &gt;98%. For the M-dwarfs in isolation the overabundance is ×9.7, and the nominal significance is 99.6%, or 3σ.</p><p>It is clear that (a) this experiment yields only small number statistics with 6 -8 targets per spectral type bin, and (b) we find more physically-associated companions than would be expected. The over-abundance of physically-associated companions is a monotonically increasing factor over the G (near nominal), to K, and M (order of magnitude excess) spectral types. These targets were selected on the basis of being strongly suspected of hosting one or more small and cool exoplanets. A direct interpretation is that widely-spaced stellar binaries, and higher order systems are over-represented among planetary hosts. Such an interpretation from this limited sample would be consistent with stellar multiples being more favorable sites for exoplanet formation, than are single stars. Another factor is that with knowledge of binarity these planets are actually larger than reported in the exoplanet archive. There has thus been a selection effect of including larger planets in the sample due to unrecognized binarity initially. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Kraus et al. (2014)</ref>, however, find from an interferometric survey of 600 Kepler planet candidate hosts sensitive to 5 -50 AU binaries (our sensitivity is primarily to binaries near and mostly beyond 50 AU, and therefore disjoint to their sample) that stellar binarity has a strong influence suppressing the planet frequency by a factor of about four.</p><p>G. W. Marcy <ref type="bibr">(2014, private communication)</ref> suggests an alternative view that multiple stars within the Kepler aperture simply increases the probability of transits existing, e.g., doubled for a binary since either of the stars might host planets at random orientations. In this approach one might expect binaries to be over-represented in the KOI list by a factor of two if the individual components have the same intrinsic planet hosting frequency as single stars. Since our over abundance at M-dwarfs is nearly a factor of 10 a discrepancy persists that simply interpreted suggests wide binaries favor the formation of small planets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">SUMMARY</head><p>The stable, high-resolution imaging provided by WFC3 UVIS on HST has allowed a careful survey for stellar companions to KOIs selected for having small and cool exoplanet candidates. In most cases no close-in companions were found that could be false positives for transits through blending of background eclipsing binaries. Our sensitivity to such companions reached 90% completeness for delta-magnitudes of 4 at 0. ′′ 2 separation, 8 at 0. ′′ 4, and &gt;9 magnitudes at 0. ′′ 8, with the latter usually exceeding the general brightness ratio that could physically be a false positive for these transits. However, in several cases we find close-in companions that are physically associated with the target star. These smaller, associated stars would not likely be a concern regarding potential false positives for exoplanets, but do call into question which of the multiple stars hosts the planet candidates with strong implications for the resulting exoplanet properties as presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Cartier et al. (2014)</ref>.</p><p>We also find, especially for our sample of M dwarf stars, that stellar multiplicity is over-represented in association with our sample having been selected as likely exoplanet hosts. Resolving whether the implied proclivity of wide multiple stars, as can be found in high-resolution imaging surveys, to form exoplanets is merely a fluke of small number statistics awaits larger studies.</p><p>Funding for Kepler, the tenth Discovery mission, was provided by NASA's Science Mission Directorate. The many people contributing to the development of the Kepler Mission are gratefully acknowledged. The individuals who joined as co-investigators on this HST proposal in early 2012 are recognized. Andrea Dupree, Francois Fressin, Matthew Holman, Jack Lissauer, Geoff Marcy, and Jason Rowe contributed directly to development of the proposal, provided extensive background discussion, or assisted in target selection. We thank Jorge Lillo-Box for providing note of his detection metric for our HST imaging. R.L.G. and K.M.S.C. have been partially supported through grant HST-GO-12893.01-A from STScI. P.K. thanks support from NASA NNX11AD21G and NSF AST-0909188. The Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds is supported by the Pennsylvania State University, the Eberly College of Science, and the Pennsylvania Space Grant Consortium. CFOP is funded by NASA through the NASA Exoplanet Science Institute. Data presented in this paper were obtained from the Mikulski Archive for Space Telescopes.</p><p>Facilities: HST (WFC3), Kepler.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. KIC-10004738 related images for illustration purposes. The left panels show deep (upper), and shallower by ×1000 displays of the image drizzled at 0. ′′ 03333 for F775W. The middle panels show the point spread function, as discussed in the text shown to the same stretch. The right panels show the difference in sense of drizzled image minus the PSF. The apparent star offset by ∼2 ′′ near 10 o'clock is a filter artifact also represented in the PSF that disappears in the difference image, while a true source near ∼2 ′′ offset at 5 o'clock becomes the most obvious feature in the difference image. Diffraction spikes and filter artifacts are removed to very high fidelity. The lower panels are meant to illustrate the inner part of the PSF, the upper panels the extended domain to ∼5 ′′ .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>7</head><label></label><figDesc>http://www.stsci.edu/hst/wfc3/phot zp lbn 8 https://cfop.ipac.caltech.edu</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. KIC-6263593 (KOI-3049) images showing the full 40×40 ′′ field of view in the upper panels. The lower panels are difference images of an inner region after subtracting the close-in bright pair. See Section 3.3 for further discussion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Note.</head><label></label><figDesc>-RA and Dec = position of HST source (J2000, decimal degrees) Dist and PA = distance (arcsec) and position angle (deg. E of N) of HST source from KOI F775W and F775W e = HST (Vega) magnitude and error of HST source Color and Color e = F555W -F775W HST -based color and error Kp and Kp e = derived Kepler magnitude from F555W, F775W and error d Kp = number of Kepler magnitudes fainter (or brighter) than KOI in HST -based Kp KIC = KepID likely corresponding to HST source KIC Kp = KIC value of Kp for likely match</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Detection completeness in percent plotted against delta magnitude for extensive simulated companions added to real images as discussed in the text. The curves are at different radial offsets as labelled in ′′ . Beyond 0. ′′ 8 curves are spaced every 0. ′′ 2, but beyond this there is little change in sensitivity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. All companion detections over the 23 targets within 2. ′′ 5 radial offset are plotted with a Kp δ-magnitude relative to the target. Detections determined to be physically associated with the target are shown with 'c', and likely background, chance associations are shown with 'b' -see Section 4.2 for discussion. The curve is developed as the 70% recovery level for each radial offset as plotted in Figure 3. The image FWHM is ∼0. ′′ 078. The dashed line showing mean noise in annuli near the bright targets, represented as a magnitude loss is discussed in Section 3.4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>spectra and the IRAF/STSDAS SYNPHOT package. The Dartmouth isochrones at [Fe/H] = 0.0 and -0.5 perform reasonably well in matching the spectral energy distri- bution of earlier type stars, but fail spectacularly in the optical with representing early to mid-M dwarfs (M3 is at F555W -F775W ∼2.4). See also similar comparisons</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Photometry of local stars from RECONS project after minor transform of V and Ic to F555W and F775W. Superposed are Dartmouth (Dotter et al. 2008; Feiden, Chaboyer &amp; Dotter 2011) isochrones for [Fe/H] = -0.5 and 0.0, labelled D-0.5 and D-0.0 respectively. The (blue) curve labelled "Emp" was formed from synthetic photometry of Pickles (1998) spectra. The (red) curve labelled "fit" is a polynomial fit to the local stars.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. Relative number of stars detected within Kp magnitude range of 18 -24 where all images are complete to this depth plotted versus galactic latitude. Number has been normalized by a mean of 13.7 stars per 1600 square arcsec image. The straight line is a fit to the distribution to be used in adjusting spatial density.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Cumulative fraction of detected stars as a function of Kp over all images.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. CMDs illustrating the relative positions for all targets listed in Table 3, and all companions within 4 ′′ . Target and companion are adjusted in color by dereddening of up to twice the KIC E(B − V ) to yield best fit. The distinction between likely physical associations and chance alignments is generally obvious. The target is the brightest star, and by design falls on the selected isochrone. A circle is superposed on the location of each star.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 KOIs with HST High Resolution Imaging</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>KIC KOI Kepler Np 
Kp 
Depth δ-mag Def 555 Def 775 
T eff 
Dist 
2853029 3259 
-
1 
15.68 
872 
7.53 
-
0.15 
5494 1325 
4139816 
812 
235 
4 
15.95 
554 
8.03 
0.17 
0.14 
4023 
495 
4813563 1959 
-
1 
14.25 
859 
7.55 
-
-
4915 
480 
5358241 
829 
53 
3 
15.39 
422 
8.32 
-
0.03 
6266 1765 
5942949 2525 
-
1 
15.70 
810 
7.61 
-
0.10 
4595 
715 
6026438 2045 
354 
3 
15.55 
356 
8.51 
-
-
4621 
710 
6149553 1686 
FP 
1 
15.89 
631 
7.89 
0.32 
-
3510 
235 
6263593 3049 
-
1 
15.04 
540 
8.05 
-
-
4582 
690 
6435936 
854 
-
1 
15.85 
1692 
6.81 
0.26 
-
3580 
265 
7455287 
886 
54 
3 
15.85 
448 
8.26 
0.22 
-
3654 
290 
8150320 
904 
55 
5 
15.79 
436 
8.29 
0.00 
0.11 
4404 
645 
8890150 2650 
395 
2 
15.99 
357 
8.50 
0.23 
0.10 
3825 
390 
8973129 2286 
-
1 
15.06 
504 
8.13 
-
-
5452 
975 
9838468 2943 
-
1 
13.85 
213 
9.06 
-
-
6036 
820 
10004738 1598 
310 
3 
14.28 
168 
9.32 
-
-
5657 
780 
10118816 1085 
-
1 
15.23 
307 
8.67 
-
-
3820 
275 
10600955 2227 
-
1 
14.87 
523 
8.09 
-
-
5848 1090 
11306996 3256 
FP 
1 
14.81 
333 
8.58 
-
-
4021 
290 
11497958 1422 
296 
5 
15.92 
787 
7.65 
0.29 
-
3690 
340 
11768142 2626 
-
1 
15.93 
818 
7.60 
0.32 
-
3620 
400 
12256520 2264 
-
1 
14.48 
334 
8.58 
-
-
5556 
800 
12470844 
790 
233 
2 
15.34 
962 
7.43 
-
-
5208 
970 
12557548 3794 
-
1 
15.69 
3186 
6.13 
-
-
4242 
550 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 Example Source Detection Table for CFOP Delivery</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>RA 
Dec 
Dist 
PA F775W F775W e Color Color e 
Kp 
Kp e d Kp 
KIC KIC Kp 
282.9975209 41.6785572 
0.000 
0.000 14.806 
0.020 
1.198 
0.020 
15.537 0.020 0.000 6263593 
15.037 
282.9974699 41.6784340 
0.478 196.900 15.284 
0.020 
1.362 
0.020 
16.080 0.020 0.543 
282.9974496 41.6783548 
0.757 194.804 20.592 
0.061 
1.280 
0.111 
21.355 0.076 5.818 
282.9970876 41.6784729 
1.207 255.271 22.400 
0.045 
0.916 
0.062 
23.017 0.045 7.480 
282.9977796 41.6788370 
1.221 
34.638 19.712 
0.015 
1.242 
0.022 
20.460 0.018 4.923 
282.9971164 41.6793261 
2.972 338.496 20.773 
0.019 
1.126 
0.027 
21.474 0.022 5.937 
282.9936923 41.6799497 11.450 295.946 22.764 
0.054 
2.436 
0.152 
23.992 0.100 8.455 
282.9961378 41.6818506 12.423 342.573 22.942 
0.060 
3.001 
0.293 
24.397 0.188 8.860 
282.9999390 41.6750932 14.065 152.477 20.422 
0.017 
2.654 
0.032 
21.738 0.024 6.201 
282.9954610 41.6749528 14.112 203.117 22.913 
0.046 
3.500 
0.721 
24.568 0.458 9.031 
283.0023335 41.6769730 14.141 113.799 21.039 
0.021 
2.055 
0.034 
22.114 0.025 6.576 
282.9980917 41.6746183 14.266 173.831 18.003 
0.013 
2.083 
0.019 
19.090 0.017 3.552 6263597 
19.349 
282.9921937 41.6778002 14.583 259.217 20.707 
0.035 
2.763 
0.068 
22.067 0.047 6.530 
282.9921506 41.6777921 14.702 259.189 20.875 
0.042 
2.694 
0.080 
22.207 0.055 6.670 
282.9974078 41.6831811 16.646 358.948 23.466 
0.072 
1.841 
0.160 
24.455 0.107 8.913 
282.9966051 41.6739474 16.780 188.445 19.552 
0.015 
0.619 
0.020 
20.050 0.018 4.513 6263592 
19.659 
282.9933695 41.6821712 17.141 319.361 20.528 
0.018 
2.625 
0.033 
21.832 0.025 6.294 
283.0013226 41.6738763 19.711 148.768 20.743 
0.018 
1.238 
0.026 
21.490 0.021 5.952 
282.9901758 41.6794287 19.998 279.017 23.558 
0.072 
2.672 
0.330 
24.881 0.212 9.343 
282.9909203 41.6828850 23.615 311.271 17.305 
0.012 
0.572 
0.017 
17.784 0.015 2.247 6263577 
17.742 
282.9904070 41.6824301 23.669 306.081 21.840 
0.029 
2.158 
0.056 
22.956 0.039 7.429 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>of Kepler targets. Included were the authors own lucky-imaging results picking off the best 10% of very short, diffraction limited exposures obtained with the 2.2 m telescope at Calar Alto Observatory, near-IR Adaptive Optics results of Adams et al. (2012), Adams et al. (2013), and Dressing et al. (2014) using the 6.5 m Multiple Mirror Telescope on Mt. Hopkins, speckle imaging (Howell et al. 2011) with the 3.5 m WIYN tele- scope on Kitt Peak and (</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>08 in 
well-calibrated optical bandpasses that can be robustly 
mapped to the Kepler bandpass. 
A recent paper by Lillo-Box, Barrado &amp; Bouy 
(2014) compared all primary published results for high-
resolution imaging </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 3 Companions with Likely Physical Association</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>KIC 
KOI offset 
PA δ-mag 
color 
χ 2 
odds ratio 
5358241 
829 0.107 239.9 
2.39 
1.034 1.123 
3703.9 
5358241 
829 3.311 335.4 
6.00 
2.659 0.032 
1.3 
6263593 3049 0.478 196.9 
0.54 
1.362 0.011 
1923.7 
10004738 1598 2.275 
65.9 
7.36 
2.933 0.038 
6.3 
11497958 1422 0.217 217.3 
1.56 
2.478 0.008 
4101.6 
11768142 2626 0.161 181.6 
1.44 
2.389 1.019 
928.1 
11768142 2626 0.201 212.7 
0.61 
2.299 0.107 
2832.9 
12256520 2264 0.949 103.8 
6.53 
2.838 0.038 
62.5 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><head>Table 4 Target in Which Host is Uncertain from High-Resolution Imaging</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>KIC 
KOI 3-σ error offset δKp Depth if host bound? 
5358241 
829 
0.57 
0.11 
2.39 
4235 
yes 
6263593 3049 
1.39 
0.48 
0.54 
1428 
yes 
6263593 3049 
1.39 
0.76 
5.82 
115460 
no 
6263593 3049 
1.39 
1.21 
7.48 
530684 
no 
6263593 3049 
1.39 
1.22 
4.92 
50704 
no 
11497958 1422 
1.03 
0.22 
1.56 
4098 
yes 
11768142 2626 
2.07 
0.16 
1.44 
3899 
yes 
11768142 2626 
2.07 
0.20 
0.61 
2253 
yes 
12256520 2264 
2.31 
0.95 
6.53 
137027 
yes 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> http://www.stsci.edu/hst/observatory/focus</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dupree</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dupree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kulesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data Reduction and Error Analysis for the Physical Sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bevington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill Book Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3508</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">977</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">736</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Boyajian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Von Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Van Belle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">757</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">593</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Esquerdo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">889</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mullally</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cantrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M S</forename><surname>Cartier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Croll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Devore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">786</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Daemgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hormuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Brandner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">498</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">567</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chaboyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jevremovi´cjevremovi´c</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Doyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1602</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wide Field Camera 3 Instrument Handbook, Version 6.0 (Baltimore: STScI)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dressel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dressing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dressing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dupree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kulesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Duchêne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARA&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">269</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Feiden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chaboyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">740</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>WFC3 2011-03</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>STScI</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Instrument Science Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">864</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2360</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fabrycky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ragozzine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">330</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Horch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sherry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Horch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">767</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Jao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Subasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caldwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">120</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whitmire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ireland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dupuy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>#347.30</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baranec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">791</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lillo-Box</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Barrado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bouy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">566</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lissauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">784</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Isaacson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">738</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pickles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">863</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">784</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stetson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">191</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">727</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
