<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:19+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Post-Keplerian corrections to the orbital periods of a two-body system and their measurability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="201630-05-25">25 May 2016 30 January 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iorio</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">I Ministero dell&apos;Istruzione</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Università e della Ricerca (M.I.U.R.)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Viale Unità di Italia 68</addrLine>
									<settlement>Bari</settlement>
									<region>(BA) 70125</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Post-Keplerian corrections to the orbital periods of a two-body system and their measurability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">0000</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="000"/>
							<date type="published" when="201630-05-25">25 May 2016 30 January 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Printed 30 January 2018</note>
					<note>(MN L A T E X style file v2.2)</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>general-celestial mechanics-ephemerides-gravitation</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The orbital motion of a binary system is characterized by various characteristic temporal intervals which, by definition, are different from each other: the draconitic, anomalistic and sidereal periods T dra , T ano , T sid. They all coincide in the Keplerian case. Such a degeneracy is removed, in general, when a post-Keplerian acceleration is present. We analytically work out the corrections T (pK) to such otherwise Keplerian periods which are induced by general relativity (Schwarzschild and Lense-Thirring) and, at the Newtonian level, by the quadrupole J 2 of the primary. In many astronomical and astrophysical systems, like exoplanets, one of the most accurately determined quantities is just the time span T exp characterizing the or-bital revolution, which is often measured independently with different techniques like the transit photometry and the radial velocities. Thus, our results could be useful, in principle, to either constrain the physical properties of the central body and/or perform new tests of general relativity, especially when no other standard observables like, e.g., the orbital pre-cessions are accessible to observations. The difference ∆T of two independently measured periods would cancel out the common Keplerian term T K leaving just a post-Keplerian correction. Furthermore, by comparing the theoretically predicted post-Keplerian expressions T (pK) with the experimental accuracy σ T exp in measuring the orbital period(s) it is possible to identify those systems whose observations should be reprocessed with genuine post-Keplerian models if T (pK) &gt; σ T exp. It seems just the case for WASP-33 b since σ T exp = 0.04 s, while 3 s T (J 2) dra 9.5 s, T (GR) dra = 0.36 s.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>From a theoretical point of view, there are many types of temporal intervals characterizing different cyclic patterns in the orbital revolution of a binary system: the draconitic 1 period, which refers to two consecutive crossings of the ascending node; the anomalistic 2 period, which characterizes the return at the periapsis; the sidereal period, i.e. the time required to describe a full revolution with respect to the fixed stars.</p><p>In a Keplerian two-body scenario, i.e. by neglecting any departures from spherical symmetry of the massive primary and the smaller revolving body under consideration and remaining within ⋆ E-mail: lorenzo.iorio@libero.it <ref type="bibr">1</ref> This adjective was originally referred to the Moon's passage at its ascending node, when an eclipse occurs. Indeed, the ancient Greeks thought that, during an eclipse, our natural satellite was swallowed up by a dragon ('δρ´ακωνδρ´ δρ´ακων', meaning literally 'which stares') hiding near the nodes of the lunar orbit <ref type="bibr">(Capderou 2005</ref>). <ref type="bibr">2</ref> The three anomalies are all zero (modulo 2π) at the pericenter <ref type="bibr">(Capderou 2005</ref>).</p><p>the Newtonian framework, all these three orbital periods coincide. It does not happen if the oblateness of the host star and, e.g., general relativity are taken into account along with their non-central additional accelerations with respect to the Newtonian monopole.</p><p>In several exoplanetary systems, one of the directly measured quantities determined with the highest accuracy is the time span T exp characterizing the orbital revolution, generally dubbed as 'orbital period' (see Section 2) . It is so because in most of them the planets orbit very closely to their parent stars; a huge number of full revolutions can be observed, with different techniques, over intervals even a few years long. Thus, given the extraordinary accuracy with which the characteristic orbital time intervals are nowadays measured for the majority of the fast revolving exoplanets, a proper modeling of their post-Keplerian modifications may represent a further, independent valuable tool to either characterize the physical properties of the host stars and/or perform new tests of the gravitational theory by Einstein. In the following, we will focus on transiting exoplanets, whose orbital periods are nowadays known at a 10 −7 − 10 −8 d = 10 −2 − 10 −3 s accuracy level ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Harpsøe et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Sanchis-Ojeda et al. 2013</ref>). We will work in a first-order per-turbation scheme to deal with the the non-central post-Keplerian accelerations of either classical and relativistic origin.</p><p>In Sections 3 to 5, we will set up a general method to consistently calculate in Section 6 the post-Keplerian corrections to the draconitic, anomalistic and sidereal periods induced by any small perturbing acceleration with respect to the Newtonian monopole, irrespectively of its physical origin. The potential application of such results to some specific astronomical scenarios is explored in Section 7. Section 8 is devoted to the conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notations</head><p>Here, basic notations and definitions used in the text are presented <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Brumberg 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Montenbruck &amp; Gill 2000)</ref>.</p><p>G : Newtonian constant of gravitation c : speed of light in vacuum M : mass of the primary µ = GM : gravitational parameter of the primary S : angular momentum of the primaryˆS primaryˆ primaryˆS : unit vector of the spin axis of the primary R : equatorial radius of the primary J 2 : dimensionless quadrupole mass moment of the primary a : semimajor axis n K = µa −3 : Keplerian mean motion</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T K = 2πn −1 K :</formula><p>Keplerian orbital period e : eccentricity p = a(1 − e 2 ) : semilatus rectum I : inclination of the orbital plane Ω : longitude of the ascending node ω : argument of pericenter q = e cos ω : nonsingular orbital element q k = e sin ω : nonsingular orbital element k ˆ l = {cos Ω, sin Ω, 0} : unit vector directed along the line of the nodes toward the ascending nodênodê m = {− cos I sin Ω, cos I cos Ω, sin I} : unit vector directed transversely to the line of the nodes in the orbital planêplanê P = ˆ l cos ω + ˆ m sin ω : unit vector directed along the line of the apsides toward the pericenterˆQ pericenterˆ pericenterˆQ = − ˆ l sin ω + ˆ m cos ω : unit vector directed transversely to the line of the apsides in the orbital plane f : true anomaly u = ω + f : argument of latitude r = r ˆ P cos f + ˆ Q sin f : position vector of the test particle in terms of f r = r ˆ l cos u + ˆ m sin u : position vector of the test particle in terms of u r = p (1 + e cos f ) −1 : distance of the test particle from the primary in terms of f r = p (1 + q cos u + k sin u) −1 : distance of the test particle from the primary in terms of u</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">v = µp −1 − ˆ P sin f + ˆ Q (cos f + e)</formula><p>: velocity vector of the test particle in terms of f</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">v = µp −1 − ˆ l (sin u + k) + ˆ m (cos u + q)</formula><p>: velocity vector of the test particle in terms of u </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE ORBITAL PERIOD(S) MEASURED IN EXTRASOLAR SYSTEMS</head><p>In transiting exoplanets, the orbital period T exp which is actually measured is the time interval T tra between two consecutive passages at the positions in the orbit, called transit centers, which minimize the sky-projected distance r sky of the planet from the star (Winn 2010). By customarily assuming the plane of the sky as reference {x, y} plane, in general, it is</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">r sky = x 2 + y 2 = p 3 + cos (2ω + 2 f ) + 2 cos 2I sin 2 (ω + f ) 2 (1 + e cos f ) = = a 2 3 + cos 2u + 2 cos 2I sin 2 u + O (e) .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In obtaining equation (1), we did not make any a-priori assumption about the orientation of the orbital plane in space; cfr. with Eq.</p><p>(5) of Winn (2010) obtained by setting Ω = 180 • . From equation (1), it turns out that, to zero order in eccentricity, T tra is the time interval from u = u * to u = u * + 2π, where u * is the specific value corresponding to the transit; it yields a local minimum of r sky (Winn 2010), but its actual value is not of strict importance here. Thus, for circular orbits, it seems reasonable to infer</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">T tra = T dra ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>i.e. it should be possible to identify the orbital period actually measured for transiting exoplanets with their draconitic period because of the argument of latitude u entering equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(1)</ref>, which is reckoned just from the line of the nodes. In the general case of an elliptical orbit, also the anomalistic period may come into play in view of f in the denominator of equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(1)</ref>. The radial velocity v r is another observable widely adopted in the field of extrasolar planetary systems; it is used also for some transiting planets themselves. Since it is <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Batten 2001)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">v r ∝e cos ω + cos (ω + f ) ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>similar considerations as before should hold: while in the circular orbit approximation the orbital period measured from the radial velocity curve should be considered as a draconitic one, in the general case it may be identified with the anomalistic period T ano .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">THE DRACONITIC PERIOD IN A POST-KEPLERIAN ORBIT</head><p>The draconitic period T dra , defined for a perturbed trajectory as the time interval between two successive instants when the real po-sition of the test particle coincides with the ascending node position on the corresponding osculating orbit, can be calculated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Mioc &amp; Radu 1977</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">T dra = 2π 0 dt du du.<label>(4)</label></formula><p>In a general post-Keplerian scenario, from the definition of the argument of latitude u, it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">du dt = dω dt + d f dt .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>In it, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Egorov 1958;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brumberg 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bertotti, Farinella &amp; Vokrouhlick´yVokrouhlick´y 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Will 2014</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">d f dt = √ µp r 2 − dω dt − cos I dΩ dt ;<label>(6)</label></formula><p>full details can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Egorov (1958)</ref>. Thus, eq. 5 can be written</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">du dt = √ µp r 2 1 − r 2 cos I √ µp dΩ dt ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>so that (Ochocimskij, <ref type="bibr">Eneev &amp; Taratynova 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mioc &amp; Radu 1977</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">dt du = r 2 α √ µp ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>in which the definition</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">α 1 1 − r 2 cos I √ µp dΩ dt (9)</formula><p>is adopted. To the first order in the disturbing acceleration entering dΩ/dt through <ref type="bibr">(Ochocimskij, Eneev &amp; Taratynova 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mioc &amp; Radu 1977</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">dΩ du = r 3 α sin uA N µp sin I ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">(8)</ref> can be expanded as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">dt du ≃ r 2 √ µp + r 4 cos I µp dΩ dt .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>When a disturbing acceleration A is present, it affects dt/du in a twofold way. A direct change with respect to the Keplerian case arises from the node rate, while further contributions come also from the first term in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(11)</ref> when the instantaneous shifts of the orbital elements {ξ} entering it are properly taken into account; in the notation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Roth (1981)</ref>, they can be dubbed as 'indirect'. More specifically, from the expression of r (u), by posing</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">F (p, q, k) r 2 √ µp ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>it is</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">F = F| K + ∆F = F| K + p, q, k ξ ∂F ∂ξ K ∆ξ (u 0 , u) ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where the subscript 'K ′ refers to the unperturbed, Keplerian ellipse, and ξ = p, q, k. As a consequence of both the indirect and direct contributions, the draconitic time lapse can be analytically computed from equation (4), with equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(11)</ref> and equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(13)</ref>, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Mioc &amp; Radu 1977</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">T (pK) dra = T dra − T K = I dra 1 + I dra 2 + I dra 3 + I dra 4 ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">I dra 1 = 2π 0 ∂F ∂p K ∆p (u 0 , u) du = = 3 2 p µ 2π 0 ∆p (u 0 , u) (1 + q cos u + k sin u) 2 du,<label>(15)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">I dra 2 = 2π 0 ∂F ∂q K ∆q (u 0 , u) du = = −2 p 3 µ 2π 0 ∆q (u 0 , u) cos u (1 + q cos u + k sin u) 3 du,<label>(16)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">I dra 3 = 2π 0 ∂F ∂k K ∆k (u 0 , u) du = = −2 p 3 µ 2π 0 ∆k (u 0 , u) sin u (1 + q cos u + k sin u) 3 du,<label>(17)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">I dra 4 = 2π 0 r 4 cos I µp dΩ dt du.<label>(18)</label></formula><p>In equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(15)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(17)</ref>, the instantaneous shifts of p, q, k are to be calculated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Mioc &amp; Radu 1977)</ref> ∆p</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">(u 0 , u) = u u 0 dp du ′ du ′ ,<label>(19)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">∆q (u 0 , u) = u u 0 dq du ′ du ′ ,<label>(20)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">∆k (u 0 , u) = u u 0 dk du ′ du ′ ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>by using the analytical expressions <ref type="bibr">(Ochocimskij, Eneev &amp; Taratynova 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mioc &amp; Radu 1977</ref>) dp du</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">= 2r 3 αA T µ ,<label>(22)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">dq du = r 3 α k sin u cot IA N µp + + r 2 α r p (q + cos u) + cos u A T µ + + r 2 α sin uA R µ ,<label>(23)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">dk du = − r 3 α q sin u cot IA N µp + c 0000 RAS, MNRAS 000, 000-000 + r 2 α r p (k + sin u) + sin u A T µ − − r 2 α cos u A R µ .<label>(24)</label></formula><p>of the derivatives of p, q, k with respect to u to the first order in the disturbing acceleration, i.e. by setting α = 1. The time derivative of the node entering equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(18)</ref> has to be calculated, to the first order in the perturbation, from equation (10) and equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">(8)</ref>.</p><p>It is intended that the right-hand-sides of equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(15)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(18)</ref> are evaluated onto the unperturbed Keplerian ellipse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">THE ANOMALISTIC PERIOD IN A POST-KEPLERIAN ORBIT</head><p>The anomalistic period T ano , defined as the time interval between two successive instants when the real position of the test particle coincides with the pericenter position on the corresponding orbit, can be calculated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Zhongolovich 1960;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">T ano = 2π 0 dt d f d f.<label>(25)</label></formula><p>In presence of a disturbing acceleration A, one has (Taratynova</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">1959; Mioc &amp; Radu 1979) dt d f = r 2 β √ µp ,<label>(26)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">β 1 1 − r 2 √ µp dω dt + cos I dΩ dt .<label>(27)</label></formula><p>The anomalistic period T ano generally differs from T K by an additive post-Keplerian term T (pK) ano which can be analytically worked out as <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">T (pK) ano = T ano − T K = I ano 1 + I ano 2 + I ano 3 ,<label>(28)</label></formula><p>with <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Zhongolovich 1960;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">I ano 1 = 3 2 p µ 2π 0 ∆p ( f 0 , f ) (1 + e cos f ) 2 d f,<label>(29)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">I ano 2 = −2 p 3 µ 2π 0 ∆e ( f 0 , f ) cos f (1 + e cos f ) 3 d f,<label>(30)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">I ano 3 = 2π 0 r 4 µp dω dt + cos I dΩ dt d f.<label>(31)</label></formula><p>In equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(29)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(30)</ref>, the instantaneous shifts of p, e are to be calculated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">∆p ( f 0 , f ) = f f 0 dp d f ′ d f ′ ,<label>(32)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">∆e ( f 0 , f ) = f f 0 de d f ′ d f ′ ,<label>(33)</label></formula><p>by using the analytical expressions <ref type="bibr">(Taratynova 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>) dp</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">d f = 2r 3 βA T µ ,<label>(34)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">de d f = r 2 β µ sin f A R + 1 + r p cos f A T + e r p A T<label>(35)</label></formula><p>of the derivatives of p, e with respect to f to the first order in the disturbing acceleration, i.e. by setting β = 1. Moreover, it is intended that the right-hand-sides of equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(29)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(31)</ref> are evaluated onto the unperturbed Keplerian ellipse. In particular, the time derivatives entering equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(31)</ref> has to be calculated, to the first order in the perturbation, from <ref type="bibr">(Taratynova 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mioc &amp; Radu 1979</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">dΩ d f = r 3 β sin (ω + f ) A N µp sin I ,<label>(36)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">dω d f = r 2 β µ − cos f A R e + 1 + r p sin f A T e − − r p cot I sin (ω + f ) A N<label>(37)</label></formula><p>and equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(26)</ref> with β = 1. An equivalent computational approach ca be found in Roth <ref type="bibr">(1981)</ref>; the expression for dt <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref> a /dθ in Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(3)</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Roth (1981)</ref> is incorrect since an overall multiplicative factor sin θ is missing in the second term of the right-hand-side. In the notation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Roth (1981)</ref>, θ is the true anomaly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">THE SIDEREAL PERIOD IN A POST-KEPLERIAN ORBIT</head><p>The sidereal period can be defined as the time interval between two successive instants when the real position of the test particle lies on a given reference direction in the sky. By assuming that the latter is the one from which the longitudes are reckoned, i.e. the x axis in the coordinate systems which are usually tied to the plane of the sky, a plausible expression for the sidereal period can be calculated by means of the true longitude 3 l as</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">T sid = 2π 0 dt dl dl,<label>(38)</label></formula><p>in close analogy with Sections 3 to 4. From the definition of l, it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">dl dt = dΩ dt + dω dt + d f dt .<label>(39)</label></formula><p>By using equation (6), equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(39)</ref> can be written</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">dl dt = √ µp r 2 1 + r 2 (1 − cos I) √ µp dΩ dt .<label>(40)</label></formula><p>3 In principle, also the mean longitude λ might be used. Nonetheless, it may be less easily identified with actually measurable repeating temporal intervals. Furthermore, also the calculation would be more cumbersome because one should adopt the mean anomaly M as fast variable of integration, while most of the available analytical expressions for the instantaneous rates of the elements, etc. use the true anomaly f . c 0000 RAS, MNRAS 000, 000-000</p><p>Post-Keplerian orbital periods 5</p><p>Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">dt dl = r 2 γ √ µp ,<label>(41)</label></formula><p>in which we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">γ 1 1 + r 2 (1−cos I) √ µp dΩ dt .<label>(42)</label></formula><p>To the first order in the disturbing acceleration entering dΩ/dt, equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(41)</ref> can be expanded as</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">dt dl ≃ r 2 √ µp + r 4 (cos I − 1) µp dΩ dt .<label>(43)</label></formula><p>In calculating equation (38) through equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(43)</ref>, the second term of equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(43)</ref> with</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">dΩ dt = rα sin (l − Ω) A N √ µp sin I<label>(44)</label></formula><p>evaluated onto the unperturbed Keplerian ellipse, i.e. for γ = 1, yields the direct correction to the sidereal period. As seen in Sections 3 to 4, further, indirect contributions arise also from the first term in equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(11)</ref> when the instantaneous shifts of the orbital elements {ψ} entering it are properly taken into account. From r (l), by posing</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">W (p, Q, K) r 2 √ µp ,<label>(45)</label></formula><p>it is</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">W = W| K + ∆W = W| K + p, Q, K ψ ∂W ∂ψ K ∆ψ (l 0 , l) ,<label>(46)</label></formula><p>where ψ = p, Q, K. Thus, by accounting for both the indirect and the direct contributions, we have for the post-Keplerian correction to the sidereal period</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">T (pK) sid = T sid − T K = I sid 1 + I sid 2 + I sid 3 + I sid 4 ,<label>(47)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">I sid 1 = 2π 0 ∂W ∂p K ∆p (l 0 , l) dl = 3 2 p µ 2π 0 ∆p (l 0 , l) (1 + Q cos l + K sin l) 2 dl,<label>(48)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">I sid 2 = 2π 0 ∂W ∂Q K ∆Q (l 0 , l) dl = −2 p 3 µ 2π 0 ∆Q (l 0 , l) cos l (1 + Q cos l + K sin l) 3 dl,<label>(49)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">I sid 3 = 2π 0 ∂W ∂K K ∆K (l 0 , l) dl = −2 p 3 µ 2π 0 ∆K (l 0 , l) sin l (1 + Q cos l + K sin l) 3 dl,<label>(50)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">I sid 4 = 2π 0 r 4 (cos I − 1) µp dΩ dt dl.<label>(51)</label></formula><p>In equations (48)-(51), the instantaneous shifts of p, Q, K are to be calculated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">∆p (l 0 , l) = l l 0 dp dl ′ dl ′ ,<label>(52)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">∆Q (l 0 , l) = l l 0 dQ dl ′ dl ′ ,<label>(53)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">∆K (l 0 , l) = l l 0 dK dl ′ dl ′ ,<label>(54)</label></formula><p>by using the analytical expressions dp dl</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">= 2r 3 γA T µ ,<label>(55)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">dQ dl = − r 3 γ K sin (l − Ω) tan (I/2) A N µp + + r 2 γ r Q + (r + p) cos l A T µp + + r 2 γ sin l A R µ ,<label>(56)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">dK dl = r 3 γ Q sin (l − Ω) tan (I/2) A N µp + + r 2 γ r K + (r + p) sin l A T µp − − r 2 γ cos l A R µ .<label>(57)</label></formula><p>to the first order in the disturbing acceleration, i.e. by setting γ = 1. It is intended that equations (48)-(57) are evaluated onto the unperturbed Keplerian ellipse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">THE POST-KEPLERIAN CORRECTIONS TO THE ORBITAL PERIODS</head><p>In this Section, we look at the Newtonian and post-Newtonian noncentral accelerations resolving the degeneracy of the orbital periods with respect to the Keplerian case. In Section 6.1, the impact of the quadrupole mass moment of the primary is considered to the Newtonian level. The general relativistic post-Newtonian accelerations are treated in Section 6.2 (Schwarzschild) and Section 6.3 (LenseThirring).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">The Newtonian quadrupole correction to the orbital periods</head><p>The classical post-Keplerian acceleration felt by a test particle in the field of an oblate primary is <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Vrbik 2005</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">A (J 2 ) = 3J 2 µR 2 2r 4 5 ˆ S · ˆ r 2 − 1 ˆ r − 2 ˆ S · ˆ r ˆ S .<label>(58)</label></formula><p>Its radial, transverse and normal components are</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">A (J 2 ) R = 3J 2 µR 2 2r 4 3 ˆ S · ˆ r 2 − 1 ,<label>(59)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">A (J 2 ) T = − 3J 2 µR 2 r 4 ˆ S · ˆ r ˆ S · ˆ t ,<label>(60)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">A (J 2 ) N = − 3J 2 µR 2 r 4 ˆ S · ˆ r ˆ S · ˆ h .<label>(61)</label></formula><p>To zero order in eccentricity, the draconitic, sidereal and anomalistic corrections due to J 2 are</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">T (J 2 ) dra = 3πJ 2 R 2 2 √ µa T (J 2 ) dra I, Ω, ˆ S + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(62)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">T (J 2 ) ano = 3πJ 2 R 2 2 √ µa T (J 2 ) ano I, Ω, ˆ S + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(63)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">T (J 2 ) sid = 3πJ 2 R 2 2 √ µa T (J 2 ) sid I, Ω, ˆ S + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(64)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">T (J 2 ) dra = −4 + 6 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 + 6 ˆ S · ˆ m 2 + + 3 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 − ˆ S · ˆ m 2 cos 2u 0 + + 6 ˆ S · ˆ l ˆ S · ˆ m sin 2u 0 − − 2 ˆ S · ˆ h ˆ S · ˆ m cot I,<label>(65)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">T (J 2 ) ano = −2 + 3 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 + 3 ˆ S · ˆ m 2 + + 3 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 − ˆ S · ˆ m 2 cos 2u 0 + + 6 ˆ S · ˆ l ˆ S · ˆ m sin 2u 0 ,<label>(66)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_69">T (J 2 ) sid = −4 + 6 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 + 6 ˆ S · ˆ m 2 + + 3 ˆ S · ˆ l 2 − ˆ S · ˆ m 2 cos 2u 0 + + 6 ˆ S · ˆ l ˆ S · ˆ m sin 2u 0 + + 2 ˆ S · ˆ h ˆ S · ˆ m tan I 2 .<label>(67)</label></formula><p>Note that equations (62)-(64) fall off as 1/ √ a. Contrary to the relativistic corrections (see Sections 6.2 to 6.3), equations (65)-(67) do depend, in general, on the initial position of the test particle along its orbit through u 0 already to zero order in eccentricity. Such a unique feature may be exploited either to enhance or reduce the magnitude of the post-Keplerian component of the period(s) measured, at least to a certain extent, if J 2 is the target of the observational campaign or, vice versa, if it is viewed as a competing source of systematic uncertainty when other dynamical effects like GR are looked for.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">The 1pN corrections to the orbital periods for a non-rotating primary</head><p>To the first post-Newtonian order (1pN), the Schwarzschild-type gravitoelectric (GE) acceleration due to a static mass is <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Soffel 1989</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">A (GE) = µ c 2 r 2 4µ r − v 2 ˆ r + 4 (ˆ r · v) v .<label>(68)</label></formula><p>The resulting corrections to the orbital periods are</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">T (GE) dra = 12π √ µa c 2 + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(69)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">T (GE) ano = 3π √ µa c 2 1 − e 2 2 T (GE) ano ,<label>(70)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">T (GE) sid = 12π √ µa c 2 + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(71)</label></formula><p>with T (GE) ano = 6 + 7e 2 + 2e 4 + 2e 7 + 3e 2 cos f 0 + 5e 2 cos 2 f 0 . <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(72)</ref> They depend on the orbital size as √ a, and depend on the initial orbital position along the orbit to O (e n ) , n 1.</p><p>For other calculations of some of the periods treated here, performed with different computational techniques and approximation schemes, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Damour &amp; Deruelle (1985)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barker, Byrd &amp; O' Connell (1986)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Soffel, Ruder &amp; Schneider (1987)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Soffel (1989)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Brumberg (1991)</ref>; Gergely, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Perjés &amp; Vasúth (2000)</ref>; Mashhoon, Iorio &amp; Lichtenegger (2001).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">The 1pN gravitomagnetic corrections to the orbital periods</head><p>The 1pN Lense-Thirring (LT) acceleration experienced by a test particle orbiting a stationary source such as a slowly rotating body is <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Soffel 1989</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">A (LT) = 2GS c 2 r 3 3 ˆ S · ˆ r ˆ r × v + v × ˆ S .<label>(73)</label></formula><p>For any values of the orbital and physical parameters characterizing known astronomical and astrophysical systems, equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(73)</ref> can be considered as a small perturbation of the Newtonian monopole.</p><p>The gravitomagnetic contributions to the orbital periods considered, to zero order in eccentricity, turn out to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">T (LT) dra = 4πS c 2 M T (LT) dra I, Ω, ˆ S + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(74)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">T (LT) ano = 0,<label>(75)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_77">T (LT) sid = 4πS c 2 M T (LT) sid I, Ω, ˆ S + O (e n ) , n 1,<label>(76)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">T (LT) dra = 2 ˆ S · ˆ h + ˆ S · ˆ m cot I,<label>(77)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_79">T (LT) sid = 2 ˆ S · ˆ h − ˆ S · ˆ m tan I 2 . (78)</formula><p>It is worthwhile noticing that equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(74)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">(76)</ref> are independent of both G and a. Moreover, equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">(77)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">(78)</ref> do not depend on the initial position of the test particle along its orbit. For different calculations of other gravitomagnetic characteristic orbital time spans present in the literature, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Mashhoon, Iorio &amp; Lichtenegger (2001)</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hackmann &amp; Lämmerzahl (2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">HOW TO USE THE MODELED POST-KEPLERIAN CORRECTIONS TO THE ORBITAL PERIODS?</head><p>In a series of papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Zhongolovich 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Amelin 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kassimenko 1966)</ref>, it was demonstrated that it is possible to measure the draconitic period of an artifical Earth's satellite 4 as the ratio of the difference of the times of passages of the sub-satellite point through a chosen parallel for two following epochs to the number of satellite revolutions corresponding to this difference. The accuracy reached at that time seems to be of the order of 10 −4 s (Kassimenko 1966); it is highly plausible that it could be improved by many orders of magnitude with the most recent techniques currently available.</p><p>In several practical Solar System scenarios, the tracking of spacecraft reaches its highest level of accuracy usually at their closest approaches to their target bodies thanks to a variety of techniques such as Doppler ranging rate, laser ranging, etc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Iess &amp; Asmar 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Iess, Asmar &amp; Tortora 2009</ref>). Thus, it appears meaningful, at least in principle, to look also at the anomalistic period.</p><p>As far as exoplanetary systems are concerned, we can use our results to predict the expected magnitude of the post-Keplerian components T (pK) of the orbital periods and compare them to the currently available experimental accuracy in measuring T exp , to be identified with some of the orbital periods considered here. If T (pK) &gt; σ Texp , a truly post-Keplerian fit of the observations is, actually, required; otherwise, the values of the system's parameters estimated with a purely Keplerian model based on the 3rd Kepler's law should be considered as wrong since they would be biased by the non-negligible post-Keplerian effect(s). By looking at WASP-33 b <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Collier Cameron et al. 2010</ref>), Eq. 62 and <ref type="bibr">4</ref> It was the Soviet spacecraft 1960 − ε 3 for which simultaneous visual tracking data were used <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Zhongolovich 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Amelin 1966;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Kassimenko 1966</ref>).</p><p>Eq. 65, computed with the currently available 5 orbital and physical parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Collier Cameron et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Smith et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lehmann et al. 2015</ref>) along with the orbital precession-induced value of J 2 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Johnson et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Iorio 2016)</ref>, yields an expected draconitic correction due to the stellar quadrupole ranging from 3 s to 9.5 s, depending on u 0 assumed as a free parameter; it is almost two orders of magntitude larger than σ Texp = 4.5 × 10 −7 d = 0.04 s ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Smith et al. 2011</ref>). Moreover, from Eq. 69, it turns out that the Schwarzschild-like draconitic period amounts to 0.36 s, which is almost one order of magnitude larger than σ Texp . Thus, it can be concluded that the data record of WASP-33 b should be re-analyzed within a truly post-Keplerian scenario including both the stellar quadrupole at the Newtonian level and general relativity.</p><p>On the other hand, if, for a given system, it were possible to have two independently measured orbital periods identifiable with some of the ones examined here, their difference ∆T would cancel out the Keplerian period T K , leaving just a post-Keplerian correction due to the fact that the perturbing accelerations remove the degeneracy. Thus, a major source of systematic uncertainty would be removed allowing, in principle, for accurate and genuine constraints on the physical parameters responsible of the post-Keplerian effects. Astrometric measurements of what could be identified with the sidereal period might be feasible in the near future with the ongoing GAIA mission for relatively detached exoplanets, perhaps characterized by a &gt; 0.5 au. To this aim, it is interesting to remark how the general relativistic corrections are either independent of the size of the orbit or grow as √ a, while the quadrupolar ones fall as 1/ √ a.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We analytically worked out the post-Keplerian corrections to some orbital periods which are degenerate in the purely Keplerian twobody scenario. We considered the Newtonian acceleration due to the oblateness J 2 of the primary, and the post-Newtonian general relativistic Schwarzschild-like and Lense-Thirring terms. We adopted a systematic perturbative approach which can be straightforwardly extended to any other disturbing acceleration, independently of its physical origin; as an example, it may find application in the orbital evolution of mass-transferring eccentric binary systems. It turned out that the orbital periods considered differ from each other in presence of the aforementioned disturbing accelerations. We did not restrict to any particular orientation of the primary's spin axis in space, and no a-priori assumptions about the orientation of the orbital plane with respect to the plane of the sky or the primary's equator were made. The removal of such limitations, common to almost all the existing papers in the literature, is important because the spatial orientation of the spin axes of astronomical bodies of potential interest is often either imperfectly known or unknown at all. Also when the situation is more favorable, as in our Solar System, the direction of the planetary spin axes is known with a necessarily limited accuracy. Finally, it must be remarked that, when data analyses spanning several decades are involved, the fact that the spins of many non-isolated bodies undergo slow precessional motions must be taken into account as well.</p><p>In principle, the results obtained represent new tools to either constrain some key physical parameters of the primary and/or design new tests of general relativity in several astronomical and as-trophysical systems, especially when no other means are available. It was demonstrated in the literature that it is possible to measure the draconitic period of an Earth's artificial satellite. Moreover, for the vast majority of the exoplanets so far discovered, for which no orbital precessions are accessible to observation, the strategy proposed here is able, in principle, to yield constraints on the parent star's oblateness which, otherwise, would not be possible to infer. To this aim, our theoretical results can be used to identify those extrasolar systems for which post-Keplerian fits should be performed to extract unbiased orbital and physical parameters if the size of the predicted post-Keplerian corrections is larger than the experimental accuracy in measuring the planetary orbital periods. If it were possible to independently measure different periods for a given system, it would be possible to take their difference by canceling out the common Keplerian component, which represents a major source of systematic uncertainty, leaving just a post-Keplerian correction.</p><p>Our results could be applied also to binaries hosting astrophysical compact objects and to the stars orbiting the supermassive black hole in Sgr A * . The continuous monitoring of all of such systems over the years with future facilities of increased accuracy will provide more and better constraints.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ˆ r = ˆ l cos u + ˆ m sin u : radial unit vectorˆh vectorˆ vectorˆh = {sin I sin Ω, − sin I cos Ω, cos I} : unit vector of the orbital angular momentum per unit mass of the test particlêparticlê t = ˆ h × ˆ r = − ˆ l sin u + ˆ m cos u : transverse unit vector ̟ = Ω + ω : longitude of pericenter l = ̟ + f : true longitude Q = e cos ̟ : nonsingular orbital element Q K = e sin ̟ : nonsingular orbital element K r = p (1 + Q cos l + K sin l) −1 : distance of the test particle from the primary in terms of l M : mean anomaly λ = ̟ + M : mean longitude A : disturbing acceleration A R = A · ˆ r : radial component of A A T = A · ˆ t : transverse component of A A N = A · ˆ h : normal component of A T dra : draconitic period T ano : anomalistic period T sid : sidereal period</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> L. Iorio</note>

			<note place="foot">c 0000 RAS, MNRAS 000, 000-000 6 L. Iorio</note>

			<note place="foot" n="5"> In fact, they were derived in a Keplerian framework. c 0000 RAS, MNRAS 000, 000-000 8 L. Iorio</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>I am grateful to J. N. Winn and M. Efroimsky for their careful reading of the manuscript and their important comments and remarks which greatly improved it. I thank also K. Masuda for useful discussions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Amelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Trajectories of Artificial Celestial Bodies as Determined from Observations / Trajectoires des Corps Celestes Artificiels Déterminées D&apos;après les Observations</title>
		<editor>Kovalevsky J.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Byrd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>O&amp;apos; Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">623</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Batten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Murdin P</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bristol</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page">2992</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Institute of Physics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bertotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Farinella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vokrouhlick´yvokrouhlick´y</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics of the Solar System</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brumberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Satellites. Orbits and Missions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SpringerVerlag France</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Collier</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. Roy. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">407</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">507</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Damour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Deruelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Inst. Henri Poincaré Phys. Théor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Egorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sov. Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">´ A</forename><surname>Gergely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Perjés</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vasúth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Suppl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hackmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lämmerzahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44059</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B W</forename><surname>Harpsøe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Asmar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Modern Physics D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Asmar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tortora</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronautica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">666</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. Roy. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">455</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Collier Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bayliss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">810</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Trajectories of Artificial Celestial Bodies as Determined from Observations / Trajectoires des Corps Celestes Artificiels Déterminées D&apos;après les Observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kassimenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Kovalevsky J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="22" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sebastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Döllinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mkrtichian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">578</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mashhoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lichtenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Lett. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mioc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Radu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomische Nachrichten</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mioc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Radu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomische Nachrichten</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Satellite Orbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Montenbruck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fortschritte der Physik</title>
		<editor>Ochocimskij D. E., Eneev T. M., Taratynova G. P.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
			<publisher>Spinger-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celestial Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanchis-Ojeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kotson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">774</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M S</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Skillen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Collier Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Smalley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. Roy. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">416</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2096</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Soffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ruder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relativity in Astrometry, Celestial Mechanics and Geodesy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Soffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heidelberg Taratynova G. P</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1959" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Fortschritte der Physik</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vrbik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Celest. Mech. Dyn. Astr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44043</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Exoplanets, Seager S.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>University of Arizona Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="77" />
			<pubPlace>Tucson</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zhongolovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Byul. Inst. Teor. Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">521</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1960" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zhongolovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Trajectories of Artificial Celestial Bodies as Determined from Observations / Trajectoires des Corps Celestes Artificiels Déterminées D&apos;après les Observations</title>
		<editor>Kovalevsky J.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
