<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">QUANTIFYING THE OBSERVATIONAL EFFORT REQUIRED FOR THE RADIAL VELOCITY CHARACTERIZATION OF TESS PLANETS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-07-04">July 4, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><surname>Cloutier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">René</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">François</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guillaume</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">QUANTIFYING THE OBSERVATIONAL EFFORT REQUIRED FOR THE RADIAL VELOCITY CHARACTERIZATION OF TESS PLANETS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-07-04">July 4, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Draft version July 4, 2018</note>
					<note>Draft version Preprint typeset using L A T E X style emulateapj v. 12/16/11</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite will conduct a 2-year long wide-field survey searching for transiting planets around bright stars. Many TESS discoveries will be amenable to mass characterization via ground-based radial velocity measurements with any of a growing suite of existing and anticipated velocimeters in the optical and near-infrared. In this study we present an analytical formalism to compute the number of radial velocity measurements-and hence the total observing time-required to characterize RV planet masses with the inclusion of either a white or correlated noise activity model. We use our model to calculate the total observing time required to measure all TESS planet masses from the expected TESS planet yield while relying on our current understanding of the targeted stars, stellar activity, and populations of unseen planets which inform the expected radial velocity precision. We also present specialized calculations applicable to a variety of interesting TESS planet subsets including the characterization of 50 planets smaller than 4 Earth radii which is expected to take as little as 60 nights of observation. Although, the efficient RV characterization of such planets requires a-priori knowledge of the &apos;best&apos; targets which we argue can be identified prior to the conclusion of the TESS planet search based on our calculations. Our results highlight the comparable performance of optical and near-IR spectrographs for most planet populations except for Earths and temperate TESS planets which are more efficiently characterized in the near-IR. Lastly, we present an online tool to the community to compute the total observing times required to detect any transiting planet using a user-defined spectrograph (RVFC).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS; <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Ricker et al. 2015</ref>) launched in April 2018, is conducting a wide-field survey over at least a 2-year long period and is expected to discover approximately 1700 new transiting exoplanet candidates at a 2-minute cadence around nearby stars over nearly the entire sky ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">Sullivan et al. 2015</ref>, hereafter S15). Due to their proximity, many candidate TESS planetary systems, or TESS objects-ofinterest (TOIs), will be amenable to precision radial velocity (RV) observations using ground-based velocimeters to establish their planetary nature and to measure the masses of identified planets. The population of TESS planets to-be discovered are on average systematically closer than the 2342 validated Kepler planets 6 of which only 243 (∼ 10%) have been characterized with RVs.</p><p>The growing number of precision velocimeters-and their variety-is vast and includes both optical and near-infrared spectrographs (APF; <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Vogt et al. 2014</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Noguchi et al. 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">HIRES;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vogt et al. 1994, HPF;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mahadevan et al. 2012, IRD;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kotani et al. 2014, iLocater;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Crepp et al. 2016</ref><ref type="bibr">, iSHELL, Rayner et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Gibson et al. 2016</ref>, MAROON-X; <ref type="bibr">Seifahrt et al. 2016, MINERVA;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Swift et al. 2015</ref>, MINERVA-Red; <ref type="bibr">Sliski et al. 2017, NEID;</ref><ref type="bibr">Allen et al. 2018, NIRPS;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bouchy et al. 2017, NRES;</ref><ref type="bibr">Siverd et al. 2016, PARAS;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chakraborty et al. 2008, PARVI, PEPSI;</ref><ref type="bibr">Strassmeier et al. 2015, PFS;</ref><ref type="bibr">Crane et al. 2010, SALT HRS;</ref><ref type="bibr">Crause et al. 2014, SO- PHIE;</ref><ref type="bibr">Perruchot et al. 2011, SPIRou;</ref><ref type="bibr">Artigau et al. 2014, TOU;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ge et al. 2016, Veloce, WISDOM;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">F˙ zrész et al. 2016)</ref>. Given the large number of velocimeters that can be used for RV characterization of TESS planet masses it is useful to understand the observational effort required to do so. That is, how many radial velocity measurements-and total observing time-are required to detect the masses of the TESS planets at a given significance. Furthermore, it is critical to access which spectrographs are best-suited to the efficient mass characterization of each transiting planet found with TESS. To address these questions, here we present an analytical formalism to compute the number of RV measurements required to detect a transiting planet's mass and apply it to the expected TESS planet yield from S15. Combining these calculations with an exposure time calculator provides estimates of the total observing time required to measure all TESS planet masses and to complete a variety of interesting science cases that will be addressed by TESS.</p><p>This paper is structured as follows: Sect. 2 describes our model used to compute the total observing time for all TESS objects-of-interest, Sect. 3 compares our model to results from existing RV follow-up campaigns of known transiting planetary systems, Sect. 4 describes the application of our model to the expected TESS planet population, and Sect. 5 reports the results for all TESS planets and for various science cases. We conclude with a discussion and conclusions in Sect. 6. Lastly, in the Appendix A we describe our freely available web-tool that utilizes the model from Sect. 2 to calculate the total observing time required to detect any transiting planet with a user-defined spectrograph.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MODELLING THE TOTAL OBSERVING TIME</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REQUIRED TO MEASURE A TRANSITING PLANET'S MASS</head><p>Here we derive equations to calculate the number of RV measurements N RV , of an arbitrary star-in our case a TESS object-of-interest (TOI)-required to measure the mass of its transiting planet at a given detection significance; i.e. with a particular RV semi-amplitude measurement uncertainty σ K . Together with calculations of the exposure time, N RV can be used to compute the total observing time required to detect each TESS planet with RVs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Calculating σ K from the Fisher Information</head><p>Given an RV time-series of a TOI y(t) taken a times t, the amount of information present in the data with regards to the value of the planet's RV semi-amplitude K is contained in the Fisher information. The amount of information regarding K is the K measurement uncertainty σ K , that is calculated by evaluating the Fisher information given a model of the observed stellar RV variations due to the planet.</p><p>The Fisher information matrix B is defined as the Hessian matrix of the lnlikelihood of the data given a model where the model is parameterized by a set of n parameters θ = {θ 1 , . . . , θ n }. Explicitly,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">B ij = − ∂ 2 ln L ∂θ i ∂θ j<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where the indices i, j = 1, . . . , n and ln L = − 1 2 (y(t) − µ(t)) T C −1 (y(t) − µ(t)) + ln detC</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">+ N RV ln 2π]<label>(2)</label></formula><p>is the generalized lnlikelihood of y(t) given a model µ(t). The RV time-series and model are each 1D vectors containing N RV measurements. The matrix C is the N RV × N RV covariance matrix of the residual time-series y(t) − µ(t). Once constructed, the Fisher information matrix can be inverted to return a new covariance matrix; the covariance matrix of the n model parameters and whose diagonal elements are equal to the measurement variances in the model parameters.</p><p>The model of observed stellar RV variations due to a single orbiting planet is a keplerian solution. Its general form is written as µ(t, P, T 0 , K, e, ω) = K[ cos (ν(t, P, T 0 , e, ω) + ω)</p><p>+ e cos ω],</p><p>in terms of the star's orbital period P , time of inferior conjunction T 0 , RV semi-amplitude K, orbital eccentricity e, argument of periapsis ω, and true anomaly ν. If we assume that the planet's orbit is circular-as was done in S15-then our keplerian model reduces to µ(t, P, T 0 , K) = −K sin ν(t, P, T 0 )</p><p>where the true anomaly can be expressed as ν(t, P, T 0 ) = 2π(t − T 0 )/P .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Calculating σK with white RV noise</head><p>Using the keplerian model given in Eq. 4 we can derive a simple analytical expression for σ K in terms of N RV from the Fisher information under a few more simplifying assumptions. From the resulting expression one can fix σ K to a desired measurement value and calculate N RV required to measure K at that precision. As a initial assumption, where we will assume that the observed RV noise is Gaussian distributed, or white. This assumption is used in the majority of RV analyses in the literature and is especially applicable to planets with semi-amplitudes much greater than the measured pointto-point RV rms. Assuming white noise, the covariance matrix C in Eq. 2 is diagonal with RV measurement variances σ 2 RV (t) along the diagonal. The resulting lnlikelihood reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ln L = − 1 2 nRV i=1 y(t i ) − µ(t i ) σ RV (t i ) 2 ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>modulo a constant offset that is independent of the model parameters.</p><p>The second simplifying assumption is rather than considering the full measurement uncertainty time-series σ(t), we will assume that the RV measurement uncertainty is well-characterized over time by a scalar value σ RV ; a common assumption when deriving model parameter uncertainties from time-series observations (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Gaudi &amp; Winn 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Carter et al. 2008</ref>). Thirdly, in our keplerian model we will assume that the values of P and T 0 are known a-priori with absolute certainty from the planet's TESS transit light curve. Although this is not strictly true, P and T 0 are often measured at high precision-compared to K-when multiple transit events are detected. Thus we can treat P and T 0 as constants rather than as model parameters such that the set of model parameters in our keplerian RV solution reduces to a single value; θ = {K}. The Fisher information matrix then reduces to the scalar value</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">B = − ∂ 2 ln L ∂K 2 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">= 1 σ 2 RV NRV i=1</formula><p>sin 2 ν(t i , P, T 0 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">= N RV 2σ 2 RV ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where in the final step we have assumed that the N RV measurements are uniformly sampled over the planet's orbital phases such that the summation term in Eq. 7 averages to one half of N RV .</p><p>The inverse of the expression in Eq. 8 is the K measurement variance or</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">σ K = σ RV 2 N RV .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>This remarkably simple expression for σ K as a function of the RV measurement uncertainty and number of RV measurements can be rearranged to calculate the value of N RV that is required to detect K of any transiting planet, with a precision of σ K , when the RV noise can be accurately treated as white.</p><p>2.1.2. Calculating σK when relaxing the white RV noise approximation</p><p>In deriving Eq. 9 we must assume that the RV timeseries noise was Gaussian distributed. However, numerous analyses of transiting systems have shown that there exist cases in which this is a poor assumption. Instead the RV residuals-after the removal of planetary models-can be temporally correlated often owing to the presence of RV signals arising from stellar activity (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Haywood et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Grunblatt et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">López- Morales et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Cloutier et al. 2017b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Dittmann et al. 2017</ref>). In such cases, a correlated 'noise' 7 model must be fit simultaneously with the planetary models to account for all suspected RV signals and any potential correlations between model parameters. One popular choice of correlated noise activity model is a Gaussian process (GP) regression model with a quasi-periodic covariance kernel of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">k(t i , t j ) = a 2 exp − (t i − t j ) 2 2λ 2 − Γ 2 sin 2 π|t i − t j | P GP ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>and covariance matrix elements</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">C ij = k(t i , t j ) + δ ij σ 2 RV (t i ) + σ 2 jitter ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where t i is the i th observation epoch in t and δ ij is the Kronecker delta function. The covariance of the GP model function is parameterized by five hyperparameters: the amplitude of the correlations a, the exponential timescale λ, the coherence parameter Γ, the periodic timescale P GP , and an additive scalar jitter σ jitter . When attempting to measure the semi-amplitude of a known transiting planet, along with a quasi-periodic GP activity model, the full set of model parameters becomes θ = {K, a, λ, Γ, P GP , σ jitter }. Hence our new Fisher information matrix will be 6 × 6 and takes into account the dependence of the K measurement precision on the remaining hyperparameters.</p><p>The elements of the Fisher information matrix are computed identically as before from Eqs. 1 and 2 but now using a non-diagonal covariance matrix C (Eq. 11). The derivation of the elements of B are provided in Appendix B. The general effect of computing σ K from this new Fisher information matrix is to decrease its expected value given a time-series of fixed N RV compared to the value obtained when using Eq. 9. The resulting N RV is typically larger than in the white noise limit. However unlike computing σ K in the white noise limit, the value of σ K when including a GP correlated noise activity model is dependent on the values of the model parameters themselves and on the time-series due to the t i − t j terms in the covariance kernel (Eq. 10) and the appearance of y(t) and σ(t) in the lnlikelihood such that B → B(t, y, σ RV , θ).</p><p>Therefore estimating σ K from the Fisher information including correlated noise requires time-series as input and numerical values for all model parameters in θ.</p><p>We note that when including a GP correlated noise activity model, a simple analytical expression for σ K in terms of σ RV and N RV cannot be derived. In this case σ K must be derived as a function of N RV from time-series of varying N RV used to compute the full Fisher information using Eq. 1 before calculating the covariance matrix of the model parameters C = B −1 and ultimately σ K from its corresponding diagonal matrix element:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">σ K = C 11 .<label>(13)</label></formula><p>2.2. Calculating σ RV for TOIs in the photon-noise limit Calculating σ K from RV time-series with either white noise or correlated noise is dependent in-part on the RV measurement uncertainty. Here we estimate the photonnoise limited RV measurement precision σ RV following the formalism from <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Bouchy et al. (2001)</ref>. Their formalism is used to calculate σ RV given the RV information content contained within a stellar spectrum over a particular wavelength range of interest.</p><p>From <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Bouchy et al. (2001)</ref> the RV measurement precision σ RV is shown to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">σ RV = c Q · S/N ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where c is the speed of light, Q is known as the quality factor of the spectrum, and S/N is the signal-to-noise ratio achieved over the full spectral range considered. The S/N contains contributions from the total number of photoelectrons N e − obtained from the source and a contribution from readout noise that begins to dominate the noise budget for the faintest TESS stars. Our S/N prescription is</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">S/N = N e − N e − + N 2 ron .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Throughout this study we assume a fixed readout noise per pixel of 5 e − and a 4 pixel PSF sampling in each orthogonal direction on the detector. The corresponding readout noise is therefore N ron = 20 e 1 . The quality factor</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">Q = i W i i A i<label>(16)</label></formula><p>is calculated from the noise-free stellar spectrum A igiven in photoelectrons and evaluated at the wavelengths Note. -Values presented here were obtained from the SVO Filter Profile Service. Explicitly, values pertaining to any of the U BV RI bands were obtained from the Generic/Johnson filter set whereas the Y JHK bands were obtained from the CFHT/Wircam filter set.</p><p>λ i -and from the optimum weighting function given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">W i = λ 2 i A i ∂A i ∂λ i 2 .<label>(17)</label></formula><p>The quality factor represents the density of the RV information content in the spectrum A i . When computing σ RV from Eq. 14 we use model stellar spectra from the PHOENIX-ACES library <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Husser et al. 2013</ref>). The spectrum for each TOI is retrieved based on the star's effective temperature T eff and surface gravity (see S15) assuming solar metallicity. The native cgs units of flux density for each model spectrum are converted to photoelectrons using the photon energy over the wavelength range provided by the PHOENIX models (λ ∈ [0.05, 5.5] µm) and assuming a fixed nominal instrumental throughput of 5%. The spectrum is then segregated into the spectrograph's various spectral bands whose central wavelengths and spectral coverage are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. In each spectral band we mask wavelengths at which the telluric transmission is &lt; 98%, where the spectral telluric absorption model is calculated at an airmass of 1 from Maunakea at R = 100, 000. The aforementioned model is obtained from the TAPAS web-tool ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bertaux et al. 2014</ref>). The remaining spectrum in each band that is largely uncontaminated by telluric absorption is resampled assuming a fixed 3 pixel PSF sampling of each resolution element. This spectrum is then convolved with a Gaussian kernel whose full width at half maximum is FWHM = λ 0 /R where R is the spectral resolution of the spectrograph. After convolving each spectrum with a Gaussian instrumental profile the spectrum is convolved with the rotation kernel presented in Gray (2008) (c.f. Eq. 17.12) that emulates the effect of rotational broadening for stars with a non-zero projected rotation velocity v sin i s . When computing the rotation kernel we adopt a linear limbdarkening coefficient of = 0.6. For each star we compute v sin i s from the known stellar radius (see S15), the inclination of the stellar spin-axis to the line-of-sight i sdrawn from a narrow geometric distribution centered on 90 • -and the stellar rotation period P rot , that we sample following the methodology described in Sect. 2.4.</p><p>After the aforementioned convolutions the PHOENIX model's wavelength grid is resampled to a constant δλ = λ 0 /R whose value is specified at the center of a reference band. For the optical spectrograph that will be considered in this study we fix the reference band to be the V band (λ 0 = 0.55 µm) whereas the reference band is fixed to the J band (λ 0 = 1.25 µm) with the near-IR spectrograph considered. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Artigau et al. (2018)</ref> compared the value of σ RV derived from stellar spectra-as we do here-to the value derived from empirical spectra from HARPS, ESPaDOnS, and CRIRES. They find small discrepancies between these values at optical wavelengths but claim that the RV precision derived from model spectra can be over-estimated in the near-IR YJ bands by ∼ 2 and under-estimated in the HK bands by ∼ 0.5. In deriving our own RV measurement precisions from spectral models in the optical or near-IR, we apply the multiplicative correct factors derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Artigau et al. (2018)</ref>. We note that these corrections were derived based on observations of a single star (i.e. Barnard's star) whereas the correction factors for other star's with unique effective temperatures and metallicities may differ from those used here. Despite that, there exists a clear discrepancy between RV measurement precisions derived from model and empirical spectra. This is at least true in a subset of spectral bands. Precise disagreements between model and observationally-derived σ RV in various bands for all spectral types is beyond the scope of this paper but may affect the photon-noise limited RV precision by a factor O(2)-depending on the spectrograph-as it does for Barnard's star from the ∼ J to K band. Note that the corresponding effect on total observing times will be O(&lt; 2) due to the other contributors to the RV uncertainty in addition to the photon-noise limit (see Sect. 2.3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Additional sources of RV noise</head><p>Often when searching for transiting planets in radial velocity the residual rms following the removal of the maximum a-posteriori keplerian planet solution exceeds the characteristic RV measurement uncertainty. This implies the existence of additional sources of RV noise. The effect of these additional noise sources is detrimental to our ability to precisely measure planet masses if not properly modelled. Therefore this excess noise should be taken into account when attempting to estimate σ K using either Eq. 9 or 13. These additional sources of noise may be attributed to stellar activity arising from dark spots, plages, and/or faculae, whose corresponding RV signals are modulated by the stellar rotation period and its harmonics, modulo the amplitude of any differential rotation (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Forveille et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bonfils et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Delfosse et al. 2013</ref>). Another source of dispersion in observed RVs may be from additional planets not seen in-transit (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Christiansen et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cloutier et al. 2017b, Bonfils et al. in prep.)</ref>; an effect that is especially pertinent when searching for small planets whose RV semi-amplitudes are less than the characteristic RV uncertainty of the time-series (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Astudillo-Defru et al. 2017b</ref>).</p><p>In order to compute N RV for each TOI using our white noise model we will absorb the aforementioned additional noise sources into an effective RV uncertainty σ eff rather than the previously assumed measurement uncertainty derived in the photon-noise limit. The effec-tive RV uncertainty is written as the quadrature sum of the systematic RV noise floor of the spectrograph σ floor (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>), the photon-noise limited RV precision, and the RV jitter arising from additional sources of RV noise such as activity and unknown planets: σ eff = σ 2 floor + σ 2 RV + σ 2 act + σ 2 planets . Eq. 9 can then be rearranged for N RV in terms of the effective RV uncertainty:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">N RV = 2 σ eff σ K 2 .<label>(18)</label></formula><p>In empirical time-series with white RV residuals σ eff can be estimated from the rms of the residual dispersion following the removal of all modelled planets. Eq. 18 is not applicable to empirical time-series that require a GP correlated noise activity model. In Sect. 3 we will compare the results from real RV campaigns to our analytic estimates as a test of their validity. However unlike in actual RV time-series, the RV jitter rms resulting from activity and unknown planets is not known a-priori for any of the TOIs in the S15 synthetic catalog. We therefore need to employ generalized statistical arguments to estimate the expected RV jitter from activity and unknown planets for each TOI. These estimates are described in Sects. 2.4 and 2.5 and are based on the empirical distributions of RV jitter from each of these two physical effects.</p><p>2.4. Estimating RV noise due to stellar activity Here we will consider estimates of the expected RV jitter due to rotationally modulated stellar activity; σ act . The arguments presented here are intended to be representative of field stars in the solar neighbourhood. Firstly, for each TOI we draw a rotation period P rot as a function of the stellar mass from either the Pizzolato et al. For active stars (P rot 10 days), <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Oshagh et al. (2017)</ref> showed through simultaneous K2 photometry and HARPS spectroscopy that monotonic correlations exist between the measured RVs and numerous spectroscopic activity indicators (e.g. log R HK , FWHM, BIS). Meanwhile quiet stars (P rot 10 days) appear to lack such strong correlations with spectroscopic activity indicators yet do correlate strongly with F 8 , the photometric flicker or photometric RMS on timescales &lt; 8 hours ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bastien et al. 2013</ref>). The F 8 parameter has been shown to correlate with asteroseismic stellar surface gravity measurements ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bastien et al. 2013</ref>) that itself correlates with RV jitter ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Bastien et al. 2014</ref>). Thus for inactive FGK stars (P rot ≥ 10 days) we adopt the following temperature dependent relation from <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Cegla et al. (2014)</ref> for the expected RV dispersion due to stellar activity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">σ act = 1 ms −1 × 84.23F 8 − 3.35, T eff ≥ 6000 K, 18.04F 8 − 0.98, T eff &lt; 6000 K.<label>(19)</label></formula><p>Typical values of σ act used to derive Eq. 19 from <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Saar et al. (2003)</ref> range from ∼ 0.5 − 10 m s −1 but with a relatively small median value of 2 m s −1 . We sample F 8 values-measured in parts-per-thousand-from the empirical Kepler distribution that has been corrected for their intrinsic Kepler magnitude ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bastien et al. 2013</ref>).</p><p>After sampling F 8 and its uncertainty we use Eq. 19 to map to the distribution of σ act for the inactive FGK stars in the sample of planet-hosting TOIs.</p><p>For active FGK stars (P rot &lt; 10 days) we revert to the log R HK activity indicator ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Noyes et al. 1984</ref>) whose distribution among nearby field FGK stars has been wellcharacterized ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Henry et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Santos et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b109">Wright et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Hall et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Isaacson &amp; Fischer 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Lovis et al. 2011</ref>). To estimate σ act for active FGK stars we compute the corresponding log R HK from P rot and B − V using the formalism from <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Noyes et al. (1984)</ref>. The following formulation from <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Santos et al. (2000)</ref> is then used to map log R HK → σ act :</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">σ act = 1 ms −1 ×    9.2R 0.75 5</formula><p>for F dwarfs 7.9R 0.55</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">5 for G dwarfs 7.8R 0.13 5 for K dwarfs,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where R 5 = 10 5 R HK . The rms of the fits in Eq. 20 are 0.17, 0.18, and 0.19 dex for FGK stars respectively. In deriving Eq. 20 as a function of spectral type, <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Santos et al. (2000)</ref> computed spectral types for each star in their sample based on their CORALIE spectra. However we lack such spectra and instead define the boundaries between FGK stars based on T eff given the limited information available for the TOIs. The assumed ranges are T eff,F ∈ (6000, 7500] K, T eff,G ∈ (5200, 6000] K, and T eff,K ∈ (3800, 5200] K. By computing log R HK and its uncertainty from sampled values of P rot and B − V , we can map from log R HK to the distribution of σ act for the active FGK stars in the sample of planet-hosting TOIs.</p><p>Lastly, for M dwarfs there exists a clean relation between log R HK and P rot (Astudillo-Defru et al. 2017a). The correlation saturates at a maximum mean value of log R HK = −4.045 for rapid rotators with P rot &lt; 10 days and falls off with rotation period out to the slowest rotating observed M dwarfs with P rot 100 days. Explicitly, Astudillo-Defru et al. (2017a) find the best-fit step-wise powerlaw to the correlation: log R HK = −1.509 log P rot − 2.550, P rot &gt; 10 days −4.045, P rot ≤ 10 days. (21) The dispersion in the relation for slow rotators is characterized by the uncertainty in the slope and intercept of 0.007 and 0.020 respectively whereas the dispersion in log R HK for rapid rotators is 0.093. Sampled values of P rot for M dwarfs are used to map to log R HK using Eq. 21 from which σ act values are estimated using a relation similar to Eq. 20 but extrapolated to M dwarfs with T eff ≤ 3800 K. The adopted coefficient and powerlaw index for M dwarfs (2 m s −1 and 0.1 respectively) were derived from the set of 23 M dwarfs with 2 P rot 150 days (c.f. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> Cloutier et al. 2018) whose RV activity rms was characterized with HARPS (X. Delfosse private communication). Additional empirical data to further calibrate these models for M dwarfs are part of an on-going study with HARPS ( <ref type="bibr">Delfosse et al. in prep.)</ref> and with a subset of active M dwarfs from CARMENES recently reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">(Tal-Or et al. 2018</ref>).</p><p>We note that the empirical distributions of RV activity used in this study were derived from observations using optical spectrographs. However, RV activity signals are known to be chromatic as they largely depend on the temperature contrast between an active region and the stellar photosphere where the contrast effect is known decrease from the optical to the near-IR (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Martín et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Huélamo et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Prato et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Reiners et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Mahmud et al. 2011</ref>). Meanwhile, Zeeman broadening of spectral features increases with wavelength ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Reiners et al. 2013</ref>). The dominant source for RV activity as a function of wavelength and spectral type is not yet fully understood ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Moutou et al. 2017</ref>) and so we choose to remain agnostic and set the near-IR RV activity equal to that which is derived in the optical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Estimating RV noise due to unseen planets</head><p>The occurrence rates of planets of various sizes around FGKM stars was well studied with the primary Kepler mission (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Fressin et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dressing &amp; Charbon- neau 2015)</ref>. For example, the cumulative occurrence rate of planets with radii r p ∈ [0.8, 22] R ⊕ around FGK stars out to 418 days is 0.87 planets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Fressin et al. 2013</ref>). For M dwarfs, small planets with r p ∈ [0.5, 4] R ⊕ with P ≤ 200 days appear to be more common with at least 2.5 such planets per M dwarf. In the TESS simulations of S15 up to one transiting planet is detected although the multiplicity of each simulated planetary system is reported. Here we use the number of additional planets around each TOI-along with the known occurrence rates of planets-to estimate the RV contribution due to these planets whose transits are not characterized with TESS.</p><p>For TOIs with a reported multiplicity N p &gt; 1, we sample the radius r p and orbital period P of the N p − 1 additional planets from the Kepler -derived occurrence rates from <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Fressin et al. (2013)</ref> for FGK dwarfs or from Dressing &amp; Charbonneau (2015) for M dwarfs. Because at most only one planet is detected in transit for each TOI and the transit probability ∝ P −2/3 , we draw the orbital periods of additional planets from values greater than the reported orbital period of the known TESS planet. In this way the TESS planet is always the innermost planet in the system and therefore most likely to transit. However, inner non-transiting planets have been detected in known transiting systems as a result of a potentially small mutual inclination (∆i ∼ 1 • ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Cloutier et al. 2017b</ref>).</p><p>When sampling the planet occurrence rates as a function of P and r p , f (P, r p ), a few caveats arise. Firstly, f (P, r p ) are reported over a coarse grid. Therefore when drawing a planet with a range of potential orbital periods and radii we sample the exact value of P and r p each from a uniform distribution bounded by the edges of that bin. Secondly, due to the poor detection sensitivity to the smallest planets at large orbital periods, f (P, r p ) is poorly constrained there. To quantify the values of f (P, r p ) in this regime we assume that f (P, r p ) evolves smoothly such that in bins where f (P, r p ) is poorly constrained, we can average the measured values in surrounding bins to populate the previously vacant bin. We restrict all pairs of planets in multi-planet systems to remain Lagrange stable according to the analytic condition from <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Barnes &amp; Greenberg (2006)</ref> while assuming circular orbits for all planets. Lastly, the sampled radii for all additional planets are converted to a planetary mass m p according to the empirically derived mean mass-radius relations from <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Weiss et al. (2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b104">) or Weiss &amp; Marcy (2014</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">m p M ⊕ =                  0.440 rp R⊕ 3 + 0.614 rp R⊕ 4 , r p &lt; 1.5 R ⊕ 2.69 rp R⊕ 0.93 , 1.5 ≤ r p /R ⊕ &lt; 4 0.56 rp R⊕ S 336.5S⊕ 0.03 1.89 , 4 ≤ r p /R ⊕ &lt; 13.7 U(150, 2000), r p ≥ 13.7 R ⊕ (22)</formula><p>where S is the irradiance received by the planet. By adopting the mean mass-radius relation this formalism neglects to reflect the diversity of exoplanet masses for a given planet radius.</p><p>The sinusoidal keplerian solution with unit amplitude has an rms value of √ 2/2 ∼ 0.707. Therefore for each additional planet i = 1, . . . , N p − 1, we can calculate σ planets,i = 0.707K i where K i is the planet's semiamplitude computed from its sampled P i , m p,i , and host stellar mass. The total value of σ planets is calculated by the quadrature addition of σ planets,i from each additional planet whose K i &gt; σ RV . This latest condition is imposed assuming that additional planets not seen intransit but whose semi-amplitudes are large compared to the RV measurement precision will be accurately modelled in the RV analysis and therefore not contribute to the residual RV rms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Exposure time calculator</head><p>Together with estimates of N RV , the exposure time t exp per TOI can be used to calculate the total observing time required to detect a TESS planet in radial velocity. For a given star, the exposure time required to achieve a desired S/N per resolution element will depend on the properties of the spectrograph and telescope used as well as on the star's magnitude in the spectral bands spanned by the spectrograph. For each TOI in this study we calculate the exposure time that is required to reach a S/N of at least 100 at the center of a reference band; V (λ = 0.55 µm) or J (λ = 1.25 µm) for optical and near-IR spectrographs respectively. The zero point flux densities in each spectral band used to calculate the S/N = √ N e − per resolution element are reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. The benefit of integrating longer is only to achieve a photon-noise limited RV precision less than a few σ act , is one of diminishing returns because the effective RV precision becomes dominated by activity and cannot be reduced by increasing t exp . Although, it is important to note that increasing t exp permits a better sampling for the spectral CCF thus improving one's ability to accurately characterize the activity and mitigate its effects. In cases for which the calculated t exp results in σ RV &gt; σ act or &gt; the expected K, we claim that the exposure time is under-estimated. To remedy this we scale-up t exp to achieve σ RV σ act and the expected K. In our exposure time calculator we do impose restrictions on the range of t exp that can be considered. Specifically, we restrict t exp ∈ [10, 60] minutes. The shortest permissible exposure time is required to help mitigate the effects of stellar pulsations and surface granulation which evolve on timescales 10 minutes ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Lovis et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Dumusque et al. 2011</ref>). The upper limit of 60 minutes is applied in order to limit the total observing time dedicated to a single star. In practice, the majority of stars requiring &gt; 60 minutes to achieve the target S/N per resolution element and beat the RV activity rms, will result in a correspondingly low σ K and will therefore not be amenable to RV characterization within a reasonable timespan. We do note that this upper limit is chosen somewhat arbitrarily and some observers may wish to increase the maximum exposure time to accommodate certain high-value targets such as temperate Earth-like planets within or near their host star's habitable zone 8 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">MODEL COMPARISON TO OBSERVATIONS</head><p>In Sect. 2 we derived Eq. 18 for the number of RV observations required to measure K of a transiting planet with a precision of σ K in an RV time-series with white noise and an effective RV uncertainty σ eff . Similar calculations can be made of σ K (N RV ) in the presence of correlated noise using the formalism discussed in Sect. 2.1.2 and Eq. 13. Here we compare our analytic estimates of N RV -under the applicable noise condition-to observational results from existing RV time-series to ensure that our model provides an accurate approximation to N RV when applied to the TOIs. We consider two sets of RV time-series of transiting planetary systems featuring either a white or correlated noise model. The latter models being restricted to a quasi-periodic GP treatment of correlated RV residuals as was assumed in Sect. 2.1.2. All systems considered must also obey the assumptions imposed when deriving σ K . To recapitulate, those assumptions are:</p><p>1. the planet's orbital solution is well-approximated as circular.  To make the analytic estimates of N RV for each observed planetary system featuring a white noise model, we use the 1σ value of σ K for one planet in the system. By the nature of the Fisher information the value of σ K for each modelled planet in a multi-planet system should be equal so long as all ephemerides are well-constrained and planet semi-amplitudes are not correlated. Indeed, the measured planet semi-amplitudes should be uncorrelated when all planets' are weakly interacting with distinct orbital periods. For each RV time-series we set the value of σ eff to the rms of the RV residuals following the removal of all RV signals modelled by the authors. Some authors report their residual rms values explicitly whilst others treat the stellar activity signal as white by fitting an additive scalar jitter parameter that we add in quadrature to the median RV measurement uncertainty of the timeseries to estimate σ eff . The planetary systems with white noise models considered in this analysis are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.</p><p>To compare our formalism in the presence of correlated noise to observed systems we consider five cases analyzed with a quasi-periodic GP correlated noise activity model. Namely CoRoT-7 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Haywood et al. 2014</ref>), K2-18 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Cloutier et al. 2017b</ref>), <ref type="bibr">Kepler-21 (López-Morales et al. 2016</ref>), Kepler-78 ( <ref type="bibr">Grunblatt et al. 2015</ref>), and LHS 1140 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Dittmann et al. 2017</ref>). The calculated value of N RV for these systems is obtained by evaluating σ K from Eq. 13 using each systems' unique RV time-series t, y, and σ RV from their respective papers along with the semi-amplitude and GP hyperparameter values plus uncertainties. The maximum likelihood parameter values are reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. Because the model parameters are known to a finite precision we Monte-Carlo sample each model parameter from a Gaussian distribution whose mean is equal to its best-fit value and standard deviation equal to the parameter's measured 1σ uncertainty. Evaluating the Fisher information matrix with 10 3 model parameter draws results in a distribution of σ K for each planet from which the distribution of N RV can be calculated using Eq. 18 after σ eff is derived identically to as in the white noise scenario.</p><p>Analytic estimates of N RV are compared to observed values for known planetary systems in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>. As evidenced in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>, the majority of planetary systems have calculated N RV values in close agreement with observed values for both the white and correlated noise scenarios. This demonstrates that our analytical models for N RV are valid for the majority of cases with one notable exception. Quantitatively, the rms of the O-C N RV values is 2.6 for the white noise cases alone and 5.2 for all planetary systems included in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref> with the exception of the curious outlier LHS 1140. Our calculated value of N RV for LHS 1140 is overestimated relative to the size of the RV time-series presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Dittmann et al. (2017)</ref> from which K is measured to be 5.34 ± 1.1 m s −1 . After Monte-Carlo sampling K and the GP hyperparameters from their measurement uncertainties we calculate a median N RV = 265 ± 64 which is ∼ 1.8 times greater than the actual time-series size (N RV = 144) at 1.9σ. The exact cause of this anomalous discrepancy is not known but may be related to how the GP covariance function is implemented although this investigation is beyond the scope of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">OVERVIEW OF COMPUTING N RV FOR THE</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPECTED TESS PLANET POPULATION</head><p>S15 predicted the population of planets that will be discovered with TESS in its 2-minute cadence observing mode. Their results are provided for one realization of their simulations and contains 1984 TOIs, each with a single transiting planet. The properties of their stellar sample is copied in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 6</ref> for easy reference. This realization contains more detected planets than the average of their simulations; ∼ 1700. We treat each TOI in the S15 sample as a bona-fide exoplanet and not as a false positive. However, some number of TOIs will ultimately be identified as false positives as historically the false positive rate of transit surveys like Kepler have yielded higher false positive rates than initially anticipated <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">(Sliski &amp; Kipping 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Morton et al. 2016</ref>). The properties of the adopted planet population were derived from planet occurrence rates measured with Kepler circa 2015. Some planetary properties, particularly the planetary radii, have since been modified slightly following the reanalysis of Kepler-planet host star properties (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Fulton et al. 2017</ref>).</p><p>Here we compute analytical estimates of N RV required to measure a planet's RV semi-amplitude-at a given precision-for the entire synthetic catalog of TESS planets from S15. Together with the exposure time calculator described in Sect. 2.6 we calculate the total observing The region above the line depicts where the observed N RV -for a given K measurement precision-are less than the value predicted by the Fisher information and would be considered anomalous. The region below the line depicts where the observed N RV are larger than the value predicted by the Fisher information implying that the K measurement uncertainty may be under-estimated.</p><p>time required to detect each planet. These calculations require estimates of RV noise sources from the RV noise floor of the employed spectrograph, photon noise, activity, and additional unseen planets. Photon noise is dependent on the RV information content contained within the stellar spectrum and varies across spectral bands. Therefore we consider RV follow-up observations taken with either a fiducial optical spectrograph or a fiducial near-IR spectrograph. The specifications corresponding to our adopted optical spectrograph are modelled after the HARPS spectrograph on the 3.6m ESO telescope at La Silla observatory ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Mayor et al. 2003</ref>). The specifications corresponding to our adopted near-IR spectrograph are modelled after the up-coming NIRPS spectrograph that will join HARPS at the 3.6m ESO telescope at La Silla observatory in 2019 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Bouchy et al. 2017</ref>). The adopted specifications for our two fiducial spectrographs are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>. Using the formalism discussed in Sect. 2.2 we calculate σ RV for each TOI with both spectrographs. For reference, the distributions of TOI σ RV for both spectrographs are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.</p><p>In Sect. A we will present a web-based N RV (σ RV ) calculator that can be used to repeat these calculations but using any spectrograph defined by the user.</p><p>As discussed in Sects. 2.3, 2.4, and 2.5, estimates of N RV are also sensitive to additive RV noise sources such as stellar activity and unseen planets. However, these astrophysical noise sources are not known a-priori for the  <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>.-The distributions of the TOI photon-noise limited RV measurement precisions derived from PHOENIX stellar models and using the formalism discussed in Sect. 2.2. The values of σ RV are computed for each of our fiducial spectrographs in the optical and near-IR with spectral bands BV R and Y JH respectively (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 4</ref>). S15 TOIs and therefore must be sampled from known distributions of applicable values of σ act and σ planets . A Monte-Carlo sampling routine is used for each TOI to sample the aforementioned quantities from the distributions discussed in Sects. 2.4 and 2.5. The value of N RV for each TOI also depends on the desired K measurement uncertainty that is set by the nature of the followup science that one wishes to conduct once the planet's mass has been characterized with RVs. For example, conventionally the detection of a planet's K requires a 3σ detection significance; 3 = K/ σ K . Conversely, targets that will be amenable to atmospheric characterization via transmission spectroscopy will benefit from a more precise measurement of the planet's bulk density that in-turn requires a mass detection significance &gt; 3σ.</p><p>In the following Sect. 5 we present results of N RV for the full TESS sample in the limit of correlated RV noise (see Sect. 2.1.2). We also consider four subsamples of TESS planets each pertaining to a unique science case that will be addressed by TESS. Each science case merits a unique choice of σ K for a particular subset of TOIs. Total observing times are then calculated as N RV ·(t exp +t overhead ). Because the exact value of t overhead varies between observatories, we will set t overhead = 0 such that its effect can easily be added to the total observing times later-on for non-zero values. To estimate N RV in the presence of correlated RV noise we construct time-series of increasing N RV from 10 − 10 3 in steps of 90. For our time-series we adopt a simple uniform window function t spanning 100 days which is sufficient to sample the full orbit of ∼ 99% of TOIs. Such simplistic time sampling is admittedly unrealistic given the expected number and frequency of nights lost due to poor observing conditions (clouds, poor seeing, etc). To that end we tested more complex window functions which included longer baselines and gaps due to observing seasons. We found results roughly consistent with the uniform window functions although this need not be true for any window function with arbitrary complexity such as those which are often obtained in practice over many observing seasons. For each of the 12 time-series with a unique N RV we compute σ K before interpolating N RV (σ K ) to the desired value of σ K . The initial guesses of the GP hyperparameters {λ, Γ, P GP } are adopted from from <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Dittmann et al. (2017)</ref> (see Methods section Radialvelocity analysis with Gaussian process regression.) with the remaining GP hyperparameters set to a = √ 2σ act and σ jitter = σ planets . The RV time-series y(t) contains keplerian contribution from the TESS planet and other sampled planets if applicable, plus correlated noise from a sample of the GP prior distribution, and white noise featuring contributions from the RV noise floor of the spectrograph <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">(Table 4)</ref> and the photon-noise limited measurement precision: σ 2 floor + σ 2 RV . The RV measurement uncertainty time-series σ RV (t) contains the aforementioned value repeated N RV times.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">RESULTS FOR THE TESS SAMPLE</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Detecting all TESS planet masses at 3σ</head><p>Here we present the results of attempting to detect the masses of all TESS planets at 3σ using either the optical or near-IR spectrograph. As such, we do not make a cut in declination and restrict targets to half of the sky. Our fiducial spectrographs are intended to be representa-tive of suites of spectrographs-with comparable on-sky performance-thus providing full sky coverage. Realistically not all TESS planets will be characterized with RVs due to either their small RV semi-amplitude, certain intrinsic stellar host properties that deter RV observations (e.g. a low apparent magnitude, rapid projected stellar rotation, or high levels of stellar activity), or simply due to a lack of available observing time. Despite this fact we present the results for all TESS planets.</p><p>Detecting a planet's mass at 3σ requires a K detection significance that is slightly larger than three because the calculation of m p from K is also dependent on other observables such as the orbital period and stellar mass whose measurement uncertainties contribute to the m p measurement uncertainty. To calculate the value of σ K required to achieve m p /σ mp = 3 we first assume that the orbital period of the planet is known to a sufficiently high fractional precision relative to the other parameters of interest (i.e. σ P /P 1) such that its contribution to σ mp can be effectively ignored. Secondly, we assume throughout this study that all stellar masses are measured with a conservative precision of 10% as many field dwarfs in the solar neighbourhood have their masses measured with a precision of 10% from mass-luminosity relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Delfosse et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b99">Torres et al. 2010</ref>). However, this assumed fractional precision will not hold for all TOIs as a subset will have their masses characterized more precisely using other advanced techniques such as asteroseismology or spectroscopy coupled with precision parallaxes (e.g. Van <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Eylen et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Fulton &amp; Petigura 2018)</ref>. We note that the calculations presented here represent conservative values if TOI stellar masses can be determined to a precision higher than 10%. Nevertheless, under our current assumptions a 3.06σ detection of K (i.e. σ K = 0.327K) is required to detect m p at 3σ.</p><p>The median results-over Monte-Carlo realizationsof our calculations are reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">Table 7</ref> for each TOI. Specifically, we report the median photon noise-limited RV precision in both the optical and near-IR spectrographs, σ act , σ planets , N RV , and total observing times in each spectrograph; t obs,opt and t obs,nIR . The values of N RV -and the corresponding t obs -are derived from the general case which includes a GP treatment of correlated RV noise.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref> we compare t obs,opt and t obs,nIR as a function of TOI effective temperature to ascertain which flavor of spectrograph is favorable for efficient RV planet mass characterization. A clear trend is discernible with the ratio of the median optical to the near-IR total observing times decreasing towards earlier spectral types. Efficient characterization of planets around late TOIs with T eff 3800 K is significantly favoured by the use of near-IR spectrographs due to the reduced photon noise exhibited by those stars in the near-IR. Conversely for TOIs with T eff 5500 K, the optical spectrograph is preferred. For intermediate TOIs the two spectrographs offer nearly consistent performance.</p><p>Modulo the effects of rotation and stellar activity the observing time required to detect a transiting planet with RVs is dependent on the host star's brightness and spectral type which directly effect σ RV . Recall that our derived values of σ RV for each TOI are based on stellar spectral models rather than on empirical spectra such as the M dwarfs observed at high resolution (R &gt; 80, 000) with the CARMENES visible and near-IR channels ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Reiners et al. 2017</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Reiners et al. (2017)</ref> claim that the RV information content peaks in the RI bands between 700-900 nm for all M dwarfs. This empirical evidence somewhat contradicts theoretical calculations based on model spectra (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Figueira et al. 2016</ref>, this study), especially for late M dwarfs whose RV information content is theorized to peak in the HK bands from 1.4-2.4 µm. Convergence towards a more precise scaling of σ RV with wavelengthfor stars of various spectral types-will be achieved in the near future with the onset of multiple new spectrographs from the optical to the near-IR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1.">Detecting TESS planet masses versus TOI spectral type</head><p>The cumulative median observing time required to detect TESS planets as a function of TOI spectral type is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4 up to 10 3</ref> hours. The results are also given in terms of the cumulative number of observing nights assuming a notional value of 7 observing hours per night. We consider spectral type bins with the following adopted definitions: mid-late M dwarfs: 2500 ≤ T eff /K &lt; 3200, early-mid M dwarfs: 3200 ≤ T eff /K &lt; 3800, FGK dwarfs: 3800 ≤ T eff /K &lt; 7600, and BA dwarfs: 7600 ≤ T eff /K &lt; 12000. Spectral type bins are considered separately because of the clear trend exhibited in total observing times with either an optical or near-IR spectrograph with T eff as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>. For example, it is clear that all 39 TESS planets around BA stars can be detected with our optical spectrograph in ∼ 140 nights whereas only ∼ 12 of those planets can be detected with the near-IR spectrograph in a thousand hours (i.e. ∼ 143 nights). Planet detections around Sunlike stars (i.e. FGK) are obtained more efficiently with the optical spectrograph with ∼ 251/964 optical detections compared to ∼ 198/964 near-IR detections in a thousand hours. Efficient M dwarf planet detections favor the near-IR spectrograph wherein a thousand hours of observing time yields ∼ 165/927 early-mid M dwarf planets or nearly all ∼ 54 mid-late M dwarf planets. These numbers are reduced to ∼ 60/927 and ∼ 21/54 in a thousand hours with our optical spectrograph.</p><p>Further demonstrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref> is the first derivative of the total number of planet detections with cumulative observing time; dN/dt. This quantity describes the efficiency of detecting planets over time as large values of the derivative highlight when planet masses may be detected in a short amount of observing time. We will continue by referring to this quantity as the detection efficiency. The detection efficiency can be used to identify after how much total observing time further planet detections become too observationally expensive. That is that when the detection efficiency drops below a set threshold value, any additional planet detections will require too much observing time that may otherwise be spent on potentially more feasible targets. For reference in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref> we highlight the value of the inverse time derivativewhich is still a measure of detection efficiency-equal to 20 hours per detection. We suggest this value as a minimum derivative value. With this threshold value planets around BA stars should be observed for up to ∼ 29 nights with an optical spectrograph before the detection efficiency drops below this threshold value. Similarly, planets around mid-late M dwarf TOIs should be observed for ∼ 43 nights with a near-IR spectrograph . Observing Sun-like and early-mid M dwarf stars can mostly proceed efficiently beyond 10 3 hours when using either spectrograph however observing early-mid M dwarfs slowly approaches 20 hours per detection after ∼ 110 nights. Observing all TOIs with the optical spectrograph-or with a network of optical spectrographs of comparable performance-until we reach a detection efficiency of 20 hours per detection would require ∼ 800 nights of cumulative observing time. In that time, ∼ 620 planets could be detected around TOIs of any spectral type with V ≤ 15. Repeating this observing campaign with the near-IR spectrograph-or with a network of near-IR spectrographs of comparable performance-would require ∼ 1600 nights of cumulative observing time. In that time ∼ 1030 planets could be detected around TOIs of any spectral type with J ≤ 13.6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.">Detecting TESS planet masses versus planet type</head><p>The cumulative median observing times required to detect TESS planets as a function of planet type are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 5 up to 10 3</ref> hours. We consider four types of planet defined by their radii to be Earths (&lt; 1.25 R ⊕ ), super-Earths (1.25 − 2 R ⊕ ), Neptunes (2 − 4 R ⊕ ), and giants (&gt; 4 R ⊕ ).</p><p>Of the 1984 planets in the S15 TESS sample, 66 are classified as Earths with 26 around stars with V ≤ median(V ) = 13.5 and 36 around stars with J ≤ median(J) = 10.7. Most Earths will be detected intransit around M dwarfs (T eff ≤ 3800 K) due to their favorable transit depths. With a thousand hours of total observing time we expect ∼ 26/66 Earths to be detected with the near-IR spectrograph compared to ∼ 15 detections in the optical. We note that detections of the smallest planets can be expensive as the detection efficiency exceeds 20 hours per detection after ∼ 11 nights or after just ∼ 8 detections in the near-IR. The detection efficiency drops more rapidly in the optical to greater than 20 hours per detection after just ∼ 6 nights or ∼ 4 detections.</p><p>Super-Earths can be detected rather efficiently in the near-IR to beyond 10 3 hours and with an optical detection efficiency better than 20 hours per detection up to ∼ 100 nights. We expect to yield ∼ 100/509 superEarths with either the optical or near-IR spectrographs after 10 3 observing hours. Neptunes are the most efficiently detected class of planet and with similar detection efficiencies between the two spectrographs. ∼ 220/1258 Neptune detections are expected in a thousand hours in the optical compared to ∼ 180/1258 in the near-IR. For Neptunes the detection efficiency remains &lt; 20 hours per detection for up to after ∼ 510 nights or ∼ 370 detections in the optical and after ∼ 960 nights or ∼ 660 detections in the near-IR. Lastly, ∼ 130/151 giant planets are detected in the optical in ∼ 80 nights at which point the optical detection efficiency begins to exceed 20 hours per detection. Similarly in the near-IR, ∼ 110/151 giants planets are detected in ∼ 85 nights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Science Case 1: mass characterization of 50 TESS</head><p>planets with r p &lt; 4 R ⊕ The TESS level one science requirement is to measure the masses of 50 small transiting planets with r p &lt; 4 Earth radii. 9 To date, the vast majority of masses for planets with r p &lt; 4 R ⊕ have been obtained with HARPS, HARPS-N, and HIRES. The onset of many up-coming precision velocimeters will provide many more instruments capable of characterizing such planets. Similarly to Sect. 5.1, we define a planet mass measurement requirement for the completion of the TESS level one science requirement of 5σ. Given our previous assumptions regarding the measurement precision on P and M s (see Sect. 5.1), a 5σ mass detection requires a 5.29σ K detection (i.e. σ K = 0.189K). According to our analytic model for N RV in the white noise limit, a 5σ mass detection requires (0.327/0.189) 2 = 2.99 more observing time than a 3σ mass detection.</p><p>The cumulative median observing time required to complete the TESS level one science requirement is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref>. Here we calculate the cumulative median observing times from various planet samples: i) the 50 small TESS planets sorted in ascending order by total observing times (i.e. the most efficient characterization of 50 small planet masses possible) and ii) for random subsets of the small TESS planets. The latter cases correspond to attempting to conduct RV follow-up observations of any subset of small TESS planet up to 50 such planets. In total there are 1833 TESS planets with r p &lt; 4 R ⊕ which causes the cumulative observing time to vary drastically depending on whether the input planet set is sorted or random. This is evidenced in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref> wherein it is  clear that selecting an optimized set-in terms of shortest median observing times-of 50 small TESS planets is by far the most efficient means of characterizing their masses. Optimized target selection results in the rapid completion of the TESS level one science requirement in only ∼ 60 nights with either spectrograph. The performance of the optical and near-IR spectrographs in completing the TESS level one science requirement are seen to be comparable when the 'best' TOIs are targeted with 31/50 being most efficiently characterized in the optical and with the remaining 19/50 being done in the near-IR. Selecting the 'best' 50 small planets naturally biases the sample towards larger planets with their larger K values, thus making their mass characterization faster with RVs. Despite this, the set of the 'best' small TESS planets with either spectrograph contains 9 super-Earths and 41 Neptunes with the average radius being 2.8 R ⊕ and the smallest planet being likely terrestrial at 1.37 R ⊕ (c.f. inset of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref>).</p><p>We note that identifying the 'best' small TESS planets cannot be done exactly until the conclusion of the full TESS planet search. By not focusing on the 'best' 50 small TESS planets and instead opting to obtain RV measurements of any small planet, the total observing time required to complete the TESS level one science requirement will be longer by more than an order of magnitude on average with either spectrograph. Although the exact time allotment will depend on the exact planet sample. However the 'best' curves for each spectrograph in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref> are nearly indistinguishable indicating that together optical and near-IR spectrographs will readily complete the TESS level one science requirement and possibly within weeks of relevant TOIs being announced due to the low number of required RV measurements, typically N RV = 32. Given the efficiency of measuring the 'best' small TESS planets at 5σ (∼ 5 hours per detection), the community may opt to focus on a larger subsample of Earth-like planets or to even increase the required mass detection significance to &gt; 5σ thus enhancing the TESS return of planets smaller than 4 R ⊕ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">A-priori estimate of the 'best' targets</head><p>Recall that identifying the optimum targets to achieve the TESS level one science requirement in the most efficient manner requires observers either to wait until the conclusion of the 2-year long TESS planet search or to select targets based on a-priori knowledge of the population of the 'best' small planets. The latter scenario is favorable as it allows targets to be observed with RVs almost concurrently with reported TESS detections thus leading to the shortest completion time of the TESS level one science requirement; i.e. ∼ 60 nights or ∼ 400 hours. Based on the predicted TESS planet population (S15) and the results of our study, we can predict the properties of the 'best' 50 small TESS planets and search for trends that will inform their selection throughout the actual TESS planet search. Here we suggest that identification of these planets can be done in an approximate way given some combination of intuitively crucial transit observables: the stellar magnitude, r p , and P . The stellar magnitude constrains the photon-noise limited RV measurement precision while the latter two quantities have a direct effect on K assuming that the mass-radius relation has a positive, non-zero slope everywhere for planets smaller than 4 R ⊕ . After considering numerous combinations of these parameters we find that the stellar magnitude and the value of the derived-from-transit quantity Ω ≡ r α p /P 1/3 -for some value of α-are good diagnostics for the total observing time required to detect a transiting planet's mass. The definition of Ω was selected to resemble the expected RV semi-amplitude K assuming a positive scaling between r p and m p (i.e. α &gt; 0) and noting that K ∝ P −1/3 . In this way, large values of Ω should correspond to large K values which directly effects the observing time required to achieve a given mass detection significance as larger signals are more easily detected with a given Rv measurement precision. We considered various values of α ∈ (0, 3] and found little discrepancy between these values with regards to where in the region of the corresponding magnitude-Ω parameter space the 'best' 50 small planets sit. Given uncertainties and possible discontinuities in the mass-radius relation for small planets we opt for α = 1.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7</ref> we compare the location of the 50 'best' small planets to the remaining 1833 small planets in the apparent magnitude-Ω parameter space. For considerations with our optical and near-IR spectrographs we use the V and J band magnitudes respectively. We note that in what follows we are marginalizing over stellar rotation and the level of stellar activity, both of which have a direct effect on our ability to detect planets in RV.</p><p>Unsurprisingly, the 50 'best' small TESS planets are localized around bright TOIs and exhibit an increasing value of Ω with stellar magnitude. That is, as the TOIs become dimmer, a larger Ω is required for a rapid RV mass detection. To encapsulate the region of the parameter space with the highest likelihood of yielding the most efficient RV planet detections (i.e. the shortest total observing times), we truncate the outer edge of the region at a 'maximum' apparent magnitude and derive a lower boundary by fitting a linear function to Ω as a function of magnitude for the 50 'best' small TESS planets before translating the lower boundary downwards to encapsulate 96% (i.e. 48 out of 50) of the 'best' small TESS planets. The resulting sets of the 'best' TOIs are {TOIs |V &lt; 10.7, Ω &gt; 0.09V + 0.28} <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(23)</ref> for follow-up with our fiducial optical spectrograph and {TOIs |J &lt; 11.7, Ω &gt; 0.14J − 0.35} <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(24)</ref> for follow-up with our fiducial near-IR spectrograph.</p><p>These sets approximately represent the TOIs with the shortest total observing times and should be seriously considered for rapid RV follow-up observations if they are known to not orbit a rapid rotator or an overly active star. Recall that stellar rotation and activity have been marginalized over in the derivation of Eqs. 23 and 24.</p><p>5.3. Science Case 2: informing the mass-radius relation of planets across the radius valley Accurate characterization of the empirical mass-radius relation for exoplanets (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Weiss et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Rogers 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b108">Wolfgang et al. 2016</ref>) is an important step towards understanding the diversity of exoplanet compositions as well as its use as a tool in predictive studies (e.g. S15; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Cloutier et al. 2017a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">, Cloutier et al. 2018</ref>). For example, consideration of small exoplanets (r p ≤ 4 R ⊕ ) with masses measured to better than 20% revealed that a large fraction of planets with r p 1.6 R ⊕ are rocky with bulk compositions consistent with that of the Earth and Venus ( ). The transition from bulk rocky compositions to less dense planets with a significant size fraction of volatile-rich envelope gas has also been shown to occur between ∼ 1.5−2.5 R ⊕ where a paucity of planets exists ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Fulton et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Van Eylen et al. 2017</ref>). The precise characterization of the mass-radius relation in the vicinity of this so-called radius valley will elucidate as to whether or not the valley persists in terms of planet bulk densities as the peaks in the bi-modal radius distribution are posited to harbour terrestrial and volatile-rich planets on opposing sides of the radius valley. Characterizing the mass-radius relation in this regime will greatly benefit from the inclusion of relevant TESS planets.</p><p>In order to accurately inform the mass-radius relation of planets across the radius valley with TESS planets, we seek a 20% fractional mass uncertainty (i.e. 5σ mass detection) following . We define TESS planets of interest as those spanning the radius valley using the period-dependent locus of planet radii-and its upper and lower bounds-as defined by the powerlaw in Van Eylen et al. (2017) from asteroseismology.</p><p>The cumulative median observing time required to detect relevant TESS planets at 5σ are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>. To avoid the bias that the most efficiently observed targets have towards larger planets and correspondingly larger K on average, the 'best' planets in this science case are selected equally from two bins on either side of the radius valley with r p ≤ 2 and &gt; 2 R ⊕ . There are 542 TESS planets that span the radius valley. RV mass characterization of all such planets will require 5 × 10 4 and 7000 observing nights in the optical and near-IR respectively. Evidently, the cumulative observing time for all TESS planet across the radius valley is likely too large to complete even with all available spectrographs. Fortu- <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>.-Top panel: the cumulative median observing time required to measure the 5σ RV masses of TESS planets spanning the radius valley (1.5 rp/R ⊕ 2.6) with either the optical spectrograph (dashed blue curves) or our near-IR spectrograph (solid red curves) . The set of thin curves are calculated from randomly ordered TOI samples whereas the thick curves are calculated from the sorted TOIs-with an equal number of planets less than and greater than 2 R oplus -thus resulting in the most observationally efficient planet detections. inset: focusing on the region up to 900 cumulative observing hours (i.e. ∼ 130 nights). Lower panel: the time derivative of the thick curves shown in the upper panel. The value of the detection efficiency equal to 20 hours per detection is highlighted by the horizontal dashed line.</p><p>nately, not all 542 planets are required to be measured in order to resolve the radius valley in planet bulk density. If instead we focus on the 'best' TESS planets then our detection efficiency with either spectrograph remains less than 20 hours per detection up to ∼ 80 − 130 nights. In that time we expect to detect ∼ 55 planets that span the radius valley with either spectrograph, if those planets are optimally chosen (c.f. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7)</ref>. This implies that optical and near-IR spectrographs are equally well-suited to characterizing the 'best' TESS planets across the radius valley with near-IR observations only becoming more efficient after ∼ 60 planet detections. With this sample of TESS planets, the hypothesized rocky/volatile-rich transition can be resolved and will help in progressing towards potentially resolving the radius/bulk density valley as a function of host spectral type.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Science Case 3: characterization of temperate</head><p>Earths &amp; super-Earths Temperate planets that orbit close to or within their host star's habitable zone are of particular interest for the search for life. Here we aim to scrutinize the masses of potentially habitable planets that we define herein as <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>.-Top panel: the cumulative median observing time required to measure the RV masses of potentially habitable TESS planets at 3σ with either the optical spectrograph (dashed blue curves) or our near-IR spectrograph (solid red curves) . Potentially habitable planets are defined as either Earths or super-Earths with rp ≤ 2R ⊕ and orbit within their host star's habitable zone as defined by ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kopparapu et al. 2013</ref>). The set of thin curves are calculated from randomly ordered TOI samples whereas the thick curves are calculated from the sorted TOIs thus resulting in the most observationally efficient planet detections. Lower panel: the time derivative of the thick curves shown in the upper panel. The value of the detection efficiency equal to 20 hours per detection is highlighted by the horizontal dashed line.</p><p>Earths and super-Earths (r p ≤ 2 R ⊕ ) orbiting within the habitable zone (HZ). To define the HZ we adopt the 'water-loss' and 'maximum-greenhouse' HZ limits from <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kopparapu et al. (2013)</ref>. There are just 17 such planets in the S15 synthetic catalog, three of which are smaller than 1.5 R ⊕ and are likely to be rocky. <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> depicts the cumulative median observing time required to detect the masses of potentially habitable TESS planets at 3σ. Due to TESS's limited observational baselines, the majority of HZ TESS planets-including the full set of 17 potentially habitable TESS planets-orbit M dwarfs and thus favor near-IR RV follow-up. The cumulative observing time required to measure all potentially habitable TESS planet masses at 3σ is ∼ 150 nights with the near-IR spectrograph. This is about fifteen times shorter than the total time required to complete the same task with the optical spectrograph. Regardless of the spectrograph used, RV follow-up of potentially habitable TESS planets will be an expensive task with just ∼ 2 planets detected in ∼ 2.5 nights after which the detection efficiency begins to require more than 20 hours per detection.</p><p>We caution that with such a small sample of potentially habitable TESS planets that the numbers presented here regarding the cumulative observing time required to detect such planets may be misleading. Due to the small number statistics the results for temperate Earths and super-Earths are highly sensitive to the true properties of those planetary systems. For example, a potentially habitable TESS planet may be detected around an M dwarf with J &lt; 10.15-the brightest TOI with a potentially habitable planet from S15-thus resulting in a shorter total observing time required to detect one such planet with RVs.</p><p>5.5. Science Case 4: characterization of favorable JWST follow-up targets The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) to-be launched in May 2020 will revolutionize our understanding of transiting exoplanet atmospheres (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Beichman et al. 2014</ref> for a summary of science cases). Many TOIs will represent some of the most interesting targets for atmospheric characterization with JWST through transmission spectroscopy observations in particular. To quantify the RV requirement needed to understand the bulk densities of these planets we will consider TOIs that are most amenable to efficient JWST observations. Specifically, TOIs with their expected S/N of transmission features ≥ 10.</p><p>For each TOI we calculate the expected S/N in transmission from the expected differential transmission depth ∆D of the planet and the photon-noise per spectral bin σ ppm ; S/N = ∆D/σ ppm . The value of σ ppm is measured in the J-band with spectral resolution R = 50 (i.e. δλ = 25 nm), an instrumental throughput of 50%, and an integration time equal to the planet's full transit duration. Values of ∆D for each TESS planet are computed up to five scale heights in a cloud-free atmosphere using the standard equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">∆D =15 ppm T p 250 K ρ 5.55 g/cm 3 −1 µ 29 u −1 R s 0.25 R −2 ,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where T p is the planet's isothermal atmospheric temperature (calculated assuming uniform heat redistribution over the planetary surface and zero albedo), ρ is the planet's bulk density, µ is the mean molecular weight of the atmosphere, and R s is the stellar radius. The atmospheric mean molecular weights of the TESS planets are not given in S15 so we adopt a very simplistic prescription of µ using a step-wise function of H/He-dominated atmospheres (µ = 2) to Earth-like atmospheres (µ = 29) for planets ≤ 2 R ⊕ . However, this simple prescription is known to be inaccurate but an approximation is necessary to facilitate the exercise of estimating ∆D for planets yet to be studied in transmission. According to Eq. 25 the interpretation of planetary transmission spectra heavily relies on a-priori knowledge of the planet's bulk density. The ρ measurement precision is derived from the measurement precision on both the planet's radius σ rp -from its TESS light curve-and on its mass measured from RVs. Due to the cubic dependence of ρ on r p compared to its linear dependence on m p , improving a planet's bulk density measurement precision is most effectively done by reducing σ rp either through more complete transit data or more precise characterization of the host stellar radius. Because of this, it is not worthwhile to sit on any TESS planet with RVs to achieve the typical mass detection significance required to precisely measure the planet's bulk density. For example, given the photometric precision for each TOI from S15 and a notional stellar radius uncertainty of 10% ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Carter et al. 2008</ref>), achieving a 3σ bulk density detection detection would require a ∼ 6.9σ mass detection on average. Such a precise RV mass measurement would require a ∼ 7.8σ K measurement or (0.327/0.129) 2 = 6.4 more observing time than a 3σ mass detection. We therefore opt for a more reasonable mass detection of 5σ, similarly to what was pursued when characterizing 50 TESS planets smaller than 4 R ⊕ and planets across the radius gap in Sects. 5.2 and 5.3. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 10</ref> depicts the cumulative median observing time required to detect the 5σ masses of TESS planets that are favorable for JWST follow-up with an expected transmission S/N ≥ 10. There are 1169 such TESS planets. By our simple prescription for ∆D for planets smaller than 2 R ⊕ and by imposing a minimum expected transmission S/N ≤ 10, the sample of 1169 favourable JWST targets has been restricted to planets larger than 2 R ⊕ -with a median value of r p = 2.9 R ⊕ -due to their systematically larger scale heights compared to Earths and super-Earths. Detecting all 1018 Neptunes and all 151 giant planets would require ∼ 10 8 nights with the near-IR spectrograph which is ∼ 40 times shorter than the total time required using the optical spectrograph. If follow-up observations are focused on the 'best' subset of favorable TESS planets for JWST follow-up, then the detection efficiency of these planets remains less than 20 hours per detection for up to ∼ 400 nights wherein ∼ 220 planets are measured with the near-IR spectrograph. Conversely, the detection efficiency in the optical drops to 20 hours per detection slightly sooner-after ∼ 360 nights but with a similar number of planet detections. Yet again spectrographs in the optical and near-IR demonstrate a comparable performance when characterizing the 'best' planets favorable for JWST follow-up with some slight improvement in the optical before its detection efficiency begins to drop off after ∼ 360 nights. It is clear that many interesting TESS planets will be readily characterized with RVs thus providing a large sample of TESS planets with precisely characterized masses and bulk densities prior to the launch of JWST.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented calculations of the observing time required to measure the masses of the expected TESS planet population using ground-based precision radial velocities. Our calculations are based on analytical estimates (see Sect. 2) of the number of RV measurements required to detect a transiting planet's RV semi-amplitude K at a given precision. When coupled to an exposure time calculator this yields the total observing time per target. Our main conclusions are summarized below.</p><p>1. The number of RV measurements required to detect a transiting planet's mass is dependent on the desired K measurement precision, the rms of the RVs observations (this includes contributions from photon-noise, stellar activity, additional unseen planets, and systematic effects), and whether or not the residual RV noise is correlated or not. Eq. 18 can be used to calculate the number of required RV measurements if the RV residuals are uncorrelated, otherwise the formalism presented in Sect. 2.1.2 must be used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Efficient characterization of transiting planet</head><p>masses for a given planet type (e.g. super-Earths) favors targets with small photon-noise limited RV measurement precisions. High precision measurements are most readily achieved with optical spectral coverage (i.e. BVR bands in this study) for Sun-like stars with T eff 5500 K whereas M dwarfs with T eff 3800 K are favored by near-IR spectrographs (i.e. YJH bands in this study).</p><p>3. Overall, the relative merits of obtaining precise RVs in the optical compared to in the near-IR are nearly equivalent. That is that RV campaigns aiming to characterize TESS planets can largely be done as effectively in either wavelength domain with the exception of the characterization of Earths (r p &lt; 1.25 R ⊕ ) and temperate TESS planets that are preferentially found around M dwarfs.</p><p>4. Not all TESS planets will be amenable to RV follow-up observations and selecting random TOIs for follow-up is an incredibly inefficient method of target selection. Instead, targets should be selected based on their apparent magnitude-to minimize the photon-noise limited RV precision-and the transit-derived quantity Ω = r p /P 1/3 . The subset of TOIs belonging to either optimal set defined by Eqs. 23 and 24 should be strongly considered for immediate RV follow-up.</p><p>5. The TESS level one science requirement of measuring the masses of 50 planets with r P &lt; 4 R ⊕ at the 20% level (i.e. 5σ mass detection) can be achieved in as little as ∼ 400 hours or ∼ 60 nights of observation.</p><p>6. ∼ 55 TESS planets spanning the radius gap for small planets (i.e. 1.5 r P /R ⊕ 2.6) can be detected efficiently at 5σ in ∼ 130 nights before the detection efficiency drops below 0.05 detections per hour (i.e. 20 hours per detection).</p><p>7. Only ∼ 2 temperate super-Earths can be detected efficiently at 3σ in ∼ 2.5 nights before the detection efficiency exceeds 20 hours per detection.</p><p>8. ∼ 220 Neptunes and giant planets amenable to transmission spectroscopy follow-up observations with JWST can be detected efficiently with a 5σ mass detection in ∼ 360 − 400 nights before the detection efficiency exceeds 20 hours per detection.</p><p>9. An online version of the Radial Velocity Follow-up Calculator used throughput this paper on the expected TESS planet population is available at http://maestria.astro.umontreal. ca/rvfc. This general-usage tool can be used to calculate the number of RV measurements and total observing time required to detect the RV semiamplitude of any transiting planet to a user-defined detection significance and with a user-defined spectrograph.</p><p>The results of this paper have been based on the synthetic planet population presented in S15. In their study they reported the expected TESS planet population (i.e. ∼ 1700 planets) recovered from the TESS 2 minute cadence observing mode of the brightest targets. Additionally, deeper full frame images at a 30 minute cadence will be released and result in even more planet candidates, some of which may still be amenable to RV follow-up observations. Another population of TOIs not considered in our calculations is the population of targets featuring only one or two transit-like events. If confirmed, the corresponding planets will be interesting in their own right as their orbits will have systematically longer periods making them cooler and of interest for future habitability studies. Lastly, the TESS mission has the possibly of being extended beyond its nominal 2-year long primary mission. If extended, the extension of the TESS observational baselines will improve the measured ephemerides of confirmed TESS planets, shed light on the nature of systems exhibiting single transit-like events, and expand the population of planets discovered with TESS (see the overview in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Bouma et al. 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Further caveats to the planet population from S15 used throughout this study were addressed by a variety of studies and corresponding updates to the expected TESS planet population (e.g. Ballard 2018; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Barclay et al. 2018</ref>). For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Barclay et al. (2018)</ref> updated the calculations of S15 by using the TESS Candidate Target List ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Stassun et al. 2017</ref>) and consequently updating the number of TESS discoveries including a decreased number of Earths and super-Earths which will have important implications for the corresponding science cases such as the bulk density characterization of TESS planets near the radius valley (r p ∼ 2 R ⊕ ). Furthermore, <ref type="bibr">Bal- lard (2018)</ref> predicted that the planet population around M1-M4 dwarfs was underestimated. The results imply a larger cumulative planet yield around M dwarfs including many systems with multiple transiting planets. This has important implications for RV follow-up campaigns of TOIs as M dwarf planets have the potential to be the most efficiently detected planets in radial velocity. In practice this will depend on the on-sky performance of many of the up-coming generation of near-IR velocimeters which have favorable RV measurement precision when observing M dwarfs. Many up-coming near-IR spectrographs are anticipated to operate with an RV noise floor of ∼ 1 m s −1 comparable to many high performance optical spectrographs but this may prove challenging as demonstrated by the CARMENES near-IR channel that seems to yield lower precision (∼ 2−3 m s −1 ) on early to mid-M dwarfs compared to the sub-1 m s −1 performance achieved in the optical ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Reiners et al. 2017</ref>, c.f. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig 6)</ref>. The focus on M dwarf planets with either class of spectrograph is well warranted as these planets represent some of the most interesting planets in terms of potential habitability and for the prospect transmission spectroscopy follow-up with JWST.</p><p>In Sect. 5.5 we presented the results for the most favorable TESS targets for transmission spectroscopy followup with JWST. In addition to identifying the 'best' such planets based on the time required to measure their masses (i.e. bulk densities) with RVs, one may also consider metrics describing the ease of detecting atmospheric features in either transmission or thermal emission as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Kempton et al. (2018)</ref>. Favorable TESS planets based on our calculations of the observing time required to detect their masses in RVs, that also overlap with favorable TESS planets based on the metrics from <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Kempton et al. (2018)</ref>, should be strongly considered for rapid RV follow-up. Similar target selection may be done based on the simulated transmission spectra from <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Louie et al. (2018)</ref> and the resulting S/N in transmission.</p><p>It is worth reiterating that although TOIs will be frequently reported following the launch and commissioning of TESS, RV follow-up teams should refrain from targeting just any TOI. Many detected planets will orbit stars either too dim or too active for efficient RV characterization. We emphasize that TOIs amenable to RV follow-up can be approximately identified-in real time-if they belong to one of the sets defined in Eqs. 23 or 24, or equivalently, if they lie in one of the shaded regions of either panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 7</ref>. However the sets of the 'best' TOIs are derived by marginalizing over the population of additional unseen planets in the system and the star's intrinsic RV activity. The former source of RV signals will not be illuminated unless RV follow-up of the system commences but the level of stellar activity can be estimated from the star's photometric variability in its TESS light curve. In addition to selecting targets based on Eqs. 23 and 24, stars with high amplitudes of photometric variability or jitter should not be considered for efficient RV follow-up campaigns.</p><p>RC thanks Raphaëlle Haywood and Jason Dittmann for useful discussions of the GP implementation, particularly for the LHS 1140 system. RC thanks the Canadian Institute for Theoretical Astrophysics for use of the Sunnyvale computing cluster throughout this work. RC is partially supported in this work by the National Science and Engineering Research Council of Canada.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RADIAL VELOCITY FOLLOW-UP CALCULATOR</head><p>Our models for the number of RV measurements N RV required to detect a transiting planet at a given significancein the presence of white or correlated RV noise-are generalizable to the majority transiting planets observed with any velocimeter. Recall that our models are only applicable to planets on nearly circular orbits, with known ephemerides, and whose orbital phase curves will be (approximately) uniformly sampled in the white noise case. Furthermore, because the results presented throughout this paper have been regarding a hypothetical planet population and with only two fiducial spectrographs, we present to the community an online web-tool version of the generalized Radial Velocity Follow-up Calculator 10 (RVFC) used throughout this study.</p><p>The RVFC is intended to serve the community by providing rapid calculations of N RV and total observing times for an arbitrary user-defined transiting planet with a user-defined spectrograph, given parameters of the planet from its transit light curve, stellar parameters, parameters of the employed spectrograph, RV noise parameters, and a small number of additional simulation parameters. The exact input parameters required by the calculator will depend on which of two possible primary modes-of-operation the user selects. In option 1, the calculator is used to calculate the photon-noise limited RV measurement precision σ RV using the formalism discussed in Sect. 2.2 and PHOENIX stellar models. Two suboptions are available for users to either add additional RV noise sources which are sampled from appropriate empirical distributions (option 1.1 ) or for the user to specify verbatim those additional noise sources (option 1.2 ). In option 2, the user can input a fixed value of σ RV thus negating the need for certain input parameters to be specified by the user and speeding up the wall time of the calculation. Option 2 also features the two suboptions available for option 1 and additionally has a third option in which the effective RV rms (i.e. the combination of all RV noise sources) is set verbatim if its value is known for the system of interest and only white noise calculations are desired (option 2.3 ). Option 2 may be viable for users whose employed spectrograph features an independent ETC, the results from which differ from those returned by the built-in RVFC ETC. The input parameters required to run the RVFC are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 5</ref>.</p><p>One notable bottleneck in the wall-time of running the RVFC is the time required to compute the photon-noise limited RV precision given a unique set of stellar and spectrograph parameters. To facilitate rapid calculations with the RVFC we opt to interpolate these values from pre-computed tables rather than perform the calculations explicitly. The tables from which σ RV values are interpolated from are computed individually for each of the spectral bands shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> and over five additional parameters: the spectral resolution, T eff , log g, Z, and v sin i s . Given values for these parameters in the RVFC, the corresponding σ RV is obtained by interpolating over this grid for each spectral band spanned by the spectrograph's wavelength domain. The remaining spectrograph parameters and stellar magnitude are then used to scale the interpolated value of σ RV to the correct S/N per resolution element. Notably, the interpolation of σ RV necessitates a trade-off between accuracy and computing time. However, the loss in accuracy we deem acceptable given the often inexact values of the other sources of RV noise (i.e. instrument stability, activity, and additional unseen planets).</p><p>Lastly, recall that the RVFC can be calculate N RV in either white or correlated RV noise limits according to our models discussed in Sects. 2.1.1 and 2.1.2 respectively. As noted in Sect. 2.1.2, the results in the latter scenario are dependent on the time-sampling which has been sampled uniformly in this study over a fixed baseline. This is also adopted in the initial version of the RVFC. As such, for users interested in calculating N RV in the presence of correlated RV noise we recommend using multiple calculations (e.g. N GP 10) to obtain the most-likely value and spread in N RV given a suite of sampled window functions. Users beware that increasing N GP will require a correspondingly longer computation time. In the future we would like to implement a way for users to upload custom window functions to avoid this ambiguity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FISHER INFORMATION WITH A QUASI-PERIODIC GAUSSIAN PROCESS REGRESSION MODEL</head><p>Here we derive the Fisher information matrix terms for a circular keplerian RV model plus a quasi-periodic GP correlated noise activity model, including an additional scalar jitter parameter. As discussed in Sect. 2.1.2 the keplerian model parameter is solely the RV semi-amplitude {K} whilst the GP covariance model has five hyperparameters Θ = {a, λ, Γ, P GP , σ jitter } that describe the quasi-periodic covariance matrix C commonly used when simultaneously fitting RV planets and stellar activity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">k ij = a 2 exp − (t i − t j ) 2 2λ 2 − Γ 2 sin 2 π|t i − t j | P GP ,<label>(B1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">C ij = k ij + δ ij σ 2 RV,i .<label>(B2)</label></formula><p>We therefore have six model parameters leading to a 6 × 6 Fisher information matrix B which is related the model parameter covariance matrix C = B −1 from which model parameter measurement uncertainties are calculated. Assuming a circular keplerian orbit for the transiting planet of interest, the residual RV vector is</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">r(t) = y(t) − (−K sin (φ(t))) (B3)</formula><p>where y are the raw RVs observed at times t and φ(t) is the planet's orbital phase centered on mid-transit. The generalized lnlikelihood from which the Fisher information matrix is calculated is then</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">ln L = − 1 2 r T C −1 r + ln detC + constant ,<label>(B4)</label></formula><p>Before populating the Fisher information matrix, we note two crucial mathematical identities</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">∂ ∂θ C −1 = −C −1 ∂C ∂θ C −1 ,<label>(B5)</label></formula><p>∂ ∂θ ln detC = tr C −1 ∂C ∂θ .</p><p>We can now proceed with calculating the general equation for each of the 21 unique Fisher information matrix entries in terms of partial derivatives of either the RV residual vector or covariance matrix C with respect to the model parameters instead of the partial derivative of the inverse covariance matrix.</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">B ij = − ∂ 2 ln L ∂θ i ∂θ j , (B7) ∂ ln L ∂θ i = ∂ ∂θ i − 1 2 r T C −1 r − 1 2 ln detC = − 1 2 ∂r ∂θ i T C −1 r − r T C −1 ∂C ∂θ i C −1 r + r T C −1 ∂r ∂θ i + tr C −1 ∂C ∂θ i , (B8) ∂ 2 ln L ∂θ i ∂θ j = − 1 2 ∂ 2 r ∂θ i ∂θ j T C −1 r − ∂r ∂θ i T C −1 ∂C ∂θ j C −1 r + ∂r ∂θ i T C −1 ∂r ∂θ j − ∂r ∂θ j T C −1 ∂C ∂θ i C −1 r − r T C −1 ∂C ∂θ j C −1 ∂C ∂θ i C −1 r + r T C −1 ∂ 2 C ∂θ i ∂θ j C −1 r − r T C −1 ∂C ∂θ i C −1 ∂C ∂θ j C −1 r + r T C −1 ∂C ∂θ i C −1 ∂r ∂θ j + ∂r ∂θ j T C −1 ∂r ∂θ i − r T C −1 ∂C ∂θ j C −1 ∂r ∂θ i + r T C −1 ∂ 2 r ∂θ i ∂θ j (B9)</formula><p>Each matrix entry is calculated using Eq. B9. In Eq. B9 there are two first order and two second order partial derivatives that must be computed with respect to each of the six model parameters: Θ = {K, a, λ, Γ, P GP , σ jitter }. </p><p>and can be computed analytically or symbolically using the open-source sympy package in python given the analytical expressions for the residual vector (Eq. B3) and the covariance matrix (Eq1. B1 &amp; B2).  Note. -The resulting number of RV measurements and total observing times reported here are computed in the general case of RVs in the presence of correlated noise (see Sect. 2.1.2). Only a portion of this table is shown here to demonstrate its form and content. A machine-readable version of the full table is available.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(2003) empirical distribution for FGK dwarfs (T eff &gt; 3800 K) or from the Newton et al. (2016) em- pirical distribution for M dwarfs (T eff ≤ 3800 K). The corresponding stellar equatorial velocity is calculated us- ing the stellar radius from S15. The projected stellar rotation velocity v sin i s is then calculated after drawing the inclination of the stellar spin-axis from a geometri- cal distribution. The value of v sin i s acts as a first-order estimate of the star's activity level (e.g. West et al. 2015; Moutou et al. 2017).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Note.</head><label></label><figDesc>-References: (1) Berta-Thompson et al. (2015), (2) Charbonneau et al. (2009), (3) Knutson et al. (2014), (4) Howard et al. (2011), (5) Bouchy et al. (2005), (6) Vanderburg et al. (2015), (7) Weiss et al. (2016), (8) Howard et al. (2013), (9) Dressing et al. (2015), (10) Burke et al. (2007) a HARPS-N measurements only.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1.-Observed values of N RV compared to the calculated values including either white or correlated RV noise for a suite of known transiting planetary systems. The colorbar indicates each planet's RV semi-amplitude. The dashed line depicts the line y = x wherein calculated N RV correspond exactly to the observed N RV . The region above the line depicts where the observed N RV -for a given K measurement precision-are less than the value predicted by the Fisher information and would be considered anomalous. The region below the line depicts where the observed N RV are larger than the value predicted by the Fisher information implying that the K measurement uncertainty may be under-estimated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.-Point estimates of the ratio of the median total observing times with an optical spectrograph to with a near-IR spectrograph as a function of TOI effective temperature. Colors are indicative of the ratio of the photon-noise limited RV precision in the optical to the near-IR. Near-IR RV observations are a more efficient means of planet mass characterization when this ratio is a few times unity. Conversely, optical RV observations are a more efficient means of planet mass characterization when this ratio is a few time smaller than unity. The shaded region spanning the ordinate ∈ [1/2, 2] approximately depicts where the use of either an optical or near-IR spectrograph offer nearly consistent performance.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4.-Upper panel: the cumulative median observing time to measure the 3σ RV masses of TESS planets as a function of host star spectral type and up to 10 3 hours. The (dashed blue curves) represent the results from the optical spectrograph whereas the (solid red curves) represent the near-IR spectrograph. Lower panel: the time derivative of the cumulative observing time curves used to indicate the RV planet detection efficiency. The horizontal dashed line highlights the value of the detection efficiency at 20 hours per detection. Note that unlike the lower panels, the upper panels do not share a common ordinate due to the differing number of planet detections around stars in each spectral type bin.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.-Upper panel: the cumulative median observing time to measure the 3σ RV masses of TESS planets as a function of planet type up to 10 3 hours. Planet type definitions are annotated above each column. The (dashed blue curves) represent the results from the optical spectrograph whereas the (solid red curves) represent the near-IR spectrograph. Lower panel: the time derivative of the cumulative observing time curves used to indicate the RV planet detection efficiency. The horizontal dashed line highlights the value of the detection efficiency at 20 hours per detection. Note that unlike the lower panels, the upper panels do not share a common ordinate due to the differing number of planet detections around stars in each spectral type bin.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6.-Top panel: the cumulative median observing time required to achieve the TESS level one science requirement of measuring the masses of 50 planets with rp &lt; 4 R ⊕ at 5σ with either the optical spectrograph (dashed blue curves) or our near-IR spectrograph (solid red curves) . The set of thin curves are calculated from randomly ordered TOI samples whereas the thick curves are calculated from the sorted TOIs thus resulting in the most observationally efficient planet detections. The latter curves for each spectrograph lie almost exactly on top of each other. Inset: a histogram showing the joint planet radii distribution of the 'best' 50 TESS planets for each spectrograph. Lower panel: the time derivative of the thick curves shown in the upper panel. The value of the detection efficiency equal to 20 hours per detection is highlighted by the horizontal dashed line.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.-The total observing time per TOI required to detect the planet's mass at 5σ with the optical spectrograph (upper panel) and the near-IR spectrograph (lower panel) as a function of the stellar apparent magnitude and the derived quantity from transit observables: Ω ≡ rp/P 1/3 . The relevant apparent magnitudes for the optical and near-IR spectrographs are V and J respectively. The 50 'best' TOIs with each spectrograph are designated by black diamonds . The shaded regions bounded by the black dashed lines approximate the regions of each parameter space with the highest likelihood of hosting planets amenable to the most efficient RV mass detections. TOIs within the shaded regions and known not to orbit an active host star should be strongly considered for rapid RV follow-up campaigns.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10.-Top panel: the cumulative median observing time required to measure the RV masses of TESS planets favorable for follow-up transmission spectroscopy observations with JWST (i.e. transmission S/N ≥ 10) at 5σ with either the optical spectrograph (dashed blue curves) or our near-IR spectrograph (solid red curves) . The set of thin curves are calculated from randomly ordered TOI samples whereas the thick curves are calculated from the sorted TOIs thus resulting in the most observationally efficient planet detections. inset: focusing on the region up to ∼ 2800 cumulative observing hours (i.e. ∼ 400 nights). Lower panel: the time derivative of the thick curves shown in the upper panel. The value of the detection efficiency equal to 20 hours per detection is highlighted by the horizontal dashed line.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>TABLE 1 Adopted Spectral Bands</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Spectral 
Central 
Effective 
Zero-point 
Band 
Wavelength Band Width 
Flux Density 
[µm] 
[µm] 
[erg/s/cm 2 /µm] 

U 
0.3531 
0.0657 
3.678 × 10 −5 
B 
0.4430 
0.0973 
6.293 × 10 −5 
V 
0.5537 
0.0890 
3.575 × 10 −5 
R 
0.6940 
0.2070 
1.882 × 10 −5 
I 
0.8781 
0.2316 
9.329 × 10 −6 
Y 
1.0259 
0.1084 
5.949 × 10 −6 
J 
1.2545 
0.1548 
2.985 × 10 −6 
H 
1.6310 
0.2886 
1.199 × 10 −6 
K 
2.1498 
0.3209 
4.442 × 10 −7 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>TABLE 2 Summary of RV Observations for Known Transiting Planets with White RV noise</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Planetary 
σ eff 
σ K 
Actual Calculated Ref. 
System 
[m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] 
N RV 
N RV 

GJ 1132 
3.38 
0.92 
25 
27.0 
1 
GJ 1214 
4.96 
1.60 
21 
19.2 
2 
HAT-P-4 
10.20 
3.00 
23 
23.1 
3 
HAT-P-8 
10.23 
4.20 
16 
11.9 
3 
HAT-P-10 
6.56 
2.70 
13 
11.8 
3 
HAT-P-12 
5.05 
1.60 
23 
19.9 
3 
HAT-P-18 
20.30 
5.20 
31 
30.5 
3 
HAT-P-22 
9.70 
3.20 
18 
18.4 
3 
HAT-P-24 
13.00 
3.60 
24 
26.1 
3 
HAT-P-26 
3.60 
0.98 
26 
27.0 
3 
HAT-P-29 
11.20 
4.60 
11 
11.9 
3 
HAT-P-33 
66.00 
17.50 
26 
28.4 
3 
HD 97658 
2.78 
0.39 
96 
101.6 
4 
HD 149026 
6.18 
1.40 
42 
39.0 
3 
HD 189733 
15.00 
6.00 
12 
12.5 
5 
HIP 116454 
2.01 
0.50 
33 
32.3 
6 
Kepler-10 
3.55 
0.34 
220 
218.0 
7 
Kepler-78 
2.60 
0.40 
79 
84.5 
8 
Kepler-93 a 
1.86 
0.27 
86 
94.9 
9 
TrES-2 
18.10 
5.70 
19 
20.2 
3 
TrES-4 
16.90 
10.00 
6 
5.7 
3 
WASP-1 
7.00 
3.20 
10 
9.6 
3 
WASP-3 
17.60 
5.90 
15 
17.8 
3 
WASP-4 
3.25 
2.30 
5 
4.0 
3 
WASP-16 
2.62 
1.60 
4 
5.36 
3 
WASP-18 
8.77 
6.20 
6 
4.0 
3 
WASP-19 
20.35 
5.00 
34 
33.1 
3 
WASP-24 
4.62 
3.20 
4 
4.2 
3 
WASP-34 
3.60 
1.70 
8 
9.0 
3 
XO-2N 
19.00 
8.00 
10 
11.3 
10 
XO-5 
11.20 
3.00 
24 
27.9 
3 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>TABLE 3 Summary of RV Observations for Known Transiting Planets with Red RV noise</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Planetary 
K 
a 
λ 
Γ 
P GP 
σ jitter 
σ eff 
σ K 
Actual 
Median 
Ref. 
System 
[m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [days] 
[days] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] 
N RV 
Calculated N RV 

CoRoT-7 
3.42 
7.0 
20.6 
1.0 
23.8 
3.44 
3.93 
0.66 
71 
61.4 ± 2.7 
1 
K2-18 
3.18 
2.8 
59.1 
1.2 
38.6 
0.25 
4.59 
0.75 
75 
80.3 ± 43.7 
2 
Kepler-21 
2.12 
6.7 
17.0 
2.4 
12.6 
1.98 
4.22 
0.66 
82 
106.7 ± 20.8 
3 
Kepler-78 
1.86 
5.6 
18.5 
2.5 
13.3 
1.10 
1.85 
0.25 
109 
119.4 ± 15.0 
4 
LHS 1140 
5.3 
9.0 
277.9 2.0 134.0 
3.0 
9.33 
1.1 
144 
265.5 ± 64.4 
5 

Note. -References: (1) Haywood et al. (2014), (2) Cloutier et al. (2017b), (3) López-Morales et al. (2016), (4) Grunblatt 
et al. (2015), (5) Dittmann et al. (2017) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>TABLE 4 Fiducial Spectrograph Specifications</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Optical Near-IR 

Spectral bands 
BV R 
Y JH 
Spectral resolution, R 
115,000 100,000 a 
Telescope aperture, D [m] 
3.6 
3.6 
RV noise floor, σ floor [m s −1 ] 
0.5 
1.0 
Throughput, 
0.05 
0.05 

a We consider the higher resolution achievable in the 

NIRPS High Accuracy Mode relative to its High Effi-

ciency Mode at R = 75, 000. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><head>TABLE 5 Descriptions of RVFC Input Parameters</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Parameter 
Units 
Required for 
Usage 
Notes 
RVFC Option(s) 

Spectrograph parameters 
Minimum spectrograph wavelength 
nm 
1 
Interpolating σ RV . 
Maximum spectrograph wavelength 
nm 
1 
Interpolating σ RV . 
Spectral resolution, R 
λ/∆λ 
1 
Interpolating &amp; calculating σ RV . 
Telescope aperture 
m 
1 
Calculating σ RV . 
Throughput 
[0-1] 
1 
Calculating σ RV . 
RV noise floor, σ floor 
m s −1 
1 
Contributes to RV rms. 
Planet parameters 
Orbital period, P 
days 
1,2 
Calculating the expected K and 
sampling unseen planets. 
Planetary radius, rp 
R ⊕ 
1,2 
Estimating mp from Eq. 22 and 
sampling unseen planets. 
Planetary mass, mp 
M ⊕ 
1,2 
Calculating the expected K. 
If unspecified, mp is estimated from 
rp and the mass-radius relation (Eq. 22). 
Stellar parameters 
Apparent magnitude, V or J 
-
1 
Calculating σ RV . 
The spectral coverage of the 
spectrograph must span either V or J. 
Stellar mass, Ms 
M 
1,2 
Calculating the expected K, 
log g for σ RV , 
sampling stellar activity, and 
sampling unseen planets. 
Stellar radius, Rs 
R 
1,2 
Calculating log g for σ RV . 
Effective temperature, T eff 
K 
1,2 
Interpolating σ RV , 
estimating stellar colors, 
sampling stellar activity, and 
sampling unseen planets. 
Metallicity, Z 
[Fe/H] 
1,2 
Interpolating σ RV . 
Projected rotation velocity, v sin is 
km s −1 
1 
Interpolating σ RV . 
Rotation period, Prot 
days 
1,2 
Calculating σ RV and 
If unspecified, Prot is estimated from 
sampling stellar activity 
Rs and v sin is assuming sin is = 1. 
RV noise sources 

Photon-noise limited RV precision, σ RV 
m s −1 
2 
Contributes to RV rms. 
RV activity rms, σact 
m s −1 
1,2 
Contributes to RV rms. 
Can be set to zero or is sampled 
if left unspecified. 
RV rms from unseen planets, σ planets 
m s −1 
1,2 
Contributes to RV rms. 
Can be set to zero or is sampled 
if left unspecified. 
Effective RV rms, σ eff 
m s −1 
2 
Calculating N RV . 
If unspecified, σ eff is computed 
from above contributing noise sources. 
Simulation parameters 
Exposure time, texp 
minutes 
1,2 
Calculating S/N and the 
total observing time. 
Overhead time 
minutes 
1,2 
Calculating σ RV . 
Desired K detection significance, K/σ K 
-
1,2 
Calculating N RV . 
Number of GP trials, N GP 
-
1,2 
Calculating N RV in the 
If zero, only do the white noise 
presence of red noise. 
calculation. If N GP &gt; 0 then we 
recommend setting N GP 10 for 
decent sampling. Value returned 
is the median of all trials if N GP ≥ 2. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="true"><head>TABLE 6 Stellar parameters from the S15 synthetic catalog</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>TOI 
α 
δ 
P 
mp 
K 
S 
Ms 
T eff 
Distance 
B 
V 
R 
Y 
J 
H 
med(v sin is) 
[deg] 
[deg] 
[days] [M ⊕ ] [m s −1 ] 
[S ⊕ ] 
[M ] 
[K] 
[pc] 
[km s −1 ] 

0000 0.44 
45.22 
9.135 
8.19 
2.03 
361.7 
1.40 6531 
100.0 
8.87 
8.47 
8.24 
7.80 
7.63 
7.46 
2.17 
0001 0.48 -66.20 14.200 
5.57 
3.11 
2.1 
0.33 3426 
60.3 
16.52 15.08 14.17 12.05 11.56 10.96 
0.23 
0002 0.65 
42.94 
4.957 
4.51 
1.66 
235.0 
1.05 5546 
97.7 
10.86 10.12 
9.72 
9.09 
8.81 
8.46 
3.24 
0003 0.92 -26.07 
2.160 
4.32 
1.95 
1240.0 
1.17 5984 
53.7 
8.61 
8.06 
7.76 
7.20 
6.98 
6.73 
5.81 
0004 1.31 -24.95 
9.753 
5.81 
2.95 
5.9 
0.46 3622 
66.1 
15.59 14.19 13.32 11.47 10.99 10.34 
0.57 
0005 1.38 
10.61 13.990 
5.89 
3.32 
2.1 
0.33 3425 
58.9 
16.48 15.04 14.13 12.01 11.52 10.92 
0.18 
0006 1.78 -71.93 
8.420 
8.15 
5.23 
4.5 
0.35 3444 
70.8 
16.73 15.29 14.38 12.28 11.79 11.19 
0.27 
0007 1.79 
-9.14 
5.618 
7.03 
9.15 
2.6 
0.15 3228 
23.4 
16.63 15.05 13.98 11.66 11.13 10.63 
0.09 
0008 1.95 -17.00 
1.344 
37.81 
16.03 
10160.0 1.63 6668 
100.0 
7.78 
7.51 
7.37 
6.83 
6.72 
6.63 
8.19 
0009 2.17 -15.53 17.140 11.57 
2.10 
341.2 
1.63 6668 
100.0 
7.78 
7.51 
7.37 
6.83 
6.72 
6.63 
7.54 

Note. -Only a portion of this table is shown here to demonstrate its form and content. A machine-readable version of the full table is available. </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>TABLE 7 Median</head><label>7</label><figDesc>radial velocity noise sources and follow-up calculations for 3σ planet mass detections of the S15 synthetic catalog</figDesc><table>TOI σ RV,opt σ RV,nIR 
σact 
σ planets σ eff,opt σ eff,nIR N RV,opt N RV,nIR t obs,opt t obs,nIR 
[m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] [m s −1 ] 
[nights] [nights] 

0000 
1.02 
3.14 
1.25 
0.00 
1.61 
3.59 
14.8 
67.6 
0.4 
1.6 
0001 
10.18 
8.21 
7.84 
2.00 
13.06 
11.62 
294.1 
159.1 
42.0 
3.8 
0002 
2.30 
3.74 
0.97 
0.00 
2.41 
3.96 
57.8 
155.7 
1.4 
3.7 
0003 
1.09 
2.77 
15.11 
0.00 
15.16 
15.41 
87.2 
125.7 
2.1 
3.0 
0004 
4.15 
6.06 
8.15 
0.77 
9.22 
10.33 
66.9 
115.2 
8.7 
2.7 
0005 
9.94 
8.04 
7.56 
1.18 
12.62 
11.17 
241.4 
111.2 
34.5 
2.6 
0006 
11.55 
9.33 
7.64 
1.21 
14.40 
12.60 
128.4 
69.8 
18.3 
1.7 
0007 
8.99 
6.69 
7.93 
3.37 
12.86 
11.30 
34.6 
32.0 
4.9 
0.8 
0008 
0.97 
4.43 
0.10 
0.00 
2.11 
5.47 
19.8 
20.0 
0.5 
0.5 
0009 
0.91 
4.11 
0.76 
0.00 
1.78 
4.85 
14.8 
108.5 
0.4 
2.6 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="7"> Note that we use the term correlated &apos;noise&apos; whereas-if arising from temporally correlated stellar activity-then this is a signal rather than noise but it is not the planetary signal that we interested in.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2">. The value of the TESS planet&apos;s P and T 0 are known to ultra-high precision compared to K such that correlations between the measured values of P , T 0 , and K are unimportant. 3. The window function of the RV time-series is (approximately) sampled uniformly over the planet&apos;s full orbital phase. 4. The white RV time-series have a characteristic scalar RV uncertainty equal to the rms of the RV residuals. 8 There are approximately nine temperate Earth-like planets that will be discovered with TESS with Teq ∈ [185, 300] K and rp ≤ 1.5 R ⊕ (S15).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="9"> https://tess.mit.edu/followup/</note>

			<note place="foot" n="10"> http://maestria.astro.umontreal.ca/rvfc</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rajagopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>246.08</idno>
		<title level="m">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">231</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">´</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Artigau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Malo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1803.07646</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">´</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Artigau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kouach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Donati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Astudillo-Defru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">600</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Astudillo-Defru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">602</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ballard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1801.04949</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Quintana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1804.05050</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">647</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bastien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">500</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">427</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bastien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beichman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta-Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">527</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bertaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lallement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ferron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Boonne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bodichon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">564</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">733</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">´</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Artigau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Messenger</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bouma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kosiarek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1705.08891</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">671</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Yee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eastman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">689</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">499</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cegla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bastien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">780</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7014</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70144</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">462</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">891</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Christiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vanderburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Claudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Benatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Carleo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99081</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cloutier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cloutier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Astudillo-Defru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">608</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cloutier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">´</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Artigau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cosentino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84461</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Crane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shectman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7735</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">773553</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Crause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sharples</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bramall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91476</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. SPIE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Crepp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">990819</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ségransan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dittmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">544</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">333</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dressing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">807</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dressing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dumusque</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">800</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">135</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dumusque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J P F G</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Figueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Adibekyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oshagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">586</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Forveille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Delfosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">645</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">766</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Petigura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1805.01453</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Petigura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>F˙ Zrész</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simcoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">990814</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gaudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">655</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">550</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sithajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99086</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">990870</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Observation and Analysis of Stellar Photospheres Grunblatt</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F. ; S K</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Haywood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">808</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Skiff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">862</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Haywood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Collier Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">443</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2517</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Soderblom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Donahue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baliunas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1086/117796</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">730</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanchis-Ojeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">503</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">381</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Huélamo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Figueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bonfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">489</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T.-O</forename><surname>Husser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Wende-Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dreizler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Isaacson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">725</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jurgenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mccracken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99086</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M.-R</forename><surname>Kempton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Louie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1805.03671</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Montet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">785</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kopparapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">765</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kotani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Suto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">914714</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>López-Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Haywood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Louie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44401</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">437</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dumusque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1107.5325</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahadevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84461</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mahmud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crockett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johns-Krull</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">736</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Osorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bouy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wainscoat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">644</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">75</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Messenger</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">822</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">472</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4563</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">821</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Noguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Izumiura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3355</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="362" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baliunas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">763</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Oliva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Origlia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">626919</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. SPIE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oshagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Figueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">606</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy III</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cristiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rebolo Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7735</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77350</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Perruchot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chazelas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pizzolato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Maggio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Micela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sciortino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ventura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">397</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Prato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Huerta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johns-Krull</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">687</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy V</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Quirrenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Amado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91471</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rayner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bonnet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84462</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">710</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">432</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shulyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Anglada-Escudé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">552</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zechmeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1711.06576</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ricker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vanderspek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Astronomical Telescopes, Instruments, and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14003</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">801</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Saar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hatzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Paulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Future of Cool-Star Astrophysics: 12th Cambridge Workshop on Cool Stars, Stellar Systems, and the Sun</title>
		<editor>A. Brown, G. M. Harper, &amp; T. R. Ayres</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="694" to="698" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cambridge Workshop on Cool Stars, Stellar Systems, and the Sun</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">361</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">265</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seifahrt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stürmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">990818</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Siverd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hygelund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">99086</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sliski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>146.09</idno>
		<title level="m">American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts #229</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">229</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sliski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">788</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">148</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stassun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Oelkers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1706.00495</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Strassmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ilyin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Järvinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astronomische Nachrichten</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">336</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">324</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta-Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">809</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Swift</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bottom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Astronomical Telescopes, Instruments, and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Szentgyorgyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baldwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">990822</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tal-Or</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zechmeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reiners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1803.02338</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Van Eylen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Agentoft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lundkvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1710.05398</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">ArXiv e-prints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vanderburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Montet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">800</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bigelow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<editor>Astronomy VIII, ed. D. L. Crawford &amp; E. R. Craine</editor>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2198</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">362</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Radovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kibrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PASP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">359</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">783</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">768</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Isaacson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">819</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Weisenburger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">812</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wolfgang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">825</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">261</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
