<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:14+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b: two transiting exoplanets detected and characterized with Kepler, SOPHIE and HARPS-N</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-10-03">October 3, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
							<email>hebrard@iap.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique de Paris</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Pierre &amp; Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>98bis boulevard Arago</addrLine>
									<postCode>UMR7095, 75014</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Observatoire de Haute-Provence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS/OAMP</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>04870</postCode>
									<settlement>Saint-Michel-l&apos;Observatoire</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Almenara</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Centro de Astrofísica</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidade do Porto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rua das Estrelas</addrLine>
									<postCode>4150-762</postCode>
									<settlement>Porto</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deleuil</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Damiani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bonomo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">INAF -Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Osservatorio 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>10025</postCode>
									<settlement>Pino Torinese</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bruno</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Montagnier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institut d&apos;Astrophysique de Paris</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Pierre &amp; Marie Curie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>98bis boulevard Arago</addrLine>
									<postCode>UMR7095, 75014</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Observatoire de Haute-Provence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CNRS/OAMP</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>04870</postCode>
									<settlement>Saint-Michel-l&apos;Observatoire</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LAM (Laboratoire d&apos;Astrophysique de Marseille) UMR 7326</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Aix Marseille Université</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13388</postCode>
									<settlement>Marseille</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b: two transiting exoplanets detected and characterized with Kepler, SOPHIE and HARPS-N</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-10-03">October 3, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received TBC; accepted TBC</note>
					<note>Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics manuscript no. article c ESO 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Planetary systems -Techniques: radial velocities -Techniques: photometric -Techniques: spectroscopic -Stars: indi- vidual: KOI-200, KOI-889</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present the detection and characterization of the two new transiting, close-in, giant extrasolar planets KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b. They were first identified by the Kepler team as promising candidates from photometry of the Kepler satellite, then we established their planetary nature thanks to the radial velocity follow-up jointly secured with the spectrographs SOPHIE and HARPS-N. Combined analyses of the whole datasets allow the two planetary systems to be characterized. The planet KOI-200 b has mass and radius of 0.68 ± 0.09 M Jup and 1.32 ± 0.14 R Jup ; it orbits in 7.34 days a F8V host star with mass and radius of 1.40 +0.14 −0.11 M and 1.51 ± 0.14 R. KOI-889 b is a massive planet with mass and radius of 9.9±0.5 M Jup and 1.03±0.06 R Jup ; it orbits in 8.88 days an active G8V star with a rotation period of 19.2 ± 0.3 days, and mass and radius of 0.88 ± 0.06 M and 0.88 ± 0.04 R. Both planets lie on eccentric orbits and are located just at the frontier between regimes where the tides can explain circularization and where tidal effects are negligible. The two planets are among the first ones detected and characterized thanks to observations secured with HARPS-N, the new spectrograph recently mounted at the Telescopio Nazionale Galileo. These results illustrate the benefits that could be obtained from joint studies using two spectrographs as SOPHIE and HARPS-N.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Exoplanets transiting in front of their host stars allow numerous key studies to be performed, including accurate radius, mass, and density measurements, atmospheric studies in absorption through transits and in emission through occultations, dynamic analyses from possible timing variations, or obliquity measurements (see, e.g., Winn 2010 for a review). Today, nearly 300 transiting exoplanets have been discovered. They were mainly detected from ground-based photometric surveys which are mostly sensitive to close-in giant planets (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr">Hébrard et al. 2013</ref>), and from their space-based counterparts CoRoT and Kepler which are sensitive to similar planets as well as to planets on longer periods and/or smaller radii. The Kepler satellite, in particular, is monitoring stars with high-precision optical photometry with the goal to detect signatures of exoplanetary transits. About 156 000 stars with magnitudes 9 &lt; V &lt; 16 are continuously observed by Kepler for more than three years now. Several candidates lists have been successively released by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borucki et al. (2011a;</ref>) then <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Batalha et al. (2013)</ref> with a list now of 2321 Kepler Objects of Interest (KOIs). An additional set of 461 new Kepler planet candidates has been recently announced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Burke et al. (2013)</ref>. That dataset provides precious inputs for exoplanetology research, for statistical analyses as well as for individual studies on particular KOIs. However in most cases photometry alone does not allow the planetary nature of the detected transits to be established. Indeed, several stellar configurations can mimic planetary transits (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Almenara et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bouchy et al. 2009a</ref>), including undiluted eclipsing binaries with low-mass stellar companions or diluted eclipsing binaries, namely "blends". Whereas such impostors represent the majority of transiting planet candidates detected by groundbased surveys or even by CoRoT, it has been argued from statistical studies that they should be particularly rare for Kepler candidates (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Morton &amp; Johnson 2011)</ref>. Other studies have shown however that a significant part of the KOIs actually are not caused by planets but by scenarios implying stellar objects only (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bouchy et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Coì on et al. 2012;</ref>). This is particularly true for close-in, giant exoplanet KOI candidates, whose false positive rate have been estimated to 34.8 ± 6.5% ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Santerne et al. 2012</ref>) or 29.3 ± 3.1% ( ).</p><p>In numerous cases radial velocities (RV) allow blend scenarios and actual planetary transits to be distinguished. In complement to photometric data, radial velocities also provide additional parameters for the identified planetary systems; in particular they allow the mass of the planets and the eccentricity of their orbits to be measured. In order to do such studies on Kepler candidates we started in 2010 a radial-velocity followup of KOIs with the SOPHIE spectrograph at Observatoire de Haute-Provence (OHP, France). We mainly focussed on the brightest stars (Kepler magnitude K p &lt; 14.7) harboring candidates of close-in, giant planets. In particular, this already allowed us to identify and characterize several new transiting plan-ets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Santerne et al. 2011a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bonomo et al. 2012</ref>) as well as more massive companions and false positives ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Ehrenreich et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bouchy et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Santerne et al. 2012;</ref>).</p><p>The installation of the HARPS-N spectrograph at the Telescopio Nazionale Galileo (TNG, La Palma, Spain) gives us the opportunity to extend that on-going program. Indeed, HARPS-N is supposed to reach a better radial-velocity precision than SOPHIE, especially for faint Kepler targets thanks to the 3.58-m diameter of the TNG, to be compared with the 1.93-m diameter of the OHP telescope hosting SOPHIE. One of the main objectives of HARPS-N is the RV follow-up of the Kepler candidates. First we used HARPS-N to follow KOIs for which our SOPHIE data suggested planet detection but with a precision preventing firm conclusion and accurate characterization. Secondly we also used HARPS-N to follow KOIs fainter than the limit K p = 14.7 adopted with SOPHIE. We present here two new transiting planet detections, one in each of the two above categories. This illustrates the benefits that could be obtained from joint studies using two spectrographs as HARPS-N and SOPHIE for the follow-up of transiting planet candidates. We describe the photometric and spectroscopic observations of both targets in Sect. 2 and the analysis of the whole datasets and the results in Sect. 3. Tidal evolution of both planets is discussed in Sect. 4 and we conclude in Sect. 5. publicly available from the MAST archive 1 . Some quarters were also observed in short cadence (every 1 minute) for both targets. Since their transits in long-cadence data are well enough sampled these short-cadence data were not used, which reduces computation time. We used the light-curve of quarters Q1 to Q13 reduced by the Photometric Analysis Kepler pipeline that accounts for barycentric, cosmic ray, background and "argabrightening" corrections ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Jenkins et al. 2010</ref>). Both light curves clearly present transits with depths of about 1 % as reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borucki et al. (2011a;</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Batalha et al. (2013)</ref>, with a typical uncertainty per data point at the level of ∼ 200 ppm for KOI-200 and ∼ 500 ppm for KOI-889. While the light curve of KOI-200 does not show any sign of stellar variability, KOI-889 shows flux modulations at levels between ∼ 2 % and ∼ 4 % peak-to-peak, depending of the epochs. An example is shown in the right panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. This is likely due to appearing spots with variable extents and locations on the rotating surface of the star. Analyses through Lomb-Scargle periodogram and autocorrelation function provide the same values for the periodicity of the modulations, which corresponds to the rotational period of the star: P rot = 19.2 ± 0.3 days. This is near to twice the orbital period of the planet. A stellar rotation period similar to the orbital period is unlikely according to the shape of the light curve and the periodogram. Before modeling the transits, we normalized fragments of the light curves by fitting an out-of-transit parabola, first without accounting for contamination. Since the Kepler spacecraft is rotating four times a year, the crowding values are different between seasons. We thus produced four crowding-uncorrected detrended light curves for both targets, one per season. This will allow us to account for differential crowding values, noises and out-of-transit fluxes in the transit modeling and in the final error budget (see Sect. 3.2). The corresponding phase-folded light curves are plotted in the upper panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>. In addition to the transit signal, the KOI-889 light curve shows a modulation with a period 19.2 days, which is likely due to appearing spots on the rotating surface of the star.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">−2 s −1 ˚ A −1 ] 10 4 10 5 Wavelength [ ˚ A] −0.2 −0.1 0.0 0.1 0.2 O-C [mag]</formula><p>KOI-889 SED cal fibers mounted at the focus of their telescope (1.93-m OHP for SOPHIE and 3.58-m TNG for HARPS-N). Their spectral ranges are similar (about 385 nm -693 nm) and their wavelength calibration is made using thorium-argon lamps. They are the only two spectrographs fed by octagonal-section fibers available now on the sky. This allows an improved stability and uniformity of the illumination for high-precision spectroscopy. SOPHIE was equipped by octagonal-section fibers in Spring 2011 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bouchy et al. 2013</ref>) and HARPS-N since its start in Spring 2012. Both instruments are located in a thermally-controlled room but while only the dispersive components are contained in a sealed constant-pressure tank in the case of SOPHIE, the whole HARPS-N instrument is encapsulated in a vacuum vessel which provides an even better radial-velocity stability. For the present studies SOPHIE was used in High-efficiency mode, yielding a resolution power λ/∆λ = 40 000, whereas HARPS-N provides λ/∆λ = 115 000. The slow read-out modes were used for the detectors of both instruments. The present HARPS-N observations were obtained just before the failure of the red side of the CCD in late September 2012. For both stars and both instruments the two optical-fiber apertures (3"-and 1"-wide for SOPHIE and HARPS-N, respectively) were used. The first aperture was centered on the target and the second one on the sky to simultaneously measure its background. It allowed us to confirm there was no Moonlight pollution in any of our spectra significantly altering the radial velocity measurement. In the case of KOI-889 another star was coincidentally present in the second SOPHIE aperture. That second star does not affect the spectra extraction procedure for the first aperture, and we double checked there was no sky pollution using the observations of other targets secured the nights we observed KOI-889.</p><p>The spectra were extracted from the detector images with the SOPHIE and HARPS-N pipelines. Based on similar structures, they include localization of the spectral orders on the 2D-images, optimal order extraction, cosmic-ray rejection, wavelength calibration, and corrections of flat-field. Then the spectra passed through weighted cross-correlation with G2-type numerical masks following the method described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baranne et al. (1996)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Pepe et al. (2002)</ref>. We adjusted the number of spectral orders used in the cross-correlations to reduce the dispersion of the measurements. Indeed, some spectral domains in the blue part of the spectra have particularly low signal-to-noise ratios (SNR), so using them degrades the precision of the radialvelocity measurement. At the end, we did not used the 15 first blue orders of the 70 available ones in the HARPS-N spectra for the cross-correlation, as well as the 13 and 19 first ones of the 39 SOPHIE orders for KOI-200 and KOI-889, respectively.</p><p>All the exposures provide a well-defined, single peak in the cross-correlation function (CCF). For KOI-200 their full widths at half maximum are 10.88 ± 0.12 km s −1 and their contrasts represent 23±4 % of the continuum for SOPHIE, the corresponding values for HARPS-N being 8.38 ± 0.06 km s −1 and 42.3 ± 0.7 %. In the case of KOI-889 the values are 10.17 ± 0.10 km s −1 and 21 ± 4 % for SOPHIE, and 7.49 ± 0.14 km s −1 and 54.7 ± 1.2 % for HARPS-N. The differences are mainly due to spectral resolutions of both instruments. The radial velocities were obtained from Gaussian fits of the CCFs, together with their associated error bars and bisector spans. They were also corrected from the interpolated drift of the spectrographs. The bisector spans error bars were estimated to be two times those of the corresponding radial velocities. The measurements are reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> and plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> (middle panel) and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 3</ref>.</p><p>In the case of KOI-200, we first obtained five SOPHIE exposures of ∼ 1 hour each in March-April 2012 that showed marginal radial velocity variations, possibly in agreement with the Kepler ephemeris. The hint of detection was reinforced with seven extra SOPHIE measurements secured in June-July 2012. However the detection was at the limit of the SOPHIE capabilities with a semi-amplitude of the order of 50 m/s whereas the SOPHIE measurements of KOI-200 typically have a ±25- m/s precision. So we re-observed KOI-200 with HARPS-N five nights in a row in August 2012, obtaining five 45-min exposures with better precisions, between ±8 and ±16 m/s. Reasonably well sampling the orbital phases of the 7.34-day period, the HARPS-N data clearly confirmed the planet detection and allow a small eccentricity to be detected <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2, left, middle panel)</ref>.</p><p>Concerning KOI-889, the target was fainter than our adopted magnitude limit on SOPHIE so we first secured in August 2012 two observations with HARPS-N, near the quadratures according to the Kepler ephemeris. Due to technical issues and poor weather conditions, these exposures were short (23 and 12 minutes only) and provided poor signal-to-noise ratios, which limited the radial velocity precisions to ±47 m/s and ±89 m/s respectively. However, it was enough to detect the 1.5-km s −1 variation between the two epochs. Such a large variation does not necessarily require HARPS-N but is enough to be detected with SOPHIE despite the faintness of the target. So starting the following night we switched that target to SOPHIE and finally secured nine observations of KOI-889 in August-September 2012 at OHP, sampling the different orbital phases of the 8.88-day period. Thanks to better weather conditions and longer exposure times (∼ 1 hour per exposure), SOPHIE allowed an improved radial-velocity precision to be reached on that target (typically ±35 m/s) by comparison with HARPS-N.</p><p>For both targets, the joint SOPHIE and HARPS-N datasets show radial velocity variations in agreement with the Kepler ephemeris <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2</ref>, middle panel). They imply semi-amplitudes in two different regimes, K 60 m/s and K 1300 m/s for KOI-200 and KOI-889 respectively, corresponding to ∼ 0.7 M Jup and ∼ 10 M Jup for both companions: they lie in the planet-mass range. Radial velocities obtained using different stellar masks (F0, G2, or K5) produce variations with similar amplitudes, so there is no evidence that the variations could be explained by blend scenarios caused by stars of different spectral types. Similarly, the cross-correlation function bisector spans show neither variations nor trends as a function of radial velocity <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 3)</ref>. A weak correlation could be seen in the case of KOI-889 but it mainly stands on the two low-SNR HARPS-N measurements. It disappears when only the nine higher-SNR SOPHIE measurements are considered. This reinforces the conclusion that the radial-velocity variations are not caused by spectral-line profile changes attributable to blends or stellar activity. We thus conclude that both targets harbor transiting giant planets, which we hereafter designate as KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">System characterization</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Parameters of the host stars</head><p>The spectral analysis of both host stars was performed with the co-added individual spectra obtained with SOPHIE once reduced and set on the rest frame. In the case of KOI-200, the second aperture which is located on the sky was subtracted from each spectrum in order to correct from the residual background sky light. For KOI-889 this was not possible because of the other star coincidentally located in the second aperture, which implied a higher uncertainty here. The total signal-tonoise ratios of the co-added spectra are 75 and 64 per resolution element at 550 nm in the continuum, for KOI-200 and KOI-889 respectively.</p><p>We performed the spectral analysis using the iterative spectral synthesis package VWA. As described in details by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Bruntt et al. (2010)</ref> and references therein, the atmospheric parameters T eff , log g * , and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref> were derived from a set of 49 Fe i and nine Fe ii weak lines carefully selected. Ionization and excitation equilibrium was imposed as well as a zero slope between the abundances given by individual lines and their equivalent width. The SME package (version 2.1: <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Valenti &amp; Piskunov 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Valenti &amp; Fischer 2005</ref>) was also applied as a check to both stars and provided similar results to those obtained with VWA, but with slightly larger error bars. As an additional verification, we also derived the surface gravity from the Ca i pressure-sensitive line at 612.2 nm. The projected rotational velocity v sin i * and the macroturbulence were determined independently from a set of isolated spectral lines in the case of KOI-200. The v sin i * measurement agrees with that obtained from the width of the crosscorrelation function (Sect. 2.2) following the method presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Boisse et al. (2010)</ref>. Due to the poor signal-to-noise ratio of the spectra, the v sin i * of KOI-889 was only measured from the cross-correlation function.</p><p>The fundamental parameters of the two host stars (mass, radius, and age) were estimated from the comparison of the location of the star in the H-R diagram with StarEvol evolution tracks ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Lagarde et al. 2012</ref>; Palacios, private com.). We used the atmospheric parameters T eff and [Fe/H] with their associated uncertainties and the distribution of stellar density derived from the  transit model (see Sect. 3.2.1 below) in the χ 2 minimization as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Santerne et al. (2011a)</ref> to derive the stellar masses, radii and gravities.</p><p>The evolutionary tracks provide an age estimate of 2.9 +1.5 −0.8 Gyr for KOI-200. We found two distinct sets of solutions for KOI-889: one corresponds to a young star of 200 Myr and the second one to a more evolved main-sequence star with an age of 10.2 ± 2.1 Gyr. The spectra of the star do not display any sign of chromospheric activity in the Ca ii lines and the rotation period (Sect. 2.1) provides gyrochronological ages of 1.7 ± 0.4 Gyr and 3.1 ± 0.7 Gyr using the relations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barnes (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Lanza (2010)</ref>, respectively. We thus favor the oldest solutions and finally adopt 6 ± 3 Gyr for the age of KOI-889.</p><p>The parameters of both stars derived from these procedures are given in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. KOI-200 is a F8V star and KOI-889 a G8V star. Both are slowly rotating. Our derived parameters are in good agreement with those estimated from photometry in the Kepler Input Catalog (KIC, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Brown et al. 2011</ref>) but our T eff , masses, and radii are slightly larger.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Parameters of the planetary systems</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1.">Method</head><p>The four normalized Kepler light curves constructed from quarters Q1 to Q13 (Sect. 2.1) were fitted together with SOPHIE and HARPS-N radial velocities (Sect. 2.2) using the PASTIS code <ref type="bibr">(Díaz et al., in prep.)</ref>. That code was already used in previous analyses (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Santerne et al. 2011b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Díaz et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Kostov et al. 2012</ref>). The transit light curves were modeled using the EBOP code <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Etzel 1981)</ref> extracted from the JKTEBOP package ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Southworth et al. 2004</ref>). As recommended by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Kipping (2010)</ref>, we used an oversampling factor of five when comparing the model with the light curves to account for the long integration time of Kepler light curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Kipping &amp; Bakos 2011</ref>). Radial velocity curves were simultaneously fitted with eccentric Keplerian orbit. No significant radial velocity drifts were detected so we assume only two bodies in each Keplerian fit. The radial velocity measurements are too sparse and the time spans are too short to allow useful constraints to be put on the presence of additional bodies in the systems. For each Kepler light curve we included the out-of-transit flux and the contamination factor as free parameters. Contamination factors reported in the KIC ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Brown et al. 2011</ref>) have been shown to be erroneous in some cases (see e.g. <ref type="bibr">KOI-205;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Díaz et al. 2013</ref>) so we chose to fit them instead of adopting the KIC values. We also account for additional sources of Gaussian noise in the light curves and radial velocities by fitting a jitter value to each data set. This is especially appropriate for Kepler data since the star is located on different CCDs each season. The system and data are finally described by 26 free parameters, listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>. These parameters were fitted using a Metropolis-Hasting Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Tegmark et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ford 2006</ref>) with an adaptive step size <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Ford 2006</ref>). To better sample the posterior distribution in case of non-linear correlations between parameters, we applied an adaptive principal component analysis to the chains and jumped the parameters in an uncorrelated space <ref type="bibr">(Díaz et al., in prep.</ref>). Two additional parameters were not free but fixed in the analysis because they are negligible here in cases of exoplanets, whereas they could have significant effects for stellar binaries. The first one is the gravity darkening coefficient fixed to β 1 = 1 (with β 1 = 4 × β; see Espinosa Lara &amp; Rieutord 2012). The second one is the mass ratio which is fixed to 0; it constraints the ellipsoid modulations of the light curves which are not detected here. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref> also lists the priors used for this analysis. Erroneous tabulated limb-darkening coefficients could alter the results (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Csizmadia et al. 2013</ref>). In order to avoid underestimation of uncertainties, we chose to let the limb-darkening coefficients free to vary instead of adopting tabulated values. Priors on the contamination factors were chosen according to the values provided by the KIC assuming 0.5% of Gaussian uncertainty. Priors on orbital period and epoch of first transit were centered on the value found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Batalha et al. (2013)</ref>, with a width about 100 times larger than the reported errors to avoid biased solutions. In general, the shapes and widths of priors were chosen to be large enough to limit the bias on the posterior. For the eccentricity of KOI-200 b which is not well constrained in the SOPHIE data, we used as prior the posterior distribution of an independent MCMC analysis of the radial velocity alone in order to faster reach the convergence of the final MCMC. KOI-200 and KOI-889 were analyzed with 55 and 40 chains leading to a total of 7 × 10 7 and 4 × 10 7 steps, respectively. Each chain was started at random points drawn from the joint prior. In both cases, all chains converged to the same solution. We used a modified version of Geweke (1992) diagnostic to determine and remove the burn-in phase of each chain. We then computed the correlation length of each converged sub-chains before thinning them. We finally merged the thinned chains that results in a total of about 1000 independent samples of the posterior distribution for both targets.</p><p>The distances of both stars were determined through another MCMC algorithm by comparing the magnitudes reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> with an interpolated grid of synthetic spectra from the PHOENIX/BT-Settl library ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Allard et al. 2012</ref>). We used the T eff , <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>, and log g * of the host star from the spectral analysis (see Sect. 3.1) with their respective errors as prior of the MCMC and let the distance and interstellar reddening as free parameters to fit the spectral energy distribution. This consisted in adjust the stellar parameters within the prior to find the best synthetic spectrum that match the observed magnitude after rescaling it from the distance luminosity of the star and correcting from the interstellar extinction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Results</head><p>The 68.3-% confidence intervals (corresponding to 1-σ intervals assuming Gaussian distributions) are listed in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. The maximum posterior models are displayed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>.</p><p>Our procedure and the quality of the Kepler data allow the contamination factors to be directly measured. They show slight variations between the four Kepler seasons, as expected due to the four different orientations of the satellite. Our derived values are similar to the ones reported in the KIC but here we can determine their uncertainties. The derived jitter is around 100 ppm for KOI-200, which is compatible with the typical value derived by <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Gilliland et al. (2011</ref><ref type="bibr">) for Kepler data (Díaz et al. 2013</ref>). In the case of KOI-889 we found ∼ 300 ppm; that excess of jitter could be explained by the activity of the star. The jitters show some variations between seasons, probably linked to the different characteristics of the four different parts of the detector that are used each season. The out-of-transit fluxes fitted for each season were found near unity with typical uncertainties of ±8 ppm and ±25 ppm for KOI-200 and KOI-889, respectively. None of the light curves show the signature of planetary occultation at the secondary eclipse phase, as expected for relatively long-period planets such as these. Occultations depths are expected here to be at most of the order of a few tens of ppm. In addition in the case of KOI-200 b, the secondary eclipse is likely to be un-observable from the Earth as the secondary impact parameter is b sec = 1.11 ± 0.23. This is the case for a significant part of eccentric planets, even on close-in orbits ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Santerne et al. 2013</ref>). Concerning the radial velocities, only the SOPHIE data for KOI-200 need a significant jitter of 28 ± 13 m/s to be added. For the other cases the dispersion of the residuals around the fit agree with the expected error bars on radial velocities.</p><p>From the results of the spectral analysis, we expect limbdarkening coefficients from Claret et al.  <ref type="formula">(2012)</ref> does not significantly change our results. Similarly, the log g * values derived from the stellar spectra agree with those derived from the stellar density. And finally, the fit of the spectral energy distribution provides the distance and the interstellar extinction E(B − V) of each target as well as the stellar parameters log g * , T eff , and <ref type="bibr">[Fe/H]</ref>, which were found to agree with the values derived from the stellar analysis itself. Thus the different analyses are coherent with respect to the different constraints they use.</p><p>Orbiting a F8 dwarf star in 7.340718 ± 0.000001 days, KOI-200 b is a giant planet with a mass of 0.68 ± 0.09 M Jup and a radius of 1.32 ± 0.14 R Jup . Its density ρ p = 0.37 ± 0.13 g/cm <ref type="bibr">3</ref> is particularly low. Whereas the SOPHIE data alone do not al-low a significant eccentricity to be detected, the five HARPS-N measurements exclude circularity for the orbit, with a residuals dispersion reduced from ±14 m/s to ±6 m/s between circular and eccentric orbits. The light curve also provides constraints on the eccentricity through the duration of the transit. In addition, in the case of a circular orbit the derived limb darkening coefficients were in poorer agreement with the ones expected from spectral analysis according <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Claret et al. (2012)</ref>. With all the constraints we finally derived e = 0.287 ± 0.062. The eccentric solution is ∼ 75 times more probable than the circular one. The equilibrium temperatures of the planet derived from T eff and R and assuming an isotropic zero-albedo are T p = 1450 ± 150 K, 1250 ± 120 K, and 1100 ± 110 K respectively at periastron, semimajor axis distance, and apoastron.</p><p>The massive planet KOI-889 b orbits a G8 dwarf star in 8.884924 ± 0.000002 days. Its mass is 9.9 ± 0.5 M Jup and its radius 1.03 ± 0.06 R Jup . It lies below the deuterium-burning mass (∼ 13 M Jup ) which could be used to distinguish planets from brown dwarfs. The eccentricity of the orbit is clearly detected in the radial velocities. The value e = 0.569 ± 0.010 could be accurately determined thanks to the large amplitude of the radial velocity variation. The equilibrium temperatures of the planet assuming an isotropic zero-albedo are T p = 1300 ± 60 K, 850 ± 40 K, and 680 ± 30 K respectively at periastron, semimajor axis distance, and apoastron. Its active host star shows the signature of evolutional spots in the light curve, but the signalto-noise ratio on the spectra is too low to allow that activity to be detected in the radial velocity jitter nor in the core of the Ca ii lines. The deduced rotation period is P rot = 19.2 ± 0.3 days which together with the measured stellar radius implies a rotation velocity V rot 2.3 km/s. This is smaller than the value v sin i * = 4.6 ± 1.0 km/s measured from the lines width. This indicates a possible underestimation of the latest value so we adopt v sin i * = 3.5 ± 1.5 km/s to take into account for the two evaluations. If the deduced rotation velocity V rot had been larger than v sin i * , it would have been consistent with sin i * &lt; 1, implying an oblique orbit of the planet with respect to the equatorial plane of the star. As this is not the case, there are no signs for spin-orbit misalignment and probably i * i p 90 • .</p><p>For both planets our derived parameters agree with the ones first measured by the Kepler team ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Borucki et al. 2011a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Batalha et al. 2013</ref>). An exception is the system scales a/R which we found to be significantly smaller than the ones initially reported from the first Kepler light curves because of the unconsidered eccentricities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Tidal evolution</head><p>With their orbital periods of 7.34 and 8.88 days, KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b are in a regime where a modest amount of transiting planets have been detected now. It is growing up with the Kepler candidates but most of them have shallow transits. Only ten transiting giant planets are known today in the period range 6 − 50 days. The mass and period of KOI-200 b are similar to those of the three planets WASP-59b, CoRoT-4b, and HAT-P17b. Concerning the massive, giant planet KOI-889 b, it has only two nearly analogs with orbital periods longer than typical periods of hot Jupiters, namely HAT-P-2b and Kepler-14b. CoRoT14b is a fourth case of massive, transiting planet, but its orbital period is shorter (1.5 d). KOI-889 b is one of the rare known massive planets orbiting a G-type star in a close-in orbit. The lack of planets in that regime was underlined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bouchy et al. (2011)</ref> who proposed that such planets would not survive too close to G dwarfs due to engulfment caused by tidal interactions with Both being on eccentric orbits, KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b are part of the borderline planets as seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 4</ref>, i.e. planets that are in the period range 6 − 30 days that lie in the crossover between a regime where the tides are sufficient to explain circularization and a regime where tidal effects are negligible. The dispersion in eccentricity of these systems can be seen as the result of different spin-down rates of young stars, as argued by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Dobbs-Dixon et al. (2004)</ref>. The case of KOI-889 b is particularly interesting since it is close to the envelope of the maximum observed eccentricity for systems in this period range.</p><p>Tidal interaction can lead either to a spiralling of the planet into the star followed by a collision, or to the asymptotic evolution towards an equilibrium, characterized by orbital circularity, co-planarity, and co-rotation. Under the assumption that the total angular momentum is conserved (i.e. neglecting magnetic breaking), it can be shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Hut 1980</ref>) that equilibrium states exist only when the total angular momentum of the system L tot is larger than some critical value L crit ; such equilibrium states are unstable if the orbital angular momentum</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">h = GM 2 M 2 p a(1 − e 2 )/(M + M p ) (</formula><p>where G is the gravitational constant) accounts for less than three quarters of L tot . A system that is expected to evolve towards a stable equilibrium is generally called "Darwin stable". So far, the vast majority of known exoplanetary systems are not Darwin stable ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Matsumura et al. 2010</ref>) and their planets are doomed to eventually fall into the host star.</p><p>In this respect, KOI-200 b is not particularly remarkable despite its eccentricity. Using the stellar rotational velocity v sin i * to assess the rotational frequency Ω of the star (assuming i * 90 • ) and taking the gyration radius γ from stellar models for the corresponding mass and temperature (Claret 1995), we can compute the stellar rotational angular momentum, or spin, L = M (γR ) 2 Ω . This assumes that the star rotates rigidly and the interior non-uniform distribution of mass is accounted for by γ. For the KOI-200 system, considering the typical value of tidal dissipation efficiency in planets Q p = 10 6 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Matsumura et al. 2008</ref> ), the timescale for the synchronization and alignment of the planet relative to the orbit is ∼ 4 × 10 5 yr so we can safely assume that the planet is in pseudo-synchronization. Taking the gyration radius of a polytropic model of index 1 for the planet, the planetary spin can also be computed. Adding both spins to the orbital angular momentum h gives the total angular momentum, which is found to be L tot 0.8 L crit . Thus the system is Darwin unstable. The subsequent evolution depends on the relative efficiency of the dissipation of the tides within the star and the planet. Either the dissipation in the planet is dominant and the circularization of the orbit will happen before any significant orbital decay can occur, or it is the efficiency of tidal dissipation in the star that will control the evolution of all the parameters, and the orbit will keep a non-null eccentricity until the engulfment. Finally, little can be inferred from the present state of the system regarding the origin of the eccentricity and the migration scenario. Considering the moderate value of the eccentricity, the lack of constraints on the obliquity or the presence of a possible companion in the system, both planetplanet scattering or migration in a disk followed by weak tidal interaction are valid hypothesis. The expected amplitude of the Rossiter-McLaughlin anomaly is ∼ 30 m/s, so the measurement of the obliquity through the spectroscopic observation of a transit is feasible.</p><p>On the other hand, KOI-889 b is much more special. The rotation period of its host star is estimated to P rot = 19.2 ± 0.3 days (Sect. 2.1). Using the same reasoning as described above we find that the system has L tot 1.3 L crit , thus allowing for the existence of equilibrium states. Furthermore h/L tot 0.9904, meaning that the system is evolving toward the stable equilibrium. Considering that n/Ω 2 (where n is the mean orbital motion), we know that the tides act to bring the planet closer to the star while circularizing the orbit. Moreover, in the frame of the weak friction model of the equilibrium tides with constant time lag, the main global features of tidal evolution can be derived, using energy and angular momentum considerations only <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Hut 1981)</ref>. It turns out that the only external parameter of the coupled differential equations that rule the temporal behavior of the orbital parameters is α, the ratio of the orbital and rotational angular momentum of the system at the stable equilibrium. For KOI-889 b, α 22.8, allowing for the existence of turning points in the evolution of both the semi-major axis and the eccentricity. The past and future evolution of the system can thus be non-monotonic (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 5</ref>). Considering that KOI-889 is a G8V star showing clear evidence of magnetic activity, this problem is furthermore complicated by the effect of stellar magnetic braking, which is not taken into account in the derivation by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hut (1981)</ref> but which makes the star to spin down (Dobbs- <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Dixon et al. 2004</ref>).</p><p>The fact that n/Ω 2 is intriguing because it is the value where Type II migration stops if the disk is truncated at the corotation radius <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Kuchner &amp; Lecar 2002)</ref>. Assuming this migration mechanism is indeed the dominant one for KOI-889 b, this would be an evidence that the tidal interactions in this system since the disappearance of the disk are either weak or that the system is young. The rotation period of the star invalidates the former interpretation as young stars are observed to rotate significantly faster, meaning that to preserve the synchronization some tidal interaction must have occurred. Moreover in both cases, the significant eccentricity of the orbit is difficult to explain because Type II migration tends to produce circular systems (e.g.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hut (1981)</ref>. The semi-major axis a is normalized to its value at the stable equilibrium a eq . The black, solid line gives the stationary points of the eccentricity, with the plus and minus signs indicating the domains where the eccentricity increases and decreases, respectively. The green and blue solid lines give the corresponding information for the semi-major axis and rotational angular velocity of the star, respectively. The dotted blue line separates the upper region where Ω &lt; 0 from the lower region where Ω &gt; 0. The red dot is the present state of the system, corresponding to an evolution where dΩ /dt &gt; 0, da/dt &lt; 0 and de/dt &lt; 0. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Benítez-Llambay et al. 2011</ref>). However, if we consider that the star was still in its pre-main-sequence phase when the disc disappeared <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Mamajek 2009)</ref>, the rapid increase of the spin of the star caused by the contraction of the radius can lead the system into a domain where the eccentricity can be excited while the orbit would widen, assuring the survival of the planet. The subsequent evolution would see the spin loss of the star caused by magnetic braking bring progressively the system in the domain where both the eccentricity and the semi-major axis are damped toward the stable equilibrium. However, the angular momentum extracted from the system by magnetic braking will eventually make the system Darwin unstable. Depending on the relative efficiency of tidal dissipation and magnetic braking, this might bring the planet to spiral into its host before the end of the main sequence lifetime of the star.</p><p>Although the age of the star KOI-889 is not well constrained, a detailed study could give useful constraint on the efficiency of the tidal dissipation in both the star and planet, as well as an estimate of the loss of angular momentum through magnetic braking. For the massive planet KOI-889 b, a direct obliquity measurement would be useful to confirm or not the correlation between spin-orbit misalignment and planetary mass suggested by <ref type="bibr">Hébrard et al. (2010; 2011)</ref>. Indeed KOI-889 b is one of the few known transiting planets in that range of radius and mass, together with HAT-P-2b, <ref type="bibr">CoRoT-14b, and Kepler-14b.</ref> Comparison between v sin i * and P rot does not suggest any spinorbit misalignment in the KOI-889 system, whose expected amplitude of the Rossiter-McLaughlin anomaly is ∼ 40 m/s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>We have presented the detection and characterization of KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b, two new transiting, close-in, giant extrasolar planets. They were first detected as promising candidates by the Kepler team from Kepler light curves. We have established their planetary nature with the radial velocity follow-up we jointly secured using both the spectrographs SOPHIE and HARPS-N, and characterized them through combined analyses of the whole photometric and spectroscopic datasets. The planet KOI-200 b orbits its F8V host star in 7.34 days and its mass and radius are 0.68 ± 0.09 M Jup and 1.32 ± 0.14 R Jup . KOI-889 b is a massive planet orbiting in 8.88 days an active G8V star with a rotation period of 19.2 ± 0.3 days; its mass and radius are 9.9 ± 0.5 M Jup and 1.03 ± 0.06 R Jup . Both planets lie on eccentric orbits and are located just at the frontier between regimes where the tides can explain circularization and where tidal effects are negligible, making them interesting systems with respect to tidal evolution. KOI-200 is yet another example to be already Darwin unstable whereas KOI-889 is one of the few known currently Darwin-stable exoplanetary systems.</p><p>Since its installation in Spring 2012 at the Telescopio Nazionale Galileo, HARPS-N allowed in particular the obliquity of the transiting planet Qatar-1 b to be measured ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Covino et al. 2013</ref>) and the metal-poor star HIP 11952 to be shown not to harbor giant planets <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Desidera et al. 2013</ref>). The two new planets KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b presented here are among the first ones to be detected and characterized with HARPS-N. Our observing program managed jointly with SOPHIE and HARPS-N shows the benefits that could be obtained for the follow-up of transiting planet candidates from coordinated observations secured with two spectrographs with different sensitivities, precisions, and accessibilities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Time samples of the Kepler light curves of KOI-200 and KOI-889 (Q5 data only). The signatures of periodic transits are easily detected, with periods of 7.34 and 8.88 days respectively. In addition to the transit signal, the KOI-889 light curve shows a modulation with a period 19.2 days, which is likely due to appearing spots on the rotating surface of the star.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Radial velocities with SOPHIE and HARPS-N Both SOPHIE (Perruchot et al. 2008; Bouchy et al. 2009b) and HARPS-N (Cosentino et al. 2012) are cross-dispersed, stabilized echelle spectrographs dedicated to high-precision radial veloc- ity measurements. Each of them is fed by a set of two opti-Hébrard et al.: Two new transiting exoplanets KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Data and best fit models for KOI-200 (left) and KOI-889 (right). The parameters of the fits are reported in Table 4. Upper panels: Kepler phase-folded light-curve (black dots with 1-σ error bars) over-plotted with the best model (red line), and residuals. Middle panels: SOPHIE (red circles) and HARPS-N (blue squares) radial velocities and 1-σ error bars phase-folded to the orbital period of the planet (on left) or as function of time (on right) over-plotted with the best model (black line), and residuals. Lower panels: Fitted spectral energy distribution (black line) over-plotted with measured magnitudes (red circles, Table 1) and corresponding integrated flux in each of the photometric bands according the fit (open circles).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Bisector span as a function of the radial velocities with 1-σ error bars for KOI-200 (top) and KOI-889 (bottom). SOPHIE data are red circles and HARPS-N are blue squares. The ranges have the same extents in the x-and y-axes on each figure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>J(1.10 −2 , 10) † N(µ, σ 2 ): Normal distribution centered on µ with a width of σ; J(a, b): Jeffreys distribution between a and b; U(a, b): Uniform distri- bution between a and b. Prior values are discussed in Sect. 3.2.1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(2012) of u a = 0.34 ± 0.02, u b = 0.30 ± 0.10 for KOI-200 and u a = 0.47 ± 0.03, u b = 0.22 ± 0.02 for KOI-889. Our fitted limb-darkening co- efficients are compatible with the expected values within 1-σ. Fixing the coefficients to the values from Claret et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Orbital eccentricity and period of KOI-200 b and KOI-889 b compared with other known extrasolar planets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Regions of different types of tidal evolution for the planetary system KOI-889, neglecting magnetic braking following Hut (1981). The semi-major axis a is normalized to its value at the stable equilibrium a eq . The black, solid line gives the stationary points of the eccentricity, with the plus and minus signs indicating the domains where the eccentricity increases and decreases, respectively. The green and blue solid lines give the corresponding information for the semi-major axis and rotational angular velocity of the star, respectively. The dotted blue line separates the upper region where Ω &lt; 0 from the lower region where Ω &gt; 0. The red dot is the present state of the system, corresponding to an evolution where dΩ /dt &gt; 0, da/dt &lt; 0 and de/dt &lt; 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>IDs, coordinates, and magnitudes of the planet-host 
stars. 

Object 
KOI-200 
KOI-889 
Kepler ID 
6046540 
757450 
USNO-A2 ID 
1275-11623662 
11200-11449160 
2MASS ID 
19322220+4121198 19243302+3634385 
RA (J2000) 
19:32:22.21 
19:24:33.02 
DEC (J2000) 
41:21:19.87 
36:34:38.57 
Kepler magn. K p 
14.41 
15.26 
GSC-V 
14.23 
-
SDSS-G 
14.876 
15.998 
SDSS-R 
14.350 
15.207 
SDSS-I 
14.212 
14.949 
2MASS-J 
13.306 ± 0.024 
13.665 ± 0.021 
2MASS-H 
13.008 ± 0.025 
13.262 ± 0.025 
2MASS-K s 
12.958 ± 0.033 
13.118 ± 0.029 
WISE-W1 
12.857 ± 0.025 
13.149 ± 0.025 
WISE-W2 
12.912 ± 0.029 
13.286 ± 0.035 
WISE-W3 
12.307 ± 0.215 
-

2. Observations and data reduction 

2.1. Photometric detection with Kepler 

The IDs, coordinates, and magnitudes of the two targets are re-
ported in Table 1. Both KOI-200 and KOI-889 were observed 
by Kepler since the beginning of the mission in May 2009. They 
were identified by Borucki et al. (2011a; 2011b) and Batalha 
et al. (2013) as hosting single periodic transits with periods of 
7.34 and 8.88 days and depths characteristic of giant planets 
(Fig. 1). No transits with different periods were detected in any 
of the light curves so there are no signs for multiple transit-
ing systems. The Kepler photometry was acquired with a time 
sampling of 29.4 minutes (long-cadence data). The Kepler ob-
servations are divided in "quarters"; at the time of writing this 
paper, all the 13 first quarters observed so-far by Kepler were 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . SOPHIE and HARPS-N measurements for the planet- host stars KOI-200 and KOI-889.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>BJD UTC 
RV 
±1 σ 
bisect.  *  
exp. SNR  † instr.  ‡ 
-2 450 000 
(km/s) 
(km/s) 
(km/s) (sec) 
KOI-200: 
5989.6552 19.302 
0.020 
-0.106 2700 
17.7 
SOP 
6014.6390 19.380 
0.022 
-0.034 2490 
17.0 
SOP 
6037.5189 19.318 
0.044 
-0.206 3600 
12.4 
SOP 
6038.5923 19.351 
0.021 
-0.048 3600 
17.7 
SOP 
6040.5504 19.208 
0.032 
-0.031 3600 
14.8 
SOP 
6099.5331 19.266 
0.016 
-0.020 3600 
19.3 
SOP 
6100.5370 19.233 
0.018 
-0.054 3600 
19.6 
SOP 
6101.4251 19.233 
0.024 
-0.016 3600 
16.1 
SOP 
6102.5506 19.273 
0.018 
-0.063 3600 
19.7 
SOP 
6123.4243 19.274 
0.027 
0.028 3600 
13.5 
SOP 
6124.5103 19.327 
0.028 
-0.008 3600 
15.4 
SOP 
6125.5146 19.348 
0.019 
-0.020 3600 
16.9 
SOP 
6155.4268 19.430 
0.012 
0.051 2700 
10.0 
HAR 
6156.4254 19.371 
0.008 
0.002 2700 
15.2 
HAR 
6157.4150 19.308 
0.011 
0.029 2700 
13.7 
HAR 
6158.4134 19.322 
0.016 
0.033 2700 
8.6 
HAR 
6159.3891 19.324 
0.011 
0.019 2700 
12.0 
HAR 
KOI-889: 
6155.5647 -63.682 
0.047 
0.052 1400 
2.3 
HAR 
6159.5726 -65.177 
0.089 
-0.258 
700 
1.1 
HAR 
6160.5219 -64.940 
0.029 
-0.155 3600 
12.2 
SOP 
6161.4375 -64.736 
0.034 
-0.033 3600 
11.1 
SOP 
6162.5235 -64.390 
0.032 
-0.202 3600 
10.1 
SOP 
6163.4458 -64.154 
0.036 
0.099 2716 
9.4 
SOP 
6182.3935 -63.709 
0.033 
-0.075 3600 
13.4 
SOP 
6184.4300 -62.995 
0.047 
-0.099 3600 
7.1 
SOP 
6185.3837 -65.137 
0.027 
-0.012 3600 
12.3 
SOP 
6191.3641 -63.649 
0.045 
-0.088 3600 
11.8 
SOP 
6192.3927 -63.011 
0.040 
0.107 3600 
12.2 
SOP 
 * : bisector spans; associated error bars are twice those of RVs. 
 †: signal-to-noise ratio per pixel at 550 nm. 
 ‡: instrument used: SOP for SOPHIE, HAR for HARPS-N. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 3 . List of free parameters and their priors used to model the data.</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> http://archive.stsci.edu/kepler/data search/search.php</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>−160</head><p>Interstellar extinction E(B − V) 0.16 ± 0.03 0.22 +0.04</p><p>Planetary physical parameters from combined analysis:</p><p>0.060 ± 0.011 0.034 ± 0.002</p><p>0.68 ± 0.09 9.9 ± 0.5 Planet radius R p [R Jup ]</p><p>1.32 ± 0.14 1.03 ± 0.06 Planet density ρ p [g cm <ref type="bibr">−3 ]</ref> 0.37 ± 0.13 11 ± 2 Planetary equilibrium temperature at a-distance T p, a (K) 1250 ± 120 850 ± 40 Planetary equilibrium temperature at periastron T p, per (K) 1450 ± 150 1300 ± 60 Planetary equilibrium temperature at apoastron T p, apo (K) 1100 ± 110 680 ± 30</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Almenara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deeg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aigrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">506</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">337</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Homeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Freytag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IAU Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">235</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baranne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">669</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batalha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Benítez-Llambay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beaugé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Boisse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eggenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">523</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bonomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">538</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">96</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">728</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Basri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">736</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queloz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IAU Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Udry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">505</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">853</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bonomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Latham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Esquerdo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bruntt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bedding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-O</forename><surname>Quirion</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">405</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1907</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">221</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Claret</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">441</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Claret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hauschildt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Witte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Coì On</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Morehead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">546</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">342</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cosentino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lovis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SPIE proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page">8446</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Covino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Esposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1304.0005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sz</forename><surname>Csizmadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Th</forename><surname>Pasternacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dreyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Desidera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sozzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bonomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1302.3093</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Damiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deleuil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">551</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dobbs-Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mardling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">610</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">464</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ehrenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-M</forename><surname>Lagrange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Espinosa Lara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rieutord</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">547</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Photometric and Spectroscopic Binary Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Etzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">642</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Charbonneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">766</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilliland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaplin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dunham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ehrenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">527</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Désert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">516</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Collier Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caldwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">713</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">408</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1758</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kipping</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">730</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kostov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hinse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1210.3850</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuchner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lecar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">574</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lagarde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Decressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Charbonnel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">543</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">77</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mamajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>American Institute</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Matsumura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rasio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Matsumura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rasio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">725</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">738</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pepe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Galland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">632</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Perruchot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kohler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SPIE proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page">70140</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bouchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">528</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bonomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hébrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">536</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moutou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">545</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Santerne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fressin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Díaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MNRAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1277</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A&amp;A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tegmark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Blanton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103501</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Piskunov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A&amp;AS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">595</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ApJS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">141</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1001.2010</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
