<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric reconnaissance of the habitable-zone Earth-sized planets orbiting TRAPPIST-1</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-02-06">6 Feb 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Julien</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth, Atmospheric and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Tech-nology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>77 Massachusetts Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hannah</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wakeford</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Astrophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Exeter</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Physics Building, Stocker Road, Devon</addrLine>
									<postCode>EX4 4QL</postCode>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Space Telescope Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3700 San Martin Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nikole</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Space Telescope Science Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3700 San Martin Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>21218</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laetitia</forename><surname>Delrez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Astrophysics Group, Cavendish Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>19 J J Thomson Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB3 0HE</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michaël</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Space sciences, Technologies and Astrophysics Research (STAR) Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Lì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Selsis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire d&apos;astrophysique de Bordeaux, Univ. Bordeaux, CNRS, B18N, allée Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>33615</postCode>
									<settlement>Pessac</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jérémy</forename><surname>Leconte</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire d&apos;astrophysique de Bordeaux, Univ. Bordeaux, CNRS, B18N, allée Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>33615</postCode>
									<settlement>Pessac</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brice-Olivier</forename><surname>Demory</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Space and Habitability</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bern</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sidlerstrasse 5, CH-3012</addrLine>
									<settlement>Bern, Switzer</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emeline</forename><surname>Bolmont</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Astrophysics Division of CEA de Saclay</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Orme des Merisiers, Bat 709</addrLine>
									<postCode>91191</postCode>
									<settlement>Gif sur Yvette</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vincent</forename><surname>Bourrier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Observatoire de lUniversité de Genève</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>51 chemin des Maillettes</addrLine>
									<postCode>1290</postCode>
									<settlement>Sauverny</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burgasser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Astrophysics and Space Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093</postCode>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Space and Habitability</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bern</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sidlerstrasse 5, CH-3012</addrLine>
									<settlement>Bern, Switzer</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emmanuël</forename><surname>Jehin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Space sciences, Technologies and Astrophysics Research (STAR) Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Lì ege</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Allée du 6 Août 19C, 4000Lì ege</addrLine>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Susan</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lederer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">NASA Johnson Space Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2101 NASA, 77058</postCode>
									<settlement>Parkway, Houston</settlement>
									<region>Texas</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Astrophysics Group, Imperial College London, Blackett Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Prince Consort Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>SW7 2AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Vlada Stamenkovi´cStamenkovi´c</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91109</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff14">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Geological and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91125</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff15">
								<orgName type="department">School of Physics &amp; Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Birmingham</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Edgbaston</addrLine>
									<postCode>B15 2TT</postCode>
									<settlement>Birmingham</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric reconnaissance of the habitable-zone Earth-sized planets orbiting TRAPPIST-1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-02-06">6 Feb 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>13,14 &amp; Amaury H. M. J. Triaud 15 * These authors contributed equally to this work.1</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Seven temperate Earth-sized exoplanets readily amenable for atmospheric studies transit the nearby ultra-cool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1 1, 2. Their atmospheric regime is unknown and could range from extended primordial hydrogen-dominated to depleted atmospheres 3-6. Hydrogen in particular is a powerful greenhouse gas that may prevent the habitability of inner planets while enabling the habitability of outer ones 6-8. An atmosphere largely dominated by hydrogen, if cloud-free, should yield prominent spectroscopic signatures in 2 the near-infrared detectable during transits. Observations of the innermost planets ruled out such signatures 9. However, the outermost planets are more likely to have sustained such a Neptune-like atmosphere 10, 11. Here, we report observations for the four planets within or near the system&apos;s &quot;Habitable Zone&quot; (HZ)-the circumstellar region where liquid water could exist on a planetary surface 12-14. These planets do not exhibit prominent spectroscopic signatures at near-infrared wavelengths either, which rules out cloud-free hydrogen-dominated atmospheres for TRAPPIST-1 d, e and f with significance of 8, 6 and 4σ, respectively. Such an atmosphere is instead not excluded for planet g. As high-altitude clouds and hazes are not expected in hydrogen-dominated atmospheres around planets with such insolation 15, 16 , these observations further support their terrestrial and potentially habitable nature. We observed transits of TRAPPIST-1 planets d, e, f, and g with four visits of the Hubble Space Telescope (HST). Each of the visits contained two planetary transits (Figure 1), planets d and f in visits 1 (4 December 2016) and 3 (9 January 2017), and planets e and g in visits 2 (29 December 2016) and 4 (10 January 2017). The observations were conducted using the &apos;forward&apos; scanning mode with the near-infrared (1.1-1.7µm) G141 grism on the wide-field camera 3 (WFC3) instrument (see Methods). We capitalized on the frequency of the transit events in the TRAPPIST-1 system to select observation windows encompassing transits from two different planets, thereby optimizing the time allocation. The time sensitivity of these observations (TRAPPIST-1&apos;s visibility window closing in January 2017) combined with our 3 &quot;multiple-transit-per-visit&quot; approach constrained us to perform exposures when HST crossed through the South-Atlantic Anomaly (SAA). Visits 1, 3, and 4 contain SAA crossing events which forces HST into GYRO mode, where its fine pointing ability is lost. The loss of fine pointing during and following the SAA crossing events cause the spectral position on the detector to change over time. In addition, during the SAA crossing a greater number of cosmic ray hits are introduced to the observations/exposures. We use the IMA output files from the CalWF3 pipeline and correct for this by cross-correlating each spectral read in the individual exposures and interpolating (see Methods). The raw light curves present primarily ramp-like systematics on the scale of HST orbit-induced instrumental settling discussed in previous WFC3 studies 17-19 (Figure 1). We chose here to not discard the first orbit of each visit-which is affected by larger systematics-but rather to develop a holistic systematic model allowing us to account for the time-dependent effects observed across the orbits of a visit 19, 20 to prevent reducing the observation baseline (see Methods). Despite the SAA crossing events in three of our visits, we mostly achieve per-orbit/visit precisions on par with what was achieved for the May 4th, 2016 observations of planets b and c. Summing over the entire WFC3 spectral range, we derived a &quot;white&quot; light curve across WFC3/G141&apos;s bandpass and reached an averaged SDNR (Standard Deviation of the Normalized Residuals) of 220 part per million (p.p.m.) over 21 of the 23 orbits (two orbits were heavily affected by the SAA crossing, see Methods), which is 1.5× the photon noise limit. We reduced, 4 corrected for instrumental systematics, and analyzed the data using independent methods presented in previous studies 9, 19, 21, 22. The independent analyses conducted by subgroups of our team yield consistent results, which we report below. We first analyzed the white light curves to measure transit depths and timings for comparison with previous observations. In retrieving these parameters, we treated each visit separately and simultaneously fitted for the two transits in each visit while accounting for instrumental sys-tematics following Ref. 9. Due to the reduced phase coverage of HST observations, we fixed the system&apos;s parameters to the values reported in the literature 1 while estimating the transit times and depths. However, we let the band-integrated limb-darkening coefficients 9 (LDCs) and the orbital inclinations 1 float under the control of priors, to propagate their uncertainties on the transit depth and time estimates with which they may be correlated. We report the transit depth and time of transit center estimates in Table 1. We note that the transit depth of planet d during visit 3 is poorly constrained and significantly affected by a 20-pixel long drift of the spectrum over the detector due to SAA crossing at the beginning of the orbit covering this transit. Although the effect of SAA crossing-and of the resulting GYRO mode-can be corrected if it occurs either during an orbit, or at its end, they cannot be corrected with high precision if the crossing occurs at the very beginning of an orbit. Beside this transit depth, all others are in agreement, within 2σ, with the values reported in the literature 1. We reach a precision of ∼40 sec on the transit timings for all but the transit of planet e during visit 4, for which neither the ingress or the egress of the planet&apos;s transit is recorded. 5 We then analyzed the light curves in 10 spectroscopic channels (1.15-1.65 µm), fitting for wavelength-dependent transit depths, instrumental systematics, and stellar baseline levels. We use the wavelength-dependent priors on the LDCs reported in Ref. 9. Our pipelines lead to an average SDNR of 520 p.p.m. per 112-second exposure (see Methods) on the spectrophotometric time series split in 10 channels (resolution = λ/∆λ = 33). We derived the transmission spectra of planets e and f jointly from visits 2 and 4 and visits 1 and 3, respectively. Due to increased scatter and cosmic ray hits during the SAA passes we were unable to derive a transmission spectrum from visit 3 for planet d or from visit 4 for planet g and used, thus only visit 1 and visit 2, respectively. The resulting transmission spectra are shown in Figure 2. The individual transmission spectra show no significant features. A comparison to aerosol-free versions of H 2-dominated atmospheres like those of the Solar System giant planets allow us to rule out such atmospheres at 8, 6, and 4 σ for TRAPPIST-1 d, e, and f respectively. The current data results in only a 2-σ confidence level for planet g, which is not significant enough to rule out this scenario for the planet. As for planets b and c 9 , many alternative atmospheric scenarios are consistent with the data such as H 2 ON N 2-, or CO 2-dominated atmospheres (shown respectively in blue, green, and grey in Figure 2), tenuous atmospheres composed of a variety of chemical species 3-6, 23 , or atmospheres dominated by aerosols 16. The consistency of HST/WFC3&apos;s transit depth estimates with those of Spitzer/IRAC/4.5µm 1 implies the lack of significant absorption features between the two different spectral ranges covered 24 , thereby further suggesting the absence of clear H 2-dominated atmospheres. 6 Hydrogen is a powerful greenhouse gas, and its presence in significant amounts in an atmosphere therefore affects a planet&apos;s habitability. The predominance of atmospheric hydrogen shapes the inner and outer edge of the Habitable Zone (HZ) 6, 8-the circumstellar region where water could stay liquid on a planetary surface 12-14. While a significant amount of H 2 could prevent the atmospheres of TRAPPIST-1&apos;s outer planets to freeze, it would lead to high surface temperatures and pressures for the inner planets that are incompatible with liquid water. In order to be habitable, the latter must therefore have lost most of their atmospheric hydrogen or have never accreted/outgassed significant amounts of hydrogen in the first place 6. Given the irradiation levels experienced by the Earth-sized planets in TRAPPIST-1&apos;s HZ, theory suggests that the probability to form aerosols in a hydrogen-rich atmosphere at the pressures probed by the transmission observations presented here is low 15, 16. If exact, aerosol formation theories thus allow us to conclude that TRAPPIST-1 d, e, f, and g do not harbor a hydrogen-dominated atmosphere and are terrestrial and potentially habitable. The next milestone in the characterization of the TRAPPIST-1 planet atmospheres require spectroscopic measurements that enable the identification of aerosols-via, e.g., attenua-tion signatures in the planets&apos; transmission spectra 25-and atmospheres with larger mean molecular weights. This milestone will be possible with the next generation of observatories 2, 26, 27 , notably the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). As the exploration of &quot;habitable-zone&quot; and &quot;temperate&quot; exoplanet atmospheres is initiated 7 over the next decade, a new light will be progressively shed on the concept of the &quot;habitable zone&quot;. This important concept is currently poorly constrained because its dependence to key parameters such as the host star type and the planet orbital configuration (incl. tidal locking) have not been mapped with the current sample at hand-the Solar System planets. New perspectives from configurations vastly different from those found in the Solar System will therefore be pivotal to improve our understanding of a planet habitability and refine the concept of habitable zone 28. 8 1. Gillon, M. et al. Seven temperate terrestrial planets around the nearby ultracool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1. Nature (2017). 2. Gillon, M. et al. Temperate Earth-sized planets transiting a nearby ultracool dwarf star.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Research</head><label></label><figDesc>Council under the FP/2007-2013 ERC Grant Agreement n 336480, and from the ARC grant for Concerted Research Actions, financed by the Wallonia-Brussels Federation. B.-O.D. acknowledges support from the Swiss National Science Foundation (PP00P2-163967). This work was also partially supported by a grant from the Simons Foundation (PI Queloz, grant number 327127). This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (grant agreement No. 679030/WHIPLASH). V.B. acknowledges the financial support of the SNSF. We thank D. Taylor, K. Stevenson, N. Reid, and K. Sembach for their assistance in the planning, execution, and/or analysis of our observations. J.d.W., H.R.W., and N.K.L. thank also the Howards-Lewis Team and F. Dory for their support and insightful contributions during the data-processing phase of this work. Author Contributions J.d.W. and N.K.L. led the management of the survey. J.d.W. planned the obser- vations. J.d.W and H.R.W. led the data reduction and analysis with the support of N.K.L., L.D., M.G., and B.-O.D. J.d.W. led the data interpretation with the support of H.R.W., N.K.L., V.S., J.L., J.E.O., and F.S. Every author contributed to write the manuscript and/or the HST proposal behind these observations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The MCMC software used by M.G. to analyze independently the photometric data is a custom Fortran 90 code that can be obtained upon request. Data Availability Statement The data that support the plots within this paper and other findings of this study are available on the Mikulski Archive for Space Telescopes (Link to TRAPPIST-1 observations)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Hubble/WFC3 white-light curves of the four TRAPPIST-1 habitable-zone planets-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Transmission spectra of TRAPPIST-1 d, e, f, and g compared to synthetic H 2 -, H 2 O-,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Methods HST WFC3 Observations. We observed the transits of TRAPPIST-1 d, e, f, and g over the course of four visits-composed respectively of 7, 5, 6, and 5 orbits-each containing two of the planetary transits. Visits 1 and 3 contain the transits of planets d and f. Visits 2 and 4 contain the transits of planets e and g. Observations were conducted using HST WFC3 IR G141 grism (1.1- 1.7µm) in forward spatial scanning mode 29 , which leads to less instrumental systematics and should be favored for faint targets 9, 18, 30 . Scans in each visit were conducted at a rate of ≈0.232 pixels per second, with a final spatial scan covering ≈26 pixels (3.38") in the cross-dispersion direction on the detector. Visits 1, 3, and 4 contain observations conducted as HST crossed the South Atlantic Anomaly (SAA). During the SAA, HST enters GYRO mode and loses its fine pointing abil- ity. (We flagged manually each frame acquired in the SAA or in GYRO mode as the relevant keywords in the file headers were not updated for each exposure.) During GYRO mode, the stellar spectrum may drift significantly across the detector array between exposures and even during the course of a single spatial scan. This results in a slanted spectral trace across the scan and detector for these affected exposures (Supplementary</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Effect of SAA crossing on HST/WFC3 exposures. Left: Raw IMA frame correspond-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 :Figure 5 :</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Near-infrared spectrum of TRAPPIST-1 as observed with HST/WFC3/G141. The</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Hubble/WFC3 spectrophotometry of the four TRAPPIST-1 habitable-zone planets-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>. 17 . Deming, D. et al. Infrared Transmission Spectroscopy of the Exoplanets HD 209458b and</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>XO-1b Using the Wide Field Camera-3 on the Hubble Space Telescope. Astrophys. J. 774, 

95 (2013). 1302.1141. 

18. Kreidberg, L. et al. Clouds in the atmosphere of the super-Earth exoplanet GJ1214b. Nature 

505, 69-72 (2014). 1401.0022. 

19. Wakeford, H. R., Sing, D. K., Evans, T., Deming, D. &amp; Mandell, A. Marginalizing In-

strument Systematics in HST WFC3 Transit Light Curves. Astrophys. J. 819, 10 (2016). 

1601.02587. 

20. Wakeford, H. R. et al. HST PanCET program: A Cloudy Atmosphere for the Promising 

JWST Target WASP-101b. Astrophys. J. 835, L12 (2017). 1701.00843. 

21. Gillon, M. et al. The TRAPPIST survey of southern transiting planets. I. Thirty eclipses of 

the ultra-short period planet WASP-43 b. Astron. Astrophys. 542, A4 (2012). 1201.2789. 

22. Demory, B.-O. et al. Hubble Space Telescope search for the transit of the Earth-mass 

exoplanet α Centauri B b. Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc. 450, 2043-2051 (2015). 1503. 

07528. 

23. Leconte, J., Forget, F. &amp; Lammer, H. On the (anticipated) diversity of terrestrial planet 

atmospheres. Experimental Astronomy 40, 449-467 (2015). 

24. Sing, D. K. et al. A continuum from clear to cloudy hot-Jupiter exoplanets without primor-

dial water depletion. Nature 529, 59-62 (2016). 1512.04341. 25. Wakeford, H. R. &amp; Sing, D. K. Transmission spectral properties of clouds for hot Jupiter 

exoplanets. Astron. Astrophys. 573, A122 (2015). 1409.7594. 

26. Barstow, J. K. &amp; Irwin, P. G. J. Habitable worlds with JWST: transit spectroscopy of the 

TRAPPIST-1 system?. Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc. 461, L92-L96 (2016). 1605.07352. 

27. Morley, C. V., Kreidberg, L., Rustamkulov, Z., Robinson, T. &amp; Fortney, J. J. Observing the 

Atmospheres of Known Temperate Earth-sized Planets with JWST. Astrophys. J. 850, 121 

(2017). 1708.04239. 

28. Zsom, A. A Population-based Habitable Zone Perspective. Astrophys. J. 813, 9 (2015). 

1510.06885. 

Acknowledgements This work is based on observations made with the NASA/ESA Hubble Space 

Telescope that were obtained at the Space Telescope Science Institute, which is operated by the Associa-

tion of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc. These observations are associated with program GO-

14873 (principal investigator J.d.W.), support for which was provided by NASA through a grant from the 

Space Telescope Science Institute. H.R.W. acknowledges funding from the European Research Council 

(ERC) under the European Unions Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) / ERC grant agree-

ment no. 336792, and funding under the STScI Giacconi Fellowship. This work was partially conducted 

while on appointment to the NASA Postdoctoral Program at Goddard Space Flight Center, adminis-

tered by USRA through a contract with NASA. L.D. acknowledges support from the Gruber Foundation 

Fellowship. E.J. and M.G. are Research Associates at the Belgian Fonds (National) de la Recherche Sci-

entifique (F.R.S.-F.N.R.S.). The research leading to these results has received funding from the European </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 : Transit depths and timings for program HST-GO-14873.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>TRAPPIST-1 d 
TRAPPIST-1 e 
TRAPPIST-1 f 
TRAPPIST-1 g 

Visit 1 

Transit depth [p.p.m.] 
3984±87 
-
6227±192 
-

Transit timing a 
726.84005±0.00041 
-
726.62108±0.00048 
-

Visit 2 

Transit depth [p.p.m.] 
-
4754±88 
-
7823±133 

Transit timing a 
-
751.87016±0.00036 
-
751.83978±0.00047 

Visit 3 

Transit depth [p.p.m.] 
8066±354 b 
-
6452±172 
-

Transit timing a 
763.28978±0.00055 b 
-
763.44484±0.00049 
-

Visit 4 

Transit depth [p.p.m.] 
-
5005±101 
-
7739±219 b 

Transit timing a 
-
764.06713±0.00176 
-
764.19120±0.00061 b 

a Timings are reported as barycentric Julian date (BJD)/barycentric coordinate time (TBD)-2,457,000. 

b The transits of planets d and g during Visit 3 and Visit 4, respectively, were discarded due to strong system-

atics induced by a large drift of the stellar spectrum (see Methods). </table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seven temperate terrestrial planets around the nearby ultracool dwarf star TRAPPIST-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperate Earth-sized planets transiting a nearby ultracool dwarf star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kepler Planets: A Tale of Evaporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1303.3899</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">775</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planetary Population Synthesis Coupled with Atmospheric Escape: A Statistical View of Evaporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1409.2879</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1411.7412</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extreme Water Loss and Abiotic O2Buildup on Planets Throughout the Habitable Zones of M Dwarfs</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitability of terrestrial-mass planets in the HZ of M Dwarfs -I. H/He-dominated atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mohanty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1601. 05143</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4088" to="4108" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reducing greenhouses and the temperature history of Earth and Mars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen Greenhouse Planets Beyond the Habitable Zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pierrehumbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gaidos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1105.0021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">734</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A combined transmission spectrum of the Earth-sized exoplanets TRAPPIST-1 b and c</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1606.01103</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">537</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Water loss from terrestrial planets orbiting ultracool dwarfs: implications for the planets of TRAPPIST-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bolmont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1605. 00616</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3728</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal Evolution of the High-energy Irradiation and Water Content of TRAPPIST-1 Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bourrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitable Zones around Main Sequence Stars</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kasting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Whitmire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Icarus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards the Minimum Inner Edge Distance of the Habitable Zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zsom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Stamenkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1304.3714</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">778</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Inner Edge of the Habitable Zone for Synchronously Rotating Planets around Low-mass Stars Using General Circulation Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kopparapu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1602.05176</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">819</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Photochemistry in Terrestrial Exoplanet Atmospheres. III. Photochemistry and Thermochemistry in Thick Atmospheres on Super Earths and Mini Neptunes. Astrophys</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>1401.0948</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">784</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermal Emission and Reflected Light Spectra of Super Earths with Flat Transmission Spectra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Morley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1511.01492</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">815</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Considerations for using Spatial Scans with WFC3</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mccullough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mackenty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hubble Space Telescope Near-IR Transmission Spectroscopy of the Super-Earth HD 97658b</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Knutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1403.4602</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">794</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Flat Transmission Spectrum of the Super-Earth GJ1214b from Wide Field Camera 3 on the Hubble Space Telescope</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Berta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1111. 5621</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">747</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">No Thermal Inversion and a Solar Water Abundance for the Hot Jupiter HD 209458b from HST/WFC3 Spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Line</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1605.08810</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Physical Model-based Correction for Charge Traps in the Hubble Space Telescope&apos;s Wide Field Camera 3 Near-IR Detector and Its Applications to Transiting Exoplanets and Brown Dwarfs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1703.01301</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astron. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">243</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1401.6181</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Constraining Exoplanet Mass from Transmission Spectroscopy. Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">342</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1473" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atmospheric Retrieval for Super-Earths: Uniquely Constraining the Atmospheric Composition with Transmission Spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1203.4018</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">753</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mass-radius Relations and Core-envelope Decompositions of Super-Earths and Sub-Neptunes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Verne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1402.4818</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">787</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">173</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
