<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-04T16:11+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">European Planetary Science Congress EPSC Abstracts</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="2012" to="784"/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>EPSC Does the innermost occurrence distribution measure tidal dissipation, reveal a flow of giant planets, or both? S. F. Taylor (1,2) (1) Unemployed, Hong Kong, (2) Participation Worldscope/Global Telescope Science</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The occurrence distribution of the shortest period giant exoplanets as found by Kepler show a drop-off that is a remarkable match to the drop-off expected by taking migration due to tides in the star [9], [6]. We present a comparison that can show the level of tidal dissipation (friction) as a function of the distribution of the ages of the star and planet system, with known dependencies on basic star and planet parameters. Use of this relation enables constraints to be put on the value of the tidal dissipation, constraints that will be improved as the distribution of the ages are determined. For the giant planets, this leads to an unexpectedly low value of tidal dissipation. This overabundance of short period giant planets may be due to a continuing resupply of longer period giant planets migrating into a shorter period pileup, disrupting the presence of smaller planets along the way. Perhaps the occurrence distribution of close Neptune sized planets will better measure the tidal friction, while the distribution of Jupiter sized planets reveals that giant planets are more likely to complete a gradual migration into the star.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introducing Infall versus Q *</head><p>The "hot Jupiter" planets, those giant planets with the shortest periods, have been shown to mostly be tidally migrating to their destruction by merger with their star, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Kepler planet (candidate) occurence distributions from <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> show a drop-off in occurrence at short periods, which have a power law index of 13/3, which <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> show is consitent with tidal migration due to tides on the star, using the equations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The homogeneous Kepler statistics are sufficient to allow us to compare calculated drop-offs as a function of tidal dissipation (friction) Q * to the actual innermost occurrence distributions. We show in <ref type="figure">figure 1</ref> and figure 2 that these distribution give different apparent values of Q * for large and medium planets, which could be explained by proposing a larger inflow of larger planets.</p><p>We find that the tidal migration increases so rapidly with smaller semi-major axis that the initial distribution matters little, so for the initial distribution we simply extend inward the power law that <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> find for the occurrence distribution beyond the drop-off. Though it has long been expected that the process of planet formation would leave a drop off of planets at the shortest period, we find that the ongoing migration erases the inner-most distribution left by planet formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Further Work</head><p>We are currently preparing models where the shift in the drop-off point can be interpreted in relation of tidal dissipation factor Q * versus realistic stellar age distribution for realistic star and planet distributions. Here we use single representative ages and star parameters for the planet masses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Summary and Conclusions</head><p>We compare what the tidal dissipation Q * in the star appears to be when looking at Jupiter and Neptune mass planets. We find a discrepancy that could be better explained by a flow of planets such as proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. This flow could be producing the "pileup" of hot Jupiters. If there is a higher rate of ongoing inward migration of Jupiter mass than of Neptune mass planets, this could explain why we find "too many" hot Jupiters shortly before they merge with the star, without requiring an especially low amount of tidal friction for giant planets. This discrepancy in the apparent value of Q * is the result of the pileup of giant planets. Compared to Neptune mass planets, there is a higher number of short period Jupiter mass planets but a lower number of longer period Jupiter mass planets. Kepler is now finding that the general trend of more smaller radii planets also holds in the short period range as more smaller planets are detected, further emphasizing the anomalous nature of the large number of Jupiter radii short period planets. That the number of short period massive planets is anomalously large is made more clear by how the pattern of more planets at smaller radii in now being observed to continue into the superearth size range at all measurable periods. Another sign of ongoing large planet migration is how the short period large planets are anti-correlated with the presence of other planets further out, but there is no such correlation for smaller short period planets. This suggests that inwardly scattered large planets make their way to the star, disrupting the orbits of smaller planets along the way, but that inwardly scattered midsize planets do not make it to the star. The resulting transient events created by the merger of planets with stars, as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, will provide an important means of quantifying planet migration.  <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>: Comparison of a range of four calculated occurrence distribution drop-offs (dotted lines) with the fit to Kepler planet candidate data (solid line) for large planets, defined as 8 to 32 earth radii or one Jupiter mass. found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> giant radii or mass planets. Calculated infall for four values of stellar tidal dissipation Q * = (10 8.0 , 10 7.5 , 10 7.0 , 10 6.5 ), is based on [3] using solar mass stars taken to be at an age of 4.5 Gigayears, and using the power law of <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> without the inward dropoff as an initial planet fraction (dashed line). sion and assisted in the search for support.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Similar comparison as figure 1 for "medium planets". The fit to Kepler data for 4 to 8 earth radii is shown with calculated infall for 15 earth mass planets and solar mass stars, at an age of 4.5 Gigayears.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>S.F.T. seeks support for continuation of this project, and also seeks participation in exoplanet confirmation projects. S.F.T. is grateful for the sacrifices of family in absence of support. These sacrifices have exceeded what should have been asked of them. We are grateful to those especially supportive members of the astronomy community who have provided discus-</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consequences of the Ejection and Disruption of Giant Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Guillochon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Enrico</forename><surname>Ramirez-Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap.J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">732</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Planet Occurrence within 0.25 AU of Solar-type Stars from Kepler</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1103.2541</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observational Evidence for Tidal Destruction of Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap.J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">698</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1357" to="1366" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Falling Transiting Extrasolar Giant Planets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Levrard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Winisdoerffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chabrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap.J.L&quot;</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">692</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Giannios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spiegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1204.0796</idno>
		<title level="m">Optical and X-Ray Transits from Planet-Star Mergers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Constraining Tidal Dissipation in Stars from The Destruction Rates of Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Penev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1205.1803</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Super-Eccentric Migrating Jupiters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Aristotle</forename><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Boaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">&amp;amp;</forename><surname>Subo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Tremaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ap.J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">750</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Observing the Luminosity Increase and Roche Lobe Overflow of Planet Destruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1009.4221</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planet Distribution Shows Planets Infall To Star After Formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The First Kepler Science Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Moffet Field, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
