<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:45+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The HATNet and HATSouth Exoplanet Surveys</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gáspár</forename><surname>Gáspár´</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08544</postCode>
									<region>NJ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gáspár´a</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Astrophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08544</postCode>
									<region>NJ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The HATNet and HATSouth Exoplanet Surveys</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The Hungarian-made Automated Telescope Network (HATNet) has been in operation since 2003, with the key science goal being the discovery and accurate characterization of transiting extrasolar planets (TEPs) around bright stars. Using six small, 11 cm aperture, fully automated telescopes in Arizona and Hawaii, as of 2017 March, it has discovered and accurately characterized 67 such objects. The HATSouth network of telescopes has been in operation since 2009, using slightly larger, 18 cm diameter optical tubes. It was the first global network of telescopes using identical instrumentation. With three premier sites spread out in longitude (Chile, Namibia, Australia), the HATSouth network permits round-the-clock observations of a 128 square arcdegree swath of the sky at any given time, weather permitting. As of this writing, HATSouth has discovered 36 transiting exoplanets. Many of the altogether ∼100 HAT and HATSouth exoplanets were the first of their kind. They have been important contributors to the rapidly developing field of ex-oplanets, motivating and influencing observational techniques, theoretical studies, and also actively shaping future instrumentation for the detection and characterization of such objects.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HATSouth</head><p>Planning of the HATSouth network (http://hatsouth.org) began in late 2007. The prototype was fully built by the summer of 2008 at Pécel, Hungary. Altogether six "HS 4 " telescope mounts were installed at the respective sites of Las Campanas Observatory (LCO), Chile, the High Energy Spectroscopic Survey (HESS) in Namibia, and Siding Spring Observatory (SSO) in Australia by November 2009. The three sites are close to equally spread in longitude, permitting round-the-clock observations. Each of the HS 4 units (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>), holds four 0.18 m diameter f/2.8 focal ratio telescope tubes on a common mount producing an 8.2 • × 8.2 • FOV on the sky, imaged using four front-side-illuminated 4K×4K CCD cameras and Sloan r filters, to give a pixel scale of 3.7 pixel −1 . The full HATSouth network, with altogether 24 optical tube assemblies, was commissioned in 2010. In periods of good weather we have realized stretches of up to 130 hours of non-stop observations, enabling the discovery of many more long period transiting exoplanet candidates than can be found by any other ground-based transit survey. What distinguishes HATSouth from other wide-field ground-based surveys is the fine pixel scale, greater sensitivity to K and M dwarf host stars, and sensitivity to long period and small radius planets.</p><p>As of March, 2017, the telescopes have opened on ∼ 2300, ∼ 2070, and ∼ 1780 nights from LCO, HESS, and SSO, respectively. Based on weather statistics through 2017, the sites have averaged 7.99 hrs, 7.50 hrs, and 5.48 hrs of useful dark hours per 24 hr time period (here dark refers to the Sun elevation below −12 • ). HATSouth has taken 3.35 million science frames at 4-minute cadence, covering 17% of the Southern sky, yielding light curves for 10 million individual sources with r &lt; 16, and ∼4 million light curves suitable for searching for transit signals. Data reduction is broadly similar to that of HATNet. To date we have identified 1800 transiting planet candidates from the HATSouth data, including approximately 300 with P &gt; 10 days, and 60 with the size of Neptune or smaller. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>From Transit Candidates to Fully Confirmed Planets</head><p>Candidate TEPs from both HATNet and HATSouth undergo spectroscopic and photometric follow-up observations to rule out false positives, confirm those that are planets, and characterize their properties. This is a massive effort, using a plethora of facilities in a coordinated manner.</p><p>Our first follow-up step is to obtain reconnaissance moderate-to high-resolution optical spectra for all candidates. The spectra are used to determine bulk properties of the star, including its radial velocity (RV), effective temperature (T eff ), surface gravity (log g), metallicity and projected equatorial rotation velocity (v sin i). These are used to identify many false positives, such as F stars transited by M dwarf stars, giants that are blended with fainter eclipsing binary stars, or other stellar triple systems. If the star is not excluded by the reconnaissance spectroscopy, it is subject to further follow-up observations. Often the RV precision of the reconnaissance measurements is sufficient to detect the wobble of the star due to the orbital motion of a massive planet. If no RV variation is detected, then additional RV monitoring may be done using a higher precision facility. More than 3000 candidates have been subject to spectroscopic follow-up, using 16 instruments altogether. (These numbers are for HATNet and HATSouth combined).</p><p>In parallel to and coordinated with spectroscopy, we also perform photometric follow-up to have a higher precision light curve for determining the system parameters, and to rule out some blended eclipsing binary false positives through higher spatial resolution observations. A total of 18 facilities have been used for this effort to gather follow-up light curves for more than 1100 candidates. We also regularly perform high-spatial resolution imaging for candidates (using AO systems, speckle imaging, and lucky imaging) to search for close stellar companions at separations less than an arcsecond.</p><p>Occasionally, additional types of follow-up are performed. This may include spectroscopic observations taken through transit to measure the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2015</ref>), or in the case of very rapidly rotating stars, to confirm the planet via Doppler tomography (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Hartman et al. 2015a;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2017</ref>).</p><p>For HAT and HATSouth, altogether, we have obtained at least some follow-up observations for ∼3200 of the 4200 candidates, confirmed ∼ 140 as substellar objects, and concluded that ∼ 2300 are false positives or false alarms. The remaining candidates require more follow-up observations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Highlights</head><p>We have been fortunate to contribute some of the exciting discoveries to the booming field of extrasolar planets. The physical parameters of these exoplanets span a very wide range, as shown in e.g. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>, exhibiting the mass-radius diagram of those ∼435 exoplanets with well measured masses and radii, and with contributions from selected projects color-coded. Some of the highlights from the HATNet and HATSouth surveys include:</p><p>HAT-P-2b: the first super-massive hot Jupiter with both mass (9.09 ± 0.24 M J ) and radius (1.16 ± 0.073 R J ) measured accurately ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bakos et al. 2007</ref>). HAT-P-7b: a short period hot Jupiter, discovered before the launch of the Kepler mission, falling in the field of Kepler, and later becoming one of the best studied exoplanets ( <ref type="bibr">Pál et al. 2008)</ref>. It was the first planet found on a retrograde orbit ( <ref type="bibr">Winn et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Narita et al. 2009</ref>). HAT-P-11b: the first transiting Neptune discovered by a ground-based survey ( <ref type="bibr">Bakos et al. 2010)</ref>. It is also the first Neptune with an orbital tilt measurement ( <ref type="bibr">Winn et al. 2010</ref>) and water vapor detection ( <ref type="bibr">Fraine et al. 2014</ref>). HAT-P-13b: the first transiting planet in a double-planet system with a closed orbit for the outer planet ( <ref type="bibr">Bakos et al. 2009</ref>). This system proved to be a rich dynamical laboratory, constraining the interior structure of the inner planet ( <ref type="bibr">Batygin et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Buhler et al. 2016</ref>). HAT-P-15b: with P = 10.3 days, was the first TEP with P &gt; 10 days found by a ground-based survey ( <ref type="bibr">Kovács et al. 2010)</ref>. Along with HAT-P-17b ( <ref type="bibr">Howard et al. 2012</ref>), these planets were important in realizing that the inflation of hot Jupiters is related to the infalling flux from their host star. HAT-P-26b: was the second transiting Neptune-sized planet found by a wide field ground-based survey <ref type="bibr">(Hartman et al. 2011a</ref>). It remains one of the few Neptunesized bodies for which transmission spectroscopy was carried out, hinting at some properties of its atmosphere <ref type="bibr">(Stevenson et al. 2016</ref>). HAT-P-32b and -33b: with R ≈ 2R J are amongst the largest radius planets ever found ( <ref type="bibr">Hartman et al. 2011b</ref>).</p><p>HAT-P-44b, -45b, and -46b: are rare multi-planet transiting hot Jupiter systems ( <ref type="bibr">Hartman et al. 2014</ref>). HAT-P-47b and -48b: are two of the lowest density planets ever found ( ¯ ρ ≈ 0.1g cm −3 ), and are members of the very rare class of short-period planets with masses intermediate between Neptune and Saturn ( <ref type="bibr">Bakos et al. 2016</ref>). HAT-P-49b: orbits one of the highest mass (M ≈ 1.54M ) host stars found to date <ref type="bibr">(Bieryla et al. 2014</ref>). HAT-P-54b: was the first ground-based transiting planet detection confirmed by</p><p>Kepler/K2 ( <ref type="bibr">Bakos et al. 2015a</ref>). HAT-P-57b: the fastest spinning host star (v sin i = 100 km s −1 ) with a transiting planet ( <ref type="bibr">Hartman et al. 2015a</ref>). This was confirmed via Doppler tomography. HAT-P-67b: is an ultra low-density planet (R ≈ 2.1 R J , M &lt; 0.59 M J ) around a rapidly rotating F subgiant, confirmed via Doppler tomography ( <ref type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2017</ref>). HATS-6b: one of only two transiting giant planets confirmed around an M dwarf star ( <ref type="bibr">Hartman et al. 2015b</ref>). HATS-7b and HATS-8b: were, respectively, the third and fourth transiting SuperNeptunes found by a ground-based survey ( <ref type="bibr">Bakos et al. 2015b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bayliss et al. 2015</ref>). HATS-9b: <ref type="bibr">(Brahm et al. 2015</ref>), at t = 10.8 ± 1.5 Gyr, is the oldest well characterized hot Jupiter, where the age of the host star is known to better than 20% precision. HATS-14b: a hot Jupiter transiting a late G dwarf star ( <ref type="bibr">Mancini et al. 2015)</ref>, which, unlike the other such objects known, has a high obliquity ( <ref type="bibr">Zhou et al. 2015</ref>). HATS-17b: with P = 16.3 days, is the longest period TEP discovered by a ground-based transit survey to date <ref type="bibr">(Brahm et al. 2016</ref>). HATS-18b: an extremely short period (P = 0.84 day) transiting Super-Jupiter which has tidally spun up its host star, enabling a strong constraint on the tidal quality factor of the star ( <ref type="bibr">Penev et al. 2016</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future Prospects</head><p>Both HATNet and HATSouth are currently running with full force. They are providing high-precision high-cadence photometric measurements for millions of stars, which can shed light on the long term variability of objects, such as, for example, peculiar stars ( <ref type="bibr">Boyajian et al. 2016)</ref>, or the secular variations of eclipsing binaries with period changes (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Tylenda et al. 2011</ref>). They are yielding thousands of transiting planet candidates, which are actively followed up by an arsenal of telescopes and instruments. Finally, they are yielding transiting planets at a high rate.</p><p>Once the Transiting Extrasolar Survey Satellite (TESS) is in operation (est. 2018), all these data components (light curves, transiting exoplanet candidates, and confirmed exoplanets) from HATNet and HATSouth will prove extremely useful. TESS will produce a high precision light curve for most bright stars on the sky, with a typical time-span of 27 days and cadence of 30 minutes. The spatial resolution of TESS will be twice as coarse as HATNet, and five times worse than HATSouth. Data from HATNet and HATSouth will be instrumental in revealing blends; systems that mimick transiting exoplanets, but are blends of eclipsing binaries with brighter stars. Archival and follow-up data from the HAT surveys will offer further synergies with TESS: the combined data-stream will enable the detection and characterization of transiting planets that would otherwise be undetected in the individual survey data, and additional astrophysics offered by the knowledge on the long term variability of the sources. Many of the TESS planet candidates will already have follow-up observations through the HAT follow-up efforts. Finally, experience from these wide-field ground based surveys will be directly carried over into scientific investigations with TESS.</p><p>In parallel to TESS, we anticipate that a new ground-based survey, called HATPI, will come online. HATPI will ultimately use an array of 63 lenses and CCDs to image the entire sky above 30 degrees (1 π steradian) on a mosaic, every 30 seconds, whenever conditions permit, yielding better than 3 mmag photometric precision at 30 s cadence for stars at r ≈ 10. Construction of HATPI at Las Campanas Observatory is under way. The massive, high-precision data from HATPI will complement TESS, and will also offer remarkable synergies with the Gaia space mission.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Two of the HATNet telescope units at Mauna Kea, on top of the Submillimeter Array hangar building. Each clamshell dome hosts a horseshoe mount, a 11 cm diameter lens, and a 4K × 4K front-illuminated CCD. The systems are fully automated, and have been running since 2004. The Subaru (left), Keck (center) and IRTF (right) telescopes are in the background.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 One of the HATSouth telescope units at Las Campanas Observatory, Chile. The diameter of the yellow optical tubes is 18 cm. Each optics is coupled with a 4K × 4K front-illuminated CCD. The twin Magellan telescopes are in the background.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 The mass-radius diagram of transiting extrasolar planets, as of 2017 March, color-coded by the projects. HATNet and HATSouth have contributed exoplanets spanning a wide range of masses and radii, along with other physical properties.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wide-Field Millimagnitude Photometry with the HAT: A Tool for Extrasolar Planet Detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Noyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kovács</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="277" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">System Description and First Light Curves of the Hungarian Automated Telescope, an Autonomous Observatory for Variability Search</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G ´ A</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lázár</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Papp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sári P Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="974" to="987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">HD 147506b: A Supermassive Planet in an Eccentric Orbit Transiting a Bright Star</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G ´ A</forename><surname>Bakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kovács</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">670</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="832" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
