<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/ResearchCloud/Projects/ExoPlanets/notebooks/grobid/grobid-0.5.2/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.2" ident="GROBID" when="2019-01-22T13:45+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">EXTREMOPHILE LIFE-FORM SURVEY ON ROCKY EXOPLANETS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-05-30">May 30, 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Madhu</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jyoti Nivas College</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>-560095</postCode>
									<settlement>Bengaluru</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jagadeesh</forename></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jyoti Nivas College</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>-560095</postCode>
									<settlement>Bengaluru</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">EXTREMOPHILE LIFE-FORM SURVEY ON ROCKY EXOPLANETS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-05-30">May 30, 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Draft version Preprint typeset using L A T E X style AASTeX6 v. 1.0</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Exoplanets</term>
					<term>Habitability</term>
					<term>Extremophiles</term>
					<term>Earth-like planets</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Search for different life-forms elsewhere is the fascinating area of research in astrophysics and astrobi-ology. Nearly 3500 exoplanets are discovered according to NASA exoplanet archive database. Earth Similarity Index (ESI) is defined as the geometrical mean of radius, density, escape velocity and surface temperature, ranging from 0 (dissimilar to Earth) to 1(Earth). In this research, rocky exoplanets that are suitable for rock dependent extremophiles, such as: Chroococcidiopsis and Acarosporamto are chosen, which can potentially survive are considered. The Colonizing Similarity Index (CSI) is introduced and analysed for 1650 rocky exoplanets, CSI is basically representing Earth-like planets that are suitable for rocky extremophiles which can survive in extreme temperatures (i.e. as hot as desert and cold as frozen lands). In this work the in-habitable exoplanets are recognised even for these rocky extremophiles to not potentially survive by using the CSI metric tool.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Extraterrestrial research in recent years is the Holy Grail of current sciences. The space missions like CoRoT and Kepler has directed a huge flow of data from exoplanetary observations, which is maintained by Planetary Habitability Laboratory-Exoplanet catalogue <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(PHL-EC, 2017</ref>). The PHL-EC data of planetary objects, such as: radius, density, escape velocity and surface temperature has been applied as the geometrical mean to a metric tool called ESI, which ranges from 0 (dissimilar to Earth) to 1 (similar to Earth) ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Schulze-Makuch et al., 2011</ref>). This tool helps us to identify the potentially habitable planets (phps) or Earth-like planets from the observed physical parameters of extra-solar systems. The exoplanetary composition is basically classified into rocky and gas giants. For planets to be rocky the mass ranges from 0.1 to 10 Earth masses and radius is of the order 0.5 to 2 Earth radii ( <ref type="bibr">Safonova et al., 2016)</ref>. Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kashyap et al. (2017)</ref> have introduced a new technique to find the surface temperature of exoplanets and formulated the Mars Similarity Index (MSI) for search of extremophile life-forms in Mars-like conditions. In this current work, we focus on rocky exoplanets in Earth-like conditions, by varying the surface temperature parameter, which is suitable for the Extremophile life-forms to reproduce and grow. Hence the Colonizing Similarity Index (CSI) is formulated and analysed for 1650 rocky exoplanets. The structure of the paper is as follows, the extremophiles and ESI are discussed in section 2 and section 3 respectively. Section 4 illustrates the CSI analysis, followed by section 5 which contains the discussion and conclusion part of the work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">EXTREMOPHILES</head><p>Extremophiles are those microbes which love extreme environments such as, very high and low temperatures. Based on the observations from the evolution of earth, the limitations of survival characteristics are defined, and compared with conditions of exoplanets ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hegde et al., 2013</ref>). The targeted extremophiles in this paper are Chroococcidiopsis and Acarosporamto, whose growth depends on rocky surface ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cumbers and Rothschild, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Nash et al., 2001</ref>). Chroococcidiopsis is a micro-organism that is tested for survival capability in outer space. The different kinds of tests performed on Chroococcidiopsis are namely: low Earth orbit, impact event, planetary ejection, atmospheric re-entry, and simulated conditions. ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cockell et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Billi, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baqu et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Cockell et al., 2011</ref>). In 2014 an Expose astrobiology lab was launched and mounted on the International space station <ref type="bibr">(Gerda Horneck et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr">, Karen Olsson-Francis et al., 2013</ref>). According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Nash et al., 2001 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Onofri et al., 2015</ref> Acarosporamto, a lichenized fungal genus survived in this Martian condition outside Earth. The well-studied indexing introduced in 2011 by <ref type="bibr">Schulze-Makuch et al., and recently Kashyap et al. 2017</ref>, has derived ESI from the threshold value (V) in the similarity scale for each quantity, which is mathematically expressed as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">V = 1 − x 0 − x x 0 + x w x . (1)</formula><p>where x is the planetary property of the exoplanet, W X is the weight exponent and x 0 is the reference to Earth in ESI.</p><p>Assuming the threshold value of V=0.8 ( 80 % similar to the reference) and defining the physical limits xa and xb as the variation with respect to x0 (ie, xa¡x0¡ xb), the weight exponents are computed as lower wa and upper wb limits, which is expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">w a = ln V ln 1 − x 0 −x a x 0 +x a , w b = ln V ln 1 − x b −x 0 x b +x 0 ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>The average weight can be written as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">w x = √ w a × w b .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Hence the Earth Similarity Index can be obtained as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E SI x = 1 − x − x 0 x + x 0 w x ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where, x is the physical parameter of the exoplanet, such as: radius (R), bulk density (ρ), escapes velocity (V e ) and surface temperature (T s ), whereas x 0 is with reference to Earth, and w x is the weight exponent. These parameters are expressed in EU (Earth Units), while the surface temperature is represented as Kelvin (K). ESI is basically classified into interior ESI and surface ESI, which are mathematically represented as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">E SI I = E SI R × E SI ρ ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>and surface ESI is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E SI S = E SI T × E SI V e ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where E SI R , E SI ρ , E SI T &amp; E SI V e are Earth Similarity Indices, calculated for radius, density, surface temperature and escape velocity, respectively. The global ESI is their geometric mean:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">E SI = E SI I × E SI S .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>From the ESI analysis, 44 potentially habitable planets were identified, keeping Mars as the threshold with ESI value 0.73.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">COLONIZING SIMILARITY INDEX (CSI)</head><p>CSI is basically representing Earth-like planets that is suitable for rocky extremophiles that can survive in extreme temperatures (i.e. as hot as desert and cold as frozen lands). Using equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">(2)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(3)</ref>, the upper and lower weight exponents are chosen for radius, density and escape velocity, similar to ESI (Schulze-Makuch et al., 2011). Mckay, 2014, re-defined the surface temperature in the range 258 -395 K for extremophiles to reproduce and grow. The CSI average weight exponents are calculated for rocky exoplanets in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>.</p><p>Here, EU = Earth Units, where Earths radius is 6371 km, density is 5.51 g/cm 3 , escape velocity is 11.19 km/s, Revolution is 365.25 days and surface gravity is 9.8 m/s 2 . The main finding in this work is that the weight exponent value of surface temperature is 2.26 for rocky extremophiles to survive, which is found to be lesser than ESI weight exponent value of 5.58 for complex life form to survive <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Schulze-Makuch et al., 2011</ref>). CSI is defined for the rock dependent extremophiles, as the geometrical mean of radius, density, escape velocity and surface temperature of exoplanets, with probabilistic range 0 to 1, where 0 indicates non-survival and 1 represents survival.</p><p>Mathematically, the CSI of each physical parameter is defined similar to ESI, which is where, x is the physical parameter of the exoplanet, such as: radius (R), bulk density (ρ), escapes velocity (V e ) and surface temperature (T s ), whereas x 0 is with reference to Earth, and w x is the weight exponent. These parameters are expressed in EU (Earth Units), while the surface temperature is represented as Kelvin (K). CSI is basically classified into interior CSI and surface CSI, which are mathematically represented as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">CSI x = 1 − x − x 0 x + x 0 w x ,<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">CSI I = CSI R × CSI ρ ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>and surface CSI is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">CSI S = CSI T × CSI V e ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where CSI R , CSI ρ , CSI T &amp; CSI V e are colonizing Similarity Indices, calculated for radius, density, surface temperature and escape velocity, respectively. The global CSI is their geometric mean:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">CSI = CSI I × CSI S .<label>(11)</label></formula><p>The data of radius, density, escape velocity, and surface temperature from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kashyap et al. 2017</ref>, is plugged in to equations 9, 10, 11, 12 along with the weight exponent value of surface temperature, 2.26 (present finding), the CSI values are computed <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 2)</ref>. The entire data table is cataloged and made available online at (Kashyap 2017a).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GRAPHICAL REPRESENTATION OF ROCKY PLANETS USING COLONIZING SIMILARITY INDEX (CSI)</head><p>The CSI threshold is Mars ( 0.79), above which the rocky exoplanets are considered to be potentially habitable for extremophiles (such as: Chroococcidiopsis and Acarosporamto) to reproduce and grow. Earth is the only known rocky planet filled with life, and has been shielded by magnetic field to protect from harmful cosmic radiation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Evans, 1942)</ref>. In order to search life else-where, we have chosen the rocky exoplanets with reference to Earth conditions and the subjects (Such as: Chroococcidiopsis and Acarosporamto) are targeted to study the reproduction and growth with its high tolerance to resist harmful cosmic radiations in the absence of planets magnetic field. Chroococcidiopsis has been selected for the colonizing test on Mars (Expose Mission by Russia) based on its following qualities: can grow on rocks, can produce oxygen, and have tolerance to survive the high energy cosmic radiations <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Billi et al. 2000)</ref>. Acarosporamto is one of the extremophile that has been tested by expose mission for 1.5 years and it has survived the test in space for Mars-like conditions ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Onofri et al., 2015</ref>). According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kashyap et al. 2017</ref>, Mars with ESI value 0.73 was defined as the threshold number for planets to be potentially habitable for complex life forms to survive, whose temperature range was defined from 273 K to 323 K. Approximately 44 potentially habitable planets (phps) was found till date. From the CSI formulation, with the threshold 0.79, it is found that 1552 exoplanets are totally in-habitable with the temperature rage in particular for these extremophiles to survive and 98 could be Phps for extremophiles to survive (provided the other atmospheric conditions are habitable). Presently many works are being performed to prove that Chroococcidiopsis is one of the major candidates for making the red planet green 1 and Russian Expose mission backs up the candidate choices used in this research. Future missions like James-Webber Space Telescope will give us deeper insights to analyze and work on these potentially habitable planets.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Scatter plot between interior CSI and surface CSI: The solid line marked for Mars will be the threshold value for potentially habitable planets</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>kas7890 .astro@gmail.com arXiv:1801.06341v3 [astro-ph.EP] 29 May 2018 3. EARTH SIMILARITY INDEX (ESI)</head><label>kas7890</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . NESI Parametric Table</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Planetary Property 
Ref. Value Weight Exponents 

for CSI 
for CSI 

Mean Radius 
1EU 
0.57 

Bulk Density 
1EU 
1.07 

Escape Velocity 
1EU 
0.70 

Surface Temperature 
288K 
2.26 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 . A sample of calculated CSI</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Names 
Radius Density Temp E. Vel CSI S CSI I CSI 

(EU) 
(EU) 
(K) 
(EU) 

Earth 
1.00 
1.00 
288 
1.00 
1.00 1.00 1.00 

Mars 
0.53 
0.73 
240 
0.45 
0.82 0.76 0.79 

Proxima Cen-b 
1.12 
0.90 
267 
1.06 
0.95 0.94 0.95 

GJ 667Cc 
1.54 
1.05 
288 
1.57 
0.92 0.92 0.92 

Kepler-296 e 
1.48 
1.03 
312 
1.50 
0.93 0.88 0.90 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>I would like to thank Dr. Margarita Safanova former visiting scientist from Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) for all the fruitful discussions. Also a special thanks to Mrs. Vani former (M. Tech Biotechnology) project intern from National Chemical Laboratory (NCL) Pune, for the brief discussions on extremophiles. This research work had made use of PHL-EC, at UPR Arecibo, 2017 http://phl.upr.edu/projects/habitable-exoplanets-catalogue/data/database, NASA Exoplanet Archive, and NASA Astrophysics Data System Abstract Service. This work was presented as a part of 105th Indian Science Congress for young scientist award program.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The BOSS and BIOMEX space experiments on the EXPOSE-R2 mission: Endurance of the desert cyanobacterium Chroococcidiopsis under simulated space vacuum, Martian atmosphere, UVC radiation and temperature extremes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baqu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Vera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rettberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Billi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronautica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ionizing-radiation resistance in the desiccation-tolerant cyanobacterium Chroococcidiopsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Billi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Friedmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Caiola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1489. 1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://science.nasa.gov/science−news/science−at−nasa/2001/ast26jan1/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied and Environmental Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of a Simulated Martian UV Flux on the Cyanobacterium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cockell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schuerger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Billi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Imre Friedmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Panitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>sp. 029</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exposure of phototrophs to 548 days in low Earth orbit: microbial selection pressures in outer space and on early earth</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cockell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rettberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rabbow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Olson-Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The ISME Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1671</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Salt Tolerance and Polyphyly in the Cyanobacterium Chroococcidiopsis (Pleurocapsales)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cumbers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rothschild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phycol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">472</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric and Magnetic Effects of Cosmic Rays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">680</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1942" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EXPOSE, an Astrobiological Exposure Facility on the International Space Station -from Proposal to Flight</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hegde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaltenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Origins of Life and Evolution of Biospheres</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">581</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colors of Extreme Exo-Earth Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hegde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaltenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rocky extreme, Mendeley Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">Doi:10.17632/kpmkbkgm3c.2</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity indexing of exoplanets in search for potential habitability: application to Mars-like worlds</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gudennavar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Doshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Safonova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysics and Space Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">146</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Requirements and limits for life in the context of exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>PNAS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12628</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lichen Flora of the Greater Sonoran Desert Region</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>., Bugartz F.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Arizona State University Lichen Her-barium publisher</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental methods for studying microbial survival in extraterrestrial environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Olsson-Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cockell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Microbiological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survival of Antarctic Cryptoendolithic Fungi in Simulated Martian Conditions On Board the International Space Station</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Onofri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Vera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zucconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Selbmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scalzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Venkateswaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rabbow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>De La Torre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Horneck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">; Phl-Ec @ Upr</forename><surname>Arecibo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1052" />
			<publisher>Planetary Habitability Laboratory</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Two-Tiered Approach to Assessing the Habitability of Exoplanets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schulze-Makuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fairn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1041</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
